<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9764-0223-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NIGHT (7th edition, volume 16, page 223)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dz71">Watches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1743367">Pretexting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559764?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NIGHT</label>, that part of the natural day during which the
                    sun is underneath the horizon; or that time when it is dark or dusky. Night was
                    originally divided by the Hebrews and other eastern nations into three parts or
                    watches. But the Romans, and after them the Jews, divided the night into four
                    parts or watches; the first of which began at sunset, and lasted till nine at
                    night, according to our way of reckoning; the second lasted till midnight; the
                    third extended to three in the morning; and the fourth ended at sunrise. The
                    ancient Gauls and Germans divided their time, not by days, but by nights; the
                    Anglo-Saxons followed the same method of reckoning; and the people of Iceland
                    and the Arabs do the same at this day. The length and shortness of the night or
                    of darkness is according to the season of the year and position of the place;
                    and the causes of this variation are now well known. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Astronomy.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Night-Watching,</hi> a practice of very
                    remote antiquity, and which belongs to the oldest regulations of police. As
                    early as the time of Solomon we find mention made of it, and likewise in the
                    Psalms of David. Sentinels were stationed in different places in Athens and in
                    other cities of Greece, and they were kept to their duty by the visitations<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194559777?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-9777-0224"/> of
                    the <hi rend="italic">thesmothetae.</hi> There were also <hi rend="italic"
                    >triumviri nocturni</hi> in the city of Rome, as we learn from the commen-tai
                    ies of Henback on the police of the Romans. It appears, however, that the design
                    of these institutions was rather the prevention of fires than the guarding
                    against alarms or dangers by night, although in process of time attention was
                    likewise paid to these objects. The apprehension of fires was the pretext of
                    Augustus, when he wished to strengthen the night-watch for suppressing nocturnal
                    commotions.</p>
                <p>It does not appear that the practice of calling out the hours became established
                    before the erection of city gates. It most probably had its rise in Germany; yet
                    it would have been attended with advantage in ancient Rome, where there were no
                    public clocks, nor any thing in private houses to indicate the hours. The
                    various periods for soldiers to mount guard were determined by water-clocks; at
                    the end of each hour they blew a horn, and by means of this signal every
                    individual was apprised of the hour of the night. It seems evident, however,
                    that these regulations were only attended to in time of war.</p>
                <p>In the city of Paris, as at Rome, night-watching was established at the very
                    commencement of the French monarchy; and De Lamare quotes the ordinances of
                    Clothaire II. upon this subject, in the year 595. The citizens at first kept
                    watch in rotation; but this practice was afterwards set aside, and, by the
                    payment of a certain sum of money, a permanent watch was established. In the
                    opinion of the learned and indefatigable Beckmann, the establishment of single
                    watchmen, to call out the hours through the streets, was peculiar to Germany,
                    and has only been copied by surrounding nations in more modern times. The
                    elector John George, in 1588, appointed watchmen in Berlin; and Mabillon
                    describes it as a practice peculiar to that country. Horns were made use of by
                    watchmen in some places, and rattles in others; the former being most proper for
                    villages, and the latter for cities.</p>
                <p>The Chinese, as early as the ninth century, had watchmen posted upon their
                    towers, who announced the hours both by day and by night, striking forcibly on a
                    suspended board, which in that country is said to be in use to the present
                    period; and at St Petersburg the watchmen employ a suspended plate of iron for a
                    similar purpose. In this manner also Christians are assembled together in the
                    Levant, for the purpose of attending divine service; and at an early period
                    monks were thus awakened in monasteries to attend to the proper hours of
                    prayer.</p>
                <p>We find mention made of steeple-watchmen in Germany in the fourteenth century. In
                    the year 1563, a churchsteeple was erected in Leisnig, and an apartment built in
                    it for a permanent watchman, who was obliged to proclaim the hours every time
                    the clock struck. In the fifteenth century permanent watchmen were kept in many
                    of the steeples at Ulm. The same thing was practised at Frankfort on the Mayne,
                    at OEttingen, and in many other places; and Montaigne records his astonishment
                    at finding a man on the steeple of Constance, who kept watch upon it
                    continually, and who upon no pretext whatever was permitted to descend.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
