<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-5160-0566-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JEWEL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:982526">Jewelers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152704">Tops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:900541">Ear</term>
                    <term ref="fast:900686">Earrings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103513">Sailing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10x8h">Jewels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m70n">Jewelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g11r">Top</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n86">Sails</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192945160?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">JEWEL</label>, any precious stone, or ornament set
                    with precious stones.</p>
                <p part="N">Jewels formed part of the ornaments with which the Jews, Greeks, and
                    Romans, especially their ladies of distinction, adorned themselves. So great was
                    the extravagance of the Roman ladies in this respect, that Pliny the Elder says
                    he saw Lollia Paulina with an equipage of this kind, amounting, according to Dr
                    Arbuthnot’s calculation, to L.322,9l6. Í3s. 4d. of our money. It is worthy of
                    observation, that precious stones amongst the Romans, and all the ancients, were
                    much scarcer, dearer, and consequently in higher estimation, than amongst us,
                    since a commerce was opened with the Indies. The ancients did not know how to
                    cut and polish them to much perfection; but coloured stones were not scarce, and
                    they cut them very well either hollow or in relief. When luxury had gained
                    ground amongst them, the Romans hung pendants and pearls in their ears; and for
                    this purpose the ears of both sexes were frequently bored. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Ears.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Jewel,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >John,</hi> a learned English divine, was born in the year 1522, and
                    educated at Oxford. In 1540, having been created bachelor of arts, he became a
                    noted tutor, and was soon afterwards chosen rhetorical lecturer in his college.
                    In February 1544, he took his degree as master of arts. Having early imbibed
                    protestant principles, he inculcated the same on his pupils; but this was
                    carried on privately till the accession of Edward VI. in 1546, when he made a
                    public declaration of his faith, and entered into a close friendship with Peter
                    Martyr, then professor of divinity at Oxford. In 1550, he took the degree of
                    bachelor of divinity, and frequently preached with great applause before the
                    university. At the same time he preached and catechised every alternate Sunday,
                    at Sunningwell in Berkshire, of which place he was rector. Upon the accession of
                    Queen Mary in 1553, he was one of the first who felt the effects of the storm
                    then raised against the Reformation; for, before any law was made, or order
                    given by the queen, he was expelled from Corpus Christi College by the fellows,
                    of their own private authority; but he continued in Oxford till he was called
                    upon, under the severest penalties, to subscribe to some of the Catholic
                    doctrines, a call which he submitted to. However, this did not secure his
                    safety, for he was obliged to fly; and, after encountering many difficulties, he
                    arrived, in the second year of Mary’s reign, at Frankfort, where he made a
                    public recantation of his subscription to the Catholic doctrines. He then went
                    to Strasburg, and afterwards to Zurich, where he attended Peter Martyr, in whose
                    house he resided. He returned to England in 1558, after Queen Mary’s death; and,
                    in 1559, was consecrated Bishop of Salisbury. This promotion was conferred upon
                    him as a reward for his great merit and learning; and another attestation was
                    given him by the university of Oxford, which, in 1565, conferred upon him in his
                    absence the degree of doctor in divinity. In this character he attended the
                    queen to Oxford the following year, and presided at the theological disputations
                    held before her majesty on that occasion. He had before distinguished himself by
                    a sermon preached at St Paul’s cross, in which he gave a public challenge to all
                    the Roman Catholics in the world to produce but one clear and evident testimony,
                    out of any father or famous writer who flourished within six centuries after
                    Christ, for any one of the articles which the Romanists maintain against the
                    church of England; and, two years afterwards, he published his famous Apology
                    for this church. In the mean time, he paid particular attention to his diocese,
                    where, in his visitations, he began, and at length perfected, such a
                    reformation, not only in his cathedral and parochial churches, but in all the
                    churches within his jurisdiction, as procured him and the whole order of bishops
                    due reverence and esteem. He was a careful and strict observer, not only of all
                    the flocks, but also of the pastors, in his diocese; and he watched so narrowly
                    the proceedings of his chancellor and archdeacons, and of his stewards and
                    receivers, that they had no opportunities of committing oppression, injustice,
                    or extortion, nor of being a burden to the people, or a scandal to himself.
                    Amidst these employments, however, he neglected the care of his health, to w
                    hich, indeed, his general course of life was unfavourable. He rose at four
                    o’clock in the morning; and, after prayers with his family at five, and in the
                    cathedral about six, he applied so intensely to his studies all the morning,
                    that he could not without difficulty be drawn from them. After dinner his doors
                    and ears were open to all suitors; and it was observed of him, as of Titus, that
                    he never sent any away sorrowful. About nine at night he called all his servants
                    to an account of how they had spent the day, and he went to prayers with them.
                    From the chapel lie withdrew again to his study till near midnight, and thence
                    retired to bed, when the gentleman, of his bed-chamber read to him till he fell
                    asleep. This watchful and laborious life, without any recreation at all, except
                    what his necessary refreshment at meals and a very few hours of rest afforded
                    him, soon wasted his life. He died at Monkton-Farley, in 1571, in the fiftieth
                    year of his age. He was the author of, LA View of a Seditious Bull sent into
                    England by Pope Pius V. in 1569; 2. A Treatise on the Holy Scriptures; 3. An
                    Exposition of St Paul’s two Epistles to the Thessalonians; 4. A Treatise on the
                    Sacrament; 5. An Apology for the National Church; 6. Several sermons,
                    controversial treatises, and other works. Bishop Jewel was one of the great
                    champions of the reformed religion, and was to the church of England what
                    Bellarmine was to that of Rome. His Apology was translated by Anne, the second
                    of the four learned daughters of Sir Anthony Coke, and mother of Sir Francis
                    Bacon. It was published, as it came from her pen, in 1564, with the approbation
                    of the queen and the prelates. The same Apology was printed in Greek at
                    Constantinople, under the direction of St Cyril the patriarch. His defence of
                    his Apology, against Harding and other Catholic divines, was held in such
                    esteem, that Queen Elizabeth, King James I. King Charles I. and four successive
                    archbishops,· ordered it to be kept chained in all parish churches for public
                    use.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Jewel</hi><hi rend="italic">Blocks,</hi> in
                    nautical language, a name given to two small blocks suspended at the extremities
                    of the main and fore top-sail yards, by means of an eye-bolt driven from without
                    into the middle of the yard-arm, parallel to its axis. The use of these blocks
                    is to retain the upper part of the top-mast studding-sails beyond the skirts of
                    the top-sails, so that each of those sails may have its full force of action,
                    which would be diminished by the encroachment of the other over its surface. The
                    halyards, by which these studding-sails are hoisted, are accordingly passed
                    through the jewel-blocks, whence, communicating with a block on the top-mast
                    head, they lead downwards to the top or decks, where they may be conveniently
                    hoisted.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:192945173?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-5173-0567"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
