<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-4796-0538-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JEFFREYS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rj49113">Turning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881352">Countesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830288">Benches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159626">Turning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012869">Mayors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919522">Face</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192944796?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">JEFFREYS</label>, StR <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >George,</hi> Baron Wem, commonly called <hi rend="italic">Judge
                        Jeffreys,</hi> was the sixth son of Mr John Jeffreys, of Acton, in
                    Denbighshire; and was educated at Westminster School, whence he removed to the
                    Inner Temple, where he applied himself to the study of the law. Alderman
                    Jeffreys, who was probably related to him, introduced him among the citizens of
                    London; and being a merry bottle companion, he soon came into great business,
                    and was chosen their recorder. He was afterwards chosen solicitor to the Duke of
                    York; and in 1680 he was knighted, and made chief justice of Chester. At length,
                    resigning the recordership, he obtained the post of chief justice of the king’s
                    bench, and, soon after the accession of James II. the great seal. During the
                    reign of King Charles II. he showed himself a bitter enemy to those dissenting
                    ministers who, in that time of persecution, were tried by him. He was one of the
                    principal advisers and promoters of all the oppressions and arbitrary measures
                    carried on in the reign of James II.; and his sanguinary and inhuman proceedings
                    against Monmouth's unhappy adherents in the west will for ever render his name
                    infamous. Whenever the prisoner was of a different party, or whenever he could
                    please the court by condemning him, instead of appearing, according to the duty
                    of his office, as his counsel, he would scarcely allow him to speak for himself,
                    but would load him with the grossest and most vulgar abuse, browbeat, insult,
                    and turn to ridicule the witnesses that spoke in his behalf, and even threaten
                    the jury with fines and imprisonment if they made the least hesitation about
                    bringing in the prisoner guilty. Yet it is said, that when he was in temper, and
                    matters perfectly indifferent came before him, no one became a seat of justice
                    better. Nay, it even appears, that when he was under no state influence, he was
                    sometimes inclined to protect the natural and civil rights of mankind, of which
                    the following instance has been recorded. The mayor and aldermen of Bristol had
                    been used to transport convicted criminals to the American plantations, and sell
                    them by way of trade. This turning to good account, when any pilferers or petty
                    rogues were brought before them, they threatened them with hanging, and then
                    some officers who attended earnestly persuaded the ignorant, intimidated
                    creatures to beg for transportation, as the only way to save their lives; and in
                    general the advice was followed. Then, without more form, each alderman in
                    course took one, and sold him for his own benefit; and sometimes warm disputes
                    arose between ,them about the next turn. This infamous trade, which had been
                    carried on for many years, coming to the knowledge of the lord chief justice, he
                    made the mayor descend from the bench, and stand at the bar in his scarlet and
                    fur, with his guilty brethren the aidermen, and plead as common criminals. He
                    then obliged them to give securities to answer informations; but the proceedings
                    were stopped by the Revolution. However, the brutality which Jeffreys commonly
                    showed on the bench, where his voice and visage were equally terrible, at length
                    exposed him to a severe mortification. A scrivener of Wapping having a cause
                    before him, one of the opponent’s council said he was a strange fellow, and
                    sometimes went to church, and sometimes to conventicles, and it was thought he
                    was a trimmer. At this the chancellor fired. “A trimmer !” said he; <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ζζ</hi> I have heard much of that monster, but never saw
                    one. Come forth, Mr Trimmer, and let me see your shape.” He then treated the
                    poor fellow so roughly, that, on his leaving the hall, he declared he would not
                    undergo the terrors of that man’s face again to save his life, and that he
                    should certainly retain the frightful impressions of it as long as he lived.
                    Soon afterwards, when the Prince of Orange landed, the lord chancellor, dreading
                    the public resentment, disguised himself in a seaman’s dress in order to leave
                    the kingdom, and was drinking in a cellar, when this scrivener, coming into the
                    cellar, and seeing again the face which had filled him with such horror,
                    started; upon which Jeffreys, fearing he was known, feigned a cough, and turned
                    to the wall with his pot of beer in his hand. But Mr Trimmer going out, gave
                    notice that he was there; and the mob rushing in, seized him, and carried him
                    before the lord mayor, who sent him with a strong guard to the lords of the
                    council, by whom he was committed to the Tower, where he died in 1689. It is
                    remarkable, that the late Countess of Pomfret met with very rude insults from
                    the populace on the western road, solely because she was grand-daughter to the
                    inhuman Jeffreys.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:192944809?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-4809-0539"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
