<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-4757-0535-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JEDO, or Jeddo</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g11r">Top</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:895648">Ditches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152704">Tops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192944757?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">JEDO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Jeddo</hi></label>, a
                    large city of Japan, the residence of the emperor, and the capital of the
                    country, as it is by much the largest city of the empire, from the resort of
                    princes and lords, who, with their numerous families and servants, swell the
                    train of the imperial court. It is situated in the province of Musasi, in 35.
                    32. of north latitude, on a large plain at the end of the gulf, which is so
                    shallow, with a muddy clay at the bottom, that no ships of any considerable size
                    can come up to the city, but must be unladen aleague or two below it. According
                    to the Japanese accounts, the city is seven miles long, five broad, and twenty
                    in circumference. It is not enclosed with a wall, but is intersected by many
                    broad ditches and canals, with high ramparts raised on both sides, on the top of
                    which are planted rows of trees. A large river, rising to the west of the city,
                    runs through it, and loses itself in the harbour. It sends off a branch, which
                    divides itself into five channels, over each of which is a stately bridge. Jedo
                    is not so regularly built as most other cities of Japan, though in some parts,
                    which have been burnt down and rebuilt, the streets cross each other at right
                    angles. The houses are small and low, being built of wood, with thin clayed
                    walls, divided within into rooms by paper screens, the floors covered with fine
                    mats, the roofs with shavings of wood. They consist entirely of combustible
                    materials, so that we need not wonder at the havoc which fires frequently
                    occasion. In this city are many stately palaces, the residences of the nobles
                    and princes, who are obliged to reside six months of the year at the imperial
                    court. They are distinguished from other houses by large court-yards and stately
                    gates; fine varnished staircases, of a few steps, lead up to the door of the
                    house, which is divided into several magnificent apartments, all on one floor,
                    only one story high, and not adorned with towers, as the castles and palaces are
                    where the· princes and lords of the empire reside in their hereditary dominions.
                    There arc, besides, numerous temples, monasteries, and other religious
                    buildings. The castle and residence of the emperor, which is a magnificent
                    structure, is situated about the middle or the city. It isofan irregular figure,
                    inclining to the circular, and is five Japanese miles in circumference. It
                    consists of two enclosures; the innermost and third castle, which is properly
                    the residence of the emperor; two other strong, well-fortified, but smaller
                    castles at the sides; and some large gardens behind the imperial palace. The
                    first and outermost castle takes in a large space of ground, which encompasses
                    the second and half the imperial residence, and is enclosed with walls and
                    ditches, and strong, well-guarded gates. This is the residence of the princes of
                    the empire, with their families, who live in commodious and stately palaces,
                    built in streets, with spacious courts shut up with strong and heavy gates. The
                    second castle takes in a much smaller space of ground. It fronts the third, the
                    residence of the emperor, and is enclosed by the first, but separated from both
                    by walls, ditches, &amp;c. Here are the stately palaces of some of the most
                    powerful princes of the empire, the councillors of state, the prime ministers,
                    chief officers of the crown, and such other persons as give immediate attendance
                    on the emperor. The castle where the emperor himself resides is enclosed with a
                    thick, strong wall of freestone, having bastions standing out, much after the
                    manner of the European fortifications. On the top of this wall are erected
                    several long buildings and square guard-houses,built in the form of towers, and
                    several stories in height. Those on the side where the imperial residence is are
                    all of freestone of an extraordinary size. It is adorned with a square tower,
                    raised many stories high, adorned with beautiful bended roofs, gilt dragons at
                    the top and corners, and many other fantastical ornaments. The second castle is
                    very small, and more like a citadel; and the third lies on the side of the
                    second, and is of much the same structure. In these two castles are bred the
                    imperial princes and princesses. The rising ground behind the imperial residence
                    is beautified with gardens and magnificent orchards. The palace itself is only
                    of one story, but it is of great height, and contains many long galleries and
                    spacious rooms, which, on removing the screens, may be narrowed or enlarged as
                    occasion requires. The structure of all the interior apartments is fine,
                    according to the fashion of the country; the ceilings, beams, and pillars are of
                    cedar, or camphire, or a peculiar sort of wood, which runs into flowers and
                    other curious figures, and is in some apartments covered only with a thin
                    transparent layer of varnish, in others japanned, or curiously carved with birds
                    and branched work neatly gilt. The floor is covered w-ith the finest white mats,
                    bordered with gold fringes or bands; and this is all the furniture to be seen in
                    the emperor’s palace. There are two strong rooms, in which are kept the imperial
                    treasures. Besides being the residence of the court, and the seat of luxury,
                    Jedo contains flourishing manufactures, and carries on an extensive commerce.
                    From the combustible materials of which the houses are formed, it is liable to
                    dreadful conflagrations. One that occurred in 1703 is supposed to have consumed
                    100,000 houses. Long. 140. E. Lat. 36. 30. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
