<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-5966-0628-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JUICE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk2p">Resins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x23n">Cake</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174597">White</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174816">Whites</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843972">Cake</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192945966?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">JUICE</label> denotes the sap of vegetables, or the
                    liquors of animals.</p>
                <p part="N">The juices of several plants are expressed to obtain their essential
                    salts, and for several medicinal purposes, with intention either to be used
                    without further preparation, or to be made into syrups and extracts. The general
                    method of extracting these juices is, by pounding the plant in a marble mortar,
                    and then by putting it into a press. In this way is obtained a muddy and green
                    liquor, which generally requires to be clarified. The juices of all plants are
                    not extracted with equal case. Some plants, even when fresh, contain so little
                    juice, that water must be added whilst they are pounded, otherwise scarcely any
                    juice could be obtained by expression. Other plants, which contain a
                    considerable quantity of juice, furnish by expression but a small quantity of
                    it, because they contain also much mucilage, which renders the juice so viscid
                    that it cannot flow. Water must also be added to these plants to obtain their
                    juice. The juices thus obtained from vegetables by a mechanical method arc not,
                    properly speaking, one of their principles, but rather a collection of all the
                    proximate principles of plants which are soluble in water; such is the
                    saponaceous extractive matter, the mucilage, the odoriferous principle, and the
                    saline and saccharine substances; all of which are dissolved in the water of the
                    vegetation of the plants. Besides these matters, the juice contains some part of
                    the resinous substance, and the green colouring matter, which in almost all
                    vegetables is of a resinous nature. These two latter substances not being
                    soluble in water, are only interposed between the parts of the other principles
                    which are dissolved in the juice, and consequently disturb its transparency.
                    They nevertheless adhere together in a certain degree, and so strongly in most
                    juices, that they cannot be separated by filtration alone. When therefore these
                    juices are to be clarified, some previous preparations must be used by which the
                    filtration may be facilitated. Juices which arc acid, and not very mucilaginous,
                    are spontaneously clarified by rest and gentle heat. The juices of most
                    antiscorbutic plants abounding in saline volatile principles, may be disposed to
                    filtration merely by immersion in boiling water; and as they may be contained in
                    close bottles, whilst they are thus heated in a water bath, their saline
                    volatile part, in which their medicinal qualities chiefly consist, may thus be
                    preserved. Fermentation is also an effectual method of clarifying juices which
                    are susceptible of it; for all liquors which have fermented clarify
                    spontaneously after fermentation. But this method is not used to clarify juices,
                    because many of them are susceptible of only an imperfect fermentation, and
                    because the qualities of most of them are injured by that process. The method of
                    clarification most generally used, and indispensably necessary for those juices
                    which contain much mucilage, is boiling with the white of an egg. This matter,
                    which has the property of coagulating in boiling water, and of uniting with
                    mucilage, does accordingly, when added to the juice of plants, unite with and
                    coagulate their mucilage, and separates it from the juice in form of scum,
                    together with-the greatest part of the resinous and earthy matters which disturb
                    its transparency. And as any of these resinous matters which may remain in the
                    liquor, after this boiling with the whites of eggs, are no longer retained by
                    the mucilage, they may be easily separated by filtration.</p>
                <p part="N">The juices, especially before they are clarified, contain almost all the
                    same principles as the plant itself; because, in the operation by which they are
                    extracted, no decomposition happens, but every thing remains, as to its nature,
                    in the same state as in the plant. The principles contained in the juice are
                    only separated from the grosser oily, earthy, and resinous parts, which compose
                    the solid matter that remains under the press. These juices, when well prepared,
                    have therefore the same medicinal qualities as the plants from which they are
                    obtained. They must evidently differ from each other as to the nature and
                    proportions of the principles with which they are impregnated, as much as the
                    plants from which they are extracted differ from each other in those
                    respects.</p>
                <p part="N">Most vegetable juices coagulate when they are exposed to the air,
                    whether they are drawn out of the plant by wounds, or naturally run out; though
                    what is called naturally running out is generally the effect of a wound in the
                    plant, from a sort of canker, or some other internal cause. Different parts of
                    the same plant yield different juices. The same veins, in their course through
                    the different parts of the plant, yield juices of a different appearance. Thus
                    the juice in the root of the cow-parsnip is of a brimstone colour, but in the
                    stalk it is white.</p>
                <p part="N">Amongst those juices of vegetables which are clammy and readily
                    coagulate, there are some which readily break with a whey. The great wild
                    lettuce, with the smell of opium, yields the greatest plenty of milky juice of
                    any known British plant. When the stalk is wounded with a knife, the juice flows
                    out readily like a thick cream, and is white and ropy; but if these wounds are
                    made at the top of the stalks, the juice that flows out of them is dashed with a
                    purple tinge, as if cream had been sprinkled over with a fcw drops of red wine.
                    Some little time after letting this out, it becomes much more purple, and
                    thickens; and finally, the thicker part of it separates, and the thin whey swims
                    at the top. The whey or thin part of this separated matter is easily pressed out
                    from the curd by squeezing between the fingers, and the curd will then remain
                    white; and on washing with water it becomes like rags. The purple whey (for in
                    this is contained all the colour) soon dries into a purple cake, and may be
                    crumbled between the fingers into a powder of the same colour. The white curd
                    being dried and kept for some time, becomes bard and brittle. It breaks with a
                    shining surface like resin, and is inflammable, taking fire at a candle, and
                    burning all away with a strong flame. The same thick part being held over a
                    gentle heat, will draw out into tough, long threads, melting like wax. The
                    purple cake made from the whey is quite different from this; and when held to a
                    candle scarce flames at all, but burns to a black coal. The whole virtue of the
                    plant seems also to consist in this thin part of its juice; for the coagulum or
                    curd, though looking like wax or resin, has no taste at all; whereas the purple
                    cake made from the serum is extremely bitter, and of a taste somewhat resembling
                    that of opium.</p>
                <p part="N">Of the same kind with the wild lettuce arc the throatwort, spurge, and
                    many other plants. These are all replete with a milky juice which separates into
                    curds and whey like that already described. But this, though a common law of
                    nature, is not universal; for there are many plants which yield the like milky
                    juices without any separation ensuing upon their extravasation. The white juice
                    of the sonchus never separates, but dries into an uniform cake; the common red
                    wild poppy bleeds freely with a milky juice; and the heads or capsules of seed
                    bleed not less freely than the rest of the plant, even after the flower is
                    fallen. The juice, on being received into a shell or other small vessel, soon
                    changes its white to a deep yellow colour, and dries into a cake which seems
                    resinous and oily, but no whey separates from it. The tragopogon, or goat’s
                    beard, when wounded, exudes freely a milky juice; it is at first white, but
                    becomes immediately yellow, and then more and more red, till at length it is
                    wholly <hi rend="italic">of</hi> a <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:192945979?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-5979-0629"/>dusky red.
                    It never separates, but dries together into one cake; and is oily and resinous,
                    but of an insipid taste. The great bindweed also exudes freely a white juice;
                    the flowers, as well as the stalks and leaves, affording this liquor. It is of a
                    sharp taste; and, as many of the purging plants are of this class, it would be
                    worth trying whether this milk is not purgative.</p>
                <p part="N">These juices, as well as the generality of others which bleed from
                    plants, are white like milk; but there are some of other colours. The juice of
                    the great celandine is of a fine yellow colour; it flows from the plant of the
                    thickness of cream, and soon dries into a bard cake, without any whey separating
                    from it. Another yellow juice is yielded by the seed-vessels of the yellow
                    centaury in the month of July, when the seeds are full grown. This is very
                    clammy; it soon hardens altogether into a cake without any whey separating from
                    it. It sticks to the fingers like bird-lime, is of the colour of pale amber, and
                    will never become harder than soft wax if dried in the shade; but if laid in the
                    sun it immediately becomes hard like resin. These cakes burn like wax, and emit
                    a very pleasant smell. The great angelica also yields a yellowish juicc on being
                    wounded; and this will not harden at all, but if kept several years will still
                    be soft and clammy, drawing out into threads or half-melted resin.</p>
                <p part="N">Other kinds of juices very different from all these are those of a gummy
                    nature. Some of these remain liquid a long time, and are not to be dried without
                    the assistance of heat; and others very quickly harden of themselves, and are
                    not inflammable. The gum of the juice of rhubarb leaves soon hardens, and is
                    afterwards soluble in commonwater, and sparkles when put into the flame of a
                    candle. The clusters of the common honeysuckle are full of a liquid gum. This
                    they frequently throw out, and it falls upon the leaves, where it retains its
                    own form. The red hairs of the <hi rend="italic">ros solis</hi> are all
                    terminated by large bladders of a thin, watery fluid. This is also a liquid gum;
                    it sticks to the fingers, draws out into long threads, and stands the force of
                    the sun all day. In the centre of each of these dew-drops there is a small red
                    bladder, which stands immediately on the summit of the red hair, and contains a
                    purple juice which may be squeezed out of it. The pinguicula, or butterwort, has
                    also a gummy matter on its leaves, in much greater quantity than the <hi
                        rend="italic">ros solis.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Some plants yield juices which are manifestly of an oily nature. These,
                    when rubbed, are not at all of a clammy nature, but make the fingers glib and
                    slippery, and do not at all harden on being exposed to the air. If the stalk of
                    elecampane be wounded, there flows out an oily juice swimming upon a wate’ry
                    one. The stalks of the hemlock also afford a similar oily liquor swimming upon
                    the other; and in like manner the white mullein, the berries of ivy, the bay,
                    juniper, dogberry tree, and the fruit of the olive, when wounded, show their oil
                    floating on the watery juice. Some of these oily juices, however, harden into a
                    kind of resin. Our ivy yields such a juice very abundantly; and the juice of the
                    small purple-berried juniper is of the same kind, being hard and fat, and not
                    very gummy. If the bark of the common ivy is wounded in March, there will ooze
                    out a tough and greasy matter <hi rend="italic">of a</hi> yellowish colour,
                    which, taken up between the fingers, feels not at all gummy or sticking, but
                    melts in handling into a sort of oil, which in process of time hardens and
                    crusts upon the wounds, and looks like brown sugar. It burns with a lasting
                    flamc, and smells very strong. The tops of the wild lettuce, and the leaves
                    growing near the tops, if examined with a magnifying glass, show a great number
                    of small bladders or drops of an oily juice of a brownish colour, hardening into
                    a kind of resin; they are easily wiped off when of any size, and are truly an
                    oily juice a little hardened. It is probable, also, that the fine blue flour or
                    powder called the <hi rend="italic">bloom,</hi> upon the surface of our common
                    plums, is no other than such an oily juice exudating from their pores in small
                    particles, and hardening into a sort of resin.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
