<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0666-0609-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NOYON (9th edition, volume 17, page 609)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3cd37">Windows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1175789">Windows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844591">Calvinism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n666/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NOYON</label>, a city of France, department of Oise, 67 miles
                    north-north-east of Paris by the railway to Brussels, is built at the foot and
                    on the slopes of a hill, and traversed by a small stream, the Verse, which joins
                    the Oise a mile farther down. The old cathedral of Notre Dame, constructed
                    during the latter half of the 12th century, is a fine example of the mixture of
                    Romanesque and Gothic architecture. In plan it is a Latin cross, with a total
                    length from east to west of 343 feet, and from north to south of 66. The west
                    front has a porch, added in the 14th century, and two unfinished towers, their
                    upper portions dating from the 13th century; its decorations have been greatly
                    mutilated. The nave (167 feet long and 66 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n667/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0667-0610"/> broad) consists of eleven bays, including those
                    of the west front, which, in the interior, forms a kind of transept. In the
                    windows of the aisles, the arches of the triforium, and the windows of the
                    clerestory the round type is maintained; but double Pointed arches appear in the
                    lower gallery; and the vaults of the roof, originally six-ribbed, were rebuilt
                    after the fire of 1293 in the prevailing Pointed style. Side chapels were added
                    in the north aisle in the 14th century and in the south aisle in the 15th and
                    the 16th, one of the latter (15th) is especially rich in decorations. The flying
                    buttresses of the building are at present (1884) being restored in the style of
                    the 12th century. From the north-west corner of the nave runs the western
                    gallery of a fine cloister, erected in 1230; and next to the cloister is the
                    chapter-house of the same date, with its entrance adorned with statues of the
                    bishops and other sculpture. The bishops’ tombs within the cathedral were
                    destroyed during the Revolution. The chapel of the bishops’ palace is an example
                    of the Early Pointed style; the second bishops’ palace is a brick and stone
                    structure in the Renaissance style; the canons’ library was built of wood in the
                    15th century; and the town-house (Gothic and Renaissance) dates from 1485-1523.
                    Among the town manuscripts is the Red Book or communal charter of Noy on.
                    Remains of the Roman walls may be traced in the foundations of various houses.
                    Noyon has a good trade, and contains large sugar-refineries, chemical-works,
                    tanneries, and cotton-spinning mills. The population of the commune and that of
                    the city were respectively 6268 and 5236 in 1872, and 6252 and 5780 in 1881.</p>
                <p>Noyon, the ancient Novioιnagus Veromanduorum, was Christianized by St Quentin at
                    the close of the 3d century; and in 531 St Medard, bishop of the district of
                    Vermandois, transferred his see thither from St Quentin. The episcopate of St
                    Eligius (640-648), the burial of Chilperic II., the coronation of Pippin the
                    Short in 752, and on the same occasion the coronation of his infant son Carloman
                    with tfιe title of king of Noyon, the coronation of Charlemagne in 771, the
                    plunder of the town by the Normans in 859 and 880, the expulsion of the
                    castellan by the inhabitants, and in 997 the recognition of the overlordship of
                    the count of Flanders are the chief points in the history of Noyon down to the
                    10th century. In the 11th the city, passing under the French crown, became one
                    of the ecclesiastical peerages of the kingdom; and at the beginning of the 12th
                    century it easily obtained a communal charter through the favour of its bishops.
                    The extent of the bishopric was considerably curtailed in 1135 by the breaking
                    off of the diocese of Tournay. Noyon was ravaged by the English and the
                    Burgundians during the Hundred Years’ War. In 1516 a truce was signed at Noyon
                    by Francis I. and Charles V. The city was captured by the Spaniards in 1552, and
                    afterwards by the Leaguers, who were expelled in 1594 by Henry IV. It lost its
                    bishopric in 1791, and is at present only the chief town of a canton in the
                    arrondissement of Compiègne. Calvin was born at Noyon in 1509.</p>
                <p>See Le Vasseur, <hi rend="italic">Annales de VÉglise Cathédrale de Noyon,</hi>
                    1633; ,Lafons de Melicocq, <hi rend="italic">Rech. hist,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >sur Noyon,</hi> 1839; Barthélemy, <hi rend="italic">Monogr. de l'Eglise Notre
                    Dame de Noyon</hi>; Vitet, <hi rend="italic">Mongr. de l'Eglise de N. D. de
                    Noyon,</hi> 1845; and Moet de la Forte Maison, <hi rend="italic">Antiquités de
                    Noyon</hi> (1845).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
