<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0512-0471-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NEY, Michel (9th edition, volume 17, page 471)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1125233">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010769">Marshals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n512/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Michel</hi></label> (1769-1815),
                    one of the bravest of Napoleon’s marshals, was born at Saarlouis on January 10,
                    1769. His father, who had been a soldier, gave him a fairly good education, and
                    obtained for him an appointment in some neighbouring mines. But his heart was
                    set on the army, and in 1787 he went to Metz and enlisted in a regiment of
                    hussars. But for the Revolution he could never have become more than a sergeant,
                    but in the new state of things he was elected lieutenant, and afterwards (1792)
                    captain of his regiment. He was aide-decamp to General Lamarque in March 1793,
                    and soon after became lieutenant-colonel, when Kléber perceived his eminent
                    military ability, and made him adjutantgeneral in August 1794. He was promoted
                    colonel in September, and his merits were so great that Jourdan and Kléber
                    actually quarrelled which should have the advantage of his services. In February
                    1795 he might have become general of brigade, but modestly refused the rank,
                    alleging his own unworthiness. He commanded the advanced guard of Kléber at the
                    battle of Altenkirchen, and was made general of brigade on the field of
                    Forchheim. He then commanded the right wing of Hoche’s army, and in 1798 took
                    Mannheim. Sent next to Switzerland, he there reorganized Masséna’s cavalry, and
                    immensely distinguished himself in Masséna’s great campaign, in which he was
                    three times wounded, and after which he was made general of division. In 1799 he
                    commanded on the Rhine, and by his skilful operations obtained the armistice
                    during which the coup d’état of Brumaire took place. In 1801 he was present at
                    Hohenlinden, and in May 1802 he married Mademoiselle Auguié, whom Josephine had
                    chosen for him at Bonaparte’s request. He became inspectorgeneral of cavalry,
                    and, after a short residence as minister in Switzerland, commandant of the camp
                    of Montreuil. It was while there that in the name of the army he begged Napoleon
                    to declare himself emperor, and on the establishment<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n513/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0513-0472"/> of the empire he was made marshal of France and
                    grand cross of the Legion of Honour. In 1805 he commanded the 6th corps of the
                    grand army, and by his victory at Elchingen, for which he was made duke of
                    Elchingen, secured the surrender of General Mack at Ulm. He was then ordered to
                    the upper Adige, and missed the battle of Austerlitz, but was present at Jena
                    and Eylau, and was so instrumental in winning the battle of Friedland that
                    Napoleon called him the <hi rend="italic">brave des braves,</hi> and gave him
                    the grand eagle of the Legion of Honour. In 1808 he was ordered to Spain with
                    the 6th corps, and received the command of Galicia, which he managed to keep in
                    subjection to the French in spite of the mountainous nature of the country. In
                    1810, in command of a corps d’armée under Masséna, he advanced into Portugal,
                    but he was so disgusted at being under Masséna’s command that perpetual quarrels
                    resulted, and not only were the French defeated at Busaco, but Ney, when
                    conducting the last column on the retreat from Torres Vedras, received more than
                    one repulse from Lord Wellington at Pombal, Redinha, and Foz d’Aronce. For his
                    opposition to Masséna Ney was recalled from Spain, but received the command of
                    the 3d corps in the grand army of 1812. At the battle of the Moskva he so
                    distinguished himself that he was made Prince de la Moskowa on the field, and in
                    the disastrous retreat from Moscow it was Ney who commanded the rear-guard, and
                    kept the relics of the grand army together. He served at Lützen and Leipsic, and
                    in the last defensive campaign of 1814, and with Macdonald remained faithful to
                    Napoleon to the last. At the Restoration he was made a peer, and in 1815 was
                    given the command of the army sent to check Napoleon on escaping from Elba. But
                    the sight of the old colours and of his old master was too much for him, and he
                    led his troops over to Napoleon’s side. In the Flemish campaign he fought the
                    battle of Quatre Bras against the English on the same day that Napoleon defeated
                    the Prussians at Ligny, and at Waterloo he commanded in person the last charge
                    of the Old Guard. He made no attempt to leave France, and was arrested as a
                    traitor; on December 5 he was found guilty of high treason by the House of Peers
                    by 169 votes to 17, and two days later he was shot in the gardens of the
                    Luxembourg. His execution caused a cry of horror; while no one would have
                    regretted the death of Fouché or many another of the innumerable traitors, it is
                    to be lamented that Ney was chosen to suffer, whose honesty was well known, and
                    had only once failed him.</p>
                <p>The character of Ney was that of a simple soldier; intensely brave, though
                    without the rash impetuosity of a Murat, he was yet as modest as he was brave;
                    as a general his conduct of the two retreats from Portugal and Russia are his
                    chief titles to fame; and, if he was not faithful to the Bourbons, he paid with
                    his life for his defection.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Mémoires du Maréchal</hi><hi rend="italic">Ney,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">publiés</hi><hi rend="italic">par</hi><hi rend="italic">sa
                    famille,</hi> Paris, 1833, which go down to the capitulation of Ulm, and were
                    translated into English in 1833; <hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                    Maréchal</hi><hi rend="italic">Ney,</hi> Paris, 1816; <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    complète du procès du Maréchal Ney,</hi> 1815, English translation, 1816; A.
                    Delmas, <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur la révision du procès du Maréchal
                    Ney,</hi> 1832; and <hi rend="italic">Military Studies by Marshal Ney written
                    for the use of his officers,</hi> translated by C. H. Caunter, with notes by
                    Major A. James, London, 1833.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
