<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0324-0311-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NECKER, Jacques (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    311)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:958978">Holsteiners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942527">Gibbons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1746469">Grandsons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q84g">Widows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n324/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NECKER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacques</hi></label>
                    (1732-1804), finance minister of Louis XVL, and convener of the states-general
                    of 1789, was born at Geneva in 1732. His father was a native of Ciistrin in
                    Pomerania, and had, after the publication of some works on international law,
                    been elected professor of public law at Geneva. Jacques Necker had been sent to
                    Paris in 1747 to become a clerk in the bank of a friend of his father, Μ.
                    Vernet. He soon afterwards established, with another Genevese, the famous bank
                    of Thelusson &amp; Necker. Thelusson superintended the bank in London (his
                    grandson was made a peer as Lord Rendlesham), while Necker was managing partner
                    in Paris. Between them the bank prospered, and both partners became very rich.
                    He chiefly occupied himself in his bank, but in 1763 fell in love w-ith Madame
                    de Verméneux, the widow of a French officer. She could not make up her mind to
                    marry any one who was not noble, and, while considering his offer, she went on a
                    visit to Geneva, where she met Suzanne Curchod, the daughter of a pastor near
                    Lausanne, to whom Gibbon had been engaged, and took such a fancy to her that she
                    brought her back as her companion to Paris in 1764. There Necker, transferring
                    his love from the widow to the poor Swiss girl, married Suzanne before the end
                    of the year. She was extremely ambitious, and encouraged her husband to try and
                    make himself a public position. He accordingly became a syndic or director of
                    the French East India Company, and, after showing his financial ability in its
                    management, defended it in an able memoir against the attacks of Morellet in
                    1769. He had also made interest with the French Government by lending it money,
                    and was appointed resident at Paris by the republic of Geneva. Madame Necker
                    assisted his ambitious views by entertaining largely the chief leaders of the
                    political, financial, and literary worlds of Paris, and her Fridays became as
                    greatly frequented as the Mondays of Madame Geoffrin, or the Tuesdays of Madame
                    Helvetius. In 1773 Necker won the prize of the Académie Française for an <hi
                    rend="italic">éloge</hi> on Colbert, and in 1775 published his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essai</hi><hi rend="italic">sur la législation et le commerce des grains,</hi>
                    in which he attacked the free-trade policy of Turgot. His wife now believed he
                    could get into office as a great financier, and made him give up his share in
                    the bank, which he transferred to his brother Louis. She was right, and in
                    October 1776 Necker was made finance minister of France, though with the title
                    only of director of the treasury, which, however, he changed in 1777 for that of
                    director-general of the finances. He did great good in regulating the finances
                    by attempting to divide the taille or poll tax more equally, by abolishing the
                    “vingtième d’industrie,” and establishing “monts du piété.” But his greatest
                    financial measures were his attempt to fund the French debt and his
                    establishment of annuities under the guarantee of the state. The operation of
                    funding was too difficult in regard to the complicated French debt to be
                    suddenly accomplished, and Necker rather pointed out the right line to be
                    followed than completed the operation. In all this he treated French finance
                    rather as a banker than as a profound political economist, and thus fell far
                    short of Turgot, who was the very greatest economist of his day. Politically he
                    did not do much to stave off the coming Revolution, and his· establishment of
                    provincial assemblies in the “pays d’élection” only tended to keep France
                    disunited. In 1781 he published his famous <hi rend="italic">Compte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Rendu,</hi> in which he drew the balance sheet of France, and was
                    dismissed from his office. Yet his dismissal was not really due to his book, but
                    tσ the influence of Marie Antoinette, whose schemes for benefiting the Due de
                    Guines he had thwarted. In retirement he occupied himself with literature, and
                    with his daughter, Mdlle Necker, who was his only child, and would be a wealthy
                    heiress. He first attempted to procure the young English statesman Mr Pitt for
                    her husband, but eventually chose the Swedish Baron Erik Magnus von
                    Staël-Holstein, on condition that his master made him Swedish ambassador at
                    Paris. Gustavus III. was quite willing, and in 1786 Mdlle Necker became Madame
                    de Staël. But neither Μ. nor Madame Necker cared to remain out of office, and in
                    1787 Necker was banished by “lettre de cachet” 40 leagues from Paris for
                    attacking Calonne. In 1788 the country, which had at the bidding of the literary
                    guests of Madame Necker come to believe that Necker was the only minister who
                    could “stop the deficit,” as they said, demanded Necker’s recall, and in
                    September 1788 he became once more director-general of the finances. He entered
                    office at a critical moment: Dauphiné was in actual rebellion, and France was
                    crying out for the summons of the states-general. Necker put a stop to the
                    rebellion in Dauphiné by legalizing its assembly, and then set to work to
                    arrange for the summons of the states-general. Throughout the early months of
                    1789 Necker was regarded as the saviour of France, but his conduct at the
                    meeting of the states-general sufficiently proved that he was not a. great
                    statesman, and showed that he regarded the states-general merely as an assembly
                    which should grant money,, not organize reforms. The same want of statesmanship
                    appeared in his vacillating conduct -with regard to the·, reunion of the three
                    orders, when he allowed the king to be forced by the assembly instead of taking
                    the lead in ordering the reunion. He was nevertheless regarded as· the cause of
                    the Revolution by the court, and on July 11, while at dinner, received the
                    abrupt order to leave France, at once. But Necker’s dismissal brought about the
                    taking-of the Bastille, which induced the king to recall his old minister. His
                    return was an absolute ovation, and he was received with joy in every city he
                    traversed. But at Paris he again proved to be no statesman. In his conceit he
                    believed he could save France alone, and refused to· act with Mirabeau or La
                    Fayette. He caused the king’s acceptance of the suspensive veto, by which he
                    sacrificed his chief prerogative in September, and destroyed all chance of a
                    strong executive by contriving the decree of November 7, by which the ministry
                    might not be chosen from the assembly. Financially he proved equally incapable
                    for a time of crisis, and could not understand the need of such extreme measures
                    as the establishment of assignats-in order to keep the country quiet. His
                    popularity-vanished when his only idea was to ask the assembly for new loans,
                    and in September 1790 he resigned his office, unregretted by a single Frenchman.
                    Not without difficulty he reached Coppet, near Geneva, an estate he had bought
                    in 1784. Here he occupied himself with literature, but Madame Necker pined for
                    her Paris salon, and died in 1794. He continued to live on at Coppet, under the
                    care of his daughter, Madame de Staël, and his niece, Madame Necker de Saussure,
                    but his time was past, and his books-had no political influence. A momentary
                    excitement was-caused by the advance of the French armies in 1798, when <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n325/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0325-0312"/> he burnt most of his political papers. He died at
                    Coppet in April 1804.</p>
                <p>The chief authorities for Necker’s life are <hi rend="italic">La</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi rend="italic">privée</hi><hi rend="italic">de Μ.
                    Keeker,</hi> by Madame de Staël-Holstein, and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notice</hi><hi rend="italic">sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la vie de Μ.
                    Neckcr,</hi> by Auguste de Staël-Holstein, his grandson, published in the
                    collection of his works edited by the latter in 1833. The bibliography of his
                    works is as follows:— <hi rend="italic">Réponse au Mémoire</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >de</hi><hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi rend="italic">T Abbé Morellet,</hi> 1769;
                    <hi rend="italic">Éloge de J. B. Colbert,</hi> 1773; <hi rend="italic">Essai sur
                    la législation et le commerce des grains,</hi> 1775; <hi rend="italic">Compte
                    résidu au Roi,</hi> 1781; <hi rend="italic">De l’administration des finances de
                    la France,</hi> 3 vols., 1784; <hi rend="italic">Mémoire en réponse au discours
                    prononcé par Μ. de Galonné,</hi> 1787; <hi rend="italic">De l’importance des
                    opinions religieuses,</hi> 1788; <hi rend="italic">Sur l'administration de Μ.
                    Neckcr, par lui-même,</hi> 1791; <hi rend="italic">Du pouvoir exécutif dans les
                    grands états,</hi> 2 vols., 1792; <hi rend="italic">Réflexions sur le procès de
                    Louis XVI.,</hi> 1792; <hi rend="italic">De la Révolution Française,</hi>
                    several editions, the last in 4 vols., 1797; <hi rend="italic">Cours de la
                    morale</hi><hi rend="italic">religieuse,</hi> 1800; <hi rend="italic">Dernières
                    vues de politique et de finance,</hi> 1802; <hi rend="italic">Manuscrits de Μ.
                    Neckcr,</hi> published by his daughter, 1804; <hi rend="italic">Suites</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">funestes d’une seule faute,</hi> published after his death. <hi
                    rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Salon de Madame Necker,</hi> by the
                    Vicomte d’Haussonville, 2 vols., 1882, compiled from the papers at Coppet,
                    should also be consulted. (H. Μ. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
