<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0723-0666-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NUTMEG (9th edition, volume 17, page 666)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205795">Réunion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1111109">Seeds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1031539">Myristica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058953">Peruvians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:813061">Arches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t15">Seeds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64c1c">Spices</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n723/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NUTMEG</label>. The spice known in commerce under this name
                    is the kernel of the seed of <hi rend="italic">Myristica</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >fragrans,</hi> Houtt., a dioecious evergreen tree, about 50 to 60 feet high,
                    found wild in the Banda Islands and a few of the neighbouring islands, extending
                    to New Guinea but not to the Philippines. Nutmeg and mace are almost exclusively
                    obtained from the Banda Islands, although the cultivation has been attempted
                    with varying success in Singapore, Penang, Bengal, Réunion, Brazil, French
                    Guiana, and the West Indies. The trees yield fruit in eight years after sowing
                    the seed, reach their prime in twenty-five years, and bear for sixty years or
                    longer. Almost the whole surface of the Banda Islands is planted with nutmeg
                    trees, which thrive under the shade of the lofty <hi rend="italic"
                    >Canarium</hi><hi rend="italic">commune.</hi> The light volcanic soil, shade,
                    and excessive moisture of these islands, where it rains more or less during the
                    whole year, seem exactly to suit the requirements of the nutmeg tree. In
                    Bencoolen the tree bears all the year round, but the chief harvest takes place
                    in the later months of the year, and a smaller one in April, May, and June. In
                    the Banda Islands the fruits are collected in small neatly-made oval baskets at
                    the end of a bamboo, which prevents bruising, the baskets being open for half
                    their length on one side and furnished with a couple of small prongs projecting
                    from the top, by which the fruit-stalk is broken, the fruit falling into the
                    basket. The ripe fruit is about 2 inches in diameter, of a rounded pear-shape,
                    and when mature splits into two halves, exposing a crimson arillus surrounding a
                    single seed. When the fruit is collected the pericarp is first removed; then the
                    arillus is carefully stripped off and dried, in which state it forms the mace of
                    commerce. The seed consists of a thin hard testa or shell enclosing a kernel,
                    which, when dried, is the nutmeg. To prepare the nutmegs for use, the seed
                    enclosing the kernel is dried at a gentle heat in a drying-house over a
                    smouldering fire for about two months, the seeds being turned every second or
                    third day. When thoroughly dried the shells are broken with a wooden mallet or
                    flat board and the nutmegs picked out and sorted, the smaller and inferior ones
                    being reserved for the expression of the fixed oil which they contain, and which
                    forms the so-called oil of mace.</p>
                <p>The dried nutmegs are then rubbed over with dry sifted lime. The process of
                    liming, which originated at the time when the Dutch held a monopoly of the
                    trade, was commenced with the view of preventing the germination of the seeds,
                    which were formerly immersed for three months in milk of lime for this purpose,
                    and a preference is still manifested in some countries for nutmegs so prepared.
                    It has, however, been shown that this treatment is by no means necessary, since
                    exposure to the sun for a week destroys the vitality of the kernel. Nor is the
                    dry liming process needful, for nutmegs keep well in their natural shell, in
                    which form they are usually exported to China. The weight of the shells,
                    however, adds one-third to the cost of freight, hence this plan is not generally
                    adopted. Penang nutmegs are never limed. The entire fruit preserved in syrup is
                    used as a sweetmeat in the Dutch East Indies.</p>
                <p>“Oil of mace,” or nutmeg butter, is a solid fatty substance of a reddish-broλvn
                    colour, obtained by grinding the refuse nutmegs to a fine powder, enclosing it
                    in bags and steaming it over large cauldrons for five or six hours, and then
                    compressing it while still warm between powerful wedges, the brownish fluid
                    which flows out being afterwards allowed to solidify. Nutmegs yield about
                    one-fourth of their weight of this substance. It is partly dissolved by cold
                    alcohol, the remainder being soluble in ether. The latter portion, about 10 per
                    cent, of the -weight of the nutmegs, consists chiefly of <hi rend="italic"
                    >myristin,</hi> which is a compound of <hi rend="italic">myristic acid,</hi> C
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 14</hi> H., <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, with glycerin. The fat which is soluble in alcohol
                    appears to consist, according to Schmidt and Roemer <hi rend="italic">(Arch.
                    Pharm.</hi> [3], xxi. pp. 34-48), of free myristic and stearic acids; the brown
                    colouring matter has not been satisfactorily investigated. Nutmeg butter yields
                    on distillation with water a volatile oil to the extent of about 6 per cent.,
                    consisting almost entirely of a hydrocarbon called <hi rend="italic"
                    >myristicene,</hi> C <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                    10</hi>, boiling at 165° C. It is accompanied by a small quantity of an
                    oxygenated oil, <hi rend="italic">myristicol,</hi> isomeric with carvol, but
                    differing from it in not forming a crystalline compound with hydrosulphuric
                    acid. Mace contains a similar volatile oil, <hi rend="italic">macene,</hi>
                    boiling at 160° C., which is said by Cloëz to differ from that of nutmegs in
                    yielding a solid compound when treated with hydrochloric acid gas.</p>
                <p>The annual imports of nutmegs to the United Kingdom amount to from 400,000 to
                    800,000 lb, each lb consisting of about 110 fair-sized nutmegs, and of mace from
                    60,000 to 80,000 lb per annum. The former are valued at from three to five
                    shillings per ft), and mace at from one to three shillings per ft).<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This spice seems to be an
                    especial favourite with the people of the United States, since the export to
                    that country exceeds that to all Europe combined.</p></note> Long, wild, or male
                    nutmegs, the produce of <hi rend="italic">Μ. tomentosa</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi rend="italic">fatua,</hi> are sometimes imported in
                    small quantities. Several species of <hi rend="italic">Myristica</hi> yield
                    fatty oils, which form commercial products, but none of these are remarkable for
                    fragrance.</p>
                <p>The name nutmeg is also applied to other fruits or seeds in different countries.
                    The Jamaica or calabash nutmeg is derived from <hi rend="italic">Monodora
                    Myristica,</hi> the Brazilian <hi rend="italic">irom Cryptocarya moschata,</hi>
                    the Peruvian from <hi rend="italic">Laurelia semperυirens,</hi> the New Holland
                    or plume nutmeg from <hi rend="italic">Λtherosperma moschata,</hi> the
                    Madagascar orclove nutmeg from <hi rend="italic">Agathophyllum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">aromaticum,</hi> and the Californian or stinking nutmeg from <hi
                    rend="italic">Torreya myristica.</hi> The cotyledons of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nectandra Puchury</hi> were at one time offered in England as nutmegs.</p>
                <p>Seemann, in <hi rend="italic">Hooker's Journ. Bot.,</hi> 1852, p. 83;
                    Collingwood, <hi rend="italic">Jburn. Lin. Soc. Bot.,</hi> 1869, p. 45;
                    Lumsdaine, <hi rend="italic">Pharm. Journ.</hi> [1], xi. p. 516; Wallace, <hi
                    rend="italic">Malay Archipelago,</hi> i. p. 452, 1869; Bickmore, <hi
                    rend="italic">Travels in E. Indian Archipelago,</hi> 1868, p. 225; <hi
                    rend="italic">Pharmacographia</hi> (2d. ed.), p. 502; <hi rend="italic">Journ.
                    Pharm. Soc.</hi> [3J, xiii. p. 304.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n724/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0724-0667"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
