<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0664-0607-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NOVGOROD (9th edition, volume 17, page 607)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jj0k">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017057">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n664/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NOVGOROD</label>, capital of the above government, is
                    situated 119 miles to the south of St Petersburg, on the low flat banks of the
                    Volkhoff, some two miles below the point where it leaves Lake Ilmen. The present
                    town is but a poor survival of the wealthy city of mediaeval times. It consists
                    of a kremlin (old fortress) and of the city, which stands on both banks of the
                    river, here connected by a handsome bridge. The kremlin was much enlarged in
                    1044, and again in 1116. Its stone walls, originally palisades, were begun in
                    1302, and much extended and embellished in 1490. It is very spacious, and
                    formerly a great number of churches and shops with wide squares stood within the
                    enclosure. Its valuable historical monuments include the cathedral of St Sophia,
                    begun in 1045 by an architect from Constantinople to take the place of the
                    original wooden structure (989), destroyed by fire in that year. Some changes
                    were made in the walls in 1688 and 1692, and the windows were enlarged, but
                    otherwise (notwithstanding several fires) the building remains unaltered. It
                    contains many highly-prized relics. Another ancient building in the kremlin is
                    Yaroslaff’s Tower, in the square where the Novgorod <hi rend="italic"
                    >vyetche</hi> (common council) met, and which still bears the name of “the court
                    of Yaroslaff”; the tower was the <hi rend="italic">gridnitscι</hi> or
                    chancellery of the secretaries of the <hi rend="italic">vyetche.</hi></p>
                <p>Several other remarkable monuments of Russian architecture still exist at
                    Novgorod, such as the church of St Nicholas, erected in 1135, and churches of
                    the 14th and 15th centuries. Within the town itself there are four monasteries
                    and convents; and the large number in the immediate neighbourhood shows the
                    great extension the city formerly had. A monument to commemorate the thousandth
                    anniversary of the foundation of the Russian state (the calling in of the
                    Varangians by Novgorod in 862) was erected in 1864. It consists of a large globe
                    on a massive pedestal, surrounded by numerous statues commemorating the leading
                    events of Russian history. Another monument commemorates the campaign of 1812.
                    On the whole, apart from its old churches and some portions of its walls,
                    Novgorod has nothing to recall the leading part it has played in the history of
                    Russia. Since the diversion from it of the great commercial highways of
                    north-western Russia its commercial influence has been very limited. Its
                    merchants still send timber, grain, and hay to St Petersburg; but the total
                    production of its manufacturing establishments—paper-mills, flour-mills,
                    saw-mills, glass-works, brick-works, match-works, and distilleries—does not
                    reach 1,000,000 roubles. A trunk railway, 45 miles long, connects the city with
                    Tchudovo on the Moscow and St Petersburg Railway. The population is 17,500.</p>
                <p>The date at which the Slavonians on their northward advance first erected forts
                    on the Volkhoff' (where it leaves Lake llnιen and where it flows into Lake
                    Ladoga) is unknown. That situated on a low terrace close by Lake Ilmen was soon
                    abandoned, and Novgorod or “New-town” arose on another which extended a mile
                    lower on both banks of the river. The older fort (Gorodische) still existed in
                    the 13th century. It is certain that, even in the 9th century, the new city on
                    the Volkhoff, whilst maintaining close relations with Kieff, already exercised a
                    kind of supremacy over the other towns of the lake region, when its inhabitants
                    in 862 invited the Varangians to the defence of the Russian towns of the north.
                    Down to the end of the 10th century Novgorod was in some sort dependent on
                    Kieff; yet it must have maintained its internal autonomy, for in 997 its
                    inhabitants obtained from their own Prince Yaroslaff a charter which granted
                    them self-government, a jurisdiction of their own, and the rule of their proper
                    <hi rend="italic">vyetche.</hi> For five centuries this charter continued to be
                    regarded as the chief written testimony of the independence of Novgorod, and was
                    ever resorted to in the struggles with the princes. From the end of the 10th
                    century the princes of Novgorod, chosen either from the sons of the great
                    princes of Kieff (until 1136) or from some other branch of the family of Rurik,
                    were always elected by the <hi rend="italic">vyetche,</hi> and swore to maintain
                    the free institutions of the town; but they were only its military defenders.
                    Their delegates were merely assessors in the courts which levied the fixed taxes
                    meant to defray the maintenance of the military force raised by the prince. The
                    <hi rend="italic">vyetche</hi> expelled the princes as soon as they provoked
                    discontent. Their election was often a subject of dispute between the wealthier
                    merchants and landowners and the poorer classes; and Novgorod, which was
                    dependent for its corn supply upon the land of Suzdal, was sometimes compelled
                    to accept a prince from the Suzdal branch instead of from that of Kieff, which
                    was more popular among the poorer classes. After 1270 the city often refused to
                    have princes at all, and the elected mayor <hi rend="italic">{posadnik}</hi> was
                    the representative of the executive in its limited attributes. Novgorod in its
                    transactions with otheι <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> cities took the name of
                    “Sovereign Great Novgorod” <hi rend="italic">{Gospodin Velikii Novgorod}.</hi>
                    The supreme power and the supreme jurisdiction were in the hands of the <hi
                    rend="italic">vyetche,</hi> whose resolutions were carefully inscribed by its
                    secretaries <hi rend="italic">{diaki}.</hi> The city, which had a population of
                    more than 80,000, was divided into sections <hi rend="italic">{kontsy},</hi>
                    radiating from its centre, and corresponding to some extent to the prevailing
                    occupations of the inhabitants; each constituted a distinct commune which
                    enjoyed a large share of independence. The <hi rend="italic">kontsy</hi> were
                    subdivided into streets <hi rend="italic">{ulitsy},</hi> which also corresponded
                    to the prevailing occupations of their inhabitants (artisans or merchants), and
                    each of which was quite independent with regard to its own affairs, such as the
                    election of priests, the maintenance of order, jurisdiction in inferior matters,
                    trade, food supply, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Trade was carried on by corporations which embodied, not only the merchants
                    proper or <hi rend="italic">gosti,</hi> but also the poorer classes; in fact, it
                    was the chief source of income, and, owing to the existence of numerous trading
                    corporations, everybody was enabled to participate in it more or less. Novgorod,
                    owing to its very advantageous position, made great advances in trade. By the
                    Volkhoff and the Neva it had direct communication with the Hanseatic and
                    Scandinavian cities. The Dnieper brought it into connexion with the
                    Bosphorus.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n665/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0665-0608"/>
                <p>and it was intermediary in the trade of Constantinople with northern Europe. The
                    rich gifts offered by the corporations to the churches of Novgorod are a present
                    testimony of the ancient wealth of the city.</p>
                <p>The Novgorod <hi rend="italic">ukshuyniki</hi> (who often associated robbery with
                    trade) at an early date penetrated to the shores of the White Sea, hunted on
                    Novaya Zemlya in the 11th century, colonized the basins of the northern Dwina,
                    descended the Volga, and, as early as the 14th century, extended their dominions
                    over the “Ugra,” beyond the Ural, into Siberia. The Zavolotchie, or the basin of
                    the northern Dwina, was early colonized, and forts were erected to maintain the
                    dominions, while two great colonies, Vyatka and Vologda, organized on the same
                    republican principles as the metropolis, favoured the further colonization of
                    north-eastern Russia.</p>
                <p>At the same time a number of flourishing minor towns <hi rend="italic"
                    >(prigorody</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">),</hi>
                    such as Novyi Torg (Torzhok), Novaya Ladoga, Pskov, and many others, arose in
                    the lake region. Pskov soon became quite independent of the metropolis, and had
                    a history of its own; the others enjoyed a large measure of independence, still
                    figuring, however, as subordinate towns in all those circumstances which implied
                    a common action of the whole region. Several contemporary testimonies state the
                    population of Novgorod in the 14th century to have reached 400,000, and add that
                    the pestilences of 1467, 1508, andl533 carried off no fewer than 134,000
                    persons. These figures, however, seem to relate rather to the Ilmen region; but
                    it may be safely admitted that, before the visitations referred to, the city,
                    with the suburbs, had a population of nearly 100,000.</p>
                <p>Throughout its history Novgorod has had to sustain many contests. Its struggle
                    against the Suzdal region began as early as the 12th century. In the following
                    century it had to contend with the Swedes and the Germans, who were animated not
                    only by the desire of territorial extension throughout the lake region but also
                    by the spirit of religious proselytism. The advances of both were checked by the
                    battles at Ladoga and Pskov in 1240 and 1242, Protected as it was by its
                    marshes, Novgorod escaped the Mongol invasion, and was able to repel the attacks
                    of the princes of Moscow by whom the Mongols were supported; but it was
                    compelled to pay a tribute, which soon became a tribute to Moscow (end of the
                    14th century). It also successfully resisted the attacks of Tver, and aided
                    Moscow in its struggle against this powerful neighbour, but it soon itself
                    experienced the power of the growing Moscow state. The first serious invasion of
                    its independence, in 1332, was turned back only with the aid of the Lithuanians.
                    But a severe blow was inflicted in 1456 by the Great Prince of Moscow, Vasilii
                    Temnyi, who, taking advantage of the internal troubles of the city, and finding
                    supporters among the Novgorod <hi rend="italic">boyars,</hi> succeeded in
                    imposing a heavy tribute. Ivan III. took possession of the Zavolotchie colonies
                    and the Perm region, and began two bloody wars, during which Novgorod fought for
                    its liberty under the leadership of Martha Posadnitsa. In 1475 Ivan III. entered
                    Novgorod, abolished its charters, and carried away 1000 of the wealthier
                    families, substituting for them families from Moscow; the old free city now
                    recognized his sovereignty. A century later Ivan IV. (the Terrible) abolished
                    the last vestige of the independence of the city. Having learned of the
                    existence of a party favourable to Lithuania, he took the field in 1570, and
                    entered Novgorod (much weakened by the recent pestilences) without opposition.
                    His followers seized nearly all the heads of monasteries and beat them to death
                    with sticks. At a given signal a general pillage began: the shops were
                    destroyed, the merchandize thrown out, the wealthier of the merchants and clergy
                    killed and thrown into the Volkhoff, whilst other plundering parties burned and
                    pillaged all stores in the villages. No less than 15,000 men, women, and
                    children were killed at Novgorod alone (60,000 according to some authorities). A
                    famine ensued, and the district of Novgorod fell into utter destitution.
                    Thousands of families were transported to Moscow, Nijni-Novgorod, and other
                    towns of the principality of Moscow. In the beginning of the 17th century
                    Novgorod was taken and held for seven years by the Swedes; and in the 18th
                    century the foundation of St Petersburg ultimately destroyed its trade. Its
                    position, however, on the water highway from the Volga to St Petersburg, and on
                    the trunk road from Moscow to the capital, still gave it some commercial
                    importance; but even this was brought to an end by the opening of the Vishera
                    canal and the Nicholas Railway, which passes 45 miles to the east of Novgorod.
                    (P. A. K. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
