<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0393-0376-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NEW CALEDONIA (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    376)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1070688">Polynesians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mp4vv80">Polynesians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p24h">Papuans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw0c">Pine</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239785">Melanesia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n393/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NEW CALEDONIA</label>, the largest island in the Pacific
                    after New Zealand, about 240 miles long, with an average breadth of 25 miles,
                    lies at the southern extremity of <hi rend="smallcaps">Melanesia (⅛.v.),</hi>
                    between 20° 10' and 22° 25' S. lat. and between 164° and 167° E. long., and,
                    like all the chief islands of that chain and the chain itself, runs northwest
                    and south-east. It was discovered by Cook in 1774, and was appropriated by the
                    French for a convict settlement in 1853. Their capital, Nouméa, with a fine
                    harbour, is near the south end of the island. An almost unbroken barrier reef
                    skirts the west shore at about 5 miles distance; on the east, which is more
                    abrupt and precipitous, it is much interrupted. To the north the reefs continue,
                    marking the former extension of the land, for about 160 miles, ending with the
                    Huon Islands. Hunea, or Isle of Pines, so called from its araucarias,
                    geologically a continuation of New Caledonia, lies 30 miles from its south-east
                    extremity. It abounded formerly in sandalwood, and consists of a central plateau
                    surrounded by a belt of cultivation. New Caledonia consists essentially of
                    confused masses and ranges of mountains, rising at Mount Humboldt to 5380 feet,
                    the plains being chiefly the deltas of rivers. The landscape is rich and
                    beautiful, varied with grand rock scenery, the coast-line being broken by
                    countless streams, often skilfully utilized by the natives for irrigation. The
                    larger rivers in the wet season form impassable morasses. The framework of the
                    island consists chiefly of argillaceous, serpentinous, and mica schists. There
                    are no active volcanoes, but great magnesian eruptions, represented by
                    serpentines, cover the greater part of the surface, especially in the
                    southeast,—the extent of sedimentary formations, ranging from Upper Devonian (to
                    which some Carboniferous rocks near Nouméa apparently belong) to Neocomian,
                    being relatively insignificant. With the serpentines occur masses of red clay
                    from the decomposed rock, and much chromate of iron, which forms the
                    metalliferous black sands of the streams. The famous nickel mines lie in the
                    Kanala district, and extend for some 60 miles along the east coast,, the rocks
                    being coated with the green ore (“garnierite,” a hydrous magnesian silicate
                    impregnated with nickel oxide), which also occurs in pockets, and is extensively
                    worked. There are also mines of copper and cobalt. Gold has only been found in
                    small quantities. In the low-lying districts to the south-east are several lakes
                    and morasses of black mud, and blocks of ironstone so abundant as to affect the
                    compass. In the north-west the rocks (in which quartz replaces the diorite) are
                    not ferruginous, and are less contorted. The hottest and the wettest months are
                    from December to March, but there is usually a fresh tradewind blowing, and the
                    climate is healthy. There is much less moisture, and the flora is of a less
                    tropical character, than farther north; it has some Polynesian and New Zealand
                    affinities, and on the west coast a partially Australian character <hi
                    rend="italic">; on</hi> the higher hills it is stunted; on the lower, however,
                    there are fine grass lands, and a scattered growth of niaulis <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Melaleuca viridiflord),</hi> useful for its timber, bark, and cajeput oil.
                    There is a great variety of fine timber trees: those at present most used are
                    the kaurie, houp, and other pines, tamanou <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Calophyllum</hi><hi rend="italic">montanum),</hi> ironwood, acacias, milneas,
                    <hi rend="italic">C</hi><hi rend="italic">ordia.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sebestena,</hi> cohu, bourao, azou. The bread-fruit, sago, banana, vanilla,
                    ginger, arrowroot, and curcuma grow wild. The cocoa nut, maize, sugar-cane,
                    coffee, cotton, rice, and tobacco (which last does not suffer like other crops
                    from the locusts) do well. The orange, indigo, lucerne, and European vegetables
                    are grown. There are probably no mammals except the rat and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pteropus</hi> and other bats. The commonest birds are pigeons (the large notou
                    and other varieties), doves, parrots, kingfishers, and ducks. The kagu <hi
                    rend="italic">(Rhinochetus</hi><hi rend="italic">jubatus),</hi> a peculiar
                    “wingless” bird, is found here only. Turtle abound on the coast, and fish, of
                    which some kinds, as the tetrodons (globe-fish), are poisonous, especially at
                    certain seasons.</p>
                <p>The population is probably about 30,000, but has diminished greatly since the
                    French occupation. There are two distinct types: one is sub-Papuan, probably
                    aboriginal, dark brown, with black frizzly hair, rounded narrow retreating
                    forehead, high cheek-bones, and flat nose depressed at the root below the
                    prominent brows; the other, with all these features modified, better-developed
                    physique, and lighter colour, strongly resembles the Polynesian, and is most
                    numerous in the east and south, where most of the upper class belong to it; but
                    the two types intermingle everywhere. The women, though hard worked, are less
                    degraded than is usual among Papuans. Their marriage ceremonies end with a
                    simulated flight and capture. The people are hospitable to strangers, and not
                    quarrelsome among themselves, though fond of war with another tribe, which is
                    declared by a masked messenger, who taking a spear and money with him thrusts
                    the former among the challenged tribe, and then, throwing down the money in
                    atonement of the injury his∙ spear may have done, is allowed to return unharmed.
                    Their weapons are clubs, slings, stone hatchets (resembling the Australian), and
                    spears with a throwing cord. Rows of stones are found commemorating the numbers
                    of enemies killed and eaten in former wars. The French have found them
                    formidable antagonists on many occasions; the last ‘ ‘ revolt” was put down
                    after much trouble and bloodshed in 1881. There are various degrees of
                    hereditary chiefships, distinguished by insignia on their houses. As in
                    some-other Pacific islands, when a son is born the chiefship passes to him, but
                    the father continues to govern as regent. They have strict ideas of
                    property—individual, village, and tribal. The people have to work on the chiefs
                    plantations and fisheries, and also work in parties for each other, breaking up
                    new land, &amp;c. This often ends in feasting and in dances <hi rend="italic"
                    >{pilu pilu),</hi> which include allegorical representations of events or
                    ideas.</p>
                <p>Their huts are usually beehive-shaped, with a single apartment,, low narrow door,
                    and no chimney. The fire inside is their only defence against mosquitoes. The
                    central pole is continued outside, usually by a rude figure surmounted by a long
                    post elaborately decorated, especially in the chiefs’ houses, which far overtop
                    the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n394/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0394-0377"/> others, and have a good deal of grotesque hand
                    carving, something like but inferior to that seen in New Zealand.</p>
                <p>The food is chiefly vegetable, so that there is considerable scarcity at certain
                    seasons; but almost anything is eaten, including all sorts of insects, and a
                    steatite earth which contains a little copper. The exception is the lizard and
                    the gecko,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Fourteen
                    varieties have been found.</p></note> of which they have a superstitious
                    dread.</p>
                <p>They believe in the power of spirits to take up their abode in persons or
                    inanimate objects, and employ the aid of the soothsayer in this and many other
                    emergencies of life. The dead are supposed to go down into the sea at the west
                    end of the island. Cocoa-nut trees, a valuable sacrifice, are cut down on the
                    death of a chief. Like other cannibals, they have a certain knowledge of anatomy
                    and surgery, and also of medicine. Their music is quite rudimentary, and
                    consists of little else than beating or sounding in time. Their money is made of
                    different sorts of shells, but other articles of value—axes, skins, mats,
                    &amp;c.—are used as mediums of exchange.</p>
                <p>The languages of the different tribes are mutually unintelligible. They express
                    abstract ideas imperfectly. Dr Patouillet says that there are several words for
                    eating, each applied to a particular article of food. Their reckoning shows the
                    same peculiarity. The numbers go up to five, and for living objects the word <hi
                    rend="italic">bird</hi> is added, for inanimate <hi rend="italic">yam, for</hi>
                    large objects <hi rend="italic">ship.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>A similar usage exists in Malay. See paper by Colonel Yule
                    in <hi rend="italic">Jour. Λnthrop. Inst.,</hi> ix. p. 290.</p></note> There are
                    other terms for bundles of sugar-canes, rows (planted) of yams, &amp;c.; and
                    sometimes things are counted by threes. Ten is two fives, 15 three fives, 20 is
                    a “man” (ten fingers and ten toes), 100 is “five men,” and so on.</p>
                <p>The free white population, settlers and miners, numbers about 3000; officials and
                    troops, 3000; transportés and déportés (ordinary and political convicts), with
                    their families, 4000 and 6700 respectively. Some of the planters and graziers
                    are fairly prosperous, but the material development of the country does not
                    advance rapidly. There seems a general want of energy, a deficiency of banking
                    facilities and of roads and means of transport. It is in fact found difficult to
                    work the settlement both as a free and as a penal colony. The larger proprietors
                    are free immigrants, but are being swamped by the more numerous small ones, who
                    are “libérés,” holding small concessions, and bound—theoretically at least—not
                    to leave the country. The déportés and transportés are under separate
                    regulations. The latter when well-behaved are hired out to the free settlers at
                    12 francs a month. The libérés either receive a very small allowance from
                    Government, or are permitted to take service, receiving 30 to 50 francs a month,
                    with their board. The sending out of the families of convicts, with the view to
                    promote settlement, has not answered well. Free concessions are offered with the
                    same object, especially to retired officials and others. Large concessions have
                    also been made to agricultural colonies, which have mostly failed. The
                    agricultural establishments worked by convicts have answered better, the lands
                    belonging partly to colonists, and the convict labourers eventually obtaining a
                    certain status, and permission to marry. Out of a total area of about 1,600,000
                    hectares, half is unfit for cultivation or pasture. Up to 1877,130,965 hectares
                    were taken up, and probably half the available land is now taken. The miners in
                    New Caledonia are chiefly Australians, but out of several hundred concessions of
                    mines, chiefly nickel, only a few have been worked. The intention of the French
                    Government to send yearly to New Caledonia 5000 <hi rend="italic"
                    >récidivistes</hi> or habitual criminals, to be released after three years’
                    detention, causes serious uneasiness in Australia.</p>
                <p>The trade was valued in 1874 at 13,471,000 francs, the imports being three times
                    the value of the exports, and the greater part carried in foreign vessels.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Principal Authorities.—</hi> Ch. Lemire, <hi rend="italic">La
                    Colonisation</hi><hi rend="italic">Française en Nouvelle Calédonie-,</hi>
                    papers—(geological) by Jules Garnier in <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Mines,</hi> 1867, and by Herteau, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ibid.,</hi> 1876, and (anthropological) by Dr Bourgarel in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mém.</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Soc. &lt;Γ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Anthropologie</hi><hi rend="italic">de Paris,</hi> vol. i.; Dr J. Patouillet,
                    <hi rend="italic">Trois ans en Nouvelle Calédonie.</hi> (C. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
