<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0397-0380-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NEWCASTLE, Dukes of (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    380)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938095">Garters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1035984">Nephews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n397/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NEWCASTLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Dukes of</hi></label>. Within
                    the space of a century there were no less than four successive creations of
                    dukes of Newcastle. William Cavendish, nephew of the first earl of Devonshire,
                    was raised to the dignity of duke of Newcastle-upon-Tyne in 1664. His son and
                    successor Henry died leaving daughters only, and one of these married John
                    Holies, earl of Clare, who was created duke in 1694. This duke died also without
                    male issue in 1711, leaving his estates to his sister’s son Thomas Pelham, who,
                    with other dignities, had the title of duke of Newcastle-upon-Tyne conferred on
                    him in 1715, and a second and similar ducal title (that of Newcastle-under-Lyme)
                    in 1757. His first dukedom became extinct at his death, but the second title was
                    granted him with remainder to the earl of Lincoln, at once his nephew and
                    nephew-in-law, whose descendants (Pelham-Cliutons) have been dukes of
                    Newcastle-under-Lyme in direct lineal succession down to the present time. Two
                    of the dukes of Newcastle, and one duchess, call for separate notice :—</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">William Cavendish, duke of Newcastle</hi> (1592- 1676),
                    son of Sir Charles Cavendish, youngest brother of the first earl of Devonshire,
                    by Catherine, daughter of Cuthbert Lord Ogle, was born in 1592. In his early
                    years he showed little inclination for study, and while at St John’s College,
                    Cambridge, he took “more delight in sports than in learning.” At an early age he
                    acquired marvellous proficiency in horsemanship and weapons, “which increased
                    much his father’s hopes of his future perfections.” His personal beauty and
                    manly accomplishments gained him special favour at the court of James I., who,
                    when his son Henry in 1610 was created prince of Wales, made Cavendish a knight
                    of the Bath. Ten years afterwards he became Viscount Mansfield and in 1628 earl
                    of Newcastle-upon-Tyne. In 1638 he was appointed by Charles I. governor of
                    Charles, prince of Wales. When the king in 1639 visited Scotland, he was
                    entertained with great splendour by the earl of Newcastle at Welbeck. On the
                    outbreak of the civil war the earl was appointed governor of the town of
                    Newcastle and the four neighbouring counties, and a short time afterwards he was
                    named general of the forces north of the Trent. In this position his energy and
                    circumspection proved invaluable to the royal cause. For his victory over
                    Fairfax at Adderton Heath, near Bradford, June 30, 1643, he was created marquis.
                    The Parliamentary generals were step by step losing their hold on the north, and
                    were reduced to the hardest straits, when they were relieved by a Scottish army
                    under the earl of Leven. Newcastle had to fall back on York, where he was
                    closely besieged when Prince Rupert hurried to his assistance. Contrary to his
                    advice Prince Rupert risked the battle of Marston Moor, which resulted in the
                    utter rout of the royal forces and the ruin of the king’s cause in the north of
                    England. Newcastle, with about eighty gentlemen, retired to the Continent. He
                    returned with Charles II. at the Restoration, when he was appointed chief
                    justice of the counties north of the Trent, and in 1664 he was created duke.
                    From this time, however, he ceased to take an active part in political life,
                    occupying himself chiefly with literary pursuits and the retrievement of his
                    broken fortunes. He died December 25, 1676, and was buried in Westminster
                    Abbey.</p>
                <p>Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Even Song</hi> is dedicated to Newcastle in very
                    eulogistic terms. The duke, besides publishing <hi rend="italic">A New Method
                    and Extraordinary Invention to Dress Horses,</hi> 1667, which had previously
                    appeared in 1657 in French, was the author of several comedies, including <hi
                    rend="italic">TheExile</hi> (doubtful); <hi rend="italic">The Country
                    Captain,</hi> 1649; <hi rend="italic">Variety,</hi> 1649; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Humorous Lovers,</hi> 1677. He also translated Moliere’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >L'Étourdi</hi> under the title <hi rend="italic">Sir Martin Mar-All.</hi> His
                    wife’s <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of him is noticed below.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Margaret Lucas, duchess of Newcastle (c.</hi>
                    1625-1673), second wife of the duke of Newcastle noticed above, was born about
                    1625, the youngest daughter of Thomas Lucas of St John’s, near Colchester,
                    Essex. She joined the court at Oxford in 1643 as maid of honour tα Henrietta
                    Maria, and met there the marquis (afterwards duke) of Newcastle, whom she
                    married at Paris in 1645, after the battle of Marston Moor. Throughout life they
                    continued to cherish a mutual admiration of a very exaggerated character, each
                    regarding the other as endowed with transcendent merits both of person and mind.
                    The duchess cultivated literary composition with exuberant fervour, and kept a
                    bevy of maids of honour obliged to <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n398/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0398-0381"/> be ready at all hours “to register her Grace’s
                    conceptions.” Walpole speaks of her as a “fertile pedant” with an “Unbounded
                    passion for scribbling”; and, although giving evidence of learning, ingenuity,
                    and imagination, her writings are fatally marred by a deficiency in judgment and
                    self-restraint.</p>
                <p>She is best known by <hi rend="italic">The, Life, of the Thrice Noble, High, and
                    Puissant Prince, William Cavendish, Duke, Marquess, and Earl of Newcastle;
                    written by the Thrice Noble,</hi><hi rend="italic">Illustriores,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and Excellent Princess, Margaret, Duchess of Newcastle, his
                    Wife,</hi> originally printed by A. Maxwell at London in 1667. She also
                    published <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Fancies,</hi> 1653; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poems and Fancies,</hi> 1653; <hi rend="italic">The World's Olio,</hi> 1655;
                    <hi rend="italic">Nature's Picture drawn by</hi><hi rend="italic">Fande'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">s Pencil to the Life,</hi> which includes an autobiography, 1656;
                    <hi rend="italic">Philosophical and Physical Opinions,</hi> 1655; <hi
                    rend="italic">Orations,</hi> 1662; <hi rend="italic">Plays,</hi> 1662; <hi
                    rend="italic">Sodable Letters,</hi> 1664; <hi rend="italic">Observations upon
                    Experimental Philosophy,</hi> 1666; <hi rend="italic">Letters and Poems,</hi>
                    1676. Her <hi rend="italic">Select Poems</hi> were edited by Brydges in 1813,
                    and her <hi rend="italic">Autobiography</hi> in 1814. The latter, edited by
                    Lower, was published along with her <hi rend="italic">Life of the Duke of
                    Newcastle</hi> in 1872.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Pelham</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Holles,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">duke of Newcastle</hi>
                    (1693-1768), who was for thirty years one of the two secretaries of state, and
                    for seven more prime minister, and whose official life extended throughout the
                    Whig supremacy of the 18th century, was the elder son of Thomas, first Lord
                    Pelham, by his second wife Lady Grace Holies, younger sister of John Holies,
                    duke of Newcastle-on-Tyne. Born in 1693, he was educated at Westminster and at
                    Clare Hall, Cambridge. In 1711 his uncle the duke of Newcastle died, and left
                    the whole of his vast estates to him. In 1712 he also succeeded his father in
                    his peerage and estates, and in 1714, when he came of age, was one of the
                    greatest landowners in the kingdom. He vigorously sustained the Whig party at
                    Queen Anne’s death, and had much influence in making the Londoners accept King
                    George. His services were too great to be neglected, and in 1714 he was created
                    earl of Clare, and in 1715 duke of Newcastle in Northumberland. He also became
                    lord-lieutenant of the counties of Middlesex and Nottingham and a knight of the
                    Garter in 1718, in which year he increased his Whig connexion by marrying Lady
                    Henrietta Godolphin, granddaughter of the great duke of Marlborough. In 1717 he
                    first held political office as lord chamberlain of the household, and in 1724
                    was chosen by Sir Robert Walpole to be secretary of state in place of Lord
                    Carteret. This office he held continuously for thirty years (1724-1754), and
                    only changed it for the premiership on his brother’s death. His long tenure of
                    office has been attributed to his great Whig connexions and his wealth, but some
                    praise must be given to his inexhaustible activity and great powers of debate.
                    He was a peculiarly muddle-headed man, and unhappy if he had not more to do than
                    he could possibly manage, but at the same time he was a consummate master of
                    parliamentary tactics, and knew how to manage the Houses of Lords and Commons
                    alike. Lord Hervey compares him with Walpole in 1735, and says—“We have one
                    minister that does everything with the same seeming ease and tranquillity as if
                    he were doing nothing; we have another that does nothing in the same hurry and
                    agitation as if he did everything.” He continued in office on Walpole’s fall in
                    1742, and became more powerful on his younger brother Henry becoming prime
                    minister in 1743. On Henry Pelham’s death in March 1754, Newcastle succeeded him
                    as premier; but people who had been accustomed to him as secretary of state
                    would not stand him as premier, and in November 1756 he gave place to the duke
                    of Devonshire. For his long services he was created duke of
                    Newcastle-under-Lyme, with remainder to the earl of Lincoln, who had married his
                    niece Catherine Pelham. In July 1757 he again became prime minister —for Pitt,
                    though a great statesman, was a bad party leader—on the understanding, according
                    to Horace Walpole, that “Mr Pitt does everything, the duke gives everything.”
                    Under this ministry England became famous abroad, but it gradually fell before
                    the young king’s affection for Lord Bute, who, after supplanting Pitt, became
                    prime minister in the room of Newcastle in May 1762. The duke went into strong
                    opposition, and lost his two lord-lieutenancies for opposing the peace of 1763.
                    In 1765 he became lord privy seal for a few months, but his health was fast
                    giving way, and he died in August 1768. The duke was certainly not a great man,
                    but he must have possessed far more ability than has generally been allowed to
                    have maintained office as long as he did; he was industrious and energetic, and
                    to his credit be it said that the statesman who almost monopolized the patronage
                    of office for half a century twice refused a pension, and finally left office
                    £300,000 poorer than he entered it.</p>
                <p>The best authority for the duke of Newcastle’s life is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memoirs of the Administration of the Right Hon. H. Pelham,</hi> by the Ven. W.
                    Coxe, 1829. See also the histories of his time, and such books as Lord Hervey’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> and Horace Walpole’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
