<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0545-0504-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NILE (9th edition, volume 17, page 504)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1431877">Bakers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1054286">Pashas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210282">Uganda</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240375">Moon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205830">Ethiopia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240674">Tropics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208478">Chad</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205669">Jordan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882n4f">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n545/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NILE</label>. This mighty river,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plate XV. shows the river system south of the
                    Tropic of Cancer. For the Egyptian portion see Plate VI., vol. vii.</p></note>
                    which after a course of 3370 miles pours into the Mediterranean a low-water
                    current of 61,500 cubic feet per second, has its cradle in the Victoria Nyanza,
                    an enormous lake in Central Africa where the line of the equator is crossed by
                    32°, 33°, and 34° of E. long., somewhere about 4000 feet above the sea. The
                    Victoria Nyanza<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Nyanza
                    means water or lake. Other names are—Nyanza Kerewe- (Linant), Neraa Bali
                    (Baker), Luero lo Luta Nzige, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “white with dead
                    locusts” (Speke), Bahari ya Pila or “Second Lake” and Bahari ya Ukara (of the
                    Sawahili), and Sea of L <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> kerewe (of the
                    Arabs).</p></note> measures 230 miles from north to south and 220 from east to
                    west. Its coast-line, which is very irregular, cannot be less than 2000 miles;
                    its water area is estimated at 27,000 miles, and its very islands have an
                    aggregate area of 1400 square miles. The physical features of the shores vary
                    greatly from district to district.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>A description will be found in Wilson and Felkin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Uganda and the Egyptian Soudan,</hi> vol. i. p. 250-54.</p></note>
                    At the south-east corner is Speke Gulf, about 60 miles, long, formed partly by a
                    deep indentation of the mainland and partly by the peninsular island of Ukerewe,
                    which is. separated from the mainland by Rugisi or Rugeshi Strait, a. narrow and
                    shallow channel about f mile long, overgrown, with rushes, papyrus, and a fine
                    network of grass which undulates beneath the foot. Bukindo is the chief village
                    on the island, which forms the territory of a separate ruler. Its inhabitants
                    murdered Lieutenant G. Shergold Smith, R.N., and Mr O’Neill, members of the
                    1876-77 expedition of the Church Missionary Society. To the north of Ukerewe
                    lies Ukara, for the most part barren, and with two rugged hills rising 200 or
                    300 feet. The natives average less than 5 feet in height (Wilson and Felkin, i.
                    pp. 99-101). Along the south and south-west coasts is a whole series of
                    islands—notably Komeh, Mysomeh, Bumbireh, and Bukerebe or Alice Island; but of
                    much more importance is the great Sesse Archipelago off the coasts of western
                    Uganda. At first entered on our maps as a single great island, it has turned out
                    to be (according to King Mtesa’s possibly somewhat exaggerated statement) a
                    cluster of four hundred mostly inhabited islands, some of the largest being 10
                    to 15 miles in length and 3 to 4 miles in breadth. Clothed as they generally are
                    with forest,, and fringed along the shore with papyrus or low jungle, they often
                    present scenes of the richest tropical luxuriance. Along the east half of the
                    northern coast are a number of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n548/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0548-0505"/> considerable islands such as Usuguru, and, at the
                    head of Napoleon Channel, Uvuma, famous for the canoe contest waged between its
                    inhabitants and King Mtesa of Uganda, of which Mr Stanley was spectator. Ugingo,
                    on the east coast, is a large island separated like Ukerewe by a narrow channel
                    from the mainland. Though when its extent is taken into account Victoria Nyanza
                    may be described as shallow in contrast to such basins as those of Tanganyika,
                    the depth, especially on the eastern side, appears to be very considerable,
                    Stanley giving 275 and even 580 feet not far from the shore. Of the affluents of
                    the lake a few only require to be mentioned. The Shimiyu, which falls into the
                    south side of Speke Gulf, was described by Stanley (March 1875) as a magnificent
                    flood a mile wide receiving the waters of the Monangah, the Luwamberri, and the
                    Duma, and having a course of 300 miles. If this were the case it would take the
                    southmost point of the Nile system as far at least as between 4° and 5° S. lat.
                    But when Lieutenant Shergold Smith saw the Shimiyu in 1876 he found it a
                    comparatively insignificant stream, and if the altitudes observed by Smith and
                    Pearson be correct it cannot be the recipient of the Luwamberri and the
                    Monangah. Instead of the Shimiyu, either the Wami (or Kiye) or the Muinguira
                    (Isanga or Isanda), both of which flow into Jordans Creek,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Named not after the Jordan, but after Speke’s
                    country-house, Jordans, in Somersetshire.</p></note> may be the southmost feeder
                    of the Nile. Of much more importance as a tributary than any of these is the
                    Kagera (of the Waganda), otherwise known as the Kitangule, Kitangure (Burton),
                    Tengure (Grant), or Alexandra Nile (Stanley), a river 450 feet wide and 85 feet
                    deep at its mouth, with a strong current, apparently pouring into the lake more
                    water than is carried off by the Nile. It may be navigated for about 50 miles,
                    and is believed to have its sources between 200 and 300 miles to the south-west.
                    There are several lakes along its course—Lake Windermere, Lake Thema, and the
                    larger Lake Alexandra not yet reached by Europeans.</p>
                <p>The leading fact in regard to the position of Victoria Nyanza in the general
                    hydrography of Central Africa is that by none of its affluents is it connected
                    with any of the other great <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> equatorial” lakes.
                    Tanganyika<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tanganyika
                    level is 2610 feet according to Joseph Thomson.</p></note> lies in a trough
                    about 1400 feet lower. Between the Victoria and Lake Nyassa (Zambesi system)
                    there is a stretch of 500 miles; and, though a large lake, part of which Stanley
                    saw in 1876, and named Gulf Beatrice, lies to the west, it forms in all
                    probability a distinct basin.</p>
                <p>In 1875 Stanley proved that the only outflow from Victoria Nyanza was by the
                    Ripon Falls on the north side of the lake. These falls (named after Earl de Grey
                    and Ripon, president of the Royal Geographical Society in 1859) were discovered
                    July 28, 1862, by Captain Speke, but from native accounts he was led to believe
                    that other streams (such as the Luajerri) issued from the lake. The Nile, as it
                    drops about 12 feet over the rocks, has a breadth of 400 to 500 feet, divided
                    into several sections by a number of wooded isles. For the next 300 miles the
                    Victoria Nile or Somerset River, as this section is called, has all the
                    character of a mountain stream racing swiftly along a rocky channel often walled
                    in by cliffs (at times 180 feet high) and broken by picturesque islands and
                    countless rapids. At first for 117 miles its course is north-northwest, but
                    reaching the Khor Kafu (on which Mruli stands), about l <hi rend="superscript">
                    o</hi> 38' N. lat. and 32° 20' E. long., it takes the north-east direction of
                    this channel, and it is not till 2° N. lat. that it again turns north-west
                    towards the Albert Nyanza. About 52 miles below the Ripon Falls, Long, who in
                    1874 boated from Urondogani to Foweira, describes himself as having passed
                    through a lake 20 to 25 miles broad; but this expanse, which appears in
                    text-books and maps (sometimes as two lakes, Kaja and Ibrahim Lakes), may have
                    been the result of a mere temporary overflow. At Karuma, below Foweira, the
                    river falls over a wall-like ledge of rock 5 feet high which extends right
                    across its bed. But the great feature of the Victoria Nile is the Murchison
                    Fall, about 2° 18' N. lat. and 3Γ 50' E. long., where the river rages furiously
                    through a rock-bound pass, and plunges at one leap of about 120 feet into a
                    gloomy abyss. Below this point, continuing between steep forest-covered hills,
                    it gradually calms down into a stream so slow and steady that at certain seasons
                    it is only from the scarcely perceptible drifting of the little green
                    water-plants, called <hi rend="italic">Pistia Stratiotes,</hi><note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Pistia
                    Stratiotes</hi> is characteristic of the Bahr al-Jebel. It is found drifting far
                    down the White Nile, but, according to Steudner, does not occur in the Bahr
                    al-Ghazâl.</p></note><hi rend="italic superscript"> z</hi> that the flow can be
                    observed. About 20 or 25 miles below the fall it enters the north end of the
                    Albert Nyanza.</p>
                <p>This lake<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Otherwise known
                    [as the Mwutan Nzige (Locust Lake) and the Luta Nzige (Dead Locust).</p></note>
                    was first reached by Baker on March 14,1864, near Vacovia on the east coast, a
                    small village of fishermen and salt-makers. From a granitic cliff 1500 feet
                    above the water he looked out over a boundless horizon on the south and
                    south-west, and towards the west descried at a distance of 50 or 60 miles, blue
                    mountains about 7000 feet high.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The descriptive phrase “blue mountains” has since been
                    converted into a geographical name, “Blue Mountains.”</p></note> The Albert
                    Nyanza was consequently entered on his map as a vast lake extending from 2° S.
                    lat. to 2° 50' N. lat., or a distance of about 380 miles. But the
                    circumnavigation of the lake by Gessi Pasha (1876), Mason Bey, and Dr Emin Bey
                    leaves no doubt that its real dimensions are—length 97 miles, average breadth 22
                    miles, and area about 2000 square miles. The western shore is in its northern
                    half overhung by lofty and precipitous mountains, but farther south is formed by
                    a wide forest-clad plain. At the south end the water is very shallow and
                    encumbered by a vast stretch of ambatch forest. Instead of the lake being, as
                    Baker contended, one of the great sources of the Nile, its functions are those
                    of a large backwater. Of course a considerable amount of drainage must reach it
                    from the surrounding high grounds, though the lakeward slopes are not very
                    extensive; but none of its tributaries appear to be of much importance as
                    feeders of the main stream. Along the western shore the depth is from 15 to 20
                    feet.</p>
                <p>Escaping by an island-studded channel from the northwest corner of the Albert
                    Nyanza, the Nile, which now takes the name of Bahr al-Jebel, or River of the
                    Mountains, continues to flow in a general northward direction. From Magungo to
                    Dufile (Dufli), 128 miles, its course is wonderfully smooth, and forms a series
                    of lake-like reaches. Below Dufile the high lands close in upon the river,
                    which, from a width of a mile at Dufile, narrows to 400 or 500 yards, and rushes
                    through a gorge. Near Mugi (50 miles below Dufile) are the formidable Yarborah
                    rapids. From Kiri (Kerrie)—an Egyptian fort on an eminence 1500 feet high on the
                    left bank—the river is again navigable, but flows with so strong a current that
                    Mr Felkin’s boat took only three and a half hours to reach Bedden, a distance of
                    some 30 miles. At Bedden a line of hills runs right athwart the channel, which
                    is divided by an island of great beauty. An iron rope ferry was established by
                    Gordon at this point, and without it the river could not be crossed. Between
                    Bedden and Rejaf (12 miles) the hills give place to park-like plains dotted with
                    large trees. About 15 miles below Rejaf, Gondokoro is passed on the right hand,
                    and there the traveller may still see the ruins of the old mission church, the
                    earthworks of Baker’s camp, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n549/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0549-0506"/> and the lemon grove from which the fruit has been
                    distributed throughout the equatorial provinces. At this point the river, about
                    656 feet wide, is divided by a large island. Eight miles farther down lies Lado
                    (often spelled Lardo) on the left bank, a well-built Egyptian town with houses
                    of burnt brick and a considerable area of cultivated land watered by shadûfs.
                    With the hill to the west of Lado, variously called Nyerkani and Luyola, the
                    mountainous region ends, and the river enters on a vast plain. The affluents
                    which it has hitherto received are for the most part short and individually
                    insignificant <hi rend="italic">Ichors</hi> (temporary streams), but two at
                    least deserve a few words of description. TheUnyama, joining the river opposite
                    J. Kuku or Neri, 10 miles below Duffle, is a perennial stream rising in the
                    prairies between Fatiko and Unyoro, and winding through a lovely country for
                    about 80 miles. The Asua (Atza of the Madi), whose mouth is 20 miles farther
                    down on the same side, is about 120 paces broad, and flows through a rocky bed
                    15 feet deep. As it receives nearly the whole drainage of the Madi and Shua
                    countries and various districts farther east, it becomes in the rainy season a
                    deep and furious torrent. The Atabbi or Atappi (the main drain of the western
                    face of the Shuli mountains) reaches the Asua a short distance above the
                    mouth.</p>
                <p>The great plain which the Nile enters below Lado, about 5° N. lat., slopes so
                    gradually towards the north that the river falls only 300 feet in a stretch of
                    more than 650 miles between Gondokoro and Khartoum. As the river has gradually
                    raised the level of both bed and banks, an overflow takes place, and lagoons or
                    side channels <hi rend="italic">(may ds)</hi> are formed wherever the bank
                    breaks down; and as these, from their position, naturally act as settling-ponds
                    they get rapidly silted up.</p>
                <p>Up to about 7° 25' N. lat., in spite of this condition of things, the Nile
                    maintains a fairly definite course, with a considerable depth of water in its
                    main current, but at this point it splits up into two branches as if to form a
                    delta. The left branch, which retains the name Bahr al-Jebel, but which may be
                    conveniently distinguished by the Denka name of Kir, continues in the line of
                    the river, and the right branch, or Bahr al-Zerâf (Giraffe River), tends rather
                    more towards the east. After flowing respectively about 160 and 140 miles, they
                    reach the Bahr al-Ghazâl, slowly gliding east with a slight deflexion to the
                    south. The whole region is a vast expanse of low swampy lands crossed by
                    secondary channels, and flooded for many miles in the rainy season. At the
                    junction of the Bahr al-Ghazâl and the Kir the permanently submerged area is
                    usually named Lake No on our maps, but the Arabs simply call it the
                    confluence—Mokren al-Bohιir. The scenes presented by this portion of the Nile
                    are of the most peculiar description. The dark and ill-smelling water shows no
                    sign of motion. On all sides stretch monotonous reaches of omm sùf <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> woolly) grass <hi rend="italic">( Vossia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">procera)</hi> and papyrus, rising 20 or 30 feet above the water so
                    as often to close the view like a stone wall; the level of the plain is broken
                    only at intervals by little mounds of earth, tenanted for the most part by white
                    ants, and covered with a clump of brushwood or trees;<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The ordinary theory is that these mounds are
                    hills constructed by the white ants; but Marno considers them as more probably
                    portions which have resisted the general process of degradation.</p></note> the
                    moisture in the air is so excessive that gunpowder left in the guns overnight is
                    reduced to a paste; mosquitoes and other swamp flies swarm in myriads. And yet
                    touches of beauty are not wanting. Water-lilies <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Nymplιeea</hi><hi rend="italic">stellata</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nympheea
                    Lotus)—</hi> white, blue, and crimson—often adorn the surface of the stream;
                    multitudes of water-fowl, from the familiar Egyptian duck and the pelican to the
                    rare and odd-looking <hi rend="italic">Balaenicevs</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >rex</hi> (abfi markιib), breed among the reeds, and at night the scene is lit
                    up by a very firmament of fire-flies.</p>
                <p>Previous to 1863 both the Kir and the Bahr al-Zerâf had been navigable within the
                    memory of man. But when the Tinné expedition passed down the river in March of
                    that year, the White Nile, the united current of the Bahr al-Jebel and the Bahr
                    al-Ghazâl, was found to be blocked by an accumulation of vegetable flotsam, and
                    it cost the crew two days’ hard labour to take their vessel through a channel
                    partially cleared by their predecessors. The obstruction rapidly increased, and
                    thirty vessels had to be employed for five weeks to open a permanent passage. In
                    1865 Baker found a dam about f of a mile wide already overgrown with reeds and
                    grass so as to form a continuation of the surrounding country. Matters went from
                    bad to worse, and the White Nile, the Kir, and the Bahr al-Zerâf were all
                    rendered impassable till, in 1874, Ismael Ayub Pasha cleared the main route by
                    the White Nile and the Kir. But in 1878 again the whole Nile rose to an unusual
                    height (the banks at Lado, 15 to 20 feet above the mean level, were overflowed),
                    and enormous quantities of vegetable debris were carried off by the current. A
                    formation of bars on an unprecedented scale was the result, and communication
                    between the upper and lower Nile was not restored till 1880.</p>
                <p>If the Kir and the White Nile, with their comparatively strong current, were thus
                    obstructed, it was natural that the more sluggish Bahr al-Ghazâl should contain
                    more extensive though less compact accumulations. In 1881 Gessi Pasha spent
                    three and a half months on a part of the voyage usually performed in five hours,
                    and lost half of his men by starvation. Between the mouths of the Kir and Bahr
                    al- <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> Arab there were twenty distinct dams.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See E. Marno, “Die
                    Sumpfregion des äquat. Nil systems,” in <hi rend="italic">Pet. Mitth.,</hi>
                    1881, and another paper in 1882.</p></note></p>
                <p>Sir Samuel Baker asserted in 1874 that from the equator to the Mediterranean not
                    a drop of water reached the Nile from the west,—the Bahr al-Ghazâl being only a
                    channel of stagnant pools and marshes <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Roy. Geog.
                    Soc.,</hi> 1873-74, p. 148). But if their total contribution be of little moment
                    in comparison with that of their eastern rivals, the western affluents are
                    exceedingly numerous, and drain a wide extent of country. Their relative
                    importance has been shown by Schweinfurth, Junker, Emin Bey, &amp;c. One or
                    two—the Rodi (Lau) and the Rohl—join the Bahr al-Jebel in its passage through
                    the plain, but by far the greater number converge to the Bahr al-Ghazâl. At its
                    lowest state, just before the commencement of the rains, this river had in 1881
                    a depth varying from 20 to 25 feet, though in many places no perceptible
                    current. It is generally navigable to Meshrat-el-Rek, about 200 or 220 miles
                    above the mouth of the Kir, and in the rainy season even small steamers may
                    ascend its tributary, the Dyur or Jur, as far as Wau. In exceptionally dry
                    seasons the channel at Meshrat-el-Rek is so utterly desiccated that
                    drinking-water can be obtained only by digging. One of the main feeders of the
                    Bahr al-Ghazâl is the Bahr al- <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> Arab, which is
                    formed by the drainage of southern Darfùr, has a breadth—about 10° 20' N. lat.
                    and 25° 20' E. long, (before it receives any of its right hand affluents)—of 360
                    feet and a depth (in December) of 4 feet, and never quite dries up even in the
                    heat of summer (Felkin, <hi rend="italic">Uganda,</hi> ii. 239). This is the
                    only considerable accession from the north: the rest of the affluents, an almost
                    countless host if all the small headstreams be included, have their rise in the
                    range of mountainous country which stretches, from the Blue Mountains of the
                    Albert Nyanza and their southern continuation, in.a general north-east direction
                    as far as 25° or 26° E. long., and forms the watershed between the Nile basin
                    and those <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n550/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0550-0507"/> probably of Lake Chad and the Congo. Flowing in
                    many cases for 400 or 500 miles, these streams in the upper part of their course
                    are of considerable volume and of much importance in the economy of the
                    countries which they traverse.</p>
                <p>About 95 miles below the junction of the Kir, and 30 below that of the Bahr
                    al-Zerâf, the White Nile receives its first great affluent from the east. The
                    Sobât, as it is called, has its headwaters (largely unexplored) distributed over
                    a wide area—the southmost rising possibly as far south as 4° N. lat. in the
                    hilly country of Atuka, the eastmost in Kaffa, and the northmost about 9° in the
                    Berta mountains.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    connexion of the Godjeb or Omo with the Sobât, first suggested by Beke in 1841,
                    and strongly opposed by Von Klöden, is still matter of doubt.</p></note> On one
                    of them there is probably a considerable lake: first inserted as Baro Lake on
                    our maps by Petermann on the report of a slave dealer, it was expunged by
                    Matteucci; but Schuver claims to have seen it from the mountains to the north,
                    and proposes to call it Haarlem Lake. The Sobât proper is navigable from June to
                    November as far as Nasser (180 miles), an Egyptian port established by Gordon in
                    1874, and even, it is said, for three days farther, though it divides into four
                    branches a short distance above this point. Junker, who visited Nasser<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Naser, <hi rend="italic"
                    >locus</hi><hi rend="italic">ubi torrentes fluunt</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic">alveum.</hi></p></note> in 1876, found the river 15 to
                    20 feet deep, flowing at the rate of 80 paces per minute between banks high
                    enough to prevent any general inundation. At the mouth of the Sobât there is an
                    Egyptian post of the same name (see <hi rend="italic">Zeitschr.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">Ges. f. Εrdk.,</hi> Berlin, 1877).</p>
                <p>The northward progress of the White Nile for the next 300 miles is through a
                    great plain stretching from the spurs of the Abyssinian highlands in the east to
                    the hilly districts of Takalla and Kordofan in the west, and consisting almost
                    exclusively of red and other sandstone, often flat as a pavement. Escaping from
                    the swampy region, the river again forms a well-marked channel, with regular and
                    sometimes high banks. Throughout the whole distance indicated a striking
                    confirmation of Baer’s law is afforded,—the fairway or deeper side of the stream
                    generally keeping to the eastern shore. About 60 miles below the Sobât mouth
                    lies (on the right bank) Fashoda, an Egyptain town founded in 1867 on the site
                    of Denab, the old “capital” of the Shilluks. In the neighbourhood of Mahadat Abu
                    Zaid (about 13° 5' N. lat.) begin the Sunt Islands, so called from the Arab name
                    for the <hi rend="italic">Acacia nilotica,</hi> a tree characteristic of the
                    White Nile.</p>
                <p>At Khartoum (Khartùm), in 15° 37' N. lat., the "White Nile is joined by its
                    greatest eastern confluent the Blue Nile<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>At Khartoum the water of the one river has a milky-limy
                    appearance, that of the other is clear and blue, except when in flood, when it
                    gains a reddish-yellow from its alluvial burden.</p></note> (Bahr el-Azrak).
                    This river has its head reservoir in Lake Tana (Tsana), which is so situated
                    that the lines of 12° N. lat. and 37° 2' E. long, cut it into four nearly equal
                    portions.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Lake Tana has
                    been explored by Bruce, Blanc, De Cosson, Piaggia, Stecker, &amp;c</p></note>
                    The height of the lake is 5658 feet (Rohlfs). From east to west the breadth is
                    about 40 miles, and the area is estimated at 2980 square miles. Between Dega and
                    Zegi a depth of 236 feet has been found, and between Korata and Zegi 219. The
                    Blue Nile, or Abai as it is called in Abyssinia, rises on the northward slopes
                    of a cluster of mountains (Mount Gesh, &amp;c.) about 11° N. lat., and flowing
                    northwards enters Lake Tana near the southwest corner, to issue again at no
                    great distance. Of the multitudinous ramifications by which the Abai and its
                    tributaries drain a large part of the Abyssinian plateau, a better idea will be
                    obtained from the map than from any description. From east and south and north
                    the mountain streams pour down into the river,—its eastmost tributary probably
                    rising east of Magdala, and its southmost between 8° and 9° N. lat. At Fazokl or
                    Famaka, 11° 17' N, lat., it begins to escape from the mountains; about 130 miles
                    farther down, after passing Rosaires and Karkoj on the right and Sennaar on the
                    left, it is joined by the Dinder; and 35 miles more bring it to the confluence
                    of the Rahad (Ra <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> ad) and the town of Abu Haraz.
                    Beyond this point it flows through the most fertile portion of the Egyptian
                    Soudan, the plain on the left hand more especially being a great grain-growing
                    district. The total length of the Abai or Blue Nile may be estimated at 960
                    miles.</p>
                <p>On the north-west side of the mountains which enclose Lake Tana are some of the
                    headwaters of the Atbara, another important tributary of the Nile; but it does
                    not reach the main stream till about 17° 41' N. lat., or 200 miles below
                    Khartoum. Its principal branch, the Settit or Takazze, has a course of about 420
                    miles through the Abyssinian plateau before it joins or (more strictly) is
                    joined by the river which gives its name to the united stream. The Khor-el-Gash,
                    or Mareb, though a considerable river in its upper regions, reaches the Atbara
                    (and thus the Nile, of which it is the northmost affluent) only during a heavy
                    rainy season (see James, JFz7&lt;Z <hi rend="italic">Tribes of the Soudan,</hi>
                    1883). A large number of these eastern tributaries are mountain torrents, of
                    enormous volume and impetuosity during the rains, and for a short time
                    afterwards, but rapidly dwindling again into mere threads of water or chains of
                    pools, and leaving the rocks and sand of their deep-cut channels as dry and
                    parched as the surrounding desert. No one who has read it will easily forget Sir
                    Samuel Baker’s graphic account of the deep pool in the bed of the Atbara into
                    which the fishes, tortoises, crocodiles, and hippopotami from a long reach of
                    the river had gradually been crowded as the water disappeared, and of the sudden
                    release effected by the return of the rainy season.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Baker, <hi rend="italic">Abyssinian
                    Tributaries of the Nile.</hi></p></note> A more recent traveller, Herr Schuver,
                    had a similar experience on the Tumat, the southern tributary of the Blue
                    Nile.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi
                    rend="italic">Petermann s Mittheilungen,</hi> 1883; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Erg.-Heft,</hi> No. 72.</p></note></p>
                <p>After receiving the Atbara the Nile continues for 650 miles through the Nubian
                    desert, where the volume of the river suffers continual diminution from the
                    extreme dryness of the air, without being recruited by a single drop of water.
                    Between Berber (an important town on the right bank 30 miles below the Atbara)
                    and Wâdy Haifa (about 600 miles) rapids and cataracts follow at intervals. The
                    highest of these, the fifth cataract of the Nile, is situated about 40 miles
                    below Berber, the fourth, 170 miles farther down, below Shitab, the third, 230
                    miles farther, at Hannek, and the second just above Wâdy Haifa. At Assuan (200
                    miles lower) are the first cataracts. Beyond that point the river flows through
                    the wonderful valley which has already been described in the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Egypt.</hi></p>
                <p>Reduced to its simplest expression, the Nile system may be said to consist of a
                    great steady flowing river fed by the rains of the tropics, controlled by the
                    existence of a vast head reservoir and several areas of repose, and annually
                    flooded by the accession of a great body of water with which its eastern
                    tributaries are flushed. The following details will enable the reader to
                    estimate the hydrographic value of the different portions:<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Cf.</hi> Keith Johnston,
                    <hi rend="italic">Africa,</hi> Appendix.</p></note> —</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Victoria Nyanza</hi> lies in a zone where rain falls all the
                    year round. At Kagei (south shore) the lake was seen by Mr Wilson in 1877 to be
                    slowly rising in the middle of February, and it had attained its maximum (2
                    feet) about the middle of May, ten days after the rain had ceased. The total
                    rainfall of this zone is not excessive. Speke’s estimate of 49 inches is
                    confirmed by Mr Wilson’s much longer experience. In Uganda there are two maximum
                    periods— March to May, and September to November.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Assua</hi> is important from 15th April to 15th
                    November.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Bahr al-Jebel,</hi> at Gondokoro, begins to rise in April,
                    and <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n551/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0551-0508"/> gradually attains a maximum of 4⅜ feet, the river
                    being then 6 to 10 feet deep.</p>
                <p>On the <hi rend="italic">Kir</hi> the rainy season lasts from the first week of
                    March to the close of October; but the 100 inches of rainfall goes largely to
                    flood the swamps.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Bahr al-Ghaztil</hi> is at its lowest in March, and begins
                    to rise soon after.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Sobdt</hi> is full from June to December.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">White Nile,</hi> at Khartoum, begins to rise in May, but
                    only gains 2 or 3 feet till July or August. Its maximum (6 feet) is reached in
                    September. Linant Bey estimated its volume at low level as 10,488 cubic feet,
                    and in flood as 213,450.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Blue Nile,</hi> at Khartoum, begins to rise in July, and
                    reaches its maximum (17⅛ feet) by August 20. Its rise is much more rapid than
                    its decline; it takes eighty days to lose the gain achieved in fifty-one. Linant
                    Bey estimated its volume at low level as 5615 cubic feet, and in" flood as
                    220,620. At Famaka it grows turbid about 20th May.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Atbara,</hi> for 150 miles above its junction with the
                    Nile, is perfectly dry from March to June.</p>
                <p>As a waterway leading into the heart of Africa, the Nile at first sight might
                    appear to be of more importance than it is. Steamers, it is true, as well as
                    sailing craft, can pass up from Egypt as far as Bedden, a distance of 2900
                    miles; but even at the period of high water (June to August) the ascent of the
                    cataracts between Wady Haifa and Berber is so dangerous for vessels of any size
                    that the river-route is seldom followed throughout. From Wady Haifa the
                    traveller may proceed by camel to El Ordeh (New Dongola), thence take boat to El
                    Dabbeh or to Old Dongola, and again proceed by land either to Berber, Sbendy, or
                    Khartoum. Or, instead, he may leave the river at Korosko, and strike through the
                    Nubian desert direct to Berber. From Berber, which is also the terminus of a
                    route often used from Souakim (Suakin) on the Red Sea, steamers ply up the
                    river, but it sometimes takes nineteen days to reach Khartoum. The difficulties
                    of navigating the Kir have already been described. Above Bedden the steamer
                    again finds a free course from Dufile to the neighbourhood of the Murchison
                    Fall; but the route to Victoria Nyanza is again overland from Magungo. It is
                    found more expeditious to come to the equatorial regions from the east coast
                    than up the Nile valley.</p>
                <p>For the botanical aspects of the Nile valley the reader is referred to
                    Schweinfurth’s papers <hi rend="italic">{Petermanris</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mittheilungen,</hi> 1868); for the general zoology to Heuglin’s sketch <hi
                    rend="italic">{Ibid.,</hi> 1869); and for an account of the fish fauna to Dr
                    Giinther’s appendix to Mr and Mrs Petherick’s <hi rend="italic">Travels in
                    Central Africa</hi> (1869).</p>
                <p>The ancients knew little of the course of the Nile above <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Meroe</hi><hi rend="italic">{q.v.).</hi> Juba, in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Libyca,</hi> quoted by Pliny, makes the Nile rise in western Mauretania, not
                    far from the ocean, in a lake presenting characteristic Nile fauna, then pass
                    underground for several days’ journey to a similar lake in Mauretania
                    Caesariensis, again continue underground for twenty days’ journey to the source
                    called Nigris on the borders of Africa and Ethiopia, and thence flow through
                    Ethiopia as the Astapus. This tissue of invention received strange favour in the
                    eyes of many subsequent geographers, and actually left its traces in some of our
                    maps down to a comparatively modern time. Strabo, who ascended the river as far
                    as Syene, states that very early investigators had connected the inundation of
                    the lower Nile with summer rains on the far southern mountains, and that their
                    theory had been confirmed by the observations of travellers under the Ptolemies.
                    Nero despatched two centurions on an expedition for the express purpose of
                    exploring the Nile, and Seneca informs us that they reached a marshy impassable
                    region, which may be easily identified with the country of the White Nile above
                    the mouth of the Sobât. To what they referred when they reported a great mass of
                    water falling from between two rocks is not so readily determined. By the time
                    of Ptolemy information had somewhat accumulated. Two streams, he says, issuing
                    from two lakes<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The two
                    lakes afterwards received the names Lake of Crocodiles and Lake of
                    Cataracts.</p></note> (one in 6° and the other in 7° S. lat.), unite in 2° N.
                    lat. to make the Nile which in 12° N. lat. receives the Astapus, a river flowing
                    from Lake Coloe (on the equator). Thus it would appear that he had heard vaguely
                    about the lakes which we know as Victoria Nyanza, Albert Nyanza, and Tana. His
                    two southern lakes, he conceived, were fed by the melting of snows on a range of
                    mountains running east and west for upwards of 500 miles—the Mountains of the
                    Moon, τδ <hi rend="italic">τηs σeKΙ)vys epos, Lunιe Montes.</hi> To this opinion
                    he was probably led by hearsay about the snow-clad summits of Kilimanjaro and
                    Kenia. On all the subsequent history of the geography of the Nile Ptolemy’s
                    theory had an enormous influence. Mediaeval maps and descriptions, both European
                    and Arabian, reproduce the Mountains of the Moon and the equatorial lakes with a
                    variety of probable or impossible modifications. Even Speke congratulated
                    himself on identifying the old Ptolemean range with the high lands to the north
                    of Tanganyika, and connected the name with that of Unyamwezi, the “country of
                    the moon.”</p>
                <p>Attacking the lake region from the east coast, the Portuguese explorers gained a
                    good deal of information which found its way into such maps as those of
                    Pigafetta (1580); but it was not till the present century that the geography of
                    those parts was placed on the basis of fully accepted observations. On November
                    14, 1770, Bruce reached Lake Tana, and considering, as he did, that the Blue
                    Nile was the main branch, very fairly claimed for himself the honour of being
                    the discoverer of the long-sought <hi rend="italic">caput Nili.</hi></p>
                <p>The following are a few of the chief dates in the progress of knowledge since
                    1800 in regard to the river system:—</p>
                <p>1807. Completion of Jacotin’s <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    l'Égypte</hi> (surveys from the Mediterranean to Assuan). 1814. Burckhardt goes
                    up the Nile, partly by land, as far as Shendi, crosses to the Atbara, and skirts
                    the east side to Gos Rajeb. 1819. Cailliaud is the first to visit Meroe. 1820.
                    Steamers first ascend the cataracts to Korosko. 1822. Cailliaud and Letorzec
                    ascend the Blue Nile with Ibrahim Pasha’s military expedition as far as Fazokl.
                    1827. Linant Bey ascends White Nile 132 geographical miles to Al Ais, in 13° 43'
                    N. lat. Prokesch von Osten surveys the Nile between Assuan and Wady Haifa. 1839.
                    Mehemet Ali sends up White Nile an expedition, usually known as the First
                    Egyptian Expedition, under Selim Bimbashi, which (28th January 1840) reaches an
                    island Badelik, in 6° 30' N. lat., but adds little information. Thibaut (Ibrahim
                    Effendi) was a member of this expedition. 1840-41. A second Egyptian expedition
                    (D ’ Arnaud, Sabatier, Werne) reaches island of Janker near Gondokoro, about 4°
                    42' N. lat. 1841-42. Third Egyptian expedition (Selim Bimbashi, D’Arnaud,
                    Sabatier, Thibaut). 1845. Brun-Rollet founds trading post not far from
                    subsequent site of Heiligenkreuz. 1846. First steamboat on White Nile. 1849.
                    Baron Von Müller surveys the Nile fromHandakto Ambakol in province of Dongola.
                    1850. Knoblecher (of Austrian mission) reached Log-wek. 1855. Rebmann
                    (missionary at Kisulutini, north-west of Mombasa) sends home map showing Lake
                    Ukerewe, extending from 0° 30' N. lat. to 13° 30' S. lat. 1858. Speke, twenty
                    marches north of Kazeh, where he had left Burton, reaches shore of Victoria
                    Nyanza. 1859. Miani reaches mouth of Unyama. 1860. Pruyssenaere starts from
                    Khartoum up the White Nile. 1862. Speke reaches Ripon Falls. Steudner passes
                    down the Ra ’ ad and Blue Nile to Khartoum. The Tinné expedition goes five
                    hours’ journey beyond Gondokoro on the White Nile. 1864. Sir Samuel Baker
                    reaches Albert Nyanza. Petherick closes a long series of wanderings in the White
                    Nile and Bahr al-Ghazâl districts. 1868-71. Schweinfurth explores the western
                    affluents of White Nile. 1871-73. Baker in the White Nile region. 1874. Watson
                    and Chippendall survey the river from Khartoum to Rejaf, and J. Kemp from Rejaf
                    to Dufile. 1875. Stanley circumnavigates Victoria Nyanza. 1877. First voyage
                    across Victoria Nyanza by Rev. C. T. Wilson and Lieutenant Shergold Smith.
                    1881-82. Schuver in the sourcedistrict of the Tumat. (H. A. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
