<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0170-0159-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">N (9th edition, volume 17, page 159)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1169292">Vowels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163387">Uvula</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bh0c">Uvula</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n170/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">N</label> denotes the dental nasal in all the languages in
                    which our alphabet is used. But the sound which we call the dental nasal varies
                    slightly in different languages according to the position of the point of the
                    tongue. This may be pressed against the back of the teeth; and then we have a
                    true “dental” sound. But the point of the tongue may also be placed not against
                    the teeth but against the front part of the palate immediately behind the gums;
                    and it is in this way that our English dentals are formed.</p>
                <p>But this same letter N, either alone or together with another letter, or
                    distinguished by some diacritical mark, can be used for a much wider range of
                    nasal sounds. It has been already pointed out (see letter Μ) that there are in
                    every language as many nasals as there are clearly distinguished classes of
                    sound produced at different parts of the mouth, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>
                    guttural or back-palatal, front-palatal, dental, labial, and others less easily
                    apprehended. Each of these classes will have its nasal, which will vary from the
                    sonant of the class only by the different position of the uvula: for the sonant
                    (as, for example, <hi rend="italic">d)</hi> the uvula is pressed up so as to
                    cover the passage through the pharynx into the nostrils, and the voice therefore
                    escapes wholly through the mouth; for the nasal (as for <hi rend="italic"
                    >n)</hi> the uvula hangs down, so that the voice passes partly behind it through
                    the nose, partly through the mouth; in all other respects the position of the
                    vocal organs for <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and for <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is
                    just the same, and the material of the sound is the same, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> breath made sonant by the vibration of the glottis. In an improved
                    alphabet, therefore, we ought in each language to have several symbols for the
                    nasals, as in Sanskrit, which had five different symbols. But no European
                    language has more than two simple symbols; and, of these two, <hi rend="italic"
                    >m</hi> is confined to one class, viz., the labial; <hi rend="italic">n,</hi>
                    simple or modified, denotes the other sounds, and therefore often differs in
                    different languages, and sometimes in the same language. It may also be employed
                    to denote a wholly different class of sounds, as the nasalized vowels of the
                    French, which will be described below.</p>
                <p>The guttural nasal is heard in “anger,” “finger,” “hunger”; it is easy to note
                    the difference of the <hi rend="italic">n</hi> as heard in these words, and in
                    “an,” “fin,” &amp;c. In English, when the sound occurs at the end of a word, it
                    is represented by <hi rend="italic">ng,</hi> as “hang,” “sing,” &amp;c.,
                    sometimes also when medial, as in the derivatives “hanger,” “singer.” It would
                    be convenient if, as has often been proposed, the superfluous symbol <hi
                    rend="italic">q</hi> were employed for this nasal. The sound is heard in German
                    as well as in English; but in French it is unknown. On the other hand, the front
                    palatal nasal is heard in the French “Boulogne,” Italian “Campagna,” Spanish
                    “ano,” “otono,” &amp;c., the diacritical mark being always used in Spanish; it
                    is not known with us; but its position in the mouth is shown by that of the
                    corresponding closed consonants, English <hi rend="italic">ch</hi> and/, and of
                    the fricative consonant of the same class, which is <hi rend="italic">y.</hi>
                    The peculiar class of sounds called “cerebral” in Sanskrit was formed by turning
                    the point of the tongue a little backward toward the top of the palate; of these
                    the nasal was by far the most frequent. Our English “dental” lies between the
                    cerebral and the true “dental,” for which (as in India) the tongue actually
                    touches the teeth,—our dental being of the kind already mentioned, in which the
                    tongue does not come farther forward than the front palate.</p>
                <p>From what has been said, it will appear that the nasals might be called nasalized
                    consonants. The guttural nasal is <hi rend="italic">g</hi> nasalized; the dental
                    nasal is <hi rend="italic">d</hi> nasalized: part of the voice in each case is
                    diverted from the mouth through the nostrils, and some nasal sound is already
                    heard while the passage through the mouth is closed by the tongue, or by the
                    lips for the production of the labial nasal; but the complete nasal sound is not
                    heard till the block of the tongue or of the lips is removed, exactly as in the
                    production of <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">b.</hi> But it is possible to nasalize vowels as well as to
                    nasalize consonants. The position of the uvula can be altered when the mouth is
                    set for sounding the vowel <hi rend="italic">a</hi> just as well as when it is
                    set for the sound of <hi rend="italic">g</hi>; and then instead of the pure
                    «-sound we get one of a nasal quality; as instead of the final consonant sound
                    of “hag” we get the nasalized guttural in “hang.” These nasalized vowels are
                    unknown to us in England; and this is the reason why we find so much difficulty
                    in pronouncing them in French. An Englishman learning French will always begin
                    by pronouncing “en” as if it were “eng,” and “on” as if it were “ong.” But the
                    French “en” is not the vowel <hi rend="italic">e</hi> plus the guttural nasal n;
                    it is the vowel <hi rend="italic">e</hi> nasalized.</p>
                <p>It is probable, though not provable, that nasal vowels were used in Latin. The
                    evidence lies in the varying spelling of words like “censor” and “cesor,”
                    “consul” and “cosol,” &amp;c.; neither is right, but each seems to be an attempt
                    to avoid an error; “censor” is a protest against sounding a nasal <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> as pure <hi rend="italic">e</hi>; and “cesor” against
                    sounding it as <hi rend="italic">e + n.</hi> Again, the Latin has “con-ficere,”
                    but “com-ponere”; now <hi rend="italic">f</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> are
                    both labials, and therefore we should expect the same treatment of the final <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> in “con” before each; probably the <hi rend="italic">n</hi>
                    marked a nasal vowel (used before a fricative consonant), whereas the <hi
                    rend="italic">m</hi> was a true nasal consonant before the closed consonant <hi
                    rend="italic">p.</hi> Cicero’s doctrine <hi rend="italic">(Orat.</hi> 159) that
                    the vowel <hi rend="italic">i</hi> is naturally long in “in-sanus,” “in-felix,”
                    &lt;tc., but short in “in-doctus,” points to the same conclusion—that the <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> before s and <hi rend="italic">f</hi> marked a long
                    nasalized vowel. Lastly, we have the spelling of Greek words like <hi
                    rend="italic">θησαυρός</hi> as “thensaurus” in Latin; it is improbable that the
                    <hi rend="italic">n</hi> here was the full consonant.</p>
                <p>It is not unlikely that the appearance and non-appearance of the nasal in the
                    dialects of the same language indicates an original nasalized vowel which has in
                    one case disappeared, in the other has passed into a vowel followed by a nasal.
                    Thus in German we find “sanft” corresponding to English “soft,” “gans” to
                    “goose,” &lt;fcc. But the vowel has been modified in such cases in compensation
                    for the loss of its original nasal quality.</p>
                <p>The phenomenon of the so-called “parasitic” nasal arises from careless
                    pronunciation; before sounding a closed consonant (like <hi rend="italic"
                    >g)</hi> the uvula is not sufficiently raised, and so a nasal of the same class
                    is heard before the <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> as in “nightingale” (compare
                    German “nachtigal”). Yet more common is the development by the nasal itself of a
                    parasitic closed consonant of its own class; many such have long been firmly
                    established, as in the words “soun∕” (Middle English “soun,” like French “son,”
                    Latin “sonu-s”), “thun/er” (A.S. “thunor ”), still rightly pronounced in the
                    north of England as “thunner”; but “gown/,” “singling,” though familiar enough,
                    have not yet made their way into polite speech. These parasitic sounds are also
                    due to careless pronunciation; if the passage through the nostrils be not kept
                    open till the articulating organs of the mouth have separated, the nasal quality
                    at the end of the sound is lost, and the closed consonant must follow. There has
                    been an odd loss of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> at the beginning of several English
                    words which has often <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0171-0160"/> been noted. It arises from our double form of the
                    indefinite article “a” and “an.” Sometimes the “a” has abstracted the “n” from
                    the beginning of the noun: thus “a nadder” has turned into “an adder,” “a
                    napron” into “an apron,” “a nauger” into “an auger.” On the other hand the
                    letter has had one compensatory gain: “an ewt” (eft) has turned into “a newt.”
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> p.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
