<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0534-0493-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NIEBUHR, Karsten (9th edition, volume 17, page
                    493)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1734394">Peasants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:958978">Holsteiners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz5d">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659q39">Surveyors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz97">Herons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n534/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NIEBUHR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karsten</hi></label>
                    (1733-1815), Eastern traveller, was born at Lüdingworth, Lauenburg, on the
                    southern border of Holstein, March 17, 1733, the son of a small farmer. He had
                    little elementary education, and for several years of his youth had to do the
                    work of a peasant. His bent was towards mathematics, and he managed to obtain
                    some lessons in surveying. It was while he was working at this subject that one
                    of his teachers, in 1760, proposed to him to join the expedition which was being
                    sent out by Frederick V. of Denmark for the scientific exploration of Egypt,
                    Arabia, and Syria. To qualify himself for the work of surveyor and geographer,
                    he studied hard at mathematics for a year and a half before the expedition set
                    out, and also managed to acquire some knowledge of Arabic. The expedition sailed
                    in January 1761, and, landing at Alexandria, ascended the Nile and devoted some
                    time to an examination of the pyramids and of the hieroglyphic writings of
                    Egypt. Proceeding to Suez, Niebuhr made a visit to Mount Sinai, and in October
                    1762 the expedition sailed from Suez to Jiddah, journeying thence overland to
                    Mocha. Here in May 1763 the philologist of the expedition, Van Haven, died, and
                    was followed shortly after by the naturalist Forskâl. San <hi rend="superscript"
                    > t</hi> a, the capital of Yemen, was visited, but the remaining members of the
                    expedition suffered so much from the climate or from the mode of life that they
                    returned to Mocha. Niebuhr seems to have saved his own life and restored his
                    health by adopting the native habits as to dress and food. From Mocha the ship
                    was taken to Bombay, the artist of the expedition dying on the passage, and the
                    surgeon soon after landing. Niebuhr was now left alone, the only surviving
                    member of the expedition. He stayed fourteen months at Bombay, and then returned
                    home by Muscat, Bushire, Shiraz, and Persepolis, visited the ruins of Babylon,
                    and thence went to Baghdad, Mosul, and Aleppo. After a visit to Cyprus he made a
                    tour through Palestine, crossing Mount Taurus to Brussa, reaching Constantinople
                    in February 1767, and Copenhagen in the following November. On his return
                    Niebuhr at once set himself to the task of preparing the records of the
                    expedition. His first volume, <hi rend="italic">Beschreibung von Arabien,</hi>
                    was published at Copenhagen in 1772, the Danish Government defraying the
                    expenses of the abundant illustrations. This was followed in 1774-78 by other
                    two volumes, <hi rend="italic">Reisebeschreibung von Arabien und anderen·
                    umliegenden Ländern.</hi> The fourth volume was not published till long after
                    his death, in 1837, under the editorship of Niebuhr’s daughter. He also
                    undertook the task of bringing out the work of his friend Forskâl, the
                    naturalist of the expedition, under the titles of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Descriptiones Animalium,</hi><hi rend="italic">Flora</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Aegyptiaco-Arabica,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Icones Rerum Naturalium</hi>
                    (Copenhagen, 1775-76). To a German periodical, the <hi rend="italic">Deutsches
                    Museum,</hi> Niebuhr contributed papers on the interior of Africa, the political
                    and military condition of the Turkish empire, and other subjects. He married in
                    1773, and for some years held a post in the Danish military service which
                    enabled him to reside at Copenhagen. In 1778, however, he accepted a position in
                    the civil service of Holstein, and went to reside at Meldorf, where he died,
                    April 26, 1815.</p>
                <p>Niebuhr was in no sense a genius nor even a man of many accomplishments, but he
                    was one of the best scientific travellers that ever lived. He was well equipped
                    for the particular service which he had to perform in connexion with the Eastern
                    expedition; above all, he was an accurate and careful observer, had the
                    instincts of the scholar, was animated by a high moral purpose, and was
                    rigorously conscientious and anxiously truthful in recording the results of his
                    observation. His works have long been classical, and even now must be consulted
                    by any one who desires to have the most trustworthy accounts, not only of the
                    geography, but of the people, the antiquities, and the archaeology of much of
                    the district of Arabia which he traversed. His narratives are simple, <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n535/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0535-0494"/> and he himself is kept almost entirely in the
                    background. He was a genuine peasant in many respects to the end of his life,
                    having many of the peasant’s virtues as well as failings.</p>
                <p>French and Dutch translations of his narratives were published during his
                    lifetime, and a condensed English translation, by Robert Heron, of the first
                    three volumes in Edinburgh, 1792. His distinguished son Barthold published a
                    short <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> at Kiel in 1817; an English version was issued
                    in 1838 in the <hi rend="italic">Lives of Eminent Men,</hi> published by the
                    Society for the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
