<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0328-0315-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NEGRO (9th edition, volume 17, page 315)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xk84r7r">Caucasians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1939238">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936387">Fur</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950358">Hair</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242088">Sahara</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208478">Chad</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n328/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NEGRO</label> (Spanish and Italian <hi rend="italic"
                    >Negro,</hi> from Latin <hi rend="italic">Niger,</hi> black) in anthropology
                    designates the distinctly dark as opposed to the fair, yellow, and brown
                    varieties of mankind. In this its widest sense it embraces all the dark races,
                    whose original home are the inter-tropical and subtropical regions of the
                    eastern hemisphere, stretching roughly from Senegambia, West Africa, to the Fiji
                    Archipelago, Pacific Ocean, west and east, and lying north and south between the
                    extreme parallels of the Philippines and Tasmania. The Negro domain thus
                    originally comprised all Africa south of the Sahara, India south of the
                    Indo-Gangetic plains, Malaysia, and the greater part of Australasia. But this
                    domain has since prehistoric times been intruded upon in the east mainly by
                    peoples of the yellow Mongoloid, in the west mainly by peoples of the fair
                    Caucasie stock. During the early and middle Tertiary epochs it appears also to
                    have been gradually broken into two great divisions—by the subsidence of lands,
                    some suppose, which are now flooded by the waters of the Indian Ocean, and to
                    which Sclater has given the name of Lemuria. To these two great eastern and
                    western geographical divisions now correspond the two great ethnical divisions
                    of the Negro stock—the Papuan or Melanesian of Malaysia and Australasia, and the
                    Negro proper of the African mainland. During the long ages that have elapsed
                    since this separation, the two branches, if originally one, have had time under
                    diverse outward conditions to become differentiated into two sufficiently marked
                    physical types, so that on strictly anthropological as well as geographical
                    grounds it becomes convenient to deal separately with the Papuan and African
                    divisions of the Negro family. The present article is confined to the latter.
                    For the Papuans see <hi rend="smallcaps">New Guinea.</hi></p>
                <p>Soudan (Siîdân), the fertile zone stretching from the Sahara towards the equator
                    nearly across the continent, is usually regarded as the true home of the African
                    Negro. But, according to the views recently advanced by Lepsius, Soudan is
                    rather an intermediate or mixed domain lying between the two Hamitic and Negro
                    ethnical groups, which have respectively occupied northern and southern Africa
                    from the remotest times. Certainly none of the chief native races in
                    Soudan—Mandingo, Joloff, Toucouleur in the west; Kanembu, Haussa, Kanuri in the
                    centre; Maba in Wadai, Nuba in the Nile valley, least of all the Fulahs of the
                    Chad and Niger basins—can be considered as of pure Negro descent. But the same
                    phenomenon of intermixture is presented in the strictly equatorial and south
                    equatorial regions, where the Fans of the Ogoway basin, the Zandey (Niam-Niam),
                    Bongo, Bari, and other Upper-Nilotic tribes, the Waganda of the Victoria Nyanza
                    of the extreme east, the Zulu-Kaffres of the extreme south, are all of Negroid
                    and even sub-Negroid rather than of strictly Negro lineage. Hence the same
                    argument that would exclude Soudan would also exclude the greater part of
                    southern Africa, and we should have to look to the hypothetical Lemuria or other
                    now submerged lands for the cradle of the Negro stock. Practically, however, the
                    whole of Africa south of the Sahara must be taken as the original habitat of the
                    race, which is there almost everywhere still found in compact masses, although
                    rarely perhaps absolutely free from foreign intermixture.</p>
                <p>But wherever found in a comparatively pure state, as on the coast of Guinea,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Here apparently is to be met
                    the most pronounced Negro type proper yet discovered. See the missionary
                    Wilson’s <hi rend="italic">Ethnographic View of Western Africa,</hi> New York,
                    1856, published anonymously.</p></note> in the Gaboon, along the lower Zambesi,
                    and in the Benua and Shari basins, the African aborigines present almost a
                    greater uniformity of physical and moral type than any of the other great
                    divisions of mankind. By the nearly unanimous consent of anthropologists this
                    type occupies at the same time the lowest position in the evolutionary scale,
                    thus affording the best material for the comparative study of the highest
                    anthropoids and the human species. The chief points in which the Negro either
                    approaches the <hi rend="italic">Quadrumane,</hi> or differs most from his own
                    congeners are :—(1) the abnormal length of the arm, which in the erect position
                    sometimes reaches the knee-pan, and λvhich on an average exceeds that of the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n329/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0329-0316"/> Caucasian by about 2 inches; (2) prognathism, or
                    projection of the jaws (index number of facial angle about 70, as compared with
                    the Caucasian 82); (3) weight of brain, as indicating cranial capacity, 35
                    ounces (highest gorilla 20, average European 45); (4) full black eye, with black
                    iris and yellowish sclerotic coat, a very marked feature; (5) short flat snub
                    nose, deeply depressed at the base or frontal suture, broad at extremity, with
                    dilated nostrils and concave ridge; (6) thick protruding lips, plainly showing
                    the inner red surface; (7) very large zygomatic arches— high and prominent cheek
                    bones; (8) exceedingly thick cranium, enabling the Negro to butt with the head
                    and resist blows which would inevitably break any ordinary European’s skull; (9)
                    correspondingly weak lower limbs, terminating in a broad flat foot with low
                    instep, divergent and somewhat prehensile great toe, and heel projecting
                    backwards (“lark heel”); (10) complexion deep brown or blackish, and in some
                    cases even distinctly black, due not to any special pigment, as is often
                    supposed, but merely to the greater abundance of the colouring matter in the
                    Malpighian mucous membrane between the inner or true skin and the epidermis or
                    scarf skin;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is also
                    noteworthy that the dark colour seems to depend neither on geographical
                    position, the isothermals of greatest heat, nor even altogether on racial
                    purity. The extremes of the chromatic scale are found in juxtaposition
                    throughout the whole Negro domain, in Senegambia, the Gaboon, upper Nile basin,
                    lower Congo, Shari valley, Mozambique. In the last region Froberville determined
                    the presence of thirty-one different shades from dusky or yellow-brown to sooty
                    black. Some of the sub-Negroid and mixed races, such as many Abyssinians,
                    Gallas, Joloffs, and Mandingoes, are quite as black as the darkest full-blood
                    Negro. A general similarity in the outward conditions of soil, atmosphere,
                    climate, food charged with an excess of carbon, such as the fruit of the
                    butter-tree, and other undetermined causes have tended to develop a tendency
                    towards dark shades everywhere in the Negro domain apart from the bias mainly
                    due to an original strain of black blood. Even the African Arabs are described
                    by Burckhardt, De Pagès, and other observers as often decidedly black.
                    Waddington mentions more particularly the Shegya Arabs south of Dongola on the
                    White Nile as distinguished by their “clear, glossy, jet black” (p. 149). The
                    same expression “jet black” is applied by Schweinfurth to the Upper-Nilotic
                    Shilluks, Nuers, and Dinkas, while the neighbouring Bongos and Mittus are
                    described as of a “red-brown” colour “like the soil upon which they reside” <hi
                    rend="italic">{Heart of Africa,</hi> i. p. 261).</p></note> (11) short, black
                    hair, eccentrically elliptical or almost flat in section, and distinctly woolly,
                    not merely frizzly, as Prichard supposed on insufficient evidence;<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This point has been fully
                    determined by P. A. Brown <hi rend="italic">{Classification of Mankind by the
                    Hair,</hi> &amp;c. ), who shows conclusively that, unlike true hair and like
                    true wool, the Negro hair is flat, issues from the epidermis at a right angle,
                    is spirally twisted or crisped, has no central duct, the colouring matter being
                    disseminated through the cortex and intermediate fibres, while the cortex itself
                    is covered with numerous rough, pointed filaments adhering loosely to the shaft;
                    lastly, the Negro pile will felt, like wool, whereas true hair cannot be felted.
                    Observing that the Negro domain is also the habitat of the most anthropoid
                    apes—gorilla and chimpanzee,—and that these bimanous and quadrumanous species
                    are both of a pronounced dolichocephalic type (index nos. 72-75), some
                    anthropologists have suggested the direct descent of the former from the latter.
                    But against this view may be urged the different texture of the pile, which,
                    although black in both, is woolly in the Negro but true hair in the ape. It may
                    further be noted that in the eastern section of the dark domain, while the
                    Papuan is still black and dolichocephalic, often excessively so, his presumed
                    progenitor the orang-outang is, on the contrary, brachycephalic, with decidedly
                    red hair. Dr Bernard Davis also recognizes brachycephaly in equatorial Africa
                    itself, four out of the eighteen skulls from this region in his collection being
                    distinctly of the round-headed type, and Schweinfurth describes the Bongos as
                    “hardly removed from the lowest grade of brachycephaly” (i. 263).</p></note>
                    (12) thick epidermis, cool, soft, and velvety to the touch, mostly hairless, and
                    emitting a peculiar rancid odour, compared by Pruner Bey to that of the buck
                    goat; (13) frame of medium height, thrown somewhat out of the perpendicular by
                    the shape of the pelvis, the spine, the backward projection of the head, and the
                    whole anatomical structure; (14) the cranial sutures, which close much earlier
                    in the Negro than in other races. To this premature ossification of the skull,
                    preventing all further development of the brain, many pathologists have
                    attributed the inherent mental inferiority of the blacks, an inferiority which
                    is even more marked than their physical differences. Nearly all observers admit
                    that the Negro child is on the whole quite as intelligent as those of other
                    human varieties, but that on arriving at puberty all further progress seems to
                    be arrested. No one has more carefully studied this point than Filippo Manetta,
                    who during a long residence on the plantations of the Southern States of America
                    noted that “the Negro children were sharp, intelligent, and full of vivacity,
                    but on approaching the adult period a gradual change set in. The intellect
                    seemed to become clouded, animation giving place to a sort of lethargy,
                    briskness yielding to indolence. We must necessarily suppose that the
                    development of the Negro and White proceeds on different lines. While with the
                    latter the volume of the brain grows with the expansion of the brainpan, in the
                    former the growth of the brain is on the contrary arrested by the premature
                    closing of the cranial sutures and lateral pressure of the frontal bone.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">La Razaa
                    Negra nel</hi><hi rend="italic">suo stato</hi><hi rend="italic">selvaggio,</hi>
                    &amp;c., Turin, 1864, p. 20.</p></note></p>
                <p>It must at the same time be confessed that the question of the mental temperament
                    of the Negro has been greatly complicated by the partisanship of interested
                    advocates on either side. But for this disturbing element it would perhaps be
                    readily admitted that the mental are at least as marked as the physical
                    differences between the dark and other races. And as both are the gradual
                    outcome of external conditions, fixed by heredity, it follows that the attempt
                    to suddenly transform the Negro mind by foreign culture must be, as it has
                    proved to be, as futile as the attempt would be to suddenly transform his
                    physical type. On his moral status, even when removed from the old associations
                    and brought directly under more favourable influences, a lurid light is cast by
                    the report of the Rev. Dr Tucker at the American Church Congress for 1883 on the
                    present condition of the black communities in the Southern States.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“I know of whole
                    neighbourhoods,” he tells us, “where there is not one single Negro couple,
                    whether legally married or not, who are faithful to each other beyond a few
                    weeks. In the midst of a prayermeeting I have known Negroes steal from each
                    other, and on the way home they will rob any hen-roost that lies conveniently at
                    hand. The most pious Negro that I know is confined in a penitentiary for an
                    atrocious murder, and he persists in saying he can see no offence against God in
                    his crime, though he acknowledges an offence against man.” Mention is further
                    made of Negro missionaries guilty of the grossest immorality, living in open
                    concubinage, addicted to thieving, lying, and every imaginary crime, yet all
                    “earnest and successful preachers, and wholly unconscious of hypocrisy. Their
                    sins, universally known, did not diminish their influence with their race. It
                    was impossible to doubt their absolute sincerity.” A much darker picture is
                    presented by the independent Negro commonwealths of Hayti, for eighty years the
                    scene of almost uninterrupted fratricidal strife.</p></note></p>
                <p>It is more correct to say of the Negro that he is non-moral than immoral. All the
                    social institutions are at the same low level, and throughout the historic
                    period seem to have made no perceptible advance except under the stimulus of
                    foreign (in recent time notably of Mohammedan) influences. Religion is a system
                    of pure fetichism and worship of ancestry associated with such sanguinary rites
                    as the “customs” of Dahomey and Ashantee, and a universal belief in sorcery.
                    Slavery continues everywhere to prevail, both as a local institution and a
                    branch of the export trade, where not checked by European Governments. Much of
                    the surplus population not thus carried off probably finds its way to the
                    shambles of the native states in the middle Congo basin and other parts where
                    cannibalism is practised, and where human flesh appears to be sold in the open
                    market-place. During its voyage down the Congo the Stanley expedition was
                    attacked at many points <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n330/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0330-0317"/> for the avowed purpose of procuring a fresh
                    supply of human food, and from other incidents of modern exploration cannibalism
                    would seem to prevail very generally in the little known equatorial regions of
                    the interior.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Amongst
                    the Niam-Niam “human fat is universally sold,” while “the Fan barter their dead
                    among themselves,” and even disinter them to be devoured <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Heart of Africa,</hi> ii. pp. 18, 19). Still more pronounced is the
                    cannibalism of the Monbuttu, who dry the bodies of the slain in battle for
                    future consumption, and “drive their prisoners before them, as butchers drive
                    sheep to the shambles, and these are only reserved to fall victims on a later
                    day to their horrible and sickly greediness” <hi rend="italic">{Ib.,</hi> ii. p.
                    93).</p></note> · Political institutions are in a rudimentary state, and where a
                    higher system has been imposed or adopted from the whites, as in Liberia, it
                    does not appear to have materially contributed to the improvement of the race.
                    The great bulk of the natives are still in the tribal condition, while in the
                    kingdoms that have been founded in Guinea and elsewhere the authority of the
                    sovereign is everywhere absolute, and its exercise often marked by the most
                    wanton and atrocious cruelty. The largest and most powerful native state is that
                    of Ulunda, whose present “muata yanvo,” or ruler, is the fourteenth in descent
                    from the founder of the dynasty. When visited in 1879 by Dr Buchner, this
                    potentate, to impress his guest with his power, caused one of his subjects to
                    assume the part of a chief just arrived from a remote province of the empire.
                    The sham cortège of soldiers and women advanced to the throne all thickly
                    plastered with mud from head to foot, and the “chief” approaching on all fours
                    deliberately rolled himself in the sand at his majesty’s feet. The
                    administration of justice is regulated, not by any sense of right or wrong, but
                    by the caprice of the king, who is himself often in the power of the navum-bula,
                    or witch-detector. Beyond what has been acquired from without, of letters there
                    is absolutely no knowledge, unless an exception be made in favour of the
                    invention or adaptation of a rude syllabic system some years ago by a native of
                    the Vei tribe. Hence literature is purely oral, and limited to a few tribal
                    legends, some folklore, proverbs, and songs of the simplest kind. The arts also
                    are exclusively of an industrial character, and restricted mainly to coarse
                    weaving, pottery, the smelting and working of metals (chiefly copper and iron),
                    agriculture, and grazing. Architecture has no existence, nor are there any
                    monumental ruins or stone structures of any sort in the whole of Negroland
                    except those erected in Soudan under Hamitic and Semitic influences. No
                    full-blood Negro has ever been distinguished as a man of science, a poet, or an
                    artist, and the fundamental equality claimed for him by ignorant philanthropists
                    is belied by the whole history of the race throughout the historic period.</p>
                <p>On the other hand the native languages, all of which belong to the agglutinating
                    order, are often very highly developed, and the Bantu group especially is
                    characterized by an intricacy of structure and an alliterative phonetic system
                    of an exceedingly delicate type.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>For this remarkable linguistic phenomenon see vol. xiii. p.
                    820.</p></note> From the wide range of this Bantu speech, which occupies all the
                    southern half of the continent except the Hottentot and Bushman territory in the
                    extreme south-west, Lepsius concludes that it is the original language of the
                    Negro race, and that the numerous linguistic groups of Soudan are merely
                    scattered fragments of that speech or of the Hamitic intruding from the north.
                    Thus has been developed his theory of the two ethnical and linguistic stocks
                    originally in exclusive possession of North and South Africa, and gradually
                    amalgamating in the now diversified intermediate zone of Soudan. But this theory
                    cannot be accepted as at all adequate to explain the present conditions in those
                    regions. It is not by any means certain that the Bantu itself was originally a
                    Negro language at all. There seems, moreover, to be good reason for believing
                    that its present diffusion over South Africa dates from comparatively recent
                    times, and that it is due to the intrusion of foreign conquerors penetrating
                    from the north-east up the Nile valley and through the region of the great lakes
                    into the Congo and Zambesi basins. Nor is it possible to regard the Mandingo,
                    Vei, Haussa, Fulah, and many other Soudanese tongues as fragments or off shoots
                    of Bantu, from which they differ as fundamentally as they do from each
                    other.</p>
                <p>To Dr Gustav Nachtigal<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Sahara</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sudan,</hi> Berlin, 1881, vol. ii. p. 283 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> See also
                    “North African Ethnology,” by A. H. Keane, in <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> for
                    March 1, 1883.</p></note> is due the recent discovery or determination of
                    another independent and widespread linguistic family, which had its original
                    home amongst the Hamitic Teda or northern Tubus of the eastern Sahara, and
                    which, gradually spreading southwards, has been imposed through the Dasa or
                    southern Tubus on the Kanembu and Kanuri of Lake Chad, the Baele of Wanyanga,
                    the Zoghawa of Dar-Fur, and other Negro or Negroid peoples of central and
                    eastern Soudan. The whole of Soudan, or, more correctly, the whole of Central
                    Africa between the equator and the Sahara, is in fact a region of linguistic
                    confusion, such as is elsewhere found only in Caucasia, Melanesia, the Anamese
                    highlands, and some parts of America. Several radically distinct stock languages
                    have already been determined, especially in Guinea, Senegambia, and the Chad
                    basin. But many more are knoλvn to be current in Adamawa, Bornu, Baghirmi,
                    Wadai, Dar-Fur, the White Nile Valley, while others will doubtless be revealed
                    by the future exploration of the lands watered by the Welle, Aruwimi, Mangala,
                    and other streams flowing either to the Nile, the Congo, or the Shari. Most of
                    them may be properly designated as strictly Negro tongues. But in the north,
                    that is, along the skirt of the Sahara, and in the east, that is in the Blue
                    Nile and Atbara basins, in Kaffa, Galla, and Somaliland, the current speech is
                    mainly Caucasie, and here also the populations are mainly Negroid and
                    sub-Negroid rather than of pure Negro descent. The Caucasie speech again is
                    represented by Hamitic, Tubu, and Semitic groups, all intruders in this Negro
                    domain from prehistoric times except the Semitic Arabic, which dates only from
                    the introduction of Islam. In attempting a complete, however brief, survey of
                    this vast ethnical and linguistic area, account must also be taken of other
                    disturbing elements within the area itself, which are of unknown origin, and
                    whose actual relations to the surrounding Negro masses are still involved in
                    much obscurity. Conspicuous amongst them are the Nubas of the Middle Nile,
                    apparently intermediate between the true Negro and the Egyptian Hamite; the
                    Fulahs of central and west Soudan, who, although now much mixed, seem to have
                    been originally distinct both from the Negro and the Hamite; the Fans, who have
                    in recent times reached the west coast just above the equator, and who are also
                    a clearly non-Negro race; lastly, the dwarfish Akkas, Obongos, and others, who
                    appear to be scattered over the whole of the continent south of 10° N. lat.
                    Many, perhaps the majority, of the Bantu-speaking southern races —Waswahili of
                    the Zanzibar coast, Waganda and others of the great lacustrine region,
                    Zulu-Kaffres of the south-east, Marutse of the Zambesi, Ovambos of the
                    south-west coast—are also variously affected by foreign elements, some no doubt
                    either Arab or Hamitic Galla penetrating from the north-east, but others drawn
                    from now long-forgotten sources. Thus the popular idea that Negroland presents a
                    homogeneous ethnical field must be dismissed as absolutely erroneous. It will be
                    safer to say that, while the Negro strain is here everywhere conspicuously
                    present, it has been repeatedly crossed and re-crossed by diverse
                    interminglings, which began with the first appearance of the Hamite on African
                    soil, and which have been continued from that vastly remote epoch down to the
                    present time.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In support
                    of this conclusion, which to some may seem overdrawn, appeal might be made to
                    the language of many modern African explorers, one of the most careful of whom
                    thus expresses himself - ‘ ‘ If we could at once grasp and set before our minds
                    facts that are known (whether as regards language, race, culture, history, or
                    development) of that vast region comprehended in the name of Africa, we should
                    have before us the witness of an intermingling of races which is beyond all
                    precedent. And yet, bewildering as the prospect would appear, it remains a fact
                    not to be gainsaid, that it is impossible for any one to survey the country as a
                    whole without perceiving that high above the multitude of individual differences
                    there is throned a principle of unity, which embraces well nigh all the
                    population” (Schweinfurth, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> i. p. 313). The
                    principle of unity here spoken of is the autochthonous black element, mostly
                    predominant, and everywhere forming the substratum, nearly as far north as the
                    tropic of Cancer.</p></note></p>
                <p>From the subjoined rough scheme of classification of the chief Negro and Negroid
                    races and languages are excluded the above-mentioned Caucasic-speaking Hamites
                    and Semites, who hem in the Negro zone proper by a mighty ethnical barrier
                    stretching almost continuously from the Senegal river through the Sahara,
                    Abyssinia, and Gallaland to the east coast at the equator. From it are also
                    omitted the Hovas, Sakalavas, Betsimisarakas, and other peoples of Madagascar,
                    all of Malagasy (Malayo-Polynesian) speech, as well as the Bosjesman and
                    Hottentot groups of the extreme south-west, as lying beyond the scope of the
                    present survey.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n331/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0331-0318"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">[Vest Soudan and Guinea.</hi><hi rend="italic">Mandingan
                    Group</hi>: Mande, Kabunga, Landöro, Tene, Gbandi, Susu, Mano, Toma, Gbese, Yei
                    (?). Mainly in South Senegambia and Upper Guinea.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Woloff Group:</hi> Joloff, Kayor, Dakar, Baol, Sine, Walo,
                    Bambara (?). Mainly between the Senegal and Gambia rivers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Felup Group</hi>: Felup, Bola, Serere, Filham, Pepel, Diola,
                    Kalium, Biafada, Pajade, Temné, Kissi, Sherbro. Between the Gambia and Sierra
                    Leone.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Liberian Group</hi>: Deh, Queah, Gurrah, Kru, Kondo, Pessa,
                    Golla, Bassa, Kabo, Yedabo, Grebo, Babo, Webo, Tebo, Nyambo. Grain and Ivory
                    coasts.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ewe Group:</hi> Aera (Ga), Fantee, Ashantee, Ffon, Mina, Jeji,
                    Dahoman, Nago, Otyi, Yoruba. Gold and Slave coasts.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ibo Group</hi>: Ibo, Nupe, Michi, Oru, Wari, Igara, Juku,
                    Kororofa, Ado, Akoto. Binue and lower Niger.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sonhray</hi>: Large, historical nation. Middle Niger, from
                    Timbuktu to Gando. Distinct speech.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fulah</hi>: Futa-Jallo, Futa-Toro, Jel, Baa, So, Mabube, Laube,
                    Beri. Senegambia and in scattered groups eastwards to Baghirmi. Distinct
                    speech.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Central Soudan and Chad Basin.</hi><hi rend="italic">Adamawa
                    Group</hi>: Batta, Dama, Fala, Burna, Marga, Holma, Ba, Bula, Kilba, Buza,
                    Mbafu, Kotafa, Woka, Fani, Doga, Longoda. Upper Binue; thence east to Logon.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tubu Group</hi>: Teda, Dasa, Kanembu, Dalatoa, Kanuri, Danawa,
                    Haussa (?), Baele, Bodele, Bulala(l), Kuka(?), Zoghawa. Tibesti, Kanem, Bornu,
                    Borku, and north Dar-Fur.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Logon Group</hi>: Logon, Mandara, Margi, Makari, Mosgu,
                    Gamergu, So (extinct), Keribina, Yedina (Buduma), Kuri (Kalea), Bede, Ngisem,
                    Kerrikerri, Babir, Fika. Bornu, lower Shari (between Adamawa and Baghirmi), Chad
                    archipelagoes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Baghirmi Group</hi>: Baghirmi, Somrai, Tummok, Kuang, Busso,
                    Gaberi, Nyillem, Ndamm, Sara, Dekakire, Sokoro, Bua Kullanga, Bua Kuli, Yussiye,
                    Sarûa. Lower and middle Shari, east to Runga and Dar-Banda.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wadai Group</hi>: Maba (Kelingen, Kajanga, Malanga, Kuno, Bili,
                    and many other subdivisions), Masalit, Mimi, Marfa, Korunga, Moëwo, Abyi,
                    Kondongo, Kabbaga, Mubi, Marta, Bakka, Birkit, Tala. Wadai and east Dar-Fur.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">East Soudan and Upper Nile.</hi><hi rend="italic">Dar-Banda
                    Group</hi>: Runga, Kredy, Ago, Silla, Bandala, Daggel, Gulla, Fana, Birrimbirri,
                    Seli, Kutingara. Upper Shari, east to Dar-Fertit.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fur Groιιp:</hi> Fur (Forang-bele), Dudunga, Kunjara, Kera,
                    Massabât, Tunjur, Dajo, Berti, Bego, Birguid, Berdûna, Jellaba, Sungor, Mararit,
                    Jebal, Guimir, Kabga. Dàr-Fur and Kordofan, between Wadai and White Nile.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Nilotic Group</hi>: Shilluk, Nuer, Dinka, Bongo, Jur, Bari,
                    Mittu, Rôl, Millow, Agar, Sofi, Lehssi, Ayell, Ayarr, Monbuttu, Janghey,
                    Fallaugh, Miauk, Bonjak, Jibbe, Kunkung, Nikuar, Madi, Loboré, Shuli, Berta,
                    Amain. White Nile and its tributaries, east to Kaffa and Gallaland, south to
                    Uganda.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Zandey</hi> (Niam-Niam): Large, compact nation, about the
                    Welle, and reaching southwards probably to the Lualaba.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">South Africa—Bantu Family.</hi><hi rend="italic">Zulu·Kaffre
                    Group</hi>: Ama-Zulu, Ama-Khosa, Ama-Fingu, Ma-Tonga, Ama-Zuazi, Ba-Tembu,
                    Matebele, Mazitu, Masai (?). Zululand, Natal, Kaffraria, and in scattered
                    fragments from the Limpopo north to the great lakes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Central Group</hi>: Be-Chuana, Ba-Suto, Ba-Rolong, Ma-Kololo,
                    Ma-Rotse, Ma-Kalaka (Ma-Nansa), Ma-Laya, Ma-Totola, Ma-Shukulombwe, Ma-Shubia,
                    Ma-Nchoia, Ma-Mbunda, Ba-Libale, Ma-Pingula, Ma-Hes, Ba-Yeiye. Upper Orange
                    river, Transvaal, Lake Ngami, upper and middle Zambesi, and Chobe river<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Ma-Kololo, as a distinct
                    people, have been destroyed by the Ma-Rotse; but their language (a mixed
                    Se-Chuana and Se-Suto dialect) survives as the <hi rend="italic">lingua
                    franca</hi> in the Ba-Rotse state, and generally between the Limpopo and Zambesi
                    (Dr Holub and I'fere Depelchin).</p></note>. <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Eastern Group</hi>: Wa-Swahili, Wa-Pokomo, Wa-Nika, Wa-Kamba,
                    Wa-Sambara, Wa-Zaramo, Achikunda, Ma-Gololo, A-Nyasa, Wa-Yao, Ma-Chinga, A-Ngulu
                    (Walolo), Ma-Kua, Ma-Tumboka, Wa-Jagga, Wa-Segua. East coast from the equator
                    south to Delagoa Bay, and inland to Lake Nyassa.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Equatorial Group</hi>: Wa-Ganda, Wa-Nyoro, Wa-Nyamwesi,
                    Wa-Sukuma, Wa-Legga, Wa-Rundi, Wa-Lha, Wa-Fipa, Wa-Bemba, Wa-Bisa, Wa-Rua,
                    Wa-Lunda, Kioko, Wa-Shinsh, Tu-Shinsh, Tu-Shilange, Tu-Ruba, Tu-Kette, Ba-Songe
                    (Ba-Luba), A-Kawanda (Ma-Wanda), Ba-Tetela, Ba-Kuba, Lovalé, Wa-Mangala, Ibonga,
                    Ba-Rumbe, Ba-Bwende. Region of the great lakes, upper and middle Lualaba, south
                    to the Lokinga (Mushinga) range.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Western Group:</hi> Ova-Herero, Ova-Mbo, Ova-Quanyama,</p>
                <p>Kibokwe, Bailunda, Kibanda, Kisanji, Nano, Sindohga, Ba-Softgo, Ma-Tamba,
                    Ma-Yakka, Ba-Kongo, Kimbunda, Ma-Hungo, Shissilongi, Ma-Yombe, Ba-Teke, Obamba,
                    Odumbo, Aduma, Bakota, Mbamba, Ashongo, Apinji, Okanda, Bangwé, Mpongwé,
                    Ba-Kalai, Isubu, Bimbia, Ba-Kwilleh, Dualia, Abo, Wuri, Qua Qua (Ba-Koko),
                    Lungasi, Edea, Bubi (Fernandian). West coast from Damaraland north to Cameroon
                    mountains; inland to about 20° E. long.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Intruders in the northern section of this group are the
                    non-Negro Fans, the Oshyeba of the other natives. There are two main
                    divisions,—Maké-Fan on the left, Mbelé-Fan on the right bank of the
                    Ogoway.</p></note></p>
                <p>The total population is vaguely estimated at 130,000,000, to which must be added
                    probably about 20,000,000 full-blood and half-caste Negroes settled either
                    as-slaves or the descendants of slaves in various parts of the world, but
                    chiefly in tropical and sub-tropical America. Owing to their peculiar qualities,
                    great muscular development, and power of endurance in hot and moist lands,
                    combined with a remarkable absence of personal self-respect, the African
                    populations have from the remotest times supplied a chief material to the slave
                    markets of the Old and the New World. For thousands of years an incessant stream
                    of black blood has been directed from the interior to the east coast and thence
                    to Madagascar, Arabia, Persia, and even India, or down the Nile to Egypt and
                    Asia Minor, or across the Sahara to the Barbary States. Since the discovery of
                    America hundreds of thousands have in the same way been shipped from the west
                    coast for the West Indies, New Spain, the British and French plantations, and
                    Brazil. Speaking generally, this black element has not amalgamated with the
                    populations of the eastern hemisphere, and has consequently left few traces of
                    its presence anywhere except in Madagascar, where there may possibly have been
                    an indigenous Negro people before the arrival of the intruding Hovas and other
                    Malay tribes. Nevertheless a strain of Negro blood is apparent, not only amongst
                    the Tuaregs and especially the Tibus of the Sahara, but also in Morocco, South
                    Algeria, Egypt, the low-lying Tehama of the West Arabian seaboard, Makran, and
                    even here and there along the coast of Malabar and Ceylon. But no statistics are
                    anywhere here available which might throw some light on the proportion of blacks
                    to the surrounding populations. We read that there may be as many as 100,000 in
                    Morocco, a large number amongst the Berbers of Wargla (South Algeria) and
                    Tripoli, and so on. It is also evident that a decided majority of the
                    inhabitants of Madagascar must be regarded as of Negroid stock, although no
                    Negro language has held its ground either there or anywhere beyond the Negro
                    domain proper.</p>
                <p>This is the more surprising that in some parts of America, notably the West
                    Indian islands, the coloured has actually replaced the indigenous and largely
                    absorbed the white element. Here we are altogether on firmer ground, and fairly
                    accurate returns enable us to form an approximate estimate of the proportion of
                    full-blood and half-caste Negroes in almost every part of the New World. On the
                    other hand, the nomenclature of these mongrels has become so perplexing, and is
                    often applied so irregularly, that it has led to many misconceptions on this
                    point. Thus the term “Creole,” applicable in Mexico only to persons of pure
                    Spanish descent, denotes in Brazil, Peru, and elsewhere the presence of black
                    blood in varying proportions. Of this bewildering nomenclature the chief terms
                    are as under :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Negro, African, Black</hi>: Full-blood Negro, whether born in
                    Africa or of African descent.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mτιlatto</hi>: Issue of black and white parents either way—a
                    constant term in America.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mestizo</hi>: Any half-breed, whether of white and Negro
                    parents, or (more commonly in Spanish America) of white and Indian parents.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Creole</hi>: Mostly white of pure descent, but also blacks of
                    pure descent (Brazil), the issue of whites and Mestizoes (Peru), and Mestizoes
                    generally (Alaska).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Zarnbo</hi>: Any half-breed, but mostly the issue of Negro and
                    Indian parents; in the United States, Peru, and West Indies of Negro and
                    Mulatto; in St Vincent the half-caste Caribs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Zarnbo Preto:</hi> Issue of Negro father and Zamba mother
                    (Mexico and elsewhere).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cholo</hi>: Issue of Zamboes (South America).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pardo:</hi> Synonymous with Mulatto (Brazil); any Mestizo
                    (Argentine States).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mamaluco</hi>: Any Mestizo, but especially the issue of whites
                    and Indians (Brazil).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Chino</hi>: Negro and Indian half-caste (Mexico, and generally
                    in Spanish America).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Casco</hi>: Direct issue of Mulattoes on both sides (South
                    America).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tente en</hi><hi rend="italic">elAyre:</hi> Mongrels in whom
                    the white element predominates (South America).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cafuso:</hi> Issue of Negro and Indian, dark shade and woolly
                    hair predominating (Brazil).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cabaret</hi>: Issue of Negress and Indian (Brazil).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cariboco, Tapanhuna, Xibaro</hi>: Local Brazilian terms of Tupi
                    origin applied to various crosses between the Negroes and Indians.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n332/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0332-0319"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Quarter oon, Quinteroon, Octoroon</hi>: Negro and white
                    half-breeds, with fresh infusion of white blood each successive generation.
                    Thus: Quarteroon has one-fourth, Quinteroon one-eighth, Octoroon one-sixteenth
                    black blood only, the last being scarcely distinguishable from a white.</p>
                <p>Before the suppression of the slave trade, during the first half of the present
                    century, from 60,000 to 70,000 Negroes were annually shipped to America, where
                    their descendants of all shades now number altogether upwards of twelve millions
                    as under :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Coloured Element.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Proportion to the Whole Population..</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>United States</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6,580,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13 per cent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mexico</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>⅜ »</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Central America</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>West Indies</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,700,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>83 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Brazil</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,000,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In Hayti the Africans have established their political autonomy, here forming two
                    independent states, with total population 820,00.0. Elsewhere slavery has been
                    everywhere abolished, except in Brazil, where it is rapidly becoming extinct.
                    Hence the whole of the coloured population now practically constitutes a class
                    of freedmen, in some places apparently dying out (Central America, Argentine
                    States), in some remaining stationary (Mexico, Peru), but in others increasing
                    rapidly. This is especially the case in the United States, as shown by the
                    subjoined returns for the whole of the present century :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Coloured Element.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Proportion to the Whole Population.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1800</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,002,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19 per cent.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1820</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,772,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1840</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,874,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>17</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1860</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,442,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,880,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1880</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6,581,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>It is obvious from this table that the Negroes, without any further importations
                    from Africa, are increasing far more rapidly than the native whites, and that
                    they would ultimately become the predominant element in the Southern States but
                    for the constant stream of migration flowing from Europe to North America. Owing
                    to this migration they decreased relatively to the rest of the population from
                    1820 to 1860. But since then they have maintained their relative proportion in
                    spite of this migration. Recently they have themselves begun to move westwards
                    at the rate of about 50,000 annually. Should the movement continue, an
                    equilibrium may be established, because the rate of mortality gains on the
                    birth-rate according as they move farther from the hot Southern States, where
                    alone the race can expect to establish itself in the republic.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> Pπιner Bey, <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur
                    les Nègres,</hi> Paris, 1861; Winwood Reade, <hi rend="italic">Savage
                    Africa·,</hi> Karl Vogt, <hi rend="italic">Vorlesungen über den Menschen·,</hi>
                    Filippo Manetta, <hi rend="italic">La Razza Negra nel</hi><hi rend="italic">suo
                    stato</hi><hi rend="italic">selvaggio e nella sua duplice condizione di</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">emancipata</hi><hi rend="italic">e di schiava,</hi> Turin, 1864;
                    John Campbell, <hi rend="italic">Negromania.</hi> Philadelphia, 1851; J. F.
                    Blumenbach, De <hi rend="italic">Generis</hi><hi rend="italic">Humani Varietate
                    Nativa,</hi> Göttingen, 1775; Lawrence, <hi rend="italic">Physiology, Zoology,
                    and Natural History of Man,</hi> 1819; Dr Paul Broca, “Memoirs” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Bulletins de la Soc. d'</hi><hi rend="italic">Anthropologie,</hi>
                    1860-78; Dr Van Evrie, <hi rend="italic">On Negroes and Negro Slavery,</hi>
                    Brehm, <hi rend="italic">Reise-Skizzen aus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Nordost-Africa;</hi> Col. Hamilton Smith, <hi rend="italic">Natural History of
                    the Human Species,</hi> Edinburgh, 1848; Hutchinson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Wanderings in West Africa·,</hi> George MacHenry, <hi rend="italic">The Cotton
                    Trade and Negro Slavery,</hi> London, 1863; S. G. Morton, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Crania</hi><hi rend="italic">Aegyptiaca·,</hi> Peter A. Browne, <hi
                    rend="italic">Classification of Mankind by the Hair and Wool of their
                    Heads·,</hi> Nott and Gliddon, <hi rend="italic">Indigenous Races of the
                    Earth,</hi> Philadelphia, 1857; Wilson, <hi rend="italic">Ethnographic View of
                    West Africa,</hi> New York, 1856; Prichard, <hi rend="italic">Natural History of
                    Man,</hi> London, 1855; Latham, <hi rend="italic">Varieties of Man,</hi> London,
                    1850; E. B. Tylor, <hi rend="italic">Anthropology,</hi> London, 1881; Pickering,
                    <hi rend="italic">Races of Man,</hi> London, 1850; R. N. Cust, <hi rend="italic"
                    >A Sketch of the Modern Languages of Africa,</hi> London, 1883; F. L. James, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Wild Tribes of the Sudan,</hi> London, 1883. The writings of
                    the travellers Leo Africanus, Bruce, Mungo Park, Denham, Clapperton, Lander,
                    Burckhardt, Barth, Richardson, Nachtigal, Schweinfurth, Baker, Junker, Beltrami,
                    for Soudan and Nile basin; of Krapf, Du Chaillu, Burton, Speke and Grant,
                    Livingstone, Magyar, Cameron, Fritsche, Bleek, Lentz, Pogge and Wissmann,
                    Schuver, Holub, Mohr, Buchner, Gussfeldt, for equatorial and south Africa. (A.
                    H. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
