<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0375-0360-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IRON MASK (9th edition, volume 13, page 360)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z73t">Masks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1011082">Masks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847566">Caring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n375/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IRON MASK</label>. The Man in the Iron Mask is the name by
                    which a French state prisoner, whose identity has given rise to much curious
                    inquiry, is universally known. The facts established by contemporaneous evidence
                    respecting this mysterious personage, who died in 1703, were, until a modern
                    writer largely added to them, neither numerous nor of very great
                    importance.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Dujunca, the
                    chief turnkey of the Bastille, whose register has fortunately been preserved,
                    gives us this account of the captive: —“On Thursday, the 18th September 1698, at
                    three o’clock in the afternoon, Μ. Saint Mars, the governor, arrived at the
                    Bastille for the first time from the islands of Sainte Marguerite and Sainte
                    Honnat. He brought with him in his own litter an ancient prisoner formerly under
                    his care at Pignerol, and whose name remains untold. This prisoner was always
                    kept masked, and was at first lodged in the Basinit·re tower. . , . I conducted
                    him afterwards to the Bertandière town, and put him in a room, which, by order
                    of Μ. de Saint Mars, I had furnished before his arrival.” A letter of Μ. de
                    Formanoir, a grandnephew of Saint Mars, furnishes the following details :—“In
                    1698 Μ. de Saint Mars exchanged the governorship of the islands forthat of the
                    Bastille. When he set off to enter on his new office he stayed with his prisoner
                    for a short time at Palteau, his estate. The Mask arrived in a litter which
                    preceded that of Μ. de Saint Mars; they were accompanied by several men on
                    horseback. The peasants went out to meet their seigneur. Μ. de Saint Mars took
                    his meals with his prisoner, who sat with his back towards the windows of the
                    room, which looked into the court-yard. The peasants of whom I made enquiry
                    could not see if he had his mask on when eating; but they observed that Μ. de
                    Saint Mars, who sat opposite to him at table, had a pair of pistols beside his
                    plate. They were attended by a single valet only, Antoine Ru, who took away the
                    dishes set down to him in an antechamber, having first carefully shut the door
                    of the dining-room. When the prisoner crossed the court-yard a black mask was
                    always on his face.” Dujunca’s journal contains this entry respecting the death
                    of the secluded prisoner, who, it may be added, was named “Μ. de Marchiel” in
                    the Bastille register:—“On Monday’, the 19th of November 1703, the unknown
                    prisoner, who had continually wonι a black velvet mask, and whom Μ. de Saint
                    Mars had brought with him from the island of Sainte Marguerite, died to-day at
                    about ten o’clock in the evening, having been yesterday taken slightly’ ill. He
                    had been a long time in Μ. de Saint Mars’s hands, and his illness was
                    exceedingly’ trifling.”</p></note> Enough indeed is related <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n376/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0376-0361"/> to show that even in his lifetime the veiled
                    prisoner had become an object of curious mystery. Other instances occur,
                    however, of captivity under like conditions; and nothing in the treatment of the
                    Mask proves that he was a personage of rank and importance. It has been
                    indisputably shown that it was no uncommon practice, especially in the reign of
                    Louis XIV., to isolate human beings and keep them immured, their very features
                    being carefully hidden, and that the victims were persons of all conditions.
                    Though one or two efforts had been previously made to find out the name of the
                    unknown prisoner, Voltaire was the first writer of note to give form and life to
                    the vague traditions that had been current about the Mask; and we may probably
                    ascribe to his suggestive account the increased importance which since his time
                    the subject has been supposed to possess. In his <hi rend="italic">Age of Louis
                    XIV.</hi> the historian hinted that the Mask was a person of high rank; and he
                    graphically described how this mysterious being endeavoured to commune with the
                    outer world by throwing out, on the shore of Sainte Marguerite, from the grated
                    window of his gloomy dungeon, a piece of fine linen, and a silver plate, on
                    which he had traced some strange characters to revêal a horrible tale of
                    misfortune. This work was published in 1751, nearly fifty years after the death
                    of the Mask; and from this time the problem who he was has been investigated
                    with no little diligence. The editor of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophic
                    Dictionary</hi> suggested that he was an illegitimate son of Anne of Austria,
                    born in 1626; and in 1790 he was identified, in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of
                    Cardinal Richelieu</hi> with a supposed twin brother of Louis XIV., put out of
                    the way by the great Cardinal to avoid the ills of a disputed succession. As
                    early as 1745 the Mask was said, by an anonymous writer, to have been the count
                    of Vermandois, one of the bastards of Louis XIV.; in 1759 M. Lagrange-Chaucel
                    endeavoured to prove that he was the duke of Beaufort, a hero of the Fronde; a
                    few years afterwards M. St Foix conjectured that he was the duke of Monmouth,
                    the English pretender of 1685; and others have laboured to show that he was
                    either a son of the Protector Cromwell, or Fouquet, the minister of Louis XIV.,
                    or Avcdick, the Armenian patriarch, whose treacherous imprisonment by the
                    ambassador of France was one of the worst acts of that unscrupulous king. The
                    claim, finally, of Ercolo Mattioli, a diplomatic agent of the duke of Mantua,
                    was put forward in 1770, and since that time has found zealous advocates in MM.
                    Roux-Fazillac, Delort, Topin, and in the late Lord Dover; indeed, until lately
                    it was generally thought that Mattioli was the mysterious captive.</p>
                <p>The claims, however, of none of these can stand the test of the searching inquiry
                    which recent discoveries have made possible. Voltaire does not inform us who the
                    Mask was; his hint that he was an exalted personage is at variance with a remark
                    of his on the same subject in a later work; and as for the tale of the attempts
                    made by the Mask to divulge his name and fate, these have been traced to a
                    Huguenot pastor, imprisoned in the islands of Sainte Marguerite. There is no
                    evidence that the illegitimate child of Anne of Austria, or the twin brother of
                    Louis XIV. ever existed. Fouquet died in 1680, the count of Vermandois in 1683,
                    and the duke of Beaufort in 1689; Monmouth fell under the axe of the headsman;
                    Avcdick was not imprisoned until 1706. The case made on behalf of Mattioli also
                    breaks down when carefully sifted. Mattioli was certainly imprisoned at
                    Pignerol, and that for a considerable time; he was also long under the care of
                    Saint Mars; and he was detained at the Sainte Marguerites, in the custody of the
                    same jailer. But on the other hand the Mask is never named in the numerous
                    documents that refer to him; he was certainly imprisoned at Exiles; and he was
                    brought from the Sainte Marguerites, and died in the Bastille; whereas
                    Mattioli’s name occurs not seldom in the correspondence of Saint Mars; he cannot
                    be traced to Exiles; and it is almost certain that he died at the Sainte
                    Marguerites in 1694.</p>
                <p>Is it impossible, then, to fix the identity of the unknown Mask? The latest
                    writer upon the subject is Μ. Jung, a French staff officer, and his diligent
                    investigations have brought us perhaps very near the solution of the problem. He
                    appears to have fully proved that the prisoner of 1698—beyond question the
                    mysterious Mask—had for many years been guarded by St Mars; that he had long
                    been known as “your ancient prisoner,” “your prisoner of twenty years standing”;
                    and that at the Sainte Marguerites he was jealously watched with precautions
                    nearly of the same kind as those afterwards taken at the Bastille. He has shown,
                    moreover, that this very prisoner was, in 1687, removed to the Sainte
                    Marguerites from Exiles, always under the eye of the same jailer, and that, too,
                    with the care and secrecy observed in the journey to the Bastille; and, finally,
                    he has traced the captive to Pignerol, still in the hands of the relentless St
                    Mars, where, in 1681, we find him designated as one of the “two prisoners of the
                    Lower Tower,” apparently for some years in confinement. This prisoner, too, is
                    never once named, which, as we have seen, was the case with the Mask. On the
                    whole it would seem that Μ. Jung has established the identity of the object of
                    our search with this unknown person. He goes, however, a great deal further, and
                    endeavours to find out the name and the history of the prisoner of the Lower
                    Tower of Pignerol. His theory is that he was a criminal who probably played a
                    prominent part in one of the numerous poisoning plots which disgraced the reign
                    of Louis XIV.; and he identifies him with a Lorraine gentleman who seems to have
                    belonged to a murderous band of conspirators against the life of the king, and
                    who, being then arrested at Peronne, was lodged in the Bastille in 1673, and
                    thence taken, he makes out, to Pignerol. His narrative abounds in interest, but
                    he has adduced no valid proof to connect the supposed prisoner captured at
                    Peronne with the prisoner of 1673; and he has not given us anything like
                    evidence to associate this last-named person with either of the prisoners of the
                    Lower Tower at Pignerol, or even to show that he reached that fortress. Besides,
                    he has not ascertained the identity of these two prisoners. The mystery of the
                    identity of the Mask thus remains unsolved; but the field of inquiry has been
                    greatly narrowed, and further investigation will not improbably discover this
                    strange historical secret. (W. O. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
