<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0214-0203-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IONA, or Icolmkill (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    203)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xp5n">Columbae</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:868816">Columba</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152439">Tombs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n214/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IONA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Icolmkill</hi></label>, a small
                    island of the Hebrides, on the west coast of Scotland, in the county of Argyll,
                    is situated about 8 miles south of Staffa and 1∣ miles west of the south-western
                    promontory of Mull, from which it is separated by the shallow Sound of Iona. Its
                    length is about 3∣ and its breadth 1∣ miles. The total area is about 2000
                    imperial acres, of which about 600 are under cul- <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi>
                    tivation. Along the north-western shore patches of green pasture alternate with
                    small irregular rocky elevations, culminating in the north of the island in
                    Dunii, which has an elevation of about 330 feet. From the base of Dunii to the
                    shore there is a stretch of low land consisting of shelly sand covered partly
                    with grass, but towards the east exhibiting a surface of unbroken and dazzling
                    whiteness. The southern part of the island consists of a combination of rocky
                    elevations and grassy ravines, the rocks in the south-west corner presenting a
                    bold and precipitous front to the sea. Geologically Iona is composed of
                    Laurentian gneiss of great variety of character and very contorted
                    stratification. Its deficiency in natural features of special interest is
                    compensated for by the striking and various views obtained of the surrounding
                    archipelago of islands, including the neighbouring Mull and Jura, and the
                    distant mountains of Skye. Fronting the sound is the small village of Iona or
                    Buile Mor, consisting of about fifty cottages. There are two churches
                    (Established and Free) and a school. Oats, barley, and potatoes are grown on the
                    island, and it affords sustenance for about 300 cattle, 600 sheep, 20 horses,
                    and 60 pigs; but the inhabitants are dependent for support as much on fishing as
                    on agriculture. Population in 1861, 264; in 1871, 236; in 1881, 243.</p>
                <p>The relics of antiquity still remaining consist of part of the cathedral church
                    of St Mary, the nunnery, some small chapels, a building called the bishop’s
                    house, and a number of ancient tombs or crosses. The cathedral, dating from the
                    13th century, is built in the usual form of a cross, and consists of nave,
                    transept, and choir, with a sacristy on the north side and chapels on the south.
                    A great portion of the walls and the central tower, about 75 feet in height, are
                    still standing. It contains a number of old tombs. To the north are the remains
                    of the conventual buildings which from a Norman arcade still standing appear to
                    have been of an older date than the cathedral. The chapel of St Oran or Odhrain
                    situated in the cemetery, on the south side of the monastery, dates probably
                    from the 11th century, and its western doorway presents a Norman arch with the
                    beak-head ornament. The cemetery, called in Gaelic <hi rend="italic">Peilig
                    Oiran,</hi> the burial-place of kings, and said to contain the remains of
                    forty-eight Scottish, four Irish, and eight Danish or Norwegian monarchs,
                    possesses a largo number of monumental stones. The remains of the nunnery
                    exhibit traces of Norman architecture. Of the numerous crosses erected in the
                    island the finest are Maclean’s cross and St Martin’s cross, which are still
                    almost entire. Both <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n215/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0215-0204"/> are richly carved with Runic knots and various
                    emblematic devices and fanciful scrolls.</p>
                <p>The original form of the name Iona was Hy, Hii, or I, the Irish for island. By
                    Adamnan in his <hi rend="italic">Life of St Columba</hi> it is called <hi
                    rend="italic">loua</hi><hi rend="italic">insula,</hi> and the present name Iona
                    originated in some transcriber mistaking the <hi rend="italic">u</hi> in <hi
                    rend="italic">loua</hi> for an n. It also received the name of Hu-colum-kill
                    (Icolmkill), that is, the island of Columba of the Cell, while by the
                    Highlanders it has been known as Innis nan Druidhneah, the island of the Druids.
                    It was in the year 563 that Columba, after leaving the shores of Ireland,
                    entered the creek of Iona noW known as <hi rend="italic">Port-a-churraich,</hi>
                    the port of the coracle, and, having satisfied himself of the suitability of the
                    island for his . purpose, founded there his famous monastery. The island was
                    then inhabited by a Pictish population, but it has been disputed whether Columba
                    obtained the grant of it from Conall, king of Dalriada, or from Brude, king of
                    the Picts. Columba was buried in Iona, but between 802 and 807 his remains were
                    transferred from it to the church of St Patrick in the county Down, Ireland. For
                    a long time the monastery of Iona held the supremacy among all the monasteries
                    and churches founded by Columba and his disciples. It was several times
                    plundered and burned by the Norsemen, and its inmates on more than one occasion
                    put to death. The Western Isles having come into the possession of Scotland in
                    1072, the monastery ot Iona was rebuilt and endowed by Queen Margaret. In 1092
                    they were, however, ceded to Magnus Barefoot of Norway, who after the renewal of
                    the cession by Edgar in 1097 visited Iona and allowed the people to retain their
                    possessions. The diocese of the Isles, founded about 838, of which Iona was the
                    seat, was united by Magnus to the bishopric of Man, and made subject to the
                    archbishopric of Drontheim in Norway. A new monastery as well as a nunnery was
                    founded by the Benedictines in 1203, and the Benedictine order either absorbed
                    or expelled the Celtic community. About 1507 the island again became the seat of
                    the bishopric of the Isles. The monastery was demolished in accordance with the
                    Act passed by the Convention of Estates in 1561. For many centuries it was much
                    frequented on account of its facilities for learning, and, as may be supposed,
                    became after the death of Columba a great resort of pilgrims, many of whom came
                    in order to die on the island that their remains might be interred in its sacred
                    soil; while the remains of persons illustrious in rank or in piety were brought
                    to it for burial from all parts of northern Europe. The site of the old
                    monastery was about a quarter of a mile north from the present ruins.</p>
                <p>See, in addition to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Columba,</hi> and the old
                    authorities therein cited, Montalernbert’s <hi rend="italic">Monks of the
                    West,</hi> vol. iii.; <hi rend="italic">The Cathedral or Abbey Church of
                    Iona,</hi> by Bishop Ewing, 1866; <hi rend="italic">Iona,</hi> by the Duke of
                    Argyll, 1870; Skene’s <hi rend="italic">Celtic Scotland,</hi> vol. ii, 1877; and
                    <hi rend="italic">Sculptured Monuments in Iona and the West Highlands,</hi> by
                    James Drummond, 1881.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
