<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0374-0359-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">IRON, Therapeutic uses of (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    359)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wr3t">Oxygen</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1049655">Oxygenators</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1049616">Oxygen</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n374/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">IRON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Therapeutic uses of</hi></label>.
                    The use of iron in the cure of disease dates from a very early period. Pliny
                    speaks of its medicinal effects, and there is reason for believing that it was
                    administered several centuries before his time. But Sydenham was the first to
                    point out its most important therapeutic property, its blood-restoring power.
                    “To the worn out and languid blood,” he says, “it gives a spur or fillip whereby
                    the animal spirits which before lay prostrate or sunk under their own weight are
                    roused and excited.”</p>
                <p>The blood is composed of a fluid wherein float roundish red bodies, the blood
                    corpuscles, which play a leading part in those tissue changes essential to life.
                    Each corpuscle consists of a stroma permeated by a red fluid, haemoglobin, which
                    has the remarkable property of readily combining with either oxygen or carbonic
                    acid, but so loosely that under slightly altered conditions these gases are as
                    readily separated from it. In the lungs the corpuscles, through their
                    haemoglobin, take up oxygen which they carry to all parts of the body. But in
                    the presence of the vital processes of disintegration and repair constantly
                    going on in the tissues, the corpuscles yield up the oxygen they have brought,
                    and supply an element necessary for these processes. Having got rid of the
                    oxygen, the haemoglobin then unites with the carbonic acid produced by tissue
                    disintegration, and the corpuscles thus reladen carry their burden Back to the
                    lungs, and discharge there the carbonic acid, taking up anew a supply of oxygen.
                    If the haemoglobiu of the blood fall below a certain standard, the supply of
                    oxygen necessary to healthy tissue changes in brain, nerve, muscle, &amp;c.,
                    becomes too limited, and the changes will be imperfectly performed; hence
                    defective vitality, general or local. Now the ingestion of iron increases the
                    haemoglobin supply when it is defective; it promotes the production of blood
                    corpuscles, and causes each corpuscle to carry with it more haemoglobin; hence
                    the health-giving power possessed by this metal. The exact method in which the
                    increase in red colouring matter is brought about we do not know, but in the
                    fact that iron forms an essential constituent of haemoglobin we have some clue
                    to its utility.</p>
                <p>Anaemia or spanaemia is the name given to that condition in which the red
                    colouring matter of the blood is below the normal amount. It is indicated by
                    pallor of skin and mucous membranes, and by a depressed condition of brain, of
                    muscle, and of the tissues generally. A beating headache is often present,
                    sustained mental or physical exertion is difficult, palpitation and
                    breathlessness are sources of inconvenience; in the female the uterine functions
                    are often in abeyance. By a chalybeate course we can usually restore to the
                    blood its due supply of haemoglobin, and cause the gradual disappearance of all
                    these symptoms.</p>
                <p>It would be impossible here to enumerate all the special forms of spanaemia in
                    which iron is prescribed. It will be sufficient to point <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n375/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0375-0360"/> out the leading conditions under which it may be
                    given with every hope of advantage, and those in which it usually fails to do
                    good. First of all, it is of marked benefit in the spanaemia of young females,
                    which is often accompanied by a faint greenish or yellowish discoloration of the
                    skill. Chlorosis is the name usually given to this condition. Here iron almost,
                    unfailingly though slowly removes the pallor, breathlessness, and palpitation,
                    increases mental and physical vigour, and restores the uterine functions. Where
                    the blood has been impoverished by haeniorrhages, want of proper food, or
                    exposure to bad hygienic conditions, iron rarely fails to improve its character,
                    provided the causes of such impoverishment are removed. In convalescence from
                    many illnesses, iron is employed with advantage, and it aids recovery from such
                    constitutional diseases as rickets and scrofula by its restorative effect on the
                    blood, sometimes too in syphilitic cachexia it is of service. On the other hand,
                    in the obscure disease called pernicious anaemia, the cause of which is so far
                    unknown, but in which the deficiency of haemoglobin is extreme, iron is rarely
                    even of temporary service. It is generally useless too in the spanaemia
                    attendant on advancing consumption where the temperature is high; some
                    physicians indeed hold that in such cases it is injurious, because it increases
                    temperature. In chronic diseases leading to spanaemia, where the cause of the
                    poverty of blood is continuously present, iron is often of but little service.
                    Such is the case in cancer and most of those emaciating ailments which tend
                    naturally to a lethal termination. But in valvular disease of the heart, iron
                    though not curative often helps to prolong life and relieve suffering, for by
                    enriching the blood it spares the heart some of its labour, and at the same time
                    strengthens the cardiac walls. In Bright’s disease too, which is often
                    accompanied with bloodlessness, iron is a most valuable medicine in prolonging
                    life even though incapable of saving it.</p>
                <p>Hitherto we have spoken of iron only in its capacity of a strengthening agent
                    acting through its power of stimulating the production of haemoglobin, but it
                    may be beneficial in other ways. It is suppose! to augment the production in the
                    blood of that active oxydizing agent ozone, but of this we have little or no
                    proof; there is, however, considerable probability that the iron which exists as
                    an albuminate in the blood serum has some direct tonic effect on the tissues
                    through which it circulates; and the astringent preparations, such as the
                    sulphate, are most effective in bracing the gastro-intestinal mucous membrane
                    when it is relaxed.</p>
                <p>Iron is of use iu some diseases of special organs and systems, partly perhaps
                    from its general tonic effect, but in part too no doubt from some, local
                    nutritive action which it has. In neuralgia, for example, it is sometimes
                    curative, more certainly so, however, if combined with quinine. In chorea, or St
                    Vitus’s dance, too, it is of value, especially when combined with arsenic. On
                    the digestive organs chalybeates have at times a good effect, some forms of
                    dyspepsia and diarrhoea being favourably influenced by them. Iron too is of
                    service often in the nocturnal incontinence of children, and is often given as
                    an emmenagogue. In gout, plethora, and most febrile ailments, the administration
                    of iron is usually held to be injurious, but in erysipelas the administration of
                    half drachm doses of the tincture of the perchloride of iron every four hours
                    has been highly lauded, and Dr Russell Reynolds advocates the use of similar
                    doses in acute rheumatisms. Iron is valued for the astringent effects of some of
                    its preparations on parts with which they come in contact, as well as for its
                    good effects on the blood and various organs after ingestion.</p>
                <p>The tincture of perchloride of iron is used as a styptic to stop bleeding from
                    the gums or from leech bites, or other slight haemoi·- rhages. Sometimes too it
                    is of service locally applied in bleeding of a more serious character, but it is
                    a strong irritant to the parts with which it comes in contact. One part of the
                    tincture of the perchloride mixed with three of water is sometimes injected up
                    the nostril to check persistent nose bleeding. Lint moistened with the tincture
                    is also used as a plug for the same purpose. For stopping haemorrhage after
                    confinement, the plan introduced by Dr Barnes of injecting a solution of
                    perchloride of iron into the uterus is frequently followed with the greatest
                    advantage. The perchloride and sulphate of iron may be given to check
                    haemorrhage from the stomach, and these salts have likewise been used to
                    decrease the discharge in gonorrhoea and leucorrhoea. The local application of
                    the tincture of perchloride of iron in diphtheria has been highly recommended,
                    and a very dilute solution is sometimes used as a rectal injection to destroy
                    thread-worms.</p>
                <p>As a medicine iron is used in many forms and combinations, and thirty-three of
                    these arc described in the <hi rend="italic">British Pharmacopoeia.</hi> The
                    metal itself, finely divided, is often administered in 1 or 2 grain
                    doses,—ferrum redactum the preparation is called,—and lozenges are made of it,
                    each containing 1 grain of reduced iron. The vinum ferri or solution of iron in
                    wine is probably the most ancient of all iron preparations. Of the oxides, the
                    peroxide and the magnetic oxide are officinal. The former was in early times
                    known under the name of saffron or crocus of iron, and was much used; but now
                    more soluble preparations of iron are usually prescribed. Recently precipitated
                    peroxide in a moist condition is one of the best antidotes for arsenical
                    poisoning if given in quarter to half ounce doses. The carbonates of iron
                    readily undergo oxidation unless mixed with sugar, which therefore enters into
                    all the phar-macopoeial preparations of iron, the saccharated carbonate of iron,
                    the pill of the carbonate of iron, and the compound iron mixture. Perhaps the
                    most commonly used and the best known astringent preparations of iron are the
                    combinations of this metal with vegetable acids, the ammonia citrate of iron and
                    the tartrate of iron, which are given in 5 to 10 grain doses, the former too in
                    the form of wine (vinum ferri citratis). The combination of citrate of iron and
                    quinine is an exceedingly valuable preparation, and is given in 3 to 5 grain
                    doses. The acetate of iron is somewhat astringent, but, though officinal, is
                    very rarely used. The sulphate and perchloride of iron are powerful astringents,
                    constricting the tissues with which they come in contact. Several preparations
                    of these salts are officinal. Their use as local applications has been alluded
                    to; internally they are given instead of the non-astringent chalybeates, when a
                    tissue-bracing as well as a blood-restoring effect is desired. They are more
                    constipating than the non-astringent chalybeates. The dose of the solution and
                    tincture of perchloride of iron is from 5 to 20 minims. The sulphate is given in
                    1 to 3 grain doses. Iodide of iron, in the form of pill or syrup, is specially
                    used iu cases of struma. The phosphate of iron and its syrup are of the greatest
                    value when given to weakly and rickety children.</p>
                <p>All the above-named iron medicines are officinal. Of those not mentioned in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Pharmacopoeia,</hi> two only need be alluded to—solution of
                    dialysed iron, which of all preparations is perhaps the least liable to disagree
                    with the stomach, and solution of the magnetic phosphate of iron in citric acid,
                    commonly known as Lightfoot’s steel, one of the most agreeable of the acid
                    solutions of iron.</p>
                <p>Many mineral waters contain iron. In most it exists as a carbonate, but in one of
                    the springs at Harrogate as chloride. Chalybeate waters are in suitable cases
                    the most effective of blood tonics.</p>
                <p>Ingestion of iron in all forms causes the stools to become black. This arises
                    from the fact that, when iron is taken, but little is absorbed; the rest passing
                    into the intestinal canal is converted into the black sulphide by the
                    sulphuretted hydrogen present there. The discoloration is devoid of all
                    significance. The evil effect of iron preparations on the teeth has been much
                    exaggerated. The acid chalybeates, if taken in a concentrated form, may indeed
                    do harm, and all iron medicines tend to blacken the teeth somewhat, but by
                    washing the mouth out with water after taking them the possibility of injury is
                    readily prevented. (D. J. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
