<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0369-0352-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LAVOISIER, Antoine Laurent</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 352</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092555">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1092647">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:953778">Heat</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:833880">Blacks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:833576">Black</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wk9g">Reformation</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LAVOISIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoine Laurent</hi></label>
                    (1743-1794), one of the founders of modern chemistry, was born in Paris, August
                    26, 1743. His father, a wealthy tradesman, gave him an excellent education at
                    the Collège Mazarin, and encouraged his desire to adopt the career of science.
                    On quitting college, he devoted himself to study with extraordinary ardour: he
                    followed the astronomical and mathematical course of Lacaille, worked in the
                    laboratory of Rouelle, and took lessons in botany from Jussieu; he renounced all
                    frivolous society, and even restricted himself to a diet of milk in order to
                    repair the damage to his constitution caused by excessive application. His first
                    public distinction was gained on the occasion of a prize offered by the Academy
                    of Sciences for an essay on the best mode of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n370/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0370-0353"/> lighting the streets of Paris. To increase the
                    sensitiveness of his eyes, he immersed himself for six weeks in a room hung with
                    black, from which all light was excluded except that of the lamps experimented
                    upon. His zeal was a pledge of success, and was rewarded with the gold medal,
                    April 9, 1766. A multitude of subjects now engaged his attention. He presented
                    to the Academy a masterly analysis of gypsum; travelled through France with
                    Guettard, who was occupied in constructing the first geological map of the
                    country, and composed a work, of which a fragment entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoire sur</hi><hi rend="italic">les couches</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    montagnes</hi> found a place in the Academy collection for 1789; refuted the
                    prevalent error as to the conversion of water into silica by repeated
                    distillation, and studied the phenomena of thunder and aurorae, of
                    crystallization and congelation. He became an associate of the Academy in 1768,
                    and in 1769 obtained the lucrative post of farmergeneral of the revenue, with a
                    view to increase the resources at his command for the advancement of
                    science.</p>
                <p>It was about the year 1770 that the vast possibilities of the new field opened to
                    the researches of chemists by the pneumatic discoveries of Black, Cavendish, and
                    Priestley were recognized by Lavoisier, and the perception gave to his genius
                    the definitive impulse hitherto wanting to it. He repeated and verified
                    experiments which became, in his hands, the means of invalidating their authors’
                    conclusions, and prepared to import the clear-cut precision of his own ideas
                    into a science as yet illogical in form and incoherent in expression. His wealth
                    and position, as well as his enthusiasm, eminently qualified him to lead a
                    successful reform. He lived in the midst of the most stimulating society of his
                    time. Between him and such men as Laplace, Monge, Berthollet, and Fourcroy the
                    constant interchange of ideas established a community of opinion in physical
                    matters so close that the separate intellectual property of each was all but
                    completely merged in the general stock.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Oeuvres</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Lavoisier,</hi> tom. i. p. 13.</p></note> On one day in each week Lavoisier
                    threw open his laboratory to a select few of his friends, communicated the
                    results of his labours, and invited their criticism and advice. By this
                    consultative system his work gained in solidity, and lost nothing in
                    originality. On the 1st of November 1772 Lavoisier, eager to secure the credit
                    of priority, deposited at the Academy a sealed packet containing the record of
                    his earliest conclusions on the crucial point of metallic oxidation. The
                    discovery by Priestley in 1774 of “dephlogisticated air” materially assisted the
                    development of the innovating doctrine, which took the form of a fully fledged
                    theory when Lavoisier in 1778 assigned to the new substance, with the name of
                    “oxygen,” the important functions of the universal “acidifying principle.” His
                    analysis of water in 1784, and synthesis of “fixed air” (called by him “carbonic
                    acid,” <hi rend="italic">Academy Memoirs,</hi> 1781), opened the way for an
                    extended view of the composition of organic as well as inorganic substances, and
                    the anti-phlogistic chemistry was completed by the publication, in 1787, of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Methode de nomenclature</hi><hi rend="italic">chimique.</hi>
                    The reform of language effected by Lavoisier in conjunction with Guyton de
                    Morveau, Berthollet, and Fourcroy was an indispensable prelude to the reform of
                    thought. With the current alchemistic jargon science, properly so-called, could
                    have no fellowship. The new terminology prevailed without change for fifty
                    years, and has been fitted, by trifling modifications, to meet the exigencies of
                    recent progress. The acceptance of the “oxygen theory” was enormously
                    facilitated by the defined and logical form given to it in Lavoisier’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Traite élémentaire de chimie</hi> (Paris, 1789). Indeed, the
                    history of science scarcely presents a second instance of a change so
                    fundamental accomplished with such ease. The partisans of phlogiston did not, it
                    is true, abandon the field without a struggle. In Berlin they met Lavoisier’s
                    demonstrations by burning him in effigy, and in Paris Lamétherie conducted, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Journal de Physique,</hi> a fierce polemic against the
                    party of innovation. The controversy was, however, brief, and its issue visibly
                    certain. Before the end of the century the reformed chemistry was everywhere in
                    a position of uncontested triumph.</p>
                <p>The enlightened activity of Lavoisier was no less conspicuous in his
                    administrative than in his scientific capacity. A prominent member of the body
                    of farmers-general during twenty-one years, he obtained the abolition of certain
                    taxes equally onerous and unproductive, and earned the gratitude of the Jews of
                    Metz by relieving them from an oppressive impost. Appointed director of the
                    powder-works by Turgot in 1776, he not only suppressed the vexatious searches
                    for saltpetre in the cellars of private houses, but succeeded in quadrupling the
                    produce of the commodity. He, moreover, improved the manufacture of gunpowder so
                    as to add one-third to its explosive force, thereby reversing the previous
                    superiority of English over French ordnance. His philanthropic zeal was
                    displayed in the provincial assembly of the Orléanais in 1787. In the year
                    following he was attached to the Caisse d’escompte, and presented a report of
                    its operations, November 21, 1789, to the Constituent Assembly. In 1790 he sat
                    on the commission of weights and measures. In 1791 he became commissary to the
                    treasury, where he established a system of accounts of unexampled punctuality.
                    Requested by the National Assembly to set forth a new scheme of taxation, he
                    composed a treatise <hi rend="italic">De la richesse territoriale de la
                    France,</hi> of which an extract, printed at the public expense, shows him to
                    have been possessed of sound and liberal views on political economy. In short,
                    to quote the words of Lalande, “Lavoisier was to be found everywhere.” But those
                    were times when to be conspicuous was to be in peril. On the 2d of May 1794,
                    Dupin, a member of the Convention, presented a frivolous accusation against the
                    whole of the ex-farmers-general, whose wealth constituted in itself an
                    inexpiable crime. Lavoisier found a hiding-place for a day or two in the
                    deserted apartments of the Academy, but, hearing that his absence was likely to
                    prejudice the cause of his colleagues, he voluntarily gave himself up. He
                    thought it impossible that his life could be taken, but expected the
                    confiscation of his property, when, as he told Lalande, he proposed to earn his
                    bread as an apothecary. Half measures, however, were not in favour with the
                    revolutionary tribunal. On the 6th of May, he, with twenty-seven others of the
                    same profession, was condemned to the guillotine, and, two days later, the
                    sentence was carried into execution. “Il ne leur a fallu,” Lagrange remarked,
                    “qu’un moment pour faire tomber cette tête, et cent années peut-être ne
                    suffiront pas pour en reproduire une semblable.” It is said that a petition
                    presented in his favour met with the brutal reply: “The republic has no need of
                    <hi rend="italic">savantsT</hi> He was preceded on the scaffold by M. Paulze,
                    whose gifted daughter he had married in 1771. He left no posterity.</p>
                <p>To the gift of a transcendent intellect Lavoisier joined the charms of a noble
                    person and winning manners. He was faithful to his friends, charitable to the
                    poor, a model husband, and a patriotic public servant. His fame as the reformer
                    of chemistry rests on no single discovery, but is involved in the first
                    principles of the science (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> p. 463). It
                    was his great merit to have made the balance the <hi rend="italic">ultima
                    ratio</hi> of the laboratory. Quantitative analysis thus became for the first
                    time possible, and a chemical reaction took in his hands the rigid form of an
                    algebraical equation.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Oeuvres,</hi> tom. i. p. 108.</p></note> His latest
                    studies were of a physiological character, and Μ. Dumas<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Leçons de Chimie,</hi>
                    1861.</p></note> found among his papers a piece showing that he had arrived at a
                    remarkable anticipation of modern views concerning the relations <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n371/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0371-0354"/> of organic to inorganic nature. He was probably
                    the first to devote systematic attention to agricultural chemistry, and obtained
                    the practical success of doubling the produce of a large farm owned by him near
                    Blois. A striking proof of his disinterested humanity is afforded by a long and
                    painful investigation of putrefying substances carried out solely with a view to
                    averting accidents in sewers. Not the least notable of his achievements is that
                    of having first formed a clear· idea as to the nature of gases, and of matter
                    generally in its relation to heat. He held that bodies exist in the solid,
                    liquid, or gaseous states according as the attractive force of their particles
                    is superior, equal, or inferior to the repulsive action of an
                    universally-diffused, imponderable fluid which he called “caloric.” Differences
                    of specific heat he attributed to differences of inter-molecular space. The
                    theory, put forward by him with due reserve, formed a useful if not
                    indispensable preliminary to further progress. He was the inventor of the
                    gasometer, and, jointly with Laplace, his coadjutor in a series of experiments
                    on specific heat, of the calorimeter.</p>
                <p>A complete edition of the writings of Lavoisier was issued in four vols. 4 to by
                    the Government of Napoleon ΠI., under the title <hi rend="italic"
                    >Oeuvres</hi><hi rend="italic">de Lavoisier</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >publiées</hi><hi rend="italic">par</hi><hi rend="italic">les soins</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de son Excellence</hi><hi rend="italic">le Ministre</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Instruction</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >publique,</hi> Paris, 1864-68. This publication comprises, besides the works
                    already mentioned, <hi rend="italic">Opuscules physiques</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et chimiques</hi> (1774), a large number of memoirs from the Academy volumes
                    (during the twenty years 1770-90 he contributed no less than fifty-eight), and
                    numerous letters, notes, and reports relating to the various affairs in which he
                    was engaged. At the time of his death he was preparing an edition of his
                    collected works, and the portions ready for the press were published by his
                    widow in 1805, in two 8vo vols, entitled <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de
                    Chimie.</hi> The plates in the <hi rend="italic">Traité élémentaire</hi> were
                    drawn and engraved by Madame Lavoisier. Biographical notices of Lavoisier are
                    given in Fourcroy’s <hi rend="italic">Notice,</hi> and by Lalande in Scherer’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Nachträge,</hi> Jena, 1796. For an account of his discoveries
                    see Dumas, <hi rend="italic">Leçons sur la Philosophie Chimique,</hi> and
                    Béchamp, <hi rend="italic">Lettres Historiques sur la Chimie.</hi> (A. Μ.
                    G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
