<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0202-0191-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LA CHALOTAIS (9th edition, volume 14, page 191)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:953778">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838487">Bretons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xk87">Bretons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hr3b">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z148">Feelings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cn1z">Feeling</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n202/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LA CHALOTAIS</label>, Louis <hi rend="smallcaps">René</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">de Caradeuc de</hi> (1701-1785), representative of the
                    French provincial parliaments in their struggles with Louis XV., was born at
                    Rennes in Brittany, March 6, 1701. He entered with <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n203/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0203-0192"/> keen vigour into the question of the
                    suppression of the Jesuits, which began to be most openly mooted after the
                    affair of Martinique; and as procureur général of the parliament of Brittany he
                    submitted to the parliament in 1761 and 1762—the very heat of the conflict—two
                        <hi rend="italic">Comptes Rendus des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Constitutions</hi><hi rend="italic">des Jésuites,</hi> which dealt the
                    society some of the most powerful blows it had received since Pascal, and
                    undoubtedly contributed largely to secure the edict of suppression in 1764. In
                    the friends of the Jesuits La Chalotais had thus prepared for himself bitter
                    enemies, and he was to feel their power in the events of the quarrel between the
                    court and the parliaments. The breach between the estates of Brittany and the
                    king, in which La Chalotais was more immediately concerned, originated in an
                    order passed by Government that the voices of two of the three estates should
                    bind the other, that is, that the clergy and citizens should control the landed
                    proprietors. To this order, designed to secure the registration of certain
                    fiscal edicts in spite of the proprietors, who formed a majority in the estates,
                    and upon whom the taxes would fall most heavily, the opposition was marked by
                    all the obstinacy of the Breton character. La Chalotais endeavoured to carry
                    through a compromise, but at the same time animadverted somewhat acrimoniously
                    upon the coercive efforts of the Due d’Aiguillon, governor of Brittany, who
                    already, as a supporter of the Jesuits, regarded the procureur with animosity.
                    When the estates, therefore, absolutely refused t ) register the edicts, the
                    court chose to regard La Chalotais as the moving spirit in the opposition; and
                    in November 1765 he was arrested on a charge of. having written certain
                    anonymous and seditious letters to the king. No attention was paid to his
                    protestations of innocence; and, when the parliament of Rennes tried to force
                    matters to a crisis by resigning in a body, Louis merely appointed commissioners
                    to sit as a new parliament and to try La Chalotais, with his son and some other
                    magistrates who had been arrested at the same time. But the question had spread
                    beyond Brittany; other provincial parliaments, and even the parliament of Paris,
                    took it up; and the strife began to assume the ominous significance of one
                    between the people and the crown. No lower tribunal ventured to pass sentence
                    upon La Chalotais, and in 1769 the king, calling the case before himself in
                    council, attempted to settle it in his own autocratic way: silence was imposed
                    as to the future, oblivion as to the past; the innocence of the accused was
                    acknowledged, but they were exiled from their province. Such a decision was no
                    settlement. The parliament, now restored, accused the Due d’Aiguillon of having
                    suborned witnesses against La Chalotais, and, when he published memoirs
                    retorting the charge, caused them to be burned by the hand of the common
                    hangman. Maupeou, minister of the king, after vainly endeavouring to enforce the
                    royal edict of silence, summoned the case before the parliament of Paris in
                    1770. That body, however, gave such unequivocal signs of favour to La Chalotais,
                    that the king interfered and quashed the whole proceedings by a “bed of
                    justice.” The entire matter thus lay over so far as it affected the procureur,
                    till the death of the king in 1774 allowed him to return to his official duties.
                    La Chalotais died at Rennes, July 12, 1785.</p>
                <p>Besides the Comptes Rendus and <hi rend="smallcaps">∖Eq</hi> Exposé Justificatif
                    (three parts, 1766-67), written in prison, La Chalotais was the author of an
                    Essai d'Education Nationals (1763), a work extravagantly praised by Voltaire. It
                    was written in view of the disorganization in matters educational that would
                    follow the expected expulsion of the Jesuits from France.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
