<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0203-0192-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LACHMANN, Karl Konrad Friedrich Wilhelm</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 192</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1138503">Summer</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n203/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LACHMANN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karl Konrad Friedrich
                    Wilhelm</hi></label> (1793-1851), a highly distinguished philologist and critic,
                    was born March 4, 1793, at Brunswick, where his father held an appointment as
                    preacher in the Andreas Kirche. In his eighth year he entered the Katharineum of
                    his native town, where the strong bent of his vigorous mind towards philology
                    and literature soon made itself unmistakably evident. In 1809 he passed to the
                    university of Leipsic as a student of philology and theology; in the same year
                    he transferred himself to Göttingen, where, under the influence of Heyne, his
                    enthusiasm for philological pursuits almost completely extinguished his interest
                    in theology; the pagan classics and particularly the Roman poets became his
                    absorbing study. Stronger even than that of Heyne was the influence of Dissen
                    over the young and rising scholar, who found additional intellectual stimulus in
                    the companionship of such fellow students as C. K. J. Bunsen, Ernst Schulze, and
                    C. A. Brandis. Under G. F. Benecke he also devoted himself to Italian and
                    English, and ultimately to Old German. In 1815 he was led by the stirring
                    political events of the day to interrupt his studious life and join the Prussian
                    army as a volunteer chasseur; in this capacity he accompanied his detachment to
                    Paris, but to his great regret never encountered the enemy. The regiment being
                    disbanded he went to Berlin, where he became an assistant master in the
                    Friedrich Werder gymnasium, and in the spring of 1816 he “habilitated” at the
                    university. His thesis was published immediately afterwards, the subject being
                    “The original form of the <hi rend="italic">Nibelung ennothfi</hi> Almost
                    simultaneously appeared his edition of Propertius. The same summer he became one
                    of the principal masters in the Fridericianum of Königsberg, where he assisted
                    his colleague Karl Köpke with his edition of Rudolf von Monfort’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Barlaam</hi><hi rend="italic">und Josaphat</hi> (1818), and also
                    took part in the researches of his friend towards an edition of the works of
                    Walther von der Vogelweide. In January 1818 he became professor extraordinarius
                    of classical philology in the university of Königsberg, where Lobeck also was;
                    he at the same time began to lecture on Old German grammar and the Middle High
                    German poets. In connexion with this task he devoted himself during the
                    following seven years to an extraordinarily minute study of all that could be
                    found, whether in print or in manuscript, relating to these subjects, and in the
                    summer of 1824 he obtained leave of absence in order that he might search the
                    libraries of Middle and South Germany for further materials. In February 1825
                    Lachmann was nominated extraordinary professor of classical and German philology
                    in the university of Berlin; <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n204/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0204-0193"/> in June 1827 he was promoted to the ordinary
                    professorship in the same department; and in 1830 he was admitted a member of
                    the Academy of Sciences. The remainder of his laborious and fruitful life as an
                    author and a teacher presents no episode requiring special record. In January
                    1851 he was seized with an inflammatory affection of the left foot, to which he
                    ultimately succumbed on March 13, 1851. See Hertz, <hi rend="italic">Karl
                    Lachmann, eine</hi><hi rend="italic">Biographie</hi> (Berlin, 1851).</p>
                <p>Laclιmann, who was the translator of the first volume of P. E. Muller’s
                    Sagaeηbibliothek des Skandinavischen Alterthums, published at Berlin in 1816, is
                    a figure of considerable importance in the history of German philology (see
                    Rudolf von Raumer, Gesch. d. germanischen Philologie, 1870). In his
                    “habilitationsschrift” on the Nibelungennoth, and still more in his review of
                    Hagen’s Nibelungen and Benecke’s Bonerius, contributed in 1817 to the Jenaische
                    Literaturzeitung, he had already laid down the rules of text criticism and
                    elucidated the phonetic and metrical principles of Middle High German in a
                    manner which marked a very distinct advance in that branch of learned
                    investigation. The rigidly scientific character of his method becomes
                    increasingly apparent in the Auswahl aus den Hochdeutschen Dichtern des
                    dreizehnten Jahrhunderts (dedicated to Benecke, 1820), in the edition of
                    Hartmann’s Iwein (the text being Lachmann’s special care, while the explanatory
                    notes are by Benecke, 1827), in those of Walther von der Vogelweide (1827) and
                    Wolfram von Eschenbach (1833), in the papers “Ueber das Hildebrandslied,” “Ueber
                    althochdeutsche Betonung und Verskunst,” “Ueber den Eingang des Parzivals,” and
                    “Ueber drei Bruchstücke niederrheinischeι ’ Gedichte” pul &gt;lished in the
                    Abhandlungen of the Berlin Academy, and in Der Nibelungen Not mit der Klage in
                    der ältesten Gestalt mit den Abweichungen der gemeinen Lesart (1826), which was
                    followed by a critical commentary in 1836. Lachmann’s “Betrachtungen über die
                    Ilias,” first published in the Abhandlungen of the Berlin Academy in 1837 and
                    1841, in which he sought to show that the Iliad consists of sixteen independent
                    “lays” variously enlarged and interpolated, have had considerable influence on
                    modern Homeric criticism. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Homer.</hi> His smaller
                    edition of the New Testament appeared in 1831, 3d ed. 1846; the larger, in two
                    volumes, in 1842-50 (Novum Testamentum Greece et Latine: Carolus Lachmannus
                    recensuit, Philippus Buttmannus Graecae lectionis auctoritates apposuit). The
                    plan of Lachmann’s edition, which has been explained by himself in the Stud. «.
                    Krit. of 1830, is a modification of the unaccomplished project of Bentley. It
                    seeks to restore the most ancient reading current in Eastern MSS., using the
                    consent of the Latin authorities (Old Latin and Greek Western Uncials) as the
                    main proof of antiquity of a reading where the oldest Eastern authorities
                    differ. Besides Propertius, Lachmann edited Catullus, 1829; Tibullus, 1829;
                    Genesius, 1834; Terentianus Maurus, 1836; Babrius, 1845; Avianus, 1845; Gaius,
                    1841-42; the Agrimensores Romani, 1848-52; and Lucretius, 1850. The last, which
                    was the main occupation of the closing years of his life, from 1845, was perhaps
                    his greatest achievement, and has been characterized by Monro as “a work which
                    will be a landmark for scholars as long as the Latin language continues to be
                    studied.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
