<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0497-0478-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LESSING, Gotthold Ephraim</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 478</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19r63">Literature</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n497/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LESSING, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gotthold Ephraim</hi></label>
                    (1729-1781), was born at Kamenz, in Upper Lusatia, Saxony, on the 22d of January
                    1729. He was descended from Clemens Lessing, a Saxon clergyman, whose name is
                    found attached to an ecclesiastical document of 1580. Lessing’s father, Johann
                    Gottfried, born in 1693, was the son of Theophilus Lessing, the burgomaster of
                    Kamenz, who died at the age of eighty-nine, when Lessing was between six and
                    seven years old. At the time of Lessing’s birth his father was one of the
                    clergymen of Kamenz, where, a few years afterwards, he became pastor primarius,
                    or head pastor. He was a man of high character, rather irascible, but earnest in
                    the fulfilment of his pastoral duties, and universally beloved for his kindness
                    to the poor. Throughout life he continued the studies in theology and church
                    history which he had successfully begun at the university of Wittenberg, and he
                    made some reputation as an original writer and as a translator of Tillotson. Of
                    the Frau Pastorin we do not know much except that she was a faithful and
                    affectionate wife and mother. They had twelve children, of whom Lessing was the
                    second who survived infancy. He seems to have been an exceedingly happy child,
                    healthy and playful, and already remarkable for his fondness for reading. After
                    attending the Latin school of Kamenz, he was sent in 1741 to the great school of
                    St Afra at Meissen, where he was maintained free of charge. Here he made such
                    rapid progress in classical and mathematical study that, towards the end of his
                    career as a pupil, he was described by the rector as “a steed that needed double
                    fodder.” Work which was oppressive to others, added the rector, was to Lessing
                    “as light as a feather.” He had the reputation of being one of the most
                    sarcastic, but at the same time one of the most loyal and generous, boys in the
                    school. In 1746 he left St Afra’s and went to the university of Leipsic,
                    nominally for the purpose of studying theology. To theology, however, he did not
                    give the slightest attention. Under Professors Christ and Ernesti he continued
                    his classical studies, and he also attended the philosophical disputations
                    presided over by his friend Kastner, a young professor of mathematics. For some
                    time Lessing was shy and retired amid his new surroundings, but being of an
                    eminently social disposition he soon became tired of this kind of life, and
                    began to form friends among his fellow-students, and strove to acquire the
                    manners of a free and polished man of the world. His <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n498/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0498-0479"/> principal friend was Weisse, who afterwards
                    attained a respectable position as a man of letters. He also became intimate
                    with Mylius, who was considerably older than himself, and had made a certain
                    mark as a literary and scientific writer. There was at this time in Leipsic an
                    excellent actress, Frau Neuber, who had gathered around her a number of
                    respectable players, and Lessing, in company with Weisse, was one of the most
                    regular attenders at her theatre. At St Afra’s he had begun a comedy, <hi
                    rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic">Junge</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gelehrte,</hi> and this he now completed. Frau Neuber immediately accepted it,
                    and it was received with much favour by the public of Leipsic.</p>
                <p>Alarmed by reports of what was supposed to be his dissolute life, the elder
                    Lessing summoned him to Kamenz, where he remained for some months. He soon
                    succeeded in overcoming the fears of his parents, who allowed him to return to
                    Leipsic on condition that he would devote himself to the study of medicine. Some
                    medical lectures he did attend; but his ambition was to become a great
                    dramatist, and as long as Frau Neuber’s company kept together he occupied
                    himself almost exclusively with the theatre, being frequently present at
                    rehearsal during the day as well as at the performance in the evening.</p>
                <p>In 1748 the company broke up, and Lessing, finding nothing to interest him in
                    Leipsic, went to Wittenberg, and afterwards, towards the end of the year, to
                    Berlin, where his friend Mylius had established himself as a journalist and man
                    of science. In Berlin Lessing now-spent three years, maintaining himself chiefly
                    by literary work. He translated two volumes of Rollin’s history, wrote some of
                    the best of his early plays, and, in association with Mylius, started a
                    periodical (which soon came to an end) for the discussion of matters connected
                    with the drama, Early in 1751 he accepted the office of literary critic to the
                    Foss <hi rend="italic">Gazette,</hi> and in this position he reviewed some of
                    the most important German and French books of the day, manifesting already to
                    some extent the learning, judgment, and wit which were to make him the greatest
                    critic of modern times. His father had been bitterly opposed to his scheme of
                    life, and in 1751 urged him to complete his studies at the university of
                    Wittenberg. Feeling the need of further thought and research, Lessing at last
                    consented, and at the close of the year left Berlin. It is worthy of note that
                    he had been brought into slight contact with Voltaire, for whom he had
                    translated some documents relating to the Hirsch trial. Voltaire’s secretary
                    having lent him a volume of the <hi rend="italic">Siècle de Louis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">XIV.,</hi> which had not yet beeu published, he took it with him
                    to Wittenberg. This came to the ears of Voltaire, who assumed that Lessing
                    intended to print either a pirated edition or an unauthorized translation. The
                    affair led to an angry correspondence, and was a subject of much talk in
                    Berlin.</p>
                <p>Lessing remained about a year in Wittenberg, where he passed most of his time in
                    the university library, every volume in which, he afterwards declared, had
                    passed through his hands. Having taken the degree of master of arts, he returned
                    to Berlin, determined to make literature his profession; and the next three
                    years were among the busiest of his life. Besides translating for the
                    booksellers, he issued several numbers of the <hi rend="italic">Theatralische
                    Bibliothek,</hi> a periodical essentially the same as that which he had begun
                    with Mylius. He also resumed his labours as critic to the <hi rend="italic">Voss
                    Gazette.</hi> For many years the most influential writer in Germany had been
                    Gottsched, the Leipsic professor, who continually proclaimed the necessity of
                    rigid adherence, in the drama and in poetry, to French rules. In his articles
                    for the <hi rend="italic">Voss Gazette,</hi> Lessing made it his principal
                    object to ridicule the pretensions of Gottsched and his school, and in a short
                    time there was no writer of whom they were so much afraid. In 1754 he produced a
                    deep impression by <hi rend="italic">Ein</hi><hi rend="italic">Vade</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mecum</hi><hi rend="italic">für den Herrn</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sam.</hi><hi rend="italic">Gotth. Lange,</hi> in which he exposed with bitter
                    satire Lange’s errors in his popular translation of Horace. During these three
                    years Lessing took a definite position in contemporary literature by issuing, in
                    six small volumes, those of his writings which he considered worthy of
                    preservation. They included his lyrics and epigrams, some of the latter being in
                    German, others in Latin. Most of his lyrics were written in Leipsic, and bad
                    already appeared, during his first residence in Berlin, in a volume of <hi
                    rend="italic">Kleinigkeiten,</hi> published without his name. Although they do
                    not, like Goethe’s lyrics, touch deep sources of natural feeling, they have the
                    merit of being bright, gay, and musical, and some of them are still sung by
                    German students. The epigrams, many of which were produced in Wittenberg, are in
                    the style of Martial, and give evidence, like Lessing’s critical writings, of a
                    keen and biting humour. Among his collected writings there was also a remarkable
                    series of <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> in which, for the first time in German
                    literature, some of the results of extensive learning were presented in a free
                    and vivid style. Even more important, perhaps, were the papers entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Rettungen,</hi> in which he undertook to vindicate the character
                    of various writers who had been misunderstood by preceding generations. One of
                    the best of these <hi rend="italic">Rettungen</hi> is on Horace, whom he defends
                    against the critics who charge him with sensuality and cowardice. In another,
                    almost equally good, he shows that Cardan, instead of being an atheist, did full
                    justice to the evidences for Christianity, as they were understood in his time,
                    while he did rather less than justice to other religions. This essay contains a
                    powerful argument in favour of Mohammedanism, developed from the point of view
                    of an intelligent believer in the Γrophet. In addition to these varied contents,
                    Lessing published in the six volumes of his <hi rend="italic">Schriften</hi> his
                    early plays and <hi rend="italic">Miss Sara Sampson.</hi> Of the former the
                    chief are <hi rend="italic">Der</hi><hi rend="italic">Junge</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Gelehrte,</hi> already mentioned, <hi rend="italic">Der
                    Freidenker,</hi><hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Juden,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Der Misogyn.</hi> Although superior to any other German comedies
                    produced at the same time, they cannot be said to reveal a high dramatic
                    faculty. In the arrangement of his plots and the balancing of his characters,
                    Lessing follows closely the methods of contemporary French comedy, and in the
                    dialogue there is often a too obvious straining after effect. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Miss Sara Sampson,</hi> written in 1755, marks a wholly different stage of his
                    development. It has many faults both in conception and in execution, but it
                    exercised a powerful influence by indicating to the dramatists of Germany that
                    materials for tragedy are to be found in the experiences of ordinary men and
                    women as well as in those of “the great.” Lessing attributed much importance to
                    this principle, which had been suggested to him chiefly by the study of
                    Richardson, whose Clarissa is almost exactly reproduced in the heroine of <hi
                    rend="italic">Miss Sara Sampson.</hi></p>
                <p>This tragedy, when represented in Frankfort-on-the-Oder, was received with so
                    much applause that he resolved to devote himself to the drama; and in fulfilment
                    of his design he suddenly quitted Berlin in October 1755, and went to Leipsic,
                    where a good theatre had been lately established. During his second residence in
                    Berlin he had made his name widely known, and he had secured several friends,
                    whose affection he retained during the rest of his life. The chief of these was
                    Moses Mendelssohn, in association with whom, in 1755, he wrote an admirable
                    treatise, <hi rend="italic">Pope</hi><hi rend="italic">ein Metaphysiker,</hi>
                    tracing sharply the lines which separate the poet from the philosopher. The
                    Berlin Academy of Sciences had offered a prize for the best essay on Pope’s
                    doctrine that “Whatever is, is right,” as compared with the optimism of
                    Leibnitz. The treatise of the two friends was written to show that there cannot
                    be a <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n499/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0499-0480"/> true comparison between a poetic and a
                    philosophic conception; and they threw much light on the aims both of Leibnitz
                    and of Pope. Other Berlin friends of Lessing were Nicolai, the bookseller, and
                    Ramler, the author of many well-known odes. He had also made the acquaintance of
                    Gleim, the Halberstadt poet, and Ewald Christian von Kleist, a Prussian officer,
                    whose fine poem, <hi rend="italic">Der Frühling,</hi> had won for him Lessing’s
                    warm esteem.</p>
                <p>In Leipsic, Lessing was asked by Winkler, a wealthy young merchant, to accompany
                    him in a foreign tour, which was to last three years. As he offered liberal
                    terms, Lessing consented; and early in the summer of 1756 they started for
                    England. They did not, however, get beyond Amsterdam, for after the outbreak of
                    the Seven Years’ War they heard that Winkler’s house was occupied by the
                    Prussian commandant; and he deemed it necessary to hasten back. After some time
                    Winkler was offended by Lessing’s intimacy with certain Prussian officers, and
                    suddenly announced to him that he must consider their engagement at an end.
                    Lessing demanded compensation, and in the end the courts decided in his favour,
                    but not until the case had dragged on for about six years. In the meantime it
                    detained him in Leipsic, and, as there was little opportunity for earning money
                    by literature in a city occupied by foreign troops, he went through a period of
                    extreme hardship. During these anxious months he begin the study of mediaeval
                    poetry, in which some interest had been awakened by the Swiss school of critics;
                    he also translated several English writings, and worked occasionally for the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliothek,</hi> a periodical edited by Nicolai. Fortunately he
                    had an opportunity of developing his friendship with Kleist, who happened to be
                    stationed in Leipsic. Kleist, a man of truly heroic temper, with the simplicity
                    of a child, was powerfully attracted by Lessing’s frank and noble nature, and
                    Lessing loved him with an ardour which was excited by no other friend, not even
                    by Mendelssohn. Kleist’s regiment being ordered to new quarters early in 1758,
                    Lessing decided not to remain behind him, and, saying farewell to his friend
                    (who was mortally wounded in the following year at the battle of Kunersdorf), he
                    returned once more to Berlin.</p>
                <p>His third residence in Berlin was made memorable by the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Literaturbriefe,</hi> a series of critical essays (written in the form of
                    letters to a wounded officer) on the principal works that had appeared since the
                    beginning of the Seven Years’ War. The scheme was suggested by Nicolai, by whom
                    the <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> were published. Those written by Lessing
                    manifested far higher intellectual power than anything he had yet accomplished.
                    The critical principles set forth in the <hi rend="italic">Literaturbriefe</hi>
                    are now universally recognized, but they were then new, and even at the present
                    day they seem to derive fresh vitality from the force, precision, and animation
                    with which he expresses them. He insisted especially on the necessity of truth
                    to nature in the imaginative presentation of the facts of life, and in one
                    letter he boldly proclaimed the superiority of Shakespeare to Corneille, Racine,
                    and Voltaire. At the same time he marked the immutable conditions to which even
                    genius must submit in order to move enduring sympathies. While in Berlin at this
                    time, he edited with Ramler a selection from the writings of Logau, a vigorous
                    epigrammatist of the 17th century, and introduced to the German public <hi
                    rend="italic">The War Songs of a Grenadier,</hi> by Gleim. He admired the vigour
                    of these songs, but in several private letters protested against the vehemence
                    of the author’s patriotism—patriotism being a virtue which, he thought, he
                    “could do very well without.” In 1759 he published <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philotas,</hi> a prose tragedy; and in the same year appeared a complete
                    collection of his fables, with an essay on the essential idea of the fable. The
                    latter is one of his best essays in criticism, defining with perfect lucidity
                    what is meant by “the action” in works of imagination, and distinguishing the
                    action of the fable on the one hand from that of the epic and the drama on the
                    other. His theory prevented him from lending poetic interest to his own fables,
                    but they surpass the works of all other German fabulists in the depth and
                    variety of the moral truths which they are intended to enforce.</p>
                <p>In 1760, weary of incessant writing, and feeling that change of scene and work
                    was necessary for his health, Lessing went to Breslau to apply for the post of
                    secretary to General Tauentzien, to whom Kleist had introduced him in Leipsic.
                    Tauentzien was not only a general in the Prussian army, but governor of Breslau,
                    and director of the mint. He willingly granted the vacant office to Lessing, who
                    retained it for more than four years. He thus found himself in circumstances
                    wholly different from those to which he had been hitherto accustomed. He
                    associated chiefly with Prussian officers, went much into society, and became
                    passionately fond of the gaming table, where he played for such high stakes that
                    even General Tauentzien expostulated with him. While, however, he seemed to be
                    wasting his energies, he never lost sight of his true goal. He gradually
                    collected a library of about 6000 volumes (which he was ultimately obliged to
                    sell); and after the conclusion of the Seven Years’War in 1763 he resumed more
                    enthusiastically than ever the studies which had been partly interrupted. In
                    investigating the early history of Christianity, he obtained a profound
                    knowledge of the fathers; and a remarkable letter to Mendelssohn shows that he
                    had penetrated more deeply than any contemporary thinker into the significance
                    of the philosophy of Spinoza. In 1764 he was prostrated by a severe illness,
                    during which he reviewed, in a rather sorrowful spirit, his past life, and
                    formed many serious resolutions for the future. Before this time he had worked
                    hard at <hi rend="italic">Laocoon,</hi> and in fresh spring mornings he had
                    sketched in a garden the plan of <hi rend="italic">Minna von Barnhelm.</hi> His
                    parents were now in exceedingly straitened circumstances, and often appealed to
                    him for aid. He responded generously to their demands, but they greatly
                    overrated his power to help them, as they assumed that he intended to remain
                    permanently in General Tauentzien’s service. In reality, he had always regarded
                    the engagement as a temporary one, and in 1765 he resigned his office, and left
                    Breslau.</p>
                <p>It seemed not improbable that he might find a suitable appointment in Dresden,
                    but he was again compelled, much against his will, to become a resident of
                    Berlin, whither he went after a brief visit to Kamenz and Leipsic. His friends
                    exerted themselves to obtain for him the office of keeper of the royal library,
                    but Frederick had not forgotten Lessing’s quarrel with Voltaire, and declined to
                    consider his claims, although, about the time when Lessing went to Breslau, he
                    had confirmed his election as a foreign member of the Berlin Academy of
                    Sciences. During the two years which Lessing now spent in the Prussian capital
                    he was restless and unhappy, yet it was during this period that he published two
                    of his greatest works— <hi rend="italic">Laocoon</hi> in 1766, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Minna von Barnhelm</hi> in 1767. <hi rend="italic">Laocoon</hi>
                    ranks as a classic not only in German but in European literature, and its style
                    alone, which is as near perfection as anything Lessing ever wrote, would almost
                    entitle it to this position. His central aim is to define by analysis the
                    limitations of poetry and the plastic arts. Many of his conclusions have been
                    corrected and extended by later criticism; but he indicated more decisively than
                    any of his predecessors the fruitful principle that each art is subject to
                    definite conditions, and that it can accomplish great results only by limiting
                    itself to its special function. The most valuable parts of the work are those
                    which relate to poetry, of which he had a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n500/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0500-0481"/> much more intimate knowledge than of sculpture
                    and painting. His exposition of the methods of Homer and Sophocles is especially
                    suggestive, and he may be said to have marked an epoch in the appreciation of
                    these writers, and of Greek literature generally. He invariably starts from the
                    consideration of doctrines set forth by other scholars (chiefly Winkelmann,
                    Caylus, and Spence); but he is never satisfied until he arrives at positive
                    principles, and he leads us towards them gradually by the paths he himself has
                    trodden, glancing at many side issues by the way. He was unable in later years
                    to complete his scheme, but even in its fragmentary form, as Goethe testifies in
                    <hi rend="italic">Wahrheit und Dichtung,</hi><hi rend="italic">Laocoon</hi> was
                    welcomed with gratitude by the most active minds of the age. The power of <hi
                    rend="italic">Minna von Barnhelm</hi> was also immediately recognized. This is,
                    on the whole, the best of Lessing’s purely dramatic writings. The hero,
                    Tellheim, is an admirable study of a manly and sensitive soldier, with somewhat
                    exaggerated ideas of conventional honour; and Minna, the heroine, is one of the
                    brightest and most attractive figures in the dramatic literature of Germany. The
                    subordinate characters are conceived with the same force and vividness; and the
                    plot, which reflects precisely the struggles and aspirations of the period that
                    immediately followed the Seven Years’ War, is simply and naturally unfolded.
                    This beautiful play is valued by the Germans, not only as a work of art, but as
                    one of the earliest and most striking manifestations of the growing spirit of
                    German nationality.</p>
                <p>In 1767 Lessing settledin Hamburg, where he had been invited to take part in the
                    institution of a national theatre. The scheme promised well, and, as he
                    associated himself with Bode, a literary man whom he respected, in starting a
                    printing establishment, he hoped that he might at last look forward to a
                    peaceful and prosperous career. The theatre, however, being mismanaged, was soon
                    closed, while the printing establishment failed, and left behind it a heavy
                    burden of debt. Many of Lessing’s letters from Hamburg breathe almost a spirit
                    of despair, and towards the end of his residence there he determined to quit
                    Germany, believing that in Italy he might find congenial labour that would
                    suffice for his wants. Even in Hamburg he made splendid contributions to
                    enduring literature, the chief being his <hi rend="italic">Hamburgische
                    Dramaturgie.</hi> It consists of criticisms of some of the plays represented in
                    the Hamburg theatre; but in these criticisms he offers a complete theory of the
                    laws of dramatic art In the main his theory is that of Aristotle, but it is
                    maintained on independent grounds and applied in new ways. By this powerful work
                    he delivered German dramatists for ever from the yoke of the classic tragedy of
                    France, and directed them to the Greek dramatists and to Shakespeare as the
                    poets who have opened most truly the fountains of tragic feeling. Another result
                    of his labours in Hamburg was the <hi rend="italic">Antiquarische Briefe,</hi> a
                    series of masterly letters in answer to Klotz, a pedantic writer who, after
                    flattering Lessing, had attacked him, and sought to establish a kind of
                    intellectual despotism by means of critical journals which he directly or
                    indirectly controlled. In connexion with this controversy, Lessing wrote his
                    brilliant little treatise, <hi rend="italic">Wie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >die</hi><hi rend="italic">Alten</hi><hi rend="italic">den Tod</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">gebildet,</hi> contrasting the mediaeval representation of death
                    as a skeleton with the Greek conception of death as the twin-brother of
                    sleep.</p>
                <p>Instead of going to Italy as he intended, Lessing accepted, in 1770, the office
                    of librarian at Wolfenbüttel, a post which was offered to him by the hereditary
                    prince of Brunswick. In this position he passed his remaining years. For a time
                    he was not unhappy, but by and by he was rendered miserable by his inability to
                    pay the debts which he had contracted in Hamburg. He missed, too, the society of
                    his friends, and his health, which had hitherto been excellent, gradually gave
                    way. In 1775 he travelled for nine months in Italy with Prince Leopold of
                    Brunswick; and in the following year he married Eva König, the widow of a
                    Hamburg merchant, with whom he had been on terms of intimate friendship. She was
                    in every way worthy of Lessing, and their correspondence during his lonely years
                    in Wolfenbüttel forms one of the most attractive elements of his biography.
                    Their happiness in each other was perfect, but it lasted only for a brief
                    period; in 1778 she died in childbed. After her death Lessing found one of his
                    chief sources of consolation in the love of his four step-children, to whom he
                    was tenderly attached.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile he had extended his fame by several important writings. Soon after
                    settling in Wolfenbüttel he found in the library an ancient manuscript, which
                    proved to be a treatise of Berengarius of Tours on transubstantiation in reply
                    to Lanfranc. Lessing was thus induced to write an essay on Berengarius,
                    vindicating his character as a serious and consistent thinker. The essay was
                    much admired by the leading theologians of Germany, and it is, on the whole, the
                    ablest and most interesting of his <hi rend="italic">Bettungen.</hi> In 1771 he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Zerstreute Anmerkungen über das Epigramm, und
                    einige der vornehmsten Epigrammatisten—</hi> a work which Herder described as
                    “itself an’epigram.” Lessing’s theory of the origin of the epigram is somewhat
                    fanciful, but no other critic has offered so many pregnant hints as to the laws
                    of epigrammatic verse, or defended with so much force and ingenuity the
                    character of Martial. In 1772 lovers of the drama were delighted by the
                    appearance of <hi rend="italic">Emilia Galotti,</hi> a tragedy which he had
                    begun many years before in Leipsic. The subject was suggested by the Roman
                    legend of Virginia, but the scene is laid in an Italian court, and the whole
                    play is conceived in accordance with the modern spirit. Its defect is that its
                    tragic conclusion does not seem to be absolutely inevitable, but there is high
                    imaginative power in the character of the prince of Guastalla and in that of
                    Marinelli, his chamberlain, who weaves the intrigue from which Emilia escapes by
                    death. The diction of <hi rend="italic">Emilia Galotti</hi> is at once refined
                    and vigorous, and there are scenes in which some of the deepest passions of
                    human nature are sounded with perfect art. Having completed <hi rend="italic"
                    >Emilia Galotti,</hi> Lessing occupied himself for some years almost exclusively
                    with the treasures of the Wolfenbüttel library. The results of his researches
                    (some of them of high value) he embodied in a series of volumes, <hi
                    rend="italic">Zur Geschichte und Literatur,</hi> the first being issued in 1773,
                    the last in the year of his death.</p>
                <p>The concluding period of Lessing’s life was devoted chiefly to theological
                    controversy. Reimarus, professor of Oriental languages in Hamburg, who commanded
                    general respect as a scholar and thinker, wrote a book entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Apologie oder Schutzschrift für die vernünftigen Verehrer
                    Gottes.</hi> The standpoint of Reimarus was that of the English deists, and he
                    investigated, without hesitation, the evidence for the miracles recorded in the
                    Bible. The manuscript of this work, after the author’s death in 1767, was
                    entrusted by his daughter, Elise Reimarus, to Lessing, who published extracts
                    from it in his <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte und Literatur,</hi> in 1774-78.
                    These extracts, the authorship of which was not publicly avowed, were known as
                    the “Wolfenbüttel Fragments.” They created profound excitement among orthodox
                    theologians, and evoked many replies, in which Lessing was bitterly condemned
                    for having issued writings of so dangerous a tendency. Lessing delighted at all
                    times in the stir of combat, and prepared to offer a fulj and vigorous defence.
                    His most formidable assailant was Pastor Goeze, of Hamburg, a sincere and
                    earnest theologian, but utterly unscrupulous in his choice of weapons against
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n501/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0501-0482"/> an opponent. To him, therefore, Lessing addressed
                    his most elaborate answers,— <hi rend="italic">Eine Parabel,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Axiomata,</hi> eleven letters with the title <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anti-Goeze,</hi> and two pamphlets in reply to an inquiry by Goeze as to what
                    Lessing meant by Christianity. These papers are not only full of thought and
                    learning; they are written with a grace, vivacity, and energy that make them
                    hardly less interesting to-day than they were to Lessing’s contemporaries. He
                    does not undertake to defend the conclusions of Reimarus; his immediate object
                    is to claim the right of free criticism in regard even to the highest subjects
                    of human thought. The argument on which he chiefly relies is that the Bible
                    cannot be considered necessary to a belief in Christianity, since Christianity
                    was a living and conquering power before the New Testament in its present form
                    was recognized by the church. The true evidence for what is essential in
                    Christianity, he contends, is its adaptation to the wants of human nature; hence
                    the religious spirit is undisturbed by the speculations and researches of the
                    boldest thinkers. The effect of this controversy was to secure wider freedom for
                    writers on theology, and to suggest new problems regarding the growth of
                    Christianity, the formation of the canon, and the essence of religion. On one
                    subject, the origin of the gospels, Lessing poured a flood of fresh light in a
                    treatise, published after his death, presenting “A New Hypothesis concerning the
                    Evangelists, regarded as merely human writers.” The Brunswick Government having,
                    in deference to the consistory, confiscated the “Fragments” and ordered Lessing
                    to discontinue the controversy, he resolved, as he wrote to Elise Reimarus, to
                    “try whether they would let him preach undisturbed from his old pulpit, the
                    stage.” In <hi rend="italic">Nathan</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Weise,</hi> written in the winter of 1778-79, he gave poetic form
                    to the ideas which he had already developed in prose. Its governing conception
                    is that noble character may be associated with the most diverse creeds, and that
                    there can, therefore, be no good reason why the holders of one set of religious
                    principles should not tolerate those who maintain wholly different doctrines.
                    This element of <hi rend="italic">Nathan</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Weise</hi> receives so much attention from its critics that many
                    of them overlook the high artistic qualities of the work. As a play it has
                    serious imperfections, but as a dramatic poem it is one of the finest creations
                    of the 18th century. The characters possess true vitality, and several passages
                    (including, of course, the famous passage setting forth the parable of the three
                    rings) have both the depth and the spontaneity which are the unmistakable notes
                    of genius. In 1780 appeared <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Erziehung des Menschengeschlechts,</hi> the first half of which he had
                    published in 1777 with one of the “Fragments.” This work, composed of a hundred
                    brief paragraphs, was the last, and is, perhaps, the most suggestive, of
                    Lessing’s writings. The doctrine on which its argument is based is that no
                    dogmatic creed can be regarded as final, but that every historical religion has
                    played a great part in the development of the spiritual life of mankind. Lessing
                    also maintains that history reveals a definite law of progress, and that
                    occasional retrogression may be necessary for the advance of the world towards
                    its ultimate goal. These ideas afterwards became familiar, but they offered a
                    striking contrast to the principles both of orthodox and of sceptical writers in
                    Lessing’s day, and gave a wholly new direction to religious philosophy. Another
                    work of Lessing’s last years, <hi rend="italic">Ernst und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Falk</hi> (a series of five dialogues, of which the first three were published
                    in 1777, the last two in 1780), also indicated in a fascinating style many new
                    points of view. Its nominal subject is freemasonry, but its real aim is to plead
                    for a humane and charitable spirit in opposition to a narrow patriotism, an
                    extravagant respect for rank, and exclusive devotion to any particular
                    church.</p>
                <p>Lessing’s theological opinions exposed him to much petty persecution, and he was
                    in almost constant straits for money. Nothing, however, broke his manly and
                    generous spirit. To the end he was always ready to help those who appealed to
                    him for aid, and he devoted himself with growing ardour to the search for truth.
                    He formed many new plans of work, but in the course of 1780 it became evident to
                    his friends that he would not be able much longer to continue his labours. His
                    health had been undermined by excessive work and anxiety, and after a short
                    illness he died at Brunswick on the 2 2d of January 1781.</p>
                <p>He was rather above the middle height, and during the greater part of his life
                    maintained an appearance of vigour and elasticity. Luther himself was not of a
                    more fearless and independent character. In an age when men of letters were fond
                    of grouping themselves in sects and coteries, Lessing pursued his own way,
                    unmoved by clamour, and indifferent to popular favour. Yet no man was ever more
                    warmly loved by friends, and he had the satisfaction of knowing that the younger
                    generation of writers looked up to him with confidence and reverence. Jacobi
                    wished for many years to make his acquaintance, but was deterred from addressing
                    him, as he explained to Lessing, by a profound consciousness of the difference
                    between himself and one whom he regarded as “a king among minds.” “We lose much,
                    much in him,” wrote Goethe after Lessing’s death, “more than we think.” It may
                    be questioned whether there is any other writer to whom the Germans owe a deeper
                    debt of gratitude. He was succeeded by poets and philosophers who for a time
                    gave Germany the first place in the intellectual life of the world, and it was
                    Lessing, as they themselves acknowledged, who prepared the way for their
                    achievements. Without attaching himself to any particular system of
                    philosophical doctrine, he fought incessantly against error, and in regard to
                    art, poetry, the drama, and religion, suggested ideas which kindled the
                    enthusiasm of aspiring minds, and stimulated their highest energies. While his
                    work was thus effective in its own day, it has lost little of its value for
                    later ages. His great dramas have imaginative qualities which appeal to every
                    generation, and an unfading charm is conferred on his critical and theological
                    writings by the power and classical purity of his style.</p>
                <p>Tlιe first edition of his collected works appeared, in 30 vols., in 1771-94. A
                    critical edition by Laclιnrann, in 13 vols., was issued in 1838-40, and this
                    edition was revised, with additions, by Malt-zahu in 1853-57. In 1868-77
                    Lessing’s works, edited by several competent scholars, were published in 20
                    vols, by Hempel, and there is an illustrated edition in 8 vols. (Grote,
                    1875-76). See <hi rend="italic">Lessing's</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben,</hi>
                    1793, by Karl G. Lessing (his brother); Danzel, <hi rend="italic">G.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">E. Lessing,</hi><hi rend="italic">sein Leben und</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">seine</hi><hi rend="italic">Werke,</hi> 1850 (completed by
                    Guhrauer, 1853-54); Stahr, <hi rend="italic">G.</hi><hi rend="italic">E.
                    Lessing,</hi><hi rend="italic">sein Leben und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >seine</hi><hi rend="italic">Werke,</hi> 1859; H. Düntzer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lessing's</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben,</hi> 1882; and in English, J. Sime, <hi
                    rend="italic">Lessing,</hi> 1877, and H. Zimmern, <hi rend="italic">Gotthold
                    Ephraim Lessing,</hi> 1878. (J. SI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
