<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0190-0179-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LABURNUM (9th edition, volume 14, page 179)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812818">Arboretums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091659">Records</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j6845h">Arboretums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n190/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LABURNUM</label> is the specific name of a familiar tree of
                    the genus <hi rend="italic">Cytisus</hi>, Dec., of the pea family or <hi
                        rend="italic">Leguminosae.</hi> It is a native of the mountains of France,
                    Switzerland, southern Germany, northern Italy, &amp;c., has long been cultivated
                    as an ornamental tree throughout Europe, and was introduced into north-east
                    America by the European colonists. Gerard records it as growing in his garden in
                    1596 under the names of anagyris, laburnum, or beane trefoyle <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Historie</hi><hi rend="italic">of Plants,</hi> p. 1239), but the date of
                    its introduction into England appears to be unknown. In France it is called
                    1’aubour—a corruption from laburnum according to Du Hamel—as also arbois, <hi
                        rend="italic">i,e.,</hi> arc-bois, “the wood having been used by the ancient
                    Gauls for bows. It is still so employed in some parts of the Mâconnois, where
                    the bows are found to preserve their strength and elasticity for half a century”
                    (Loudon, <hi rend="italic">Arboretum,</hi> ii. p. 590).</p>
                <p>Several varieties of this well-known tree are cultivated, differing in the size
                    of the flowers, in the form of the foliage, &lt;fcc., such as the “oak-leafed”
                        <hi rend="italic">(quercifolvum), pendulum,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >crispum,</hi> &amp;c. One of the most remarkable forms is <hi rend="italic"
                        >C. Adami,</hi> Poir. <hi rend="italic">(C. purpurascens,</hi> Hort.), which
                    bears three kinds of blossoms, viz., racemes of pure yellow flowers, others of a
                    purple colour, and others of an intermediate brick-red tint—all three kinds
                    being borne by one and the same tree. The last are hybrid blossoms, and are
                    sterile, with malformed ovules, though, curiously enough, the pollen appears to
                    be good. The yellow and purple “reversions” are fertile. It originated in Paris
                    in 1828 by Μ. Adam, who inserted a “shield” of the bark of <hi rend="italic">C.
                        purpureus,</hi> Scop., into a stock of <hi rend="italic">C. Laburnum,</hi>
                    L. A vigorous shoot from this bud was subsequently propagated. Hence it would
                    appear that the two distinct species mentioned above became united by their
                    cambium layers, and the trees propagated therefrom subsequently reverted to
                    their respective parentages in bearing both yellow and purple flowers, but
                    produce as well blossoms of an intermediate or hybrid character. Such a result,
                    Mr Darwin observes, may be called a “graft-hybrid.” For full details see
                    Darwin’s <hi rend="italic">Animals and Plants under Domestication.</hi></p>
                <p>The laburnum has highly poisonous properties. A case is recorded of nearly fatal
                    results to several boys who masticated the roots on finding they tasted like
                    liquorice, which is a member of the same family as the laburnum. It has proved
                    fatal to cattle, though hares and rabbits eat the bark of it with avidity <hi
                        rend="italic">(Gardener's Chronicle,</hi> 1881, vol. xvi. p. 666). The seeds
                    also are highly poisonous, possessing emetic as well as narcotico-acrid
                    principles, especially in a green state. Gerard <hi rend="italic">(loc.
                        cit.)</hi> alludes to the powerful effect produced on the system by taking
                    the bruised leaves medicinally. Pliny records that bees will not visit the
                    flowers (W. <hi rend="italic">H.,</hi> xvi. 31), but this may be an error, for
                    Mr Darwin found by experiment that insects play an important part in the
                    fertilization of the laburnum.</p>
                <p>The heart wood of the laburnum is of a dark reddish-brown colour, hard and
                    durable, and takes, a good polish. Hence it is much prized by turners, and used
                    with other coloured woods for inlaying purposes. The laburnum has been called
                    false ebony from this character of its wood.</p>
                <p>The roots are subject to a peculiar disease, not at all uncommon in other members
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Leguminosae,</hi> the fine rootlets swelling into
                    minute club-shaped processes called exostoses, resembling coral-branches in
                    shape. Large masses of such, one or two inches in diameter, may be found at the
                    extremities of the roots of old laburnum trees. They are apparently caused by a
                    fungus which appears to be ubiquitous, as the disease is rarely, if ever, known
                    to be absent, though it does not seem to cause much if any injury to the health
                    of the plants it attacks. See <hi rend="italic">Studier</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ofver Leguminosernas</hi><hi rend="italic">rotknolär,</hi> 1874, by Dr
                    Jacob Erikssen: also <hi rend="italic">Gardener's Chronicle,</hi> 1879, xi. p.
                    209, and xii. p. 112.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
