<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0699-0676-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LINSEED</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 676</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t15">Seeds</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:813025">Archangels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1111109">Seeds</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1013130">Meal</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1049655">Oxygenators</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LINSEED</label> is the seed of the common flax or lint, <hi
                    rend="italic">Linum usitatissimum,</hi> from which also the well-known fibre
                    flax is obtained. The plant itself is figured and described under <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Flax,</hi> vol. ix. p. 293. The fruit of the flax plant
                    consists of a globose capsule which splits into five cocci, each containing two
                    seeds. These seeds, the linseed of commerce, are of a lustrous brown colour
                    externally, and a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n700/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0700-0677"/> compressed and elongated oval, form, with a
                    slight beak or projection at one extremity. The brown testa contains, in the
                    outer of the four coats into which it is microscopically distinguishable, an
                    abundant secretion of mucilaginous matter; and it has within it a thin layer of
                    albumen, enclosing a pair of large oily cotyledons. The seeds when placed in
                    water for some time become coated with glutinous matter from the exudation of
                    the mucilage in the external layer of the epidermis; and by boiling in sixteen
                    parts of water they exude sufficient mucilage to form with the water a thick
                    pasty decoction. The cotyledons contain the valuable linseed oil referred to
                    below. Linseed grown in tropical countries is much larger and more plump than
                    that obtained in temperate climes, but the seed from the colder countries, on
                    the other hand, yields a finer quality of oiL Fliickiger and Hanbury found that
                    six seeds of Sicilian linseed, thirteen of Black Sea, and seventeen of Archangel
                    linseed weighed respectively one grain. The average composition of linseed may
                    be fairly represented by the following analysis by Dr Thomas Anderson: -—
                    albuminous substances, 24 ’ 44; oil, 34Ό0; gum sugar and cellulose, 30*73; ash,
                    3 ’ 33; water, 7 ’ 50. Linseed is cultivated and secured as a crop in all,
                    European flax-growing countries, where the seed is probably not less valuable
                    than the fibre. It is also obtained from Egypt and India, being cultivated in
                    the latter country solely on account of the seed.</p>
                <p>Apart from its value as a source of oil, and for sowing, linseed is not a product
                    of much economic importance. It formed an article of food among the Greeks and
                    Romans, and it is said that the Abyssinians at the present day eat it roasted.
                    The oil is to some extent used as food in Russia, and in parts of Poland and
                    Hungary. Linseed meal, partly on account of its bland oily constitution, is a
                    valuable material for poultices. At one time the crushed seeds were the
                    officinally recognized cataplasmic material, but the readiness with which that
                    preparation became rancid through the oxidation of its abundant oil frequently
                    rendered it a dangerous application for open sores. The <hi rend="italic">lini
                    farina</hi> of the pharmacopoeia is now the powdered meal of the cake left after
                    expression of the oil, with a proportion of olive oil added when about to be
                    used. An infusion of linseed under the name of “linseed tea” is a popular
                    diluent in bronchial and other inflammatory affections. The abundant mucilage in
                    linseed meal makes it a most useful material for luting stoppers in chemical
                    jars, and other such joints in glass-work. Linseed cake, the marc left after the
                    expression of the oil, is a most valuable feeding substance for cattle.
                    According to a recent analysis by Dr Voelcker <hi rend="italic">(Jourιι. Poy.
                    Agric. Sοc.,</hi> 2d ser., vol. xvii. p. 659) it contains in 100 parts—oil,
                    10∙90; albuminous compounds, 24’56; mucilage, sugar, and digestible fibre,
                    31*97; woody fibre, 11 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 47; ash, 6'20; moisture,
                    14 ’ 90.</p>
                <p>Linseed is subject to extensive and detrimental adulterations, resulting not only
                    from careless harvesting and cleaning, whereby seeds of the flax dodder and
                    other weeds and grasses are mixed with it, but also from the direct admixture of
                    cheaper and inferior oil seeds, such as wild rape, mustard, sesame, poppy,
                    &amp;c., the latter adulterations being known in trade under the generic name of
                    “buffum.” In 1864, owing to the serious aspect of the prevalent adulteration, a
                    union of traders was formed under the name of the “Linseed Association,” the
                    members of which bind themselves to give compensation for all adulterations in
                    excess of 4 per cent, of foreign matter. Highly adulterated linseed is, however,
                    still very common outside the field of operations of the Linseed
                    Association.</p>
                <p>The quantity of linseed imported into the United Kingdom during the year 1881 was
                    1,829,838 quarters, of a value of £4,395,061. About one-half of this amount,
                    937,059 quarters, valued at £2,299,877, came from the East Indies, and the
                    imports from Russia, amounting to 728,358 quarters, valued at £1,694,720,
                    account for the greater part of the remainder.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Linseed Oil,</hi> the most valuable and characteristic of the
                    series of drying oils, is obtained by expression from the seeds, with or without
                    the aid of heat. Preliminary to the operation of pressing, the seeds are crushed
                    between a {&gt;air of revolving rollers, and ground to a fine meal under ιeavy
                    edge stones on a stone bed. For the extraction of the fine quality of oil known
                    as cold-drawn the meal is, without further preparation, filled into woollen or
                    canvas bags and enclosed in horse-hair envelopes for pressure, either in a Dutch
                    mill worked by means of wedges and falling stampers or in a screw press, or,
                    what is now more prevalent, in a special form of hydraulic press. The oil so
                    obtained is of a clear yellow colour, and is comparatively devoid of odour and
                    taste. The cake left by cold pressure is again ground up, heated in a steam
                    kettle to about 212° Fahr., and while hot submitted to further pressure, which
                    results in the exudation of a less pure oil of a brownish-yellow colour. In
                    general practice, cold-drawn oil is little prepared; the linseed after grinding
                    is submitted to a high heat, whereby the mucilage in the epidermis is destroyed,
                    and the oil flows more freely; and in many crushing establishments the oil is
                    obtained by a single operation under the press. The yield of oil from different
                    classes of seed varies, but from 23 to 28 per cent, of the weight of the seed
                    operated on should be obtained. A good average quality of seed weighing about
                    392 lb per quarter has been found in practice to give out 109 lb of oil.</p>
                <p>Commercial linseed oil has a peculiar rather disagreeable sharp taste and smell;
                    its specific gravity is given as varying from 0 ’ 928 to 0 ’ 953, and it does
                    not solidify under the influence of very low temperature. It is soluble in 32
                    parts of alcohol, sp. gr. 0 ’ 82, in 6 parts of boiling alcohol, and in 16 of
                    ether. By saponification it yields about 95 per cent, of fatty acids,
                    principally linoleic acid (C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 26</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>), a body peculiar to
                    the drying oils, and by treatment with oxide of lead about nine-tenths of the
                    resulting lead salt is found to be linoleate of lead. The oil may be perfectly
                    bleached by treatment with a solution of green sulphate of iron, with repeated
                    shaking and exposure to the light for a period of four to six weeks. Exposed to
                    the air in thin films, linseed oil absorbs oxygen and forms a resinous
                    semielastic caoutchouc-like mass, oxylinoleic acid, C <hi rend="subscript">
                    16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 26</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>. The oil,
                    when boiled with small proportions of litharge and minium, undergoes the process
                    of résinification in the air with greatly increased rapidity. Sacc found by
                    boiling 2500 grains of raw oil for ten minutes with 30 grains each of litharge
                    and minium, and weighing after twenty-four hours exposure to the atmosphere,
                    that the oil had lost only 60 grains. A second sample he boiled till there was a
                    loss of 5 per cent, in weight, when the product assumed the consistency of
                    molasses; and a third portion boiled to a loss of 12 per cent became a
                    caoutchouc-like mass. The first of these products he found dried, on exposure,
                    to a fine transparent varnish; the second did not resinify after fifteen days’
                    exposure; and the atmosphere had no effect on the third portion. The weight of
                    the film of the first after complete résinification was increased 50 per cent,
                    through absorption of oxygen, and the rate at which absorption took place was
                    much influenced by heat.</p>
                <p>To these physical properties the varied industrial applications of linseed oil
                    are principally due. Its most important use is certainly found in the
                    preparation of oil paints and varnishes. By painters both raw and boiled oil are
                    used, the latter not only forming the Erincipal medium in oil painting, but also
                    serving separately as the asis of all oil varnishes. Boiled oil is prepared in a
                    variety of ways—that most common being by heating the raw oil in an iron or
                    copper boiler, which, to allow for frothing, must only be about three-fourths
                    filled. The boiler is heated by a furnace, and the oil is brought gradually to
                    the point of ebullition, at which it is maintained for two hours, during which
                    time moisture is driven off, and the scum and froth which accumulate on the
                    surface are ladled out. Then by slow degrees a proportion of “dryers” is
                    added—usually equal weights of litharge and minium being used to the extent of 3
                    per cent, of the charge of oil; and with these a small proportion of umber is
                    generally thrown in. After the addition ol the dryers the boiling is continued
                    two or three hours; <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n701/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0701-0678"/> the Are is then suddenly withdrawn, and the oil
                    is left covered up in the boiler for ten hours or more. Before sending out, it
                    is usually stored in settling tanks for a few weeks, during which time the
                    uncombined dryers settle at the bottom as “foots.” Besides the dryers already
                    mentioned, acetate of lead, borate of manganese, binoxide of manganese, sulphate
                    of zinc, and other bodies are used. The theory of the influence of boiling and
                    of the addition of these bodies on linseed oil is not well understood. By Liebig
                    it was suggested that they simply removed the mucilaginous and other foreign
                    constituents of the oil which by their presence intercepted the action of
                    oxygen; but by Chevreul and others the opinion was held that the chemicals used,
                    by giving up oxygen to the oil, thereby induce a more rapid and energetic
                    absorption from the air. However this may be, it does not appear at least that
                    boiling is essential for the production of that active condition of the oil, as
                    it may also be induced by treatment of cold raw oil with lead acetate and other
                    agencies. Boiled oil is now very largely used in the manufacture of linoleum
                    floor-cloth. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Linoleum.</hi></p>
                <p>Linseed oil is also the principal ingredient in printing and lithographic inks.
                    The oil for ink-making is prepared by heating it in an iron pot up to the point
                    where it either takes fire spontaneously or can be ignited with any flaming
                    substance. After the oil has been allowed to burn for some time according to the
                    consistence of the varnish desired, the pot is covered over, and the product
                    when cooled forms a viscid tenacious substance which in its most concentrated
                    form may be drawn into threads. By boiling this varnish with dilute nitric acid
                    vapours of acrolein are given off, and the substance gradually becomes a solid
                    non-adhesive mass the same as the ultimate oxidation product of both raw and
                    boiled oil.</p>
                <p>Linseed oil is subject to various falsifications, chiefly through the addition of
                    cotton-seed, niger-seed, and hemp-seed oils; and rosin oil and mineral oils also
                    are not infrequently added. Except by smell, by change of specific gravity, and
                    by deterioration of drying properties, these adulterations are difficult to
                    detect. (J. PA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
