<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0369-0352-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LAVENDER (9th edition, volume 14, page 352)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804414">Alcoholics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804361">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51v7b">Spikes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LAVENDER</label>, botanically <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lavandula,</hi> a genus of <hi rend="italic">Labiatae</hi> distinguished by
                    an ovate tubular calyx, a twolipped corolla, of which the upper lip has two and
                    the lower three lobes, and four stamens bent downwards.</p>
                <p>The plant to which the name of lavender is commonly applied, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lavandula vera,</hi> D.C., is a native of the mountainous districts of the
                    countries bordering on the western half of the Mediterranean, extending from the
                    eastern coast of Spain to Calabria and northern Africa, growing in some places
                    at a height of 4500 feet above the sea-level, and preferring stony declivities
                    in open sunny situations. It is cultivated in the open air as far north as
                    Norway and Livonia. Lavender forms an evergreen undershrub about 2 feet high,
                    with greyish-green hoary linear leaves, rolled under at the edges when young;
                    the branches are erect, and give a bushy appearance to the plant. The flowers
                    are borne on a terminal spike at the summit of a long naked stalk, the spike
                    being composed of 6-10 verticillasters or dense cymes in the axils of small,
                    brownish, rhomboidal, tapering, opposite bracts, the verticillasters being more
                    widely separated towards the base of the spike. The calyx is tubular, contracted
                    towards the mouth, marked with 13 ribs and 5-toothed, the posterior tooth being
                    the largest. The corolla is of a pale violet colour, but darker on its inner
                    surface, tubular, two-lipped, the upper lip with two and the lower with three
                    lobes Both corolla and calyx are covered with stellate hairs, amongst which are
                    imbedded shining oil glands to which the fragrance of the plant’is due. The
                    leaves and flowers of lavender are said to have been used by the ancients to
                    perfume their baths; hence the name <hi rend="italic">Lavandula</hi> is supposed
                    to have been derived from <hi rend="italic">lavare,</hi> to wash. But, although
                    N. <hi rend="italic">Stoechas</hi> was well known to the ancients, no allusion
                    unquestionably referring to <hi rend="italic">L. vera</hi> has been found in the
                    writings of classical authors, the earliest mention of the latter plant being in
                    the 12th century by the abbess Hildegard, who lived near Bingen on the Rhine.
                    Under the name of llafant or llafantly it was known to the Welsh physicians as a
                    medicine in the 13th century. In England lavender is cultivated chiefly for the
                    distillation of its essential oil, of which it yields on an average 1∣ per cent,
                    when freed from the stalks, but in the south of Europe the flowers form an
                    object of trade, being exported to the Barbary states, Turkey, and America.</p>
                <p>In Great Britain lavender is grown in the parishes of Mitcham, Carshalton, and
                    Beddington in Surrey, where about 300 acres are under cultivation, and in
                    Hertfordshire, in the parish of Hitchin, to the extent of 50 acres. The most
                    suitable soil seems to be a sandy loam with a calcareous substratum, and the
                    most favourable position a sunny slope in localities elevated above the level of
                    fogs, where the plant is not in danger of early frost and is freely exposed to
                    air and light. At Hitchin lavender is said to have been grown as early as 1568,
                    but as a commercial speculation its cultivation dates back only to 1823. The
                    plants at present in cultivation do not produce seed, and the propagation is
                    always made by slips or by dividing the roots. The latter plan has only been
                    followed since 1860, when a large number of lavender plants were killed by a
                    severe frost. Since that date the plants have been subject to the attack of a
                    fungus, in consequence of which the price of the oil has been considerably
                    enhanced, and the disease is likely, if it continues, to affect seriously the
                    cultivation of the herb. At Market Deeping in Lincolnshire, where lavender was
                    formerly grown, its cultivation has been discontinued on this account.</p>
                <p>The flowers are collected in the beginning of August, and taken direct to the
                    still. The yield of oil depends in great measure upon the weather. After a wet
                    and dull June and July the yield is sometimes only half as much as when the
                    weather has been bright and sunshiny. From 12 to 30 lb of oil per acre is the
                    average amount obtained. The oil contained in the stem has a more rank odour and
                    is less volatile than that of the flowers; consequently the portion that distils
                    over after the first hour and a half is collected separately.</p>
                <p>The finest oil is obtained by the distillation of the flowers with' out the
                    stalks, but the labour spent upon this adds about 10s. per lb to the expense of
                    the oil, and the same end is practically attained by the fractional
                    distillation. The oil mellows by keeping three years, after which it
                    deteriorates unless mixed with alcohol; it is also improved by redistillation.
                    Oil of lavender is distilled from the wild plants in Piedmont and the South of
                    France, especially in the villages about Mont Ventoux near Avignon, and in those
                    some leagues west of Montpellier. The best French oil realizes scarcely
                    one-sixth of the price of the English oil. Cheaper varieties are made by
                    distilling the entire plant.</p>
                <p>Oil of Lavender is a mobile liquid having a specific gravity from 0 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 78 to 0 ’ 96 (Zeller). It appears to be a mixture
                    in variable proportion of oxygenated oilsand a stearoptene, the latter being
                    identical, according to Dumas, with common camphor. Its adulteration with
                    alcohol may be detected by chloride of calcium dissolving in it and forming a
                    separate layer of liquid at the bottom of the vessel. Glycerin acts in the same
                    way. If it contain turpentine it will not dissolve in three volumes of alcohol,
                    in which quantity the pure oil is perfectly soluble.</p>
                <p>Lavender flowers were formerly considered good for “all disorders of the head and
                    nerves”; a spirit prepared with them was known under the name of palsy drops. At
                    the present day a compound spirit of lavender, official in the British
                    pharmacopoeia, is sometimes given in conjunction with other stimulants to
                    nervous and hysterical persons suffering from depression of spirits, or is used
                    to give a colour and flavour to medicine.</p>
                <p>Lavender water consists of a solution of the volatile oil in spirit of wine with
                    the addition of the essences of musk, rose, bergamot, and ambergris, but is very
                    rarely prepared by distillation of the floweιs with spirit.</p>
                <p>In the climate of New York lavender is scarcely hardy, but in the vicinity of
                    Philadelphia considerable quantities are grown for the market, the dried flowers
                    being used for sachels or scent bags and for perfuming linen, &amp;c. In
                    American gardens sweet basil <hi rend="italic">{Ocimum basilicum)</hi> is
                    frequently called lavender.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lavandula, Spica</hi> (D. C.), a species which differs from <hi
                        rend="italic">L. vera</hi> chiefly in its smaller size, more crowded leaves,
                    and linear bracts, is also used for the distillation of an essential oil, which
                    is known in England as oil of spike and in France under the name of essence
                    d’aspic. It is used in painting on porcelain and in veterinary medicine. The oil
                    as met with in commerce is less fragrant than that of <hi rend="italic">L.
                        vera,—</hi> probably because the whole plant is distilled, for the flowers
                    of the two species are scarcely distinguishable in fragrance. <hi rend="italic"
                        >L. Spica</hi> does not extend so far north, nor ascend the mountains beyond
                    2000 feet. It cannot be cultivated in Britain except in sheltered situations. A
                    nearly allied species, <hi rend="italic">L. lanata</hi> (Boiss. ), a native of
                    Spain, with broader leaves, is also very fragrant, but does not appear to be
                    distilled for oil.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lavandula</hi><hi rend="italic">Stoechas</hi> (L. ), a species
                    extending from the Canaries to Asia Minor, is distinguished from the above
                    plants by its blackish purple flowers, and shortly-stalked spikes crowned by
                    conspicuous purplish sterile bracts. The flowers were official in the London
                    pharmacopoeia as lateas 1746. They are still used by the Arabs as an expectorant
                    and antispasmodic. The Stcechades (now called the isles of Hyères near Toulon)
                    owed their name to the abundance of the plant growing there.</p>
                <p>Several other species of lavender (twenty in all) are known, some of which extend
                    as far east as to India. A few which differ from the above in having divided
                    leaves, as <hi rend="italic">L. dentata,</hi><hi rend="italic">L.
                        abrotanoides,</hi><hi rend="italic">L. multifolia, L. pinnata,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">L. viridis,</hi> have been cultivated in greenhouses, &amp;c.,
                    in England.</p>
                <p>Sea lavender is a name applied in England to several species of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Statice,</hi> a genus of littoral Plumbaginaceous plants. Lavender cotton
                    is a species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Santolina,</hi> small,
                    yellow-flowered, evergreen undershrubs of the Composite order.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Pharrnacograρhia,</hi> p. 476; De Candolle, <hi
                        rend="italic">Prodromus,</hi> xii. p. 145; <hi rend="italic">Phann.
                        Journal,</hi> (1) xi. p. 33; (1) viii. p. 276; (2) i. p. 278; (3) ill. p.
                    326; (3) iv., p. 161; (3) V. p. 182; (3) vlii. p. 301; (3) x. p. 686; Guigins,
                        <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Lavandes,</hi> 1826. ‘ (E. Μ. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
