<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0293-0278-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LANDOR, Walter Savage</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 278</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d79g">Riches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nz3s">Hunting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n293/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LANDOR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Walter Savage</hi></label>
                    (1775-1864), born at Warwick, January 30, 1775, died at Florence, September 17,
                    1864. In the course of this long life he had won for himself such a double crown
                    of glory in verse and in prose as has been won by no other Englishman but
                    Milton. And with that special object of his lifelong veneration he had likewise
                    in common other claims upon our reverence to which no third competitor among
                    English poets can equally pretend. He had the same constancy to the same
                    principles, the same devotion to the same ideal of civic and heroic life; the
                    same love, the same loyalty, the same wrath, scorn, and hatred, for the same*
                    several objects respectively; the same affection and kinship to the spirit of
                    the Romans, the same natural enjoyment and mastery of their tongue. Not accident
                    merely but attraction must in any case have drawn them to enlist in the ranks
                    and serve under the standard of the ancient Latin army of patriots and poets.
                    But to Landor even more than to Milton the service of the Roman Muse was a
                    natural and necessary expression of his genius, a spontaneous and just direction
                    of its full and exuberant forces. At the age of twenty he published an eloquent
                    and elegant vindication of her claims upon the service and devotion of modern
                    writers,—the first sketch or suggestion of a longer essay, to be published in
                    its final form just fifty-two years later. In 1795 appeared in a small volume,
                    divided into three books, <hi rend="italic">The Poems of Walter Savage
                    Landor,</hi> and, in pamphlet form of nineteen pages, an anonymous <hi
                    rend="italic">Moral Epistle, respectfully dedicated to Earl Stanhope.</hi> No
                    poet at the age of twenty ever had more vigour of style and fluency of verse;
                    nor perhaps has any ever shown such masterly command of epigram and satire, made
                    vivid and vital by the purest enthusiasm and most generous indignation. Three
                    years later appeared the first edition of the first great work which was to
                    inscribe his name for ever among the great names in English poetry. The second
                    edition of <hi rend="italic">Gebir</hi> appeared in 1803, with a text corrected
                    of grave errors and improved by magnificent additions. About the same time the
                    whole poem was also published in a Latin form, which for might and melody of
                    line, for power and perfection of language, must always dispute the palm of
                    precedence with the English version. In 1808, under an impulse not less heroic
                    than that which was afterwards to lead Byron to a glorious death in redemption
                    of Greece and his own good fame, Landor, then aged thirty-three, left England
                    for Spain as a volunteer to serve in the national army against Napoleon at the
                    head of a regiment raised and supported at his sole expense. After some three
                    months’ campaigning came the affair of Cintra and its disasters; “his troop,” in
                    the words of his biographer, “dispersed or melted away, and he came back to
                    England in as great a hurry as he had left it,” but bringing with him the
                    honourable recollection of a brave design unselfishly attempted, and the
                    material in his memory for the sublimest poem published in our language between
                    the last masterpiece of Milton and the first masterpiece of Shelley—one equally
                    worthy to stand unchallenged beside either for poetic perfection as well as
                    moral majesty—the lofty tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Count Julian,</hi> which
                    appeared in 1812, without the name of its author. No comparable work is to be
                    found in English poetry between the date of <hi rend="italic">Samson</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Agonistes</hi> and the date of <hi rend="italic">Prometheus
                    Unbound</hi>; and with both these great works it has some points of greatness in
                    common. The superhuman isolation of agony and endurance which encircles and
                    exalts the hero is in each case expressed with equally appropriate magnificence
                    of effect. The style of <hi rend="italic">Count Jτdian,</hi> if somewhat
                    deficient in dramatic ease and the fluency of natural dialogue, has such might
                    and purity and majesty of speech as elsewhere we find only in Milton so long and
                    so steadily sustained.</p>
                <p>In May 1811 Landor had suddenly married Miss Julia Thuillier, with whose looks he
                    had fallen in love at first sight in a ball-room at Bath; and in June they
                    settled for awhile at Llanthony Abbey in Wales, from whence he was worried in
                    three years’ time by the combined vexation of neighbours and tenants, lawyers
                    and lords-lieutenant; not <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n294/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0294-0279"/> before much toil and money had been nobly wasted
                    on attempts to improve the sterility of the land, to relieve the wretchedness
                    and raise the condition of the peasantry. He left England for France at first,
                    but after a brief residence at Tours took up his abode for three years at Como;
                    “and three more wandering years he passed,” says his biographer, “between Pisa
                    and Pistoja, before he pitched his tent in Florence in 1821.” In 1824 appeared
                    the first series of his <hi rend="italic">Imaginary Conversations,</hi> in 1826
                    “the second edition, corrected and enlarged”; a supplementary third volume was
                    added in 1828; and in 1829 the second series was given to the world. Not until
                    1846 was a fresh instalment added, in the second volume of his collected and
                    selected works. During the interval he had published his three other most famous
                    and greatest books in prose: <hi rend="italic">The Citation and Examination of
                    William Shakespeare,</hi> 1834; <hi rend="italic">Pericles and Aspαsia,</hi>
                    1836; <hi rend="italic">The Pentarneron,</hi> 1837. To the last of these was
                    originally appended <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic">Pentalogia,</hi>
                    containing five of the very finest among his shorter studies in dramatic poetry.
                    In 1847 he published his most important Latin work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poemata</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Inscriptiones,</hi>
                    comprising, with large additions, the main contents of two former volumes of
                    idyllic, satiric, elegiac, and lyric verse; and in the same golden year of his
                    poetic life appeared the very crown and flower of its manifold labours, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Hellenics of Walter Savage Laηdor,</hi> enlarged and
                    completed. Twelve years later this book was reissued, with additions of more or
                    less value, with alterations generally to be regretted, and with omissions
                    invariably to be deplored. In 1853 he put forth <hi rend="italic">The Last Fruit
                    off an Old Tree,</hi> containing fresh conversations, critical and controversial
                    essays, miscellaneous epigrams, lyrics, and occasional poems of various kind and
                    merit, closing with <hi rend="italic">Five Scenes</hi> on the martyrdom of
                    Beatrice Ceiιci, unsurpassed even by their author himself for noble and heroic
                    pathos, for subtle and genial, tragic and profound, ardent and compassionate
                    insight into character, with consummate mastery of dramatic and spiritual truth.
                    In 1856 he published <hi rend="italic">Antony and Octavius—Scenes for the
                    Study,</hi> twelve consecutive poems in dialogue which alone would suffice to
                    place him high among the few great masters of historic drama. In 1858 appeared a
                    metrical miscellany bearing the title of <hi rend="italic">Dry Sticks Fagoted by
                    W. S. Landor,</hi> and containing among other things graver and lighter certain
                    epigrammatic and satirical attacks which reinvolved him in the troubles of an
                    action for libel; and in July of the same year he returned for the last six
                    years of his life to Italy, which he had left for England in 1835. Embittered
                    and distracted by domestic dissensions, if brightened and relieved by the
                    affection and veneration of friends and strangers, this final period of his
                    troubled and splendid career came at last to a quiet end on the 17th of
                    September 1864. In the preceding year he had published a last volume of <hi
                    rend="italic">Heroic Idyls, with additional poems,</hi> English and Latin,—the
                    better part of them well worthy to be indeed the “last fruit” of a genius which
                    after a life of eighty-eight years had lost nothing of its majestic and pathetic
                    power, its exquisite and exalted loveliness.</p>
                <p>A complete list of Landor’s writings, published or privately printed, in English,
                    Latin, and Italian, including pamphlets, fly-sheets, and occasional newspaper
                    correspondence on political or literary questions, it would be difficult to give
                    anywhere and impossible to give here. From nineteen almost to ninety his
                    intellectual and literary activity was indefatigably incessant; but, herein at
                    least like Charles Lamb, whose cordial admiration he so cordially returned, he
                    could not write a note of three lines which did not bear the mark of his “Roman
                    hand” in its matchless and inimitable command of a style at once the most
                    powerful and the purest of his age. The one charge which can ever seriously be
                    brought and maintained against it is that of such occasional obscurity or
                    difficulty as may arise from excessive strictness in condensation of phrase and
                    expurgation of matter not always superfluous, and sometimes almost
                    indispensable. His English prose and his Latin verse are perhaps more frequently
                    and more gravely liable to this charge than either his English verse or his
                    Latin prose. At times it is well nigh impossible for an eye less keen and swift,
                    a scholarship less exquisite and ready than his own, to catch the precise
                    direction and follow the perfect course of his rapid thought and radiant
                    utterance. This apparently studious pursuit and preference of the most terse and
                    elliptic expression which could be found for anything he might have to say could
                    not but occasionally make even so sovereign a master of two great languages
                    appear “dark with excess of light”; but from no former master of either tongue
                    in prose or verse was ever the quality of real obscurity, of loose and nebulous
                    incertitude, more utterly alien or more naturally remote. There is nothing of
                    cloud or fog about the path on which he leads us; but we feel now and then the
                    want of a bridge or a handrail; we have to leap from point to point of narrative
                    or argument without the usual help of a connecting plank. Even in his dramatic
                    works, where least of all it should have been found, this lack of visible
                    connexion or sequence in details of thought or action is too often a source of
                    sensible perplexity. In his noble trilogy on the history of Giovanna queen of
                    Naples it is sometimes actually difficult to realize on a first reading what has
                    happened or is happening, or how, or why, or by what agency,—a defect alone
                    sufficient, but unhappily sufficient in itself, to explain the too general
                    ignorance of a work so rich in subtle and noble treatment of character, so sure
                    and strong in its grasp and rendering of “high actions and high passions,” so
                    rich in humour and in pathos, so royally serene in its commanding power upon the
                    tragic mainsprings of terror and of pity. As a poet, he may be said on the whole
                    to stand midway between Byron and Shelley,—about as far above the former as
                    below the latter. If we except Catullus and Simonides, it might be hard to match
                    and it would be impossible to overmatch the flawless and blameless yet living
                    and breathing beauty of his most perfect elegies, epigrams, or epitaphs. As
                    truly as prettily was he likened by Leigh Hunt “to a stormy mountain pine which
                    should produce lilies.” His passionate compassion, his bitter and burning pity
                    for all wrongs endured in all the world, found only their natural and inevitable
                    outlet in his lifelong defence or advocacy of tyrannicide as the last resource
                    of baffled justice, the last discharge of heroic duty. His tender and ardent
                    love of children, of animals, and of flowers, makes fragrant alike the pages of
                    his writing and the records of his life. He was as surely the most gentle and
                    generous as the most headstrong and hot-headed of heroes or of meu. Nor ever was
                    any man’s best work more thoroughly imbued and informed with evidence of his
                    noblest qualities. His loyalty and liberality of heart were as inexhaustible as
                    his bounty and beneficence of hand. Praise and encouragement, deserved or
                    undeserved, came yet more readily to his lips than challenge or defiance.
                    Reviled and ridiculed by Lord Byron, he retorted on the offender living less
                    readily and less warmly than he lamented and extolled him dead. On the noble
                    dramatic works of his brother Robert he lavished a magnificence of sympathetic
                    praise which his utmost self-estimate would never have exacted for his own. Age
                    and the lapse of time could neither heighten nor lessen the fulness of this rich
                    and ready generosity. To the poets of his own and of the next generation he was
                    not readier to do honour than to those of a later growth, and not seldom of
                    deserts far lower and far lesser claims than theirs. That he was not <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n295/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0295-0280"/> unconscious of his own, and avowed it with the
                    frank simplicity of nobler times, is not more evident or more certain than that
                    in comparison with his friends and fellows he was liable rather to undervalue
                    than to overrate himself. He was a classic, and no formalist; the wide range of
                    his just and loyal admiration had room for a genius so far from classical as
                    Blake’s. Nor in his own highest mood or method of creative as of critical work
                    was he a classic only, in any narrow or exclusive sense of the term. On either
                    side, immediately or hardly below his mighty masterpiece of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pericles and</hi><hi rend="italic">Aspasia,</hi> stand the two scarcely less
                    beautiful and vivid studies of mediaeval Italy and Shakespearean England. The
                    very finest flower of his immortal dialogues is probably to be found in the
                    single volume comprising only “Imaginary Conversations of Greeks and Romans his
                    utmost command of passion and pathos may be tested by its transcendent success
                    in the distilled and concentrated tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Tiberius and
                    Vipsania,</hi> where for once he shows a quality more proper to romantic than
                    classical imagination,—the subtle and sublime and terrible power to enter the
                    dark vestibule of distraction, to throw the whole force of his fancy, the whole
                    fire of his spirit, into the “shadowing passion” (as Shakespeare calls it) of
                    gradually imminent insanity. Yet, if this and all other studies from ancient
                    history or legend could be subtracted from the volume of his work, enough would
                    be left whereon to rest the foundation of a fame which time could not sensibly
                    impair. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. c. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
