<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0741-0718-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIVERWORTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 718</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:850250">Cells</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1116836">Shooting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:935345">Fronde</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865884">Coats</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1097331">Riccia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937845">Gardeners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz6186h">Cells</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c40">Shooting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qt62">Fronde</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m6299t">Urns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n741/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIVERWORTS</label>. The Liverworts or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hepaticae</hi> constitute a group of the higher <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cryptogamia,</hi> allied to the mosses. Their shoots are either <hi
                    rend="italic">thalloid,</hi> in some genera (<hi rend="italic">Marchantiaj)</hi>
                    highly differentiated in structure, in others <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Anthoceros)</hi> of simple homogeneous texture, with an upper and lower
                    surface, the latter fixed to the ground by capillary rootlets, and generally
                    margined with minute scales; or they are <hi rend="italic">foliose,</hi> the
                    central stem bearing on each side a row of leaves, consisting of one series of
                    cells invested with a structureless epidermis, and destitute of nerves, such as
                    prevail in the leaves of mosses. Frequently on the inferior aspect a third row
                    of leaf-like scales is found, differing from the former, and known as stipules,
                    bracteoles, or amphigastria. Hence the shoots, although typically trilateral,
                    often appear bilateral. The reproductive organs of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hepaticae</hi> are of two kinds—sexual and asexual.</p>
                <p>I. The sexual germs of the mosses and <hi rend="italic">Hepaticae</hi> were first
                    described by Hedwig just one hundred years ago (1782). They consist, as in the
                    higher plants, of germ-cells and sperm-cells. As the fronds approach maturity
                    the terminal leaves become modified so as to form an involucrum, within which a
                    special covering appears, the colesule or perianth, surrounding the pistillidia;
                    this is tubular, conical, or compressed in form, with the mouth plicate and
                    generally dentate.</p>
                <p>On section of the colesule a number of minute flask-shaped bodies are found,
                    attached to the apex of the stem, which have been named archigonia or
                    pistillidia. After fertilization one of these enlarges, active cell formation
                    proceeding from the central cell at the base, within which appears the
                    germ-cell, which in time becomes the capsule, the ultimate contents producing
                    spores arranged in fours, and elongated cells bearing within spiral filaments
                    (elaters). Until the maturity of the spores, the sporangium remains at the base
                    of the colesule, but at length the outer coat (calyptra) ruptures near the
                    summit, and by the rapid evolution of the cells of the fruit-stalk (seta) the
                    capsule is borne upwards. At this stage, which is of brief duration, the fronds
                    look as if dotted with black-headed pins on white stalks. Released from
                    pressure, the hygrometric action of the elater soon ruptures the wall of the
                    capsule, which divides, in the majority of species, into four valves, and the
                    spores are scattered around.</p>
                <p>The antheridia are sometimes found imbedded in crypts within the substance of the
                    thallus <hi rend="italic">(S,iccif),</hi> or in special receptacles either
                    sessile or raised above the surface of the same <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Marchantia).</hi> In the foliose <hi rend="italic">Hepaticae</hi> they are
                    usually seated in the axils of modified leaves (perigonial), sometimes appearing
                    beneath the fertile involucra (monoecious), or on special branches of the same
                    plant (paroecious), or they occur on separate plants (dioecious). The antheridia
                    are much smaller than the capsules, spherical or ovoid in form, and seated on a
                    short footstalk. They are invested with a single coat of tabular cells. Before
                    maturity they are greenish, but when ripe their colour turns to yellow. On
                    pressure they rupture irregularly, and allow the escape of crowds of lenticular
                    cells, which revolve actively under the microscope until the ciliated phytozoa
                    within them are released.</p>
                <p>The phytozoa of mosses were first figured by Unger (1834), who described them as
                    consisting of a thick body, and a thin thread-like prolongation, which goes in
                    advance when the body is in motion, and is spiral in form. Thuret has since
                    shown that the so-called “tail” bears two long oscillating cilia. Hofmeister
                    first observed the formation of the free germinal vesicle within the basal cell
                    of the pistillidium as the direct result of fertilization.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n742/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0742-0719"/>
                <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Asexual Germs.—</hi> Beyond the true fructification, in the
                    majority of <hi rend="italic">Hepaticae,</hi> certain bodies are met with, which
                    are known as gemmae, but which differ from each other in complexity and
                    significance.</p>
                <p>(1) In some <hi rend="italic">Harchantiae</hi> basket-like or crescentic
                    receptacles are found, containing lenticular bodies, which, under favourable
                    conditions, will produce new fronds.</p>
                <p>(2) On the borders of the leaves, especially near the apex of the shoots,
                    prolification from the ordinary cellular tissue is met with in most <hi
                    rend="italic">Hepaticae,</hi> in the form of detached cells or tufts of such
                    cells. These are generally described as gemmae, but resemble more closely the
                    <hi rend="italic">gonidia</hi> of lichens, and probably aid in the diffusion of
                    dioecious species, which from the absence of ⅛ or $ plants would otherwise
                    become extinct.</p>
                <p>(3) Another process has been ascribed to gemmation, but has been more happily
                    named by Dr A. Braun <hi rend="italic">rejuvenescence</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >{Verjungung').</hi> In decayed or apparently withered fronds, certain cells,
                    after a period of rest, assume new activity and multiply so as to give rise to
                    new individuals <hi rend="italic">{Anthoceros, Riccia,</hi> &lt;fcc.).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Distinction between</hi><hi rend="italic">Hepaticae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic">Musci.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    There is scarcely a character in the definition of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hepaticae</hi> which might not refer to some genus of mosses, although the
                    definition as a whole may be sufficiently distinctive, and practically there is
                    no difficulty in distinguishing one from the other.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Musci</hi> the urn-case or capsule generally opens by means
                    of a lid, and the mouth is surrounded by a peristome divided into four, eight,
                    or more teeth. A columella is nearly always present, and the spores ripen in a
                    sac between the former and the walls of the capsule. From the early elongation
                    of the fruit rudiment, the calyptra is ruptured at an earlier stage, the upper
                    part investing the urn-case like a cap, during the development of the spores;
                    the lower remnant remains at th⅛ base of the seta (which, as well as the
                    capsule, is composed of more ligneous texture than in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hepaticae)</hi> as the vaginula. The spore gives rise to a confervoid
                    prothallus often extensively branched, and from this the leaf-buds arise. The
                    leaves are imbricated on all sides of the stem, and the phyllotaxis is usually
                    ⅜, ⅜, or j. The leaves are frequently strengthened by a midrib, and the rootlets
                    are divided by numerous septa.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Habitat.</hi> —The <hi rend="italic">Hepaticae</hi> are
                    cosmopolitan in range, and form a relatively important average of the alpine
                    vegetation, being abundant in moist equable and insular places, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> Ireland, Scotland, New Zealand. They are also met with
                    in more tropical zones, such as South America, India, Java, and the West
                    Indies.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Classification.</hi></p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="italic">Marchantiaceae.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Fronds
                    thalloid, prostrate, furcate; epidermis pierced with curious stomata; inner
                    section areolate, occupied by green gonidial cells, lower surface simply
                    cellular, emitting long rootlets, papillose within.</p>
                <p>(a) <hi rend="italic">Marchantieae.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Capsules
                    aggregate on a stalked receptacle: <hi rend="italic">e.g., Marchantia,
                    Asterella, Fegatella, Dumortiera, Lunu-laria,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>(δ) <hi rend="italic">Targionicae.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Antheridia
                    immersed; involucre like a split pea; capsule nearly sessile, below the
                    apex.</p>
                <p>(c) <hi rend="italic">Riccieae.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Antheridia and
                    pistillidia immersed, the latter emitting the spores by the decay of the walls;
                    spores without elaters: <hi rend="italic">e.g., Riccia, Ricciella,</hi>
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Jungermanniaceae.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Capsule
                    solitary terminal on the primary shoots or on short lateral ones, splitting into
                    four valves.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">*</hi><hi rend="italic">Foliosae.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(</hi><hi rend="italic">a)</hi> Leaves <hi rend="italic">succubous: e.g.,
                    Jungermannia, Scapania, Lopho-colea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic">b)</hi> Leaves <hi rend="italic"
                    >incubous: e.g., Lijennia, Frullania,</hi><hi rend="italic">Schisma,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lepi∙</hi><hi rend="italic">dozia, kc.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >*</hi><hi rend="italic">*</hi><hi rend="italic">Frondosae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >: e.g., Pellia, Blasia, Petalophyllum, kc.</hi></p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="italic">Anthoceroteae.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Capsule horn
                    or pod-like, opening by one or two valves, columella central, spores
                    intermingled with deformed elaters: <hi rend="italic">e.g., Anthoceros,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Monoclaea.</hi><hi rend="italic">Uses.—At</hi> the present time
                    the <hi rend="italic">Hepaticae</hi> are of little practical use to man. „ In
                    the dark ages of medicine, when the doctrine of “signatures” was in fashion, the
                    strongly-marked epidermic cells were supposed to resemble the structure of the
                    liver, and the species were esteemed “a sovran remedy” in liver complaints. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Hepatica fontana</hi><hi rend="italic">{Marchantia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">polymorpha)</hi> of Casper Bauhine, “which grows near springs,
                    wells, and watery places, very lowe, almost like a moss, and puts out flowers
                    about June, not unlike <hi rend="italic">stars,</hi>” is wonderfully commended
                    by Schroder, in those disorders of the liver which arise from too much heat <hi
                    rend="italic">{English Dispensary,</hi> 1733). A few species possess a pungent,
                    bitter taste <hi rend="italic">{Porella)</hi> resembling that of <hi
                    rend="italic">Sedum</hi><hi rend="italic">acre.</hi> Many also evolve a musky
                    odour, observable in the woods and fields after rain, and incorrectly referred
                    to the smell of moist earth.</p>
                <p>Beyond the beauty of tint and outline, which light up many a dreary ravine, they
                    supply abundant material for the microscope, enabling us by the translucency of
                    tissue, and their easy preservation, so long as moisture is supplied, to study
                    cell and leaf-structure, and the wonders of reproduction, as no other class will
                    do.</p>
                <p>Lastly, many fern-growers have of late included the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hepaticae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Musci</hi> in their lists of favourites,
                    the variety adding immeasurably to the interest of their collections. Most of
                    the species are readily cultivated in a cold frame or fernery, the atmosphere of
                    which must be kept moist and equable. In the renowned ferneries of Mr Backhouse
                    of York, A. Stansfield of Todmorden, and the Glasnevin Gardens, Dublin, species
                    have long been cultivated, many foreign to the climate, and introduced with
                    foreign plants. (B. C. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
