<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0886-0857-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LONGEVITY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 857</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:973308">Infusoria</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="46" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1179191">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n886/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LONGEVITY</label> is a term that may be applied to express
                    either the length or duration of life of any organism, or the prolongation of
                    life to an advanced age. The first meaning is the more scientific of the two, as
                    it may be applied to the duration of the life of any organism, although that
                    duration may be relatively short; thus, we may contrast the longevity of the
                    mould which lives only a few hours with that of the forest tree which has
                    survived for centuries, or the longevity of the ephemeral insect with that of an
                    eagle or a swan, whose lives may be prolonged to over a century. On the other
                    hand, the second meaning is the more common, as when an instance of very
                    advanced age is spoken of as an example of great longevity.</p>
                <p>The information we possess as to the natural duration of life of the lower forms
                    of plants and animals is very meagre, and it can scarcely be asserted that in
                    all there is a natural period of Jife. A simple 'organism composed of cells, or
                    even one more complicated but still having the organs necessary to life
                    constructed upon a simple type, may continue to live and grow so long as
                    external conditions are favourable. There may be no tendency to decay of tissue
                    inherent in the organism, so that life may be prolonged until a change in
                    external conditions, quickly or slowly, so affects the processes of nutrition as
                    to make the continuance of life impossible beyond a certain time. It is also
                    highly probable that in both the animal and vegetable worlds comparatively few
                    individuals are permitted to live undisturbed for a sufficient length of time to
                    allow any inherent tendencies to decay to show themselves. In the struggle for
                    existence few individuals even reach maturity; at an early period they are used
                    to support the lives of other and perhaps stronger organisms.</p>
                <p>Excluding the lower forms of plants, as to the duration of whose lives we know
                    nothing, the higher plants may be classed, according to duration of life, as
                    follows :— <hi rend="italic">annuals,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >semi-annuals,</hi> which grow up in spring and die in autumn <hi rend="italic"
                    >; biennials,</hi> which die at the end of the second year; and <hi
                    rend="italic">perennials,</hi> the duration of which may last from four to
                    thousands of years. Succulent plants have a short life, lasting only one or two
                    years; the formation of wood is necessary for prolonged vegetable existence. It
                    has been pointed out that strongly scented plants have often a longer duration
                    of life than those destitute of smelt Thus thyme, mint, hyssop, marjoram, sage,
                    &lt;fcc,, can live for two years or longer; whilst lettuce, wheat, oats, barley,
                    live no more than a year. Trees of rapid growth, such as fir, birch,
                    horse-chestnut, form soft wood, and have a comparatively short life; whilst
                    hard-wood trees, such as the oak, grow slowly and live long. It is not, however,
                    an invariable rule that trees yielding hard wood live longest. The beech,
                    cypress, juniper, walnut, and pear all form hard wood, but they do not live so
                    long as the lime, which forms a softer wood. Trees which are long in producing
                    leaves and fruit, and which also retain these for a long time, live longer than
                    those in which these changes occur quickly. Fruitbearing trees, producing a sour
                    harsh fruit in the wild state, have longer lives than those bearing sweet fruits
                    in the cultivated state. By skilful pruning, or lopping off the branches and
                    buds, the term of life of even short-lived plants may be lengthened.</p>
                <p>According to Hufeland, the chance any plant has of attaining a great age depends
                    on the following conditions: —(1) it must grow slowly; (2) it must propagate
                    slowly and late in life; (3) it must have a certain degree of solidity and
                    hardness in its organs, a sufficiency of wood, and the sap must not be too
                    watery; (4) it must be large and have a considerable extent of surface; and (5)
                    it must rise into the atmosphere. If we view a tree as consisting of an enormous
                    number of buds clustered on a common stem in which the vessels or channels for
                    the circulation of the sap remain pervious, and in which also new wood is formed
                    annually, there seems to be no limit to age, provided external conditions are
                    favourable. Many large trees have reached a vast age, as shown by the following
                    table compiled by De Candolle :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Years.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Years.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Elm <hi rend="italic">(Ulmus
                            campestris)</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>335</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Oriental plane <hi rend="italic"
                            >(Platanus orientalis)</hi> 720</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cvυress <hi rend="italic">(CuDressus
                            SemOervireηS</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">..</hi>
                            350</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cedar <hi rend="italic">(Cedrus
                            Libani)..</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>800</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Clιeirοstemοn
                            platanoides</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lime <hi rend="italic">(Tilia</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">europaea)..</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1076-1147</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ivy <hi rend="italic">(Hedera</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Helix)</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>450</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Oak <hi rend="italic">(Quercus Robur)
                            ..</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>. 810, 1080,1500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Larch <hi rend="italic"
                            >(Larix</hi><hi rend="italic">europaea)</hi></p><p>Chestnut <hi
                            rend="italic">(Castanea</hi><hi rend="italic">vesca)</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>576</p><p>600</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Yew <hi rend="italic">(Taxus baccata)
                            ..</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>( 1214,1458</p><p>1
                            2588,2880</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Orange <hi rend="italic">(Citrus
                            Aurantium)...</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>630</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Taxodium</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">distichum....</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3000-4000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Palms <hi rend="italic"
                            >(Ceroxylon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cocos)...</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>. 600-700</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Baobob <hi rend="italic">(Adansonia
                            digitata)</hi> 5000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Olive <hi rend="italic">(Olea</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">europaea)</hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >.............</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>700</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In the animal kingdom there is great variety as regards the duration of life, but
                    no accurate data have yet been collected. Certain <hi rend="italic"
                    >Infusoria</hi> have been watched during the whole period of their existence,
                    which has not lasted more than forty-eight hours; on the other hand, <hi
                    rend="italic">Actiniae,</hi> or sea anemones, may live to a long age, as shown
                    by the case of a specimen of <hi rend="italic">Actinia mesembryanthemum,</hi>
                    still alive in Edinburgh, which belonged to Sir John Dalyell, and which must be
                    at least about seventy years of age. It is highly probable that cold-blooded
                    animals, such as fishes, frogs, toads, in which tissue-changes go on with
                    extreme slowness, especially during a period of muscular inactivity, may live
                    for many years. In the imperial fish-ponds of ancient Rome lampreys were said to
                    have attained their sixtieth year; pike and carp have been ascertained to live a
                    hundred and fifty years; tortoises have reached the age of one hundred years;
                    and it is alleged by natives of India that the crocodile may live for at least a
                    hundred years, and that there seems to be no limit to its time of growth. Many
                    birds have a long period of life. Eagles and crows have been known to live a
                    hundred years, and parrots have been kept in confinement for sixty years.
                    Peacocks attain an age of twenty years; barn-door fowls live for a much shorter
                    period, from six to twelve years. Small birds seem to have shorter lives than
                    large ones. Blackbirds, goldfinches, and canaries have been known to live for
                    twenty years; but many of the smaller birds attain an age of only five or six
                    years.</p>
                <p>Amongst mammals, the elephant is supposed to attain the greatest age, reaching
                    above a hundred years; the camel generally lives to fifty years, and may live to
                    eighty; the horse does not live more than forty years; the deer, thirty years;
                    the ox, fifteen to twenty years; sheep, goats, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n887/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0887-0858"/> foxes, hares, rabbits, from seven to ten years;
                    and dogs and pigs from fifteen to twenty years Certain general statements may be
                    made, which do not deserve to be termed laws, but which briefly express
                    relations that undoubtedly exist in many cases between the degree of longevity
                    enjoyed by any species of animal and the conditions of its existence.</p>
                <p>1. A relation can often be traced between the duration of life and the time of
                    the development of the animal <hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >utero.</hi> To this statement there are many exceptions, as will be apparent
                    from the following table, in which the periods of gestation are given on the
                    authority of Professor Owen <hi rend="italic">{Comp. Anat. and Phys, of
                    Vertebrates,</hi> vol fit):—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Name.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Period of Gestation in
                            Days.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Longevity in Years.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Name.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Period of Gestation in
                            Days.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Longevity in Years.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Elephant</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>593</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>100</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Monkey (C⅛δus)...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>150</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Giraffe</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>440</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Not known.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>p⅛</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>120</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15-20</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mare and Ass</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>330</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30-40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Marmoset</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>120</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Net known.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cow</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>286</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15-20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Lemur
                            αlbifrοns...</hi> Wolf, Jackal, Dog</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>105</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Not known.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Human Being</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>280</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>80-100</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>63</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15-20</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Roe Deer</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>280</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cat</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15-20</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Red Deer )</p><p>Fallow Deer ....
                            j</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>245</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bat (<hi rend="italic">Vesper 1 iliο
                            ) noctula) f</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Not known.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hippopotamus ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>234</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Not known.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kangaroo</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>38</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Not known.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In the case of birds no relation of this kind can be discovered. For times of
                    incubation of many birds see Owen, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> vol. ii. p.
                    257.</p>
                <p>2. It would appear that the sooner a being attains maturity the sooner it
                    propagates, and the shorter, will be the duration of its life. The reproductive
                    act may be regarded as the culminating act of the organism, requiring the
                    highest degree of vitality, and involving the largest expenditure of energy.
                    This act will therefore be performed when the organism has reached maturity; in
                    some cases the animal reaches maturity late, in other cases early; but in all
                    the epoch of maturity may be taken as about a fifth part of the whole duration
                    of life. Thus the elephant and the human being do not reach maturity till say
                    the twentieth year, and the period of longevity is about a hundred years; the
                    horse, ass, and bull are mature in the third or fourth year, and live from
                    fifteen to twenty years; sheep come to maturity in the second year, and live
                    from eight to ten years; whilst rabbits and guinea pigs are mature within one
                    year, and live only from four to five years. Here again there are exceptions,
                    as, for example, the cat is mature before the end of the first year, and still
                    it may live to the age of twenty years. Much information is still required on
                    these points before a law can be formulated.</p>
                <p>The question of longevity, however, probably presents the greatest interest in
                    its relation to man. It is still a popular belief that the earliest inhabitants
                    of the world possessed an incredible strength, were of an enormous size, and
                    lived to a very great age; and the ages of the patriarchs before the flood are
                    often taken literally, although the conditions making such long lives possible
                    are at variance with those of human existence at the present day. In ancient
                    history there are instances given of heroes who attained the age of several
                    hundred years, but these must be regarded as mythical. For an interesting
                    account of these, see Hufeland’s <hi rend="italic">Art of Prolonging Life,</hi>
                    p. 62 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p>
                <p>The following are a few instances of extreme longevity which have been placed on
                    record :—Margaret Patten, 137; the countess of Desmond, 145; Thomas Parr, 152;
                    Thomas Damme, 154; John Rovin, 172; and Peter Torton, 185. There can be little
                    doubt that the ages of these persons have been much exaggerated. They lived at a
                    time when no accurate chronological records were kept, and when it was the habit
                    to fix the dates of occurrences by comparing them in the memory with other
                    events believed to have happened about the same time. Thus there were many
                    sources of fallacy, although the narrators no doubt believed their statements to
                    be quite accurate. Still these were instances of prolongation of human life far
                    beyond the usual limits, and there is no reason f®r doubting that they all lived
                    till they were upwards of a hundred years of age.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the best authenticated instance of this kind is that of the famous Thomas
                    Parr of Shropshire. “He was a poor farmer’s servant, and obliged to maintain
                    himself by daily labour. When above one hundred and twenty years of age he
                    married a widow for his second wife, who lived with him twelve years, and who
                    asserted that during that time he never betrayed any signs of infirmity of age.
                    Till his one hundred and thirtieth year he performed all his usual work, and was
                    accustomed even to thresh. Some years before his death his eyes and memory began
                    to fail, but his hearing and senses continued sound to the last. In his one
                    hundred and fifty-second year his fame had reached London; and, as the king was
                    desirous of seeing so great a rarity, he was induced to take a journey thither.
                    This, in all probability, shortened his existence, which he otherwise might have
                    preserved some years longer; for he was treated at court in so royal a manner,
                    and his mode, of living was so totally changed that he died soon after, at
                    London, in .1635. He was one hundred and fifty-two years and nine tnonths old,
                    and had lived under nine kings of England. What was most remarkable in regard to
                    this man is that, when his body was opened by Dr Harvey (the discoverer of the
                    circulation of the blood), his internal organs were found to be in the most
                    perfect state, nor was the least symptom of decay to be discovered in them. His
                    cartilages even were not ossified, as is the case in all old people. The
                    smallest cause of death had not yet settled in his body; and he died merely of a
                    plethora, because he had been too well treated.”—Hufeland, p. 71.</p>
                <p>The late Sir George Cornewall Lewis attempted to show that all such narratives
                    were so inaccurate as to reduce the ages of the parties to something under a
                    hundred years, and he was disposed to think that there had been no instance of a
                    human being attaining the age of a hundred years. But subsequent cases have
                    shown that a few have attained that great age. In these cases the evidence has
                    not been of a collateral kind, nor has it depended on human memory, but it has
                    been established by written records. Scarcely a year passes without instances
                    occurring in which the evidence that the deceased attained a hundred years
                    cannot be controverted, and there is no doubt that, when a sufficient time from
                    the beginning of the system of registration of births has elapsed, such cases
                    will be more common.</p>
                <p>The average duration of life in Europe is about thirty-four years. It oscillates
                    between 28 ’ 18 years (Prussia) and 39 ’ 8 years (Schleswig-Holstein,
                    Lauenburg). In Naples it is quoted at 31 ’ 65 years. This falls far short of the
                    possible longevity, a circumstance chiefly to be accounted for by the great
                    mortality in the early years of life. According to De Quatrefages, the duration
                    of life is almost universally the same amongst the best known peoples.
                    Laplanders live to a great age, men of from seventy to ninety years of age being
                    common among them. The American Indians have apparently as long a life, on the
                    average, as the white men living in the same locality. It would appear to be the
                    same in the case of the negro. Prichard quotes from an official document of the
                    State of New Jersey, showing that the census gave one negro centenarian in the
                    1000, but only one white centenarian in 150,000; on the other hand, the negro of
                    the Senegal ages early, and does not live long. In his native place he is
                    exposed to unhealthy influences which tell upon him, although he resists the bad
                    effects of these longer and better than the white man; but when he is
                    transplanted to America he enjoys a longer life.</p>
                <p>The manner of life and nature of the occupation, apart from hereditary and
                    special causes, have a most important influence on the duration of life. Few
                    emperors or kings have attained the age of eighty; and, of more than three
                    hundred popes, only six have exceeded the age of eighty. It <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n888/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0888-0859"/> would seem that brain work is not unfavourable to
                    longevity. It is almost proverbial that statesmen and judges often reach an
                    advanced age. Many men famous in literature and science have lived to an old.
                    age. Thus from fifty to sixty we have Tasso, Virgil, Shakespeare, Molière,
                    Dante, Pope, Ovid, Horace, Racine, Demosthenes; from sixty to seventy, Lavater,
                    Galvani, Boccaccio, Fenelon, Aristotle, Cuvier, Milton, Rousseau, Erasmus,
                    Cervantes; from seventy to eighty, Dryden, Petrarch, Linnaeus, Locke, Handel,
                    Galileo, Swift, Roger Bacon, Charles Darwin; from eighty to ninety, Thomas
                    Carlyle, Young, Plato, Buffon, Goethe, Franklin, Sir W. Herschel, Newton,
                    Voltaire, Halley; and from ninety to one hundred, Sophocles, Leeuwenhoek,
                    Michelangelo, Titian. Physicians are often long lived: Boerhaave, Haller, Gall,
                    Darwin, Van Swieten, Fallopius, Jenner, Cullen, Galen, and Spallanzani died
                    between seventy and eighty years of age, and Harvey, Duhamel, Pinel, Morgagni,
                    Heberden, and Ruysch between eighty and ninety; whilst the father of medicine,
                    Hippocrates, is credited with one hundred and nine years.</p>
                <p>A valuable set of statistics have been collected by Hirt <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Krankheiten der Arbeiter)</hi> regarding the
                    influence of trades on longevity. An abstract of these will be found in Buck’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Hygiene and Public Health,</hi> vol. ii. pp. 71, 72.</p>
                <p>The best indication of longevity in a community is given by the expectation of
                    life from any given age. It is obtained by adding together the number of years
                    which the entire population live from any specified age, and dividing the
                    resulting total “years of life” by the number living at the year of age for
                    which the expectation of life is desired <hi rend="italic">(English Life
                    Table,</hi> p. xxxiii). Thus we may find the duration of the portion of human
                    life which an individual at any age may expect to enjoy. Such calculations are
                    of great value in connexion with assurance, and indeed in all pecuniary
                    transactions in which the value of life contingencies are taken into account.
                    They are the bases of all systems of life assurance. Life assurance companies
                    have now been able to collect sufficient numbers of cases of their own
                    experience on which to find trustworthy calculations showing the expectation of
                    life at different ages. Such tables have really been compiled from selected
                    cases, namely, from those who have assured, and consequently differ somewhat
                    from those compiled on the broader data obtained from the whole population. The
                    following table, derived from both sources of information, is given briefly to
                    indicate the expectation of life, or the longevity, from various ages, reference
                    being made for details to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Insurance.</hi> The
                    table to be read thus: a person at thirty years of age has an average
                    expectation of living 33 ’ 3 years longer, or of attaining the age of 63 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 3 years.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ages.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>England and wales. Farr,
                            1838-54.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Combined Experience of</p><p>17
                            English <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></p><p>Offices, 1843. <hi
                            rend="subscript"> l</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>I Ages.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>England and wales.</p><p>Farr,
                            1838-54.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Combined Experience of 17 English
                            Offices, 1843.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40 ∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13 9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13∙77</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>47 4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48'36</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>70</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8∙54</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>39 ∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>41∙49</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>80</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5∙1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4∙78</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>33 3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>34 43</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙11</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26 ∙7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27’28</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>I 95</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2∙2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙28</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20 T</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                            18</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>i</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>What are the physiological conditions in the human being that determine
                    longevity? In the first place, there is the influence of heredity. Certain
                    peculiarities of tissue are transmitted from parent to offspring that determine
                    whether or not the tissue will remain for a lengthened period of time in a
                    normal condition, or whether it will quickly yield to external influences and
                    take on an abnormal action. As the life of the body is really the sum of the
                    lives of its constituent parts, or in other words, of the cellular elements
                    composing it, it is evident that anything affecting the healthy action of these
                    elements will affect the life of the body as a whole. In some individuals the
                    tissues have what may be termed a hereditary taint, by which is meant a want of
                    stability, so that they pass readily from a normal into an abnormal condition;
                    and this is unfavourable to longevity.</p>
                <p>In the next place, even healthy tissues capable of resisting ordinary influences
                    may be unable to resist long-continued unfavourable conditions. In course of
                    time slow changes begin in the tissue; these in turn affect the organ in which
                    the tissue exists, and the organ, by improperly performing its functions,
                    injures the organism. Thus it is that habitually breathing an impure atmosphere,
                    eating improper food, saturating the body with drugs or with alcohol,
                    over-exerting the nervous system by excitement or prolonged brain-work or worry,
                    and sexual excesses debilitate the body by working slow but sure changes in the
                    tissues which will inevitably tell upon the longevity of the individual.</p>
                <p>But even in the most favourable conditions there seems to be a limitation to the
                    healthy action of tissues, and old age comes on. Whether this is or is not the
                    result of long hereditary transmission it is not of much practical importance to
                    ask, as it is a state of things all flesh is heir to. But, if it be hereditary,
                    as is highly probable, there is the satisfaction of knowing that hereditary
                    states can be slowly influenced by individuals living in the best possible
                    conditions and transmitting the influences of good moral and physical hygiene.
                    If bad hereditary qualities are transmitted, good qualities have even a better
                    chance of being perpetuated, as they favour the individual in the struggle for
                    existence. Thus a race which has a low degree of longevity may acquire, by
                    persistent attempts to live in the best conditions, a long average duration of
                    life. This is also true, though to a less extent, of an individual life.</p>
                <p>Each tissue has a life of its own; it is developed, reaches maturity, declines,
                    and dies. It may be replaced by successive generations of similar tissues, but
                    the power of reproduction of tissue becomes weakened, and by slow degrees the
                    tissue may disappear, or it may become so altered as to be quite unlike what it
                    was at first. By these tissue-changes functional changes of great importance to
                    the body are brought about. Thus, as age comes on, the blood becomes poorer;
                    respiration is less active; the vital capacity of the chest, that is the
                    working-quantity of air, is diminished; the temperature of the body is slightly
                    increased, so that the aged are more sensitive to cold; the digestive organs are
                    less vigorous; the walls of <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> the arteries become
                    hardened by earthy matter, and lose their elasticity; the veins become dilated,
                    and the circulation is not efficiently performed; the teeth decay and disappear;
                    the cartilages become calcified and hard; the skin is shrivelled and dry, and
                    cutaneous respiration and excretion are less perfect; the hair whitens or falls
                    off; the stature and the weight diminish. By and by muscular movements are less
                    energetic and less precise; the hands tremble and the head shakes; and there is
                    a tottering gait. The cartilages of the larynx ossify, the vocal cords lose
                    their elasticity, and the voice becomes a shrill treble. Then the involuntary
                    muscular tissues are affected so that the bladder is less powerful and
                    defaecation is feeble. The transparent media of the eye become dimmed, the near
                    point of vision is pushed back so that the old man becomes presbyopic, or
                    far-sighted, and the power of accommodation, or focussing of the eye, is
                    entirely lost; the delicate mechanism of the drum and bones of the ear is
                    impaired, so that deafness results; and even touch becomes less delicate. Slowly
                    the intellectual faculties become weakened, the emotions are blunted, and the
                    memory becomes by degrees less <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n889/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0889-0860"/> trustworthy, and at last vanishes. Much of the
                    time is now spent in sleep, and unless some intercurrent disease snaps the
                    thread of life there is a slow ebbing of existence into natural death.
                    Essentially these phenomena are due to delicate changes in the tissues, visible
                    only with the aid of the microscope. These changes are those of wasting or
                    atrophy, meaning a failure of nutrition, or fatty changes, or those caused by
                    infiltration into the tissue of earthy matter, which soon, destroys its healthy
                    functions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> Elliotson, <hi rend="italic">Human
                    Physiology,</hi> Hufeland, <hi rend="italic">Art of Prolonging Life·,</hi> P.
                    Flourens, <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">la Longévité Humaine, et de
                    la Quantité de Vie sur la Globe</hi>; Quetelet, <hi rend="italic">Physique
                    Sociale,</hi> vol. i. p. 308; De Quatrefages, <hi rend="italic">The Human
                    Species·,</hi><hi rend="italic">An</hi><hi rend="italic">Account of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Persons</hi><hi rend="italic">remarkable for their</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Health</hi><hi rend="italic">and Longevity, by</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">Physician,</hi> London, 1829; Sir G.
                    Cornewall Lewis’s <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>; Thoms, <hi rend="italic">On
                    Longevity.</hi> (J. G. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
