<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0699-0676-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LINOLEUM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 676</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:999278">Linoleum</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:927635">Floors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:927616">Flooring</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:878973">Cork</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:802066">Air</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d58r">Floors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28g7v">Cloth</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j696">Steam</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LINOLEUM</label> is a kind of floor-cloth, invented and
                    introduced by Mr F. Walton, who in 1860 obtained a patent for its manufacture.
                    It consists of a preparation of linseed oil and ground cork intimately mixed and
                    spread in a uniform layer over a sheet of rough jute canvas. Under the name of
                    kamptulicon, a material similar in appearance and properties, but in which
                    prepared indiarubber took the place of oxidized linseed oil, was in use to a
                    limited extent previous to the introduction of linoleum; the latter material,
                    however, was found to possess several advantages; among others it had the merit
                    of comparative cheapness as against kamptulicon, which it entirely supplanted.
                    Linoleum also became a formidable competitor with the old form of oil
                    floor-cloth, and on the expiry of Mr Walton’s patent the manufacture of the new
                    material was very generally taken up in Kirkcaldy, the principal seat of the
                    floor-cloth trade. In the hands of Messrs Michael Nairn &amp; Co., who were the
                    first to introduce the floor-cloth industry into Scotland, the machinery used
                    for making linoleum has been improved in important respects, and the ingenuity
                    and resource of Mr Walton, the original patentee, have discovered several new
                    adaptations and modifications of his original invention.</p>
                <p>The making of linoleum involves three distinct preliminary operations—(1) the
                    oxidation of the linseed oil, (2) the grinding of the cork, and (3) the weaving
                    of the jute canvas backing. Of these operations the oxidation of the oil is the
                    most peculiar and distinctive. The linseed oil is first boiled with litharge in
                    the way practised for preparing ordinary boiled oil (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Linseed),</hi> and it is next oxidized by exposure, in exceedingly thin films,
                    to the influence of air. To secure the exposure of sufficient surfaces of oil to
                    the atmosphere, a large lofty apartment is hung with sheets or continuous webs
                    of calico cloth, which are allowed to depend from near the roof into troughs or
                    tanks on the floor. These webs of calico are kept sufficiently far apart to
                    allow free circulation of air between them. They are daily drenched with boiled
                    oil by allowing it to trickle down from the top over their entire surface, the
                    distribution being effected by a special arrangement of movable tanks and tubs.
                    It will be seen that an enormous surface of oil can thus be exposed within a
                    comparatively limited space. The influence of oxygen on the oil films is
                    facilitated by the blowing of heated air into the chamber so as to keep up a
                    continual circulation; and the activity of the process is unpleasantly
                    manifested by the extremely acrid odour which is evolved by the oil. Day by day
                    the thickness of the coating of oxidized oil increases, and when a deposit of
                    about half an inch has been accumulated, the drenching is stopped. The product,
                    now ready for being withdrawn, forms firm translucent sheets of a caoutchouclike
                    substance having a straw yellow colour, possessed of a certain amount of
                    elasticity, and communicating no oily stain to paper. These sheets are now tom
                    into small pieces and reduced to a uniform plastic mass by means of powerful
                    crushing rollers, after which the material is placed in a close boiler with the
                    addition of certain proportions of kawrie gum, rosin, and ochre, umber, or other
                    pigment, according to the ground-colour desired. The boiler is heated by steam,
                    and the entire mass, being thoroughly incorporated by means of stirrers, is run
                    into a shallow trough, from which, after cooling and solidifying, it is taken in
                    large slabs. These are piled up awaiting future use, and when required for
                    manufacturing purposes they are cut into blocks about the size of an ordinary
                    brick.</p>
                <p>Ground cork, which is the second essential constituent of linoleum, may be made
                    from cork cuttings and scraps; but, the supply of such material being unequal to
                    the demand, bale cork, of secondary quality as imported, is very largely used.
                    It is first broken to pieces about the size of a nut; the fragments are fed into
                    the hopper of a mill; and the cork passes thence between a pair of ordinary
                    millstones in which it is reduced to a meal-like condition, in exactly the same
                    way as wheat is ground to flour. The product is sifted, and the insufficiently
                    ground portions are returned to be passed again through the mill. In the
                    grinding of the cork great care is necessary to prevent iron, stone, or other
                    hard foreign material from getting into the mill, as such substances, causing
                    sparks between the stones, readily give rise to explosions in air so laden with
                    fine dust as that of the mill necessarily is.</p>
                <p>In the making of the jute backing the only notable feature is the great width of
                    the loom, in which webs 12 feet broad are woven by Messrs Nairn. The maximum
                    width of that produced by other makers, however, has hitherto been 6 feet.</p>
                <p>The actual preparation of linoleum floor-cloth in the factory of Messrs Nairn is
                    conducted in a continuous series of operations by machinery which has been
                    patented by that firm. The bricks of oxidised oil and the requisite proportion
                    of cork are thrown into a hopper, where they are thoroughly mixed in a kind of
                    pug mill, whence the mixture is shot forward in a tube, at the open end of which
                    it is sliced off in thin crumbling masses by a revolving knife. Spread out in
                    thin sheets, it passes from this between a series of steam-heated rollers, from
                    the last of which it is scratched off by a circular drum covered with sharp
                    steel points, and falls in a fine shower into a feeding box the whole width of
                    the linoleum to be made. From this feeding box the mixture is uniformly
                    delivered on the surface of the canvas, which here meets it, and passing
                    immediately between powerful smooth rollers, the semiplastic mixture is firmly
                    squeezed on the surface of, and rendered adherent to, the rough open canvas
                    which forms its back. The distance between the upper and lower compressing
                    roller determines the thickness of the linoleum, three standard thicknesses
                    being recognized, viz., <hi rend="subscript"> b</hi> ¾-, and ⅛ parts of an inch.
                    Linoleum of the thickness of ⅛ of an inch is also made for public libraries and
                    readingrooms on account of its perfect noiselessness. It only remains to coat or
                    waterproof the raw canvas back with oil paint, and the floor-cloth is finished
                    as plain linoleum. The printing of patterns in various colours on its surface is
                    done as described under <hi rend="smallcaps">Floor-Cloth,</hi> vol. ix. p. 329.
                    Corticine is a form of linoleum, in which the oil is oxidized by chemical
                    agents.</p>
                <p>Recently a method of ornamenting linoleum with patterns in the form of tiles or
                    tessarae, the colour of each tile going right through to the canvas or
                    sufficiently deep for constant wear, has been devised and patented by Mr C. F.
                    Leake. The patentee prefers to use canvas first covered with a thin linoleum
                    coating. This he brings on a table on which are a series of moulds corresponding
                    with the coloured tile pattern required. Into each mould is put the required
                    quantity of properly-coloured granulated linoleum material, which is compressed
                    into solid tiles by the descent of plungers. The part covered by the pattern is
                    carried forward and powerfully squeezed between hydraulic rams, the tiles being
                    thus made smooth, homogeneous, and firmly adherent, while in the meantime the
                    moulds are being filled and a new set of tiles prepared in the first stage of
                    the operation. Mr Walton, the original patentee of linoleum, has adapted a
                    preparation of oxidized oil and cork or other thickening mateπal embossed with
                    patterns for wall decorations under the name of “Lincrusta Walton.” (J. PA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
