<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0893-0864-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LONGINUS (9th edition, volume 14, page 864)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fj36">Platonists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dj16">Stoics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066881">Platonists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133750">Stoics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883769">Critics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883735">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999835">Lists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n893/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LONGINUS</label>, a philosophical critic of great eminence,
                    and one of the brightest spirits of antiquity, uniting Greek subtlety with Roman
                    fervour, flourished in the 3d century, and is known to have perished under
                    sentence of the emperor Aurelian in 273 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> He forms
                    one of the last brilliant cluster of pagan literati; and Porphyry, round whom it
                    centred, was the pupil of Longinus. As Porphyry is known to have been born in
                    233, it is probable that his preceptor, who could not have been less than twenty
                    years his senior, may have been born about 210 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>
                    The main authority for the facts of his life is a notice in Suidas, where we
                    find it stated in a preface to a list of his writings that “Longinus Cassius,
                    philosopher, preceptor of Porphyry the philosopher, a learned scholar and
                    critic, lived in the time of the emperor Aurelian, and was cut off by him as
                    having conspired with Zeuobia, the wife of Odenathus.” From the same authority
                    we learn that Phronto, the rhetorician of Emesa in Syria, was his uncle, and
                    that Phrontonis, sister of Phronto, was mother to Longinus, who thus became heir
                    to his uncle Phronto. As to his birthplace there is no tradition, but it is
                    probable that he was a native of Syria, possibly of Emesa, to which his uncle
                    belonged. He tells us, as we learn from fragments of his works, that he enjoyed
                    great advantages in travel and education, that his parents, being rich, took him
                    to travel and he saw much of the world, and that he studied at Athens under
                    Phronto, at Alexandria under Ammonius Saccas and the pagan Origenes, and at Rome
                    under Plotinus and Amelius. The Neo-Platonic philosophy was then in the
                    ascendant, but Longinus did not embrace the new speculations which Plotinus was
                    then developing, and continued a Platonist of the old type. Hence the sting of a
                    sarcasm attributed to Plotinus—“Longinus may be a philologer, but he is no
                    philosopher.” Longinus does not appear to have reciprocated the sarcastic
                    feeling, for we have still extant a fragment of a letter in which he asks
                    Porphyry to come to Phoenicia and to bring with him the treatises of Plotinus,
                    for, he observes, though he does not feel much attraction for the subjects, he
                    yet likes the man. The reputation which Longinus acquired by his learning was
                    immense; it was of him that Eunapius first used the expression that has since
                    become proverbial “a living library ”—in modern phrase, a walking
                    encyclopaedia.</p>
                <p>The most conspicuous event of his life was also the most tragic in its
                    consequences. He became secretary to Zenobia, the widowed queen of Palmyra, who
                    acquired from him a knowledge of Greek, and made him her chief counsellor in
                    state affairs. In this capacity he favoured the policy by which she aimed at
                    independence of the Roman empire, encouraged, doubtless, to do so by the recent
                    fate of Valerian, and by the feebleness of the tenure by which Rome held the
                    Syrian provinces. Aurelian, however, crushed the pretension, and, while Zenobia
                    lost her power and wasled captive to Rome, Longinus paid the forfeit of his
                    life. According to Zosimus, Zenobia sought to exculpate herself with Aurelian by
                    laying the whole blame on her adviser. He died bravely, not seeking to escape
                    his fate by suicide as a Stoic might have done, but following the example of
                    Socrates and the precept of Plato, to whose philosophy he adhered.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is probable that he
                            owed part of his political fervour to the influence or inheritance of
                            the name “Cassius,” from whatever source this surname was derived. The
                            associations of this name were distinctly anti-imperial and even
                            regicidal, as seen in Caius Cassius and in Cassius
                    Chaerea.</p></note></p>
                <p>The remains of Longinus that have come down to us, unfortunately scanty, are
                    partly fragments of letters and extracts from criticisms on points of diction;
                    and they bear out the impression we derive from the historical notices of the
                    man. He is vivid and yet minute, lively and penetrating, and his observations
                    show taste, learning, and judgment. Among the most notable of the fragments we
                    have a defence of the Platonic doctrine of the soul as a distinct essence from
                    the body, which defines clearly his philosophical position.</p>
                <p>It only remains to advert in a few words to the remarkable production called the
                        <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Sublime,</hi> which has usually passed
                    current as a work of Longinus. This remarkable work, which is among the most
                    notable productions of ancient criticism, second only in importance to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Poetics</hi> of Aristotle, and superior to that work in
                    luminous beauty and sense of form, cannot be with certainty ascribed to
                    Longinus, although the internal evidence favours the usual ascription. Of the
                    two most startling difficulties the first is the absence of any mention of a
                    treatise πepl <hi rend="italic">iiψoυs</hi> in the list by Suidas. The
                    enumeration is, however, incomplete, and the phrase “many other works,” with
                    which it closes, may be held to cover much. A more formidable difficulty is the
                    circumstance that in the most important <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n894/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0894-0865"/> manuscript (that in the Paris Library, No.
                    2036, of the 10th century) the heading is <hi rend="italic">Διονυσίου</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">t) ∆oyyivoυ,</hi> giving thus an alternative author
                    “Dionysius,” and in the other important MS., the Laurentian at Florence, the
                    title is <hi rend="italic">'∆vωviμoυ,</hi> implying that the author was unknown.
                    According to Vaucher <hi rend="italic">(Études,</hi> p. 134) this title is not
                    the original one, and there are traces of an earlier title <hi rend="italic"
                        >∆oyyivoυ,</hi> which had formed the superscription. Full information as to
                    the critical question will be found in the editions of A. E. Egger <hi
                        rend="italic">(Longini</hi><hi rend="italic">quae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >supersunt,</hi> Paris, 1837), Vaucher’s <hi rend="italic">Études</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Critiques</hi><hi rend="italic">sur le Traité du Sublime et
                        sur les écrits de Longin,</hi> Geneva, 1854, and Otto Jahn’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Διονυσίου</hi><hi rend="italic">¾ ∆oyyivoυ τrepl υψoυs</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Sublimitate Libellus,</hi> Bonn,
                    1867. Vaucher ascribes the treatise to Plutarch, but the evidence negatives that
                    supposition, and, although there are difficulties in ascribing the work
                    absolutely to Longinus, as Boileau and Gibbon and the critics of last century
                    traditionally assumed, there is no other name than that of Longinus that
                    presents so many concurring circumstances, to justify provisionally the current
                    ascription. The fragments that remain of the undoubted works of Longinus are
                    largely characterized by the same lively force and epigrammatic terseness which
                    distinguish the treatise, “On the Sublime.” The translations of this treatise
                    into all the European tongues have been almost innumerable, including the famous
                    one by Boileau, which rendered the work the favourite text-book of the
                    bellelettristic critics in the last century. The most important English
                    translations are by William Smith, 1739, frequently reproduced; Hathaway, 1834;
                    Spurdens, 1836. (W. D. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
