<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0746-0723-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIVIUS ANDRONICUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 723</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:861276">Ciceronianism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1120522">Slaves</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m29x">Dorians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n746/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIVIUS ANDRONICUS</label> occupies the position of the oldest
                    among the recognized poets of Rome. He determined the course which Roman
                    literature followed for more than a century after his time. The imitation of
                    Greek comedy, tragedy, and epic poetry, which produced great results in the
                    hands of Naevius, Plautus, Ennius, and their successors, received its first
                    impulse from him. To judge, however, by the very insignificant remains of his
                    writings, and by the testimonies of Cicero and Horace to his merits, he can have
                    had no pretension either to original genius or to artistic accomplishment. His
                    real claim to distinction was that he was the first great schoolmaster of the
                    Roman people, and the first acknowledged medium through which the genius of
                    Greece acted on the Roman mind, and found for itself a rude expression in the
                    Latin language. His name, in which the Greek <hi rend="italic">Andronicus</hi>
                    is combined with the gentile name of one of the great Roman houses, while
                    indicative of his own position as a manumitted slave, is also significant of the
                    influences by which Roman literature was fostered,—viz., the culture of men who
                    were either Greeks or “semi-Graeci” by birth and education, and the protection
                    and favour afforded to them by the more enlightened members of the Roman
                    aristocracy. He is supposed to have been a native of Tarentum, and to have been
                    brought while still a boy, after the capture of that town in 272 B.C., as a
                    slave to Rome. He lived in the household of a member of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >gens</hi><hi rend="italic">Livia,</hi> probably of that branch of it to which
                    M. Livius Salinator, the colleague of C. Claudius Nero in the year of the battle
                    of the Metaurus, belonged. We learn from Suetonius that, like Ennius after him,
                    he obtained his living by teaching Greek and Latin; and it was probably as a
                    schoolbook, rather than as a work of literary pretension, that his translation
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> into Latin Saturnian verse was executed.
                    This work was still used in schools’ when Horace was taught at Rome by the
                    famous grammarian and disciplinarian Orbilius. From the few fragments of the
                    translation that have been preserved it may be inferred that it was owing to the
                    conservatism of educational methods, rather than to its fitness to impart to
                    boys in the Ciceronian age instruction either in Greek literature or in the
                    Latin language, that it enjoyed this distinction. But at the time when it
                    appeared it must have satisfied a real want. In the wars with Pyrrhus and
                    Tarentum the Romans had for the first time come into close contact with the
                    Greeks; and during the First Punic War (from 261 to 241 B.C.), in which Sicily
                    was the chief battleground of the combatants, this contact was much closer. The
                    knowledge of Greek became essential to men in a high position, as a means of
                    intercourse with Greeks; and at the same time the new ideas and new interests of
                    Greek literature began to exercise something of that stimulating and refining
                    power over the minds of the leading men which it exercised in a later generation
                    over Scipio Africanus, T. Quintius Flamininus, M. Fulvius Nobilior, and others
                    like them. But the presence of the Roman armies in southern Italy and Sicily
                    must have accustomed many who had no means of obtaining a literary education to
                    the representations of the Greek tragic and comic poets. Although the great
                    creative age of the Athenian drama was passed, the passion for the
                    representation of the old plays still continued, and was not confined to Athens.
                    The number of theatres of which the remains are still seen in Sicily—as at
                    Segesta, Syracuse, Catania, Taormina—indicate that, in the island in which
                    Epicharmus had produced his old Dorian comedies, the representation of tragedy
                    and comedy continued to be a most important element in the life of the people.
                    But the Romans and Italians had an indigenous drama of their own, known by the
                    name of <hi rend="italic">Satura,</hi> which prepared them for the reception of
                    the more regular Greek drama. The distinction between this <hi rend="italic"
                    >Satura</hi> and the plays of Euripides or Menander was that it had no regular
                    plot. This the Latin drama first received from Livius Andronicus; but it did so
                    at the cost of its originality. In the year 240, the year after the end of the
                    First Punic War, he produced at Rome a translation of a Greek play (it is
                    uncertain whether a comedy or tragedy), and this representation marks the
                    beginning of Roman literature. In this translation he discarded the native
                    Saturnian metre, and adopted the iambic, trochaic, and cretic metres, to which
                    Latin more easily adapted itself than either to the hexameter or to the lyrical
                    measures of a later time. He continued to produce plays for more than thirty
                    years after this time. The titles of some of his tragedies are <hi rend="italic"
                    >Achilles,</hi><hi rend="italic">Aegisthus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Hguus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Trojanus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Hermione,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Tereus,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> all suggestive of subjects which were
                    treated by the later tragic poets of Rome. The titles of some of his comedies
                    are <hi rend="italic">Gladiolus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Ludius,</hi> &lt;tc. In
                    the year 207, when, if he was a captive after the taking of Tarentum, he must
                    have been of a great age, he was appointed to compose the hymn of thanksgiving
                    for the victory of the Metaurus. Another tribute of national recognition paid
                    him was that, as a compliment to him, the “college” or “guild” of poets obtained
                    a place of meeting in the temple of Minerva on the Aventine.</p>
                <p>A good account of his remains is to be found in Wordsworth’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fragments and Specimens of Early Latin.</hi> The fragments of his dramas are to
                    be found in Ribbeck’s <hi rend="italic">Tragicorum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Latinorτιm Reliquiae,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Comicorum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Latinorum Reliquiae.</hi> (W. Y. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
