<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0896-0867-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LONGUEVILLE, Anne Geneviève, Duchesse de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 867</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:981348">Jansenists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010769">Marshals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1012623">Maxims</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1041386">Nuns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:964412">Husbands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n051">Maxims</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kq6z">Nuns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n896/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LONGUEVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anne Geneviève, Duchesse
                    de</hi></label> (1619-1679), who played the greatest part in the troubles of the
                    Fronde, and whose name has come down to posterity as the brilliant intriguer in
                    polities in her early and the pious protectress of the nuns of Port Royal in her
                    later years, was the only daughter of Henri de Bourbon, Prince de Condé, and his
                    wife Charlotte Marguerite de Montmorency, and the only sister of Louis, the
                    great Condé. She was born on August 28, 1619, in the prison of Vincennes, into
                    which her father had been thrown for opposition to Marshal D’Ancre, the
                    favourite of Marie de’ Medici, who was then regent in the minority of Louis
                    XIII. She was educated in the convent of the Carmelites in the Rue St Jacques at
                    Paris, which had been recently established under the influence of St Teresa’s
                    reforms by nuns of the strictest piety, whose teaching she never entirely
                    forgot. Her early years were clouded by the execution of the young and brilliant
                    Due de Montmorency, her mother’s only brother, for intriguing against the great
                    Richelieu in 1631, and that of her mother’s cousin the Comte de Montmorency
                    Boutteville for duelling in 1635; but, in spite of their sorrow, her parents
                    made their peace with Richelieu, and when she was introduced into society in
                    1635 she found plenty of court gaiety to enjoy. She soon became one of the
                    bright particular stars of the Hôtel Rambouillet, where all that was learned,
                    witty, and gay in France used to assemble, and which had not yet degenerated
                    into the meeting place of those <hi rend="italic">précieuses</hi> whom Molière
                    was to laugh out of existence. It was first proposed to marry her to the young
                    Prince de Joinville, and thus unite the Guises and Condés, but he died in 1639,
                    and her parents could only find for her husband the Duc de Longueville, a prince
                    of the blood indeed, and governor of Normandy, but a widower, and twice her age.
                    The marriage could not be a happy one, but the young duchess long remained
                    faithful to him, and bore him four children. After Richelieu’s death her father
                    became chief of the council of regency during the minority of Louis XIV., her
                    brother Louis won the great victory of Rocroy in 1643 (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Condé),</hi> and the duchess became of political importance. In 1647 she
                    accompanied her husband to Münster, where he was sent by Mazarin as chief envoy,
                    and where she charmed the German diplomatists who were making the treaty of
                    Westphalia, and was addressed as the “goddess of peace and concord.” On her
                    return she fell in love with the Due de la Rochefoucauld, the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Maxims,</hi> who made use of her love to obtain influence over her
                    brother, and thus win titles and honours for himself. She was the guiding spirit
                    of the first Fronde, when she brought over Armand, Prince de Conti, her second
                    brother, and her husband to the malcontents, but she failed to attract Condé
                    himself, whose loyalty to the court overthrew the first Fronde. However, La
                    Rochefoucauld won the titles he desired. The second F ronde was again her work,
                    owing to her lover’s disgust at losing his new honours, and in it she played the
                    most prominent part in attracting to the rebels first Condé and later Turenne
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Condé).</hi> It is not necessary to give the whole
                    history of the wars of the Fronde, which is detailed elsewhere, but it must be
                    noticed that the duchess herself only-mingled in politics to please her lover,
                    and gain his ends. In the last year of the war she was accompanied into Guienne
                    by the young and handsome Due de Nemours, her intimacy with whom gave La
                    Rochefoucauld an excuse for abandoning her, and who himself immediately returned
                    to his old mistress the Duchesse de Chevreuse. Thus abandoned, and in disgrace
                    at court, the duchess betook herself to religion. She accompanied her husband to
                    his government at Rouen, and devoted herself to good works. She took for her
                    director Μ. Singlin, so famous in the history of Port Royal, and from that time
                    began her new religious life. Till 1663 she chiefly lived in Normandy, when her
                    husband died, and she came to Paris. There she became more and more Jansenist in
                    opinion, and her piety and the remembrance of her influence during the
                    disastrous days of the Fronde, and above all the tender love her brother, the
                    great Condé, bore her, made her a conspicuous figure. The king pardoned her, and
                    in every way showed the respect he had for her. She became the great protectress
                    of the Jansenists; it was in her house that Arnauld, Nicole, and De Lane were
                    protected; and to her influence must be in great part attributed the release of
                    De Sacy from the Bastille, the introduction of Pomponne into the ministry and of
                    Arnauld to the king. Her famous letters to the pope are part of the history of
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Port Royal</hi> (&lt;7∙t'.), and as long as she lived the
                    nuns of Port Royal des Champs were left in safety. Through the latter years of
                    her life she had, despite the honour in which she was held, much to bear. Her
                    elder son resigned his title and estates, and became a Jesuit under the name of
                    the Abbé d’Orleans, while the younger, after leading a very debauched life, was
                    killed, bravely leading the attack in the passage of the Rhine in 1673. As her
                    health failed she devoted herself more and more to religion, and hardly ever
                    left the convent of the Carmelites in which she had been educated. On her death
                    in 1679 she was buried with great splendour by her brother Condé, and her heart,
                    as she had directed, was sent to the nuns of that Port Royal des Champs which
                    she had so greatly protected and defended. Her life is noteworthy, both from the
                    harm she did in the turbulent days of the Fronde, though she acted, hardly
                    knowing what she did, from love rather than from selfish ambition, and also from
                    the greatness of her penitence, when her protection of Port Royal more than
                    redeemed her fame, and gave her a title to the grateful remembrance of all who
                    reverence true piety and learning more than the artificial glitter of the reign
                    of the “grand monarque.”</p>
                <p>The chief authority for Madame de Longueville’s life is a little book in two
                    volumes by Villefore the Jansenist, published in 1738.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n897/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0897-0868"/>
                <p>Cousin has devoted four volumes to her, which, though immensely diffuse, give a
                    vivid picture of her time. Her connexion with Port Royal should be studied in
                    Arnauld’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> and in the different histories of that
                    institution.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
