<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0247-0236-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LAMBERT, John (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    236)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1079666">Protectorates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006241">Majorities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw1h">Protectorates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n247/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LAMBERT, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1619-1694),
                    was born in 1619 at Calton Hall in the parish of Kirkby Malharn, in the West
                    Riding of Yorkshire. His family was of ancient lineage, and long settled in the
                    county. He studied at the Inns of Court, but without making the law his
                    profession. In 1640 he married Frances, daughter of Sir William Lister. He was
                    present at the great meeting of the Yorkshire gentry on Heyworth Moor (3d Juue
                    1642), and in September was appointed a captain of horse under
                    Lieutenant-Colonel Fairfax. He did good service at the siege of Hull (11th
                    October 1642), at Bradford (5th March 1644), and at the important engagement at
                    Selby (10th April 1644). At Marston Moor (2d July 1644) he commanded part of Sir
                    Thomas Fairfax’s cavalry on the right wing. He was sent into York to arrange
                    terms for the surrender of the city, which took place July 16,1644. When the
                    “New Model” army was formed in the beginning of 1645, Colonel Lambert was
                    appointed commissarygeneral of the army in the north. He beat the royalists at
                    Keighley and Ferrybridge, and took several strong places. He followed Fairfax’s
                    campaign in the west of England in 1646, and was a commissioner with Cromwell
                    and others for the surrender of Oxford in the same year.</p>
                <p>When the quarrel between the army and the parliament began, Lambert threw himself
                    warmly into the army’s cause. He is said by Clarendon to have assisted Ireton in
                    drawing up the several addresses and remonstrances issued by the army, both men
                    having had some experience in the law, and being “of a subtle and working
                    brain.” In August 1647 Lambert was sent as major-general by Fairfax to take
                    charge of the forces in the northern counties. His wise and just managing of
                    affairs in those parts is commended by Whitelocke. He displayed personal courage
                    in suppressing a mutiny among his troops, kept strict discipline, and showed
                    much diligence in hunting down the mosstroopers who infested the moorland
                    country.</p>
                <p>When the Scotch army under the marquis of Hamilton invaded England in the summer
                    of 1648, Lambert was obliged to retreat till Cromwell came up from Wales, and
                    joining him destroyed the Scotch army in three days’ fighting from Preston to
                    Warrington. Lambert pressed Hamilton with the cavalry, and took him prisoner at
                    Uttoxeter, a few days after the battle. He then marched back into Scotland,
                    where he was left in charge of the troops. In December 1648 he sat down before
                    Pontefract Castle, which held out till March 1649. Lambert was thus absent from
                    London at the time of the violence put upon the parliament by Colonel Pride, and
                    the other measures which led to the king’s death.</p>
                <p>Cromwell, when appointed to the command of the war in Scotland (26th July 1650),
                    took Lambert with him as major-general. He was wounded at Musselburgh, but was
                    with Cromwell at Dunbar on the 2d of September, when the soldiers begged that
                    Lambert might lead them the next day, and Cromwell willingly gave his consent.
                    He defeated the “Protesters” or “Western Whigs” at Hamilton, on the 1st of
                    December 1650. In the following July he was sent over into Fife to get a
                    position in the rear and flank of the Scotch army near Falkirk, and force them
                    to decisive action by cutting off their supplies from Perth. A battle fought at
                    Inverkeithing, with heavy loss to the Scots, in which Lambert behaved with great
                    gallantry, gave him the position he required, and he improved it by taking
                    Inchgarvie and Burntisland. Charles now (as Lambert had foreseen) made for
                    England. Lambert with the cavalry was ordered to harass his march down the
                    western shires, while Cromwell followed through Yorkshire and the Midlands. In
                    the action at Warrington Bridge Lambert again distinguished himself by his
                    personal courage, and at Worcester also (3d September 1651), where he commanded
                    the forces on the eastern bank of the Severn, and had his horse shot under him.
                    Parliament now conferred on him a grant of lands in Scotland worth £1000 per
                    annum.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0248-0237"/>
                <p>In November 1651 he was made a commissioner to settle the affairs of Scotland,
                    and on the death of Ireton he was appointed lord deputy of Ireland in February
                    1652. He accepted the office with pleasure; but his magnificent preparations
                    offended the Commons, who limited his office to the term of six months. Lambert
                    hereupon resigned the deputyship without entering on its duties.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding this affront Lambert took part with Cromwell in the expulsion of
                    the Rump (20th April 1653) and its council of state. He was joined to the
                    lord-general and two others as additional members of the little parliament of
                    nominees, making up the number to one hundred and forty-four. He presented the
                    act of resignation of that assembly, and was principally concerned in drawing up
                    the address requesting Cromwell to assume the protectorate, and the Instrument
                    of Government, which was the constitution of the Protectorat rule. At the
                    installation of Cromwell he bore a prominent part. In the parliament of 1654,
                    and again in 1656, Lambert (or Lord Lambert as he is now generally called) sat
                    as member for the West Riding of Yorkshire. When the proposal to declare Oliver
                    king was started in parliament (February 1657) he at once declared strongly
                    against it. A hundred officers headed by Fleetwood and Lambert waited on the
                    Protector, and begged him to put a stop to the proceedings. Lambert was not
                    convinced by Cromwell’s arguments, and Cromwell and he henceforward never spoke
                    to each other as friends. On his refusal to take the official oath of allegiance
                    to the Protector, Cromwell deprived him of his commissions, giving him, however,
                    a pension of £2000 a year. He retired to his house and garden at Wimbledon, and
                    appeared no more in public during Oliver Cromwell’s lifetime.</p>
                <p>On the accession of Richard he seems to have expected the first place in the
                    army, but was not unwilling to be second to Fleetwood. The Protector was between
                    two parties—the court party, who wished to hold to the “Petition and Advice,”
                    and the army party or Wallingford House party, who, whilst supporting Richard as
                    Protector, wished to put the control of the army into stronger hands. Richard
                    saw that to deliver up the power of the sword was to abdicate, and refused to
                    make Fleetwood general. Lambert was elected for Pontefract in Richard’s
                    parliament, and took part with the republican malcontents who soon combined with
                    Wallingford House. Councils of officers were held, which Lambert, though holding
                    no commission, was invited to attend. They determined to stand by the “good old
                    cause” and to demand the dissolution of the parliament as being too full of
                    monarchical and Presbyterian notions —in fact, to put the civil power aside and
                    set up a military government in its stead. The Protector dissolved parliament
                    (22d April 1659). The officers, unable to rule without a parliament, restored
                    the Rump as representing the Commonwealth (7th May 1659). Richard’s Protectorate
                    had practically ended with his parliament, and he now laid down the show of
                    royalty. Sir George Booth and Sir Thomas Middleton headed a royalist rising in
                    Cheshire, which Lambert put down after a sharp encounter near Chester. He
                    promoted a petition from his army that Fleetwood might be made lord-general and
                    himself majorgeneral. The republican party in the house took offence. The
                    Commons (12th October 1659) cashiered Lambert, Desborough, and other officers,
                    and retained Fleetwood’s commission as chief of a military council of seven,
                    republicans of the old sort. Lenthall, the speaker, was to give his orders to
                    the army. On the next day (13th October) Lambert caused the doors of the House
                    to be shut and the members kept out. On the 26th a “committee of safety” was
                    appointed, of which Lambert was a member. He was also appointed major-general of
                    all the forces in England and Scotland, Fleetwood being general. Lambert was now
                    sent with a large force to meet Monk, who was in command of the English forces
                    in Scotland, and either negotiate with him or force him to terms. Monk, however,
                    declared for the liberty and authority of parliament, and set his army in motion
                    southward. The committee of safety was obeyed no more than the Rump had been.
                    The soldiers themselves cried out for the restoration of parliament, and on the
                    26th &lt;.f December the Rump was recalled to restore some appearance of lawful
                    authority.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile the bulk of Lambert’s army was dissolved by the mere appearance of Lord
                    Fairfax in arms on Marston Moor, and he was kept in suspense by Monk’s deceits
                    and delays, till his whole army fell from him, and he came back to town almost
                    alone. Monk marched unopposed to London, and declared for a “free parliament.”
                    The “excluded” Presbyterian members were recalled. Lambert was sent to the Tower
                    (3d March 1660), from which he escaped a month later (9th April 1660). He tried
                    to rekindle the civil war in favour of the Commonwealth, but was speedily
                    recaptured, and sent back to the Tower (2 4th April). On the Restoration he,
                    along with Vane, was exempted from danger of life by an address of both Houses
                    to the king. The next parliament (1662) brought a charge of high treason against
                    them. Vane was beheaded, but Lambert was spared, and remained in custody in the
                    island of Guernsey for the remainder of his life. He died at the age of
                    seventy-five, in 1694.</p>
                <p>Lambert would have left a better name in history if he had been a Cavalier. His
                    genial, ardent, and excitable nature, easily raised and easily depressed, was
                    more akin to the royalist than the puritan spirit. Vain and sometimes
                    overbearing, as well as ambitious, he believed that Cromwell could not stand
                    without him, and, when Cromwell was dead, he imagined himself equal to succeed
                    him, and thought that the first place must be his by right. Yet his ambition was
                    less selfish than that of Monk. Lambert is accused of no ill faith, no want of
                    generosity, no cold and calculating policy. Lambert was not merely a soldier. He
                    was an able writer and speaker, and an accomplished negotiator, and took
                    pleasure in quiet and domestic pursuits. He learnt his love of gardening from
                    Lord Fairfax, who was also his master in the art of war. He painted flowers,
                    besides cultivating them, and incurred the blame of Mrs Hutchinson by “dressing
                    his flowers in his garden and working at the needle with his wife and his
                    maids.” He made no special profession of religion; but no imputatiι n is cast
                    upon his moral character by his detractors. It has been said that he became a
                    Roman Catholic before his death. <hi rend="subscript"> χ</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(f. w. c.*)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
