<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0764-0741-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LLOYD’S (9th edition, volume 14, page 741)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww77113">Brokers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999835">Lists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:805585">Alleys</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n764/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LLOYD’S</label>, an association of merchants, shipowners,
                    underwriters, and ship and insurance brokers, having its headquarters in a suite
                    of rooms in the north-east corner of the Royal Exchange, London. Originally a
                    mere gathering of merchants for business or gossip in a coffeehouse kept by one
                    Edward Lloyd in Tower Street, London, the earliest notice of which occurs in the
                        <hi rend="italic">London Gazette</hi> of 18th February 1688, this
                    institution has gradually become one of the greatest and most perfect
                    organizations in the world in connexion with commerce. The establishment existed
                    in Tower Street up to 1692, in which year it was removed by the enterprising
                    proprietor to Lombard Street, in the very centre of that portion of the old city
                    of London most frequented by merchants of the highest class. Shortly after this
                    event Mr Lloyd gave another proof of his enterprise and intelligence by the
                    establishment of a weekly newspaper furnishing commercial and shipping news, in
                    those days an undertaking of no small difficulty. This paper took the name of
                        <hi rend="italic">Lloyd's News,</hi> and, though its life was not a
                    prolonged one, it was destined to be the precursor of the now ubiquitous <hi
                        rend="italic">Lloyd's List,</hi> the oldest existing paper, the <hi
                        rend="italic">London Gazette</hi> excepted, of the present day. In Lombard
                    Street the business transacted at Lloyd’s coffee-house steadily grew in extent
                    and importance, but it does not appear that throughout the greater part of the
                    18th century the merchants and underwriters frequenting the rooms were bound
                    together by any rules, or acted under any organization. By and by, however, the
                    rapid increase of marine insurance business made a change of system and improved
                    accommodation absolutely necessary, and accordingly, after finding a temporary
                    resting-place in Pope’s Head Alley, the underwriters and brokers finally settled
                    down in the Royal Exchange in March 1774. One of the first improvements in the
                    mode of effecting marine insurance springing out of this new state of things was
                    the introduction of a printed form of policy. Hitherto various forms had been in
                    use; and, to avoid the numerous disputes consequent on a practice so loose and
                    unsatisfactory, the committee of Lloyd’s proposed a general form, which was
                    finally adopted by the members on the 12th of January 1779, and which remains in
                    use, with only a few slight alterations, to this day. The two most important
                    events in the history of Lloyd’s during the present century are the
                    reorganization of the association in 1811, and the passage of an Act in 1871
                    granting to Lloyd’s all the rights and privileges of a corporation sanctioned by
                    parliament. According to this Act of Incorporation, the three main objects for
                    which the society exists are—first, the carrying out of the business of marine
                    insurance; secondly, the protection of the interests of the members of the
                    association; and thirdly, the collection, publication, and diffusion of
                    intelligence and information with respect to shipping. In the promotion of the
                    last-named object, obviously the foundation upon which the entire superstructure
                    rests, an intelligence department has been gradually developed which for
                    wideness of range and efficient working has no parallel among private
                    enterprises in any country.</p>
                <p>The rooms at Lloyd’s are available only to subscribers and members. The former
                    pay an annual subscription of five guineas without entrance fee, but have no
                    voice in the management of the institution. The latter consist of
                    nonunderwriting members, who pay an entrance fee of twelve guineas, and of
                    underwriting members, who pay a fee of one hundred pounds. Underwriting members
                    are also required to deposit securities to the value of .£5000 to .£10,000,
                    according to circumstances, as a guarantee for their engagements. The management
                    of the establishment is delegated by the members to certain of their number
                    selected as a “committee for managing the affairs of Lloyd’s.” With this body
                    lies the appointment of all the officials and agents of the institution, the
                    daily routine of duty being entrusted to a secretary and a large staff of clerks
                    and other assistants. The mode employed in effecting an insurance at Lloyd’s is
                    very simple. The business is done entirely by brokers, who write upon a slip of
                    paper the name of the ship and shipmaster, the nature of the voyage, the subject
                    to be insured, and the amount at which it is valued. If the risk is accepted,
                    each underwriter subscribes his name and the amount he agrees to take or
                    underwrite, the insurance being effected as soon as the total value is made up.
                    The sum paid by the insured to the underwriters is denominated the premium, a
                    tax upon the profits of the merchant which the progress of science, of the art
                    of shipbuilding, and of navigation has in these days reduced to a very moderate
                    figure. (w. p. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
