<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0272-0257-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LANCASTER, Joseph (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    257)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn1111w">Scholars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106878">Scholars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n272/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LANCASTER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi></label>
                    (1778-1838), was born in Southwark in 1778, and was the son of a Chelsea
                    pensioner. He had few opportunities of regular instruction, but he very early
                    showed unusual seriousness and desire for learning. At sixteen he looked forward
                    to the dissenting ministry; but soon after his religious views altered, and he
                    attached himself to the Society of Friends, with which he remained associated
                    for many years, until long afterwards he was disowned by that body. At the age
                    of twenty he began to gather a few poor children under his father’s roof and to
                    give them the rudiments of instruction, without a fee, except in cases in which
                    the parent was willing to pay a trifle. Soon a thousand children were assembled
                    in the Borough Road; and, the attention of the duke of Bedford, Mr Whitbread,
                    and others having been directed to his efforts, he was provided with means for
                    building a schoolroom, and supplying needful materials. The main features of his
                    plan were the employment of older scholars as monitors, and an elaborate system
                    of mechanical drill, by means of which these young teachers were made to impart
                    the rudiments of reading, writing, and arithmetic to large numbers at the same
                    time. The material appliances for teaching were very scanty—a few leaves torn
                    out of spelling-books and pasted on boards, some slates, and a desk spread with
                    sand, on which the children wrote with their fingers. The order and cheerfulness
                    of the school and the military precision of the children’s movements were very
                    striking, and began to attract much public observation at a time when the
                    education of the poor was almost entirely neglected. Lancaster had the skill
                    which gains the loyalty of subordinates, and he succeeded in inspiring his young
                    monitors with fondness for their work and with pride in the institution of which
                    they formed a part. As these youths bècame <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n273/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0273-0258"/> more trustworthy, he found himself at leisure
                    to accept some of the numerous invitations which crowded upon him, and to
                    expound what he called “his system” by lectures in various towns. In this way
                    many new schools were established, and placed under the care of young men whom
                    he had trained. In a memorable interview with George HL, Lancaster was
                    encouraged by the expression of the king’s wish that every poor child in his
                    dominions should be taught to read the Bible. Royal patronage brought in its
                    train resources, fame, and public responsibility, which proved to be beyond
                    Lancaster’s own powers to sustain or control. He was vain, reckless, and
                    improvident. In 1808 a few noblemen and gentlemen came to his rescue, paid his
                    debts, became his trustees, and founded the society which was at first called
                    the Royal Lancasterian Institution, but was afterwards more widely known as the
                    British and Foreign School Society. With the strongest wish to retain his
                    services and to treat him with liberality, they soon found that he was impatient
                    of control, and that his wild impulses and heedless extravagance made it
                    impossible to work with him. He quarrelled with the committee, set up a private
                    school at Tooting, became bankrupt, and in 1818 emigrated to America. There he
                    met at first with a warm reception, gave several courses of lectures which were
                    well attended, and wrote to friends at home letters full of enthusiasm and of
                    high hopes for future usefulness, not unmingled with bitter denunciations of
                    what he called the ingratitude and treachery of those who had been associated
                    with him in England. But his fame was short-lived. The miseries of debt and
                    disappointment were aggravated by sickness, and he settled for a time in the
                    warmer climate of Caracas. He afterwards visited St Thomas and Santa Cruz, and
                    at length returned to New York, the corporation of which city made him a public
                    grant of 500 dollars in pity for the misfortunes which had by this time reduced
                    him to lamentable poverty. He afterwards visited Canada, where for a time his
                    prospects brightened. He gave lectures at Montreal, and was encouraged to open a
                    school which enjoyed an ephemeral success, but was soon abandoned. A small
                    annuity provided by his friends in England was his only means of support. He
                    formed a plan, however, for returning home and giving a new impetus to his
                    “system,” by which he declared it would be possible “to teach ten thousand
                    children in different schools, not knowing their letters, all to read fluently
                    in three weeks to three months.” But these visions were never realized. He was
                    run over by a carriage in the streets of New York in October 1838, and was so
                    much injured that he died in a few hours.</p>
                <p>As one of the two rival inventors of what was called the “monitorial” or “mutual”
                    method of instruction, his name was prominent for many years in educational
                    controversy. Dr <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew Bell</hi> {q. v.) had in 1797
                    published an account of his experiments in teaching; and Lancaster in his first
                    pamphlet, published in 1803, frankly acknowledges his debt to Bell for some
                    useful hints. The two worked independently, but Lancaster was the first to apply
                    the system of monitorial teaching on a large scale. As an economical experiment
                    his school at the Borough Road was a signal success. He had one thousand
                    scholars under discipline, and taught them to read, write, and work simple sums
                    at a yearly cost of less than 5s. a head. His tract Improvements in Education
                    described the gradation of ranks, the system of signals and orders, the
                    functions of the monitors, the method of counting and of spelling, and the
                    curious devices he adopted for punishing offenders. Bell’s educational aims were
                    humbler, as he feared to “elevate above their station those who were doomed to
                    the drudgery of daily labour,” and therefore did not desire to teach even
                    writing and ciphering to the lower classes. The main difference between them was
                    that the system of the one was adopted by ecclesiastics and Conservatives,—the
                    “National Society for the Education of the Poor in the principles of the
                    Established Church” having been founded in 1811 for its propagation; while
                    Lancaster’s method was patronized by the Edinburgh Review, by Whig statesmen, by
                    a few liberal Churchmen, and by Nonconformists generally. It was the design of
                    Lancaster and his friends to make national education Christian, but not
                    sectarian,—to cause the Scriptures to be read, explained, and reverenced in the
                    schools, without seeking by catechisms or otherwise to attract the children to
                    any particular church or sect. This principle, since almost universally adopted
                    by the school boards of England, was at first vehemently denounced as deistic
                    and mischievous, and as especially hostile to the Established Church. To do them
                    justice, it must be owned that the rival claims and merits of Bell and Lancaster
                    were urged with more passion and unfairness by their friends than by themselves.
                    Y et neither is entitled to hold a very high place among the world’s teachers.
                    Bell was cold, shrewd, and self-seeking. Lancaster had more enthusiasm, a
                    genuine and abounding love for children, and some ingenuity in devising plans
                    both for teaching and governing. But he was shiftless, wayward, and
                    unmethodical, and incapable of sustained and high-principled personal effort.
                    His writings were not numerous. They consist mainly of short pamphlets
                    descriptive of the successes he attained at the Borough Road. His last
                    publication, An Epitome of the Chief Events and Transactions of his Own Life,
                    appeared in America in 1833, and is characterized, even more strongly than his
                    former writings, by looseness and incoherency of style, by egotism, and by a
                    curious incapacity for judging fairly the motives either of his friends or his
                    foes.</p>
                <p>Subsequent experience has not justified the sanguine estimate of the Edinburgh
                    Reviewer, who so early as 1810 described Lancaster’s method as “a beautiful and
                    inestimable discovery, a plan now brought very near to perfection, by which
                    education could be placed within the reach of all classes.” We have since come
                    to believe that intelligent teaching requires skill and previous training, and
                    that even the humblest rudiments are not to be well taught by those who have
                    only just acquired them for themselves, or to be attained by mere mechanical
                    drill. But in the early stages of national education the monitorial method
                    served a valuable purpose. It brought large numbers of hitherto neglected
                    children under discipline, and gave them elementary instruction at a very cheap
                    rate. Moreover, the educational results attained were in no sense contemptible.
                    The little monitors were often found to make up in brightness, tractability, and
                    energy for their lack of experience, and to teach the arts of reading, writing,
                    and computing with surprising success. And one cardinal principle of Bell and
                    Lancaster is of prime importance. They regarded a school, not merely as a place
                    to which individual pupils should come for guidance from teachers, but as an
                    organized community whose members have much to leanι from each other. They
                    sought to place their scholars from the first in helpful mutual relations, and
                    to make them feel the need of common efforts towards the attainment of common
                    ends. (J. G. F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
