<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0188-0177-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LA BRUYÈRE, Jean de (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    177)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n188/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LA BRUYÈRE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean de</hi></label>
                    (1645-1696), essayist and moralist, was born at Paris in August 1645, and not,
                    as has more commonly been asserted, at Dourdan (Seine-et-Oise) in 1639. His
                    family was of the middle class, and his reference to a certain Geoffroy de la
                    Bruyère, a crusader, is only a satirical illustration of a method of
                    selfennoblement common in France as in some other countries. Indeed he himself
                    always signed the name Delabruyère in one word, thus avowing his <hi
                        rend="italic">roture.</hi> His progenitors, however, were of respectable
                    position, and he could trace them back at least as far as his great-grandfather,
                    who had been a strong Leaguer. La Bruyère’s own father held a municipal
                    appointment in the capital, and seems as well as his son to have been in easy
                    circumstances. The son was educated by the Oratorians, and at the university of
                    Orleans; he was called to the bar, and in 1673 bought a post in the revenue
                    department at Caen, which gave the status of noblesse and a certain income. He
                    afterwards in 1687 sold this office. His predecessor in it was a relation of
                    Bossuet, and it is thought that the transaction was the cause of La Bruyère’s
                    introduction to the great orator. Bossuet, who from the date of his own
                    preceptorship of the dauphin, was a kind of agent-general for tutorships in the
                    royal family, introduced him in 1683 or 1684 to the household of the great
                    Condé, whose grandson Henri Jules de Bourbon he was charged to educate. The rest
                    of his life was passed in the household of the prince or else at <hi
                        rend="superscript"> cn</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> urt</hi><hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> , ani</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> seems</hi> to have
                    profited by the inclination which all the Condé family had for the society of
                    men of letters without suffering from the capricious and tyrannical temper which
                    was also one of the characteristics of the house. Very little is known of the
                    events of this part or indeed of any part of his life. Although he certainly
                    mixed freely in society at a time when more gossip was committed to paper than
                    at almost any other, the notices of him are very few, though they are almost
                    always favourable. The impression derived from them is of a silent observant but
                    somewhat awkward man, resembling in manners our own Addison, whose master in
                    literature La Bruyère undoubtedly was. Yet despite the numerous enemies which
                    his book raised up for him, most of the few personal notices we have are, as has
                    been said, favourable—notably that of St Simon, an acute judge and one bitterly
                    prejudiced against roturiers generally. There is a curious passage in a letter
                    from Boileau to Racine in which he regrets that “nature has not made La Bruyère
                    as agreeable as he would like to be,” which, as he at the same time calls him a
                    “fort honnête homme,” and says that he would lack nothing were it not for the
                    conduct of nature in this respect, can only refer to the want of manner just
                    noticed. His <hi rend="italic">Caractères</hi> appeared in 1688, and at once, as
                    Malezieu had predicted, brought him “bien des lecteurs et bien des ennemis.” At
                    the head of these were Thomas Corneille, Fontenelle, and Benserade, who were
                    pretty clearly aimed at in the book, as well as innumerable other persons, men
                    and women of letters as well as of society, on whom the cap of La Bruyère’s
                    fancy-portraits was fitted by manuscript “keys” which were at once compiled by
                    the scribblers of the day. The friendship of Bossuet and still more the
                    protection of the Condés defended the author quite sufficiently, and he
                    continued to insert fresh portraits of his contemporaries in each new edition of
                    his book. Those, however, whom he had attacked were powerful in the Academy, and
                    numerous defeats awaited La Bruyère before he could make his way into that
                    guarded hold. He was defeated thrice in 1691, and on one memorable occasion he
                    had but seven votes, five of which were those of Bossuet, Boileau, Racine,
                    Pelisson, and Bussy-Rabutin. It was not till 1695 that he was elected, and even
                    then an epigram, which, considering his admitted insignificance in conversation,
                    was not of the worst, <hi rend="italic">haesit</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >lateri</hi><hi rend="italic">:—</hi></p>
                <p>“Quand la Bruyère se présente Pourquoi faut il crier haro?</p>
                <p>Pour faire un nombre de quarante Ne falloit il pas un zéro ?”</p>
                <p>His unpopularity was, however, chiefly confined to the subjects of his sarcastic
                    portraiture, and to the hack writers of the time, of whom he was wont to speak
                    with a disdain only surpassed by that of Pope. His description of the leading
                    newspaper of the day as “immédiatement au dessous du rien” is the best
                    remembered specimen of these unwise attacks which, both in France and England,
                    retarded the establishment of an independent profession of letters for many
                    years. La Bruyère’s discourse of admission at the Academy was, like his
                    admission itself, severely criticized, yet it is certainly one of the best of
                    its kind. With the <hi rend="italic">Caractères,</hi> the translation of
                    Theophrastus, and a few letters, it completes the list of his literary work,
                    with the exception of a curious and much-disputed posthumous treatise. La
                    Bruyère died very suddenly, and not long after his admission to the Academy. He
                    is said to have become suddenly deaf in an assembly of his friends, and, being
                    carried home to the Hotel de Condé, to have expired of apoplexy a day or two
                    afterwards. It is not surprising that, considering the recent panic about
                    poisoning, the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n189/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0189-0178"/> bitter personal enmities which he had
                    excited, and the peculiar circumstances of his death, suspicions of foul play
                    should have been entertained, but there seems to be no foundation for them. Two
                    years after his death appeared certain <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sur le Quiétisme,</hi> alleged to have been found among his
                    papers incomplete, and to have been completed by the editor. As these dialogues
                    are far inferior in literary merit to La Bruyère’s other works, their
                    genuineness has been denied. But the straightforward and circumstantial account
                    of their appearance given by their editor, the Abbé Dupin, a man of acknowledged
                    probity, the intimacy of La Bruyère with Bossuet, whose views in his contest
                    with Fénelon these dialogues are designed to further, and the entire absence at
                    so short a time after the alleged author’s death of the least protest on the
                    part of his friends and representatives, seem to be decisive in their
                    favour.</p>
                <p>Although for reasons to be given shortly it is permissible to doubt whether the
                    value of the <hi rend="italic">Caractères</hi> has not been somewhat exaggerated
                    by traditional French criticism, they deserve beyond all question a high place
                    among the great works of French literature. The plan of the book is thoroughly
                    original, if that term may be accorded to a novel and skilful combination of
                    existing elements. That the little treatise of Theophrastus may have furnished
                    the first idea of it is doubtless true, but only a very small part of the
                    Frenchman’s work is due to the Greek. With the ethical generalizations and
                    social Dutch painting of Theophrastus La Bruyère combined the peculiarities of
                    the Montaigne essay, of the <hi rend="italic">Pensées</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Maximes</hi> of which Pascal and La Rochefoucauld are the masters
                    respectively, and lastly of that peculiar 17th century product, the portrait or
                    elaborate literary picture of the personal and mental characteristics of an
                    individual. The result was quite unlike anything that had been before seen, and
                    it has not been exactly reproduced since, though the essay of Addison and Steele
                    resembles it very closely, especially in the introduction of fancy portraits. In
                    the titles of his work and in its extreme desultoriness La Bruyère reminds the
                    reader of Montaigne, but he aimed too much at sententiousness to attempt even
                    the apparent continuity of the great essayist. The short paragraphs of which his
                    chapters consist are made up of maxims proper, of criticisms literary and
                    ethical, and above all of the celebrated sketches of individuals baptized with
                    names taken from the plays and romances of the time. These last are undoubtedly
                    the great feature of the work, and that which gave it its immediate if not its
                    enduring popularity. They are wonderfully piquant, extraordinarily life-like in
                    a certain sense, and must have given great pleasure or more frequently exquisite
                    pain to the originals, who were in many cases unmistakable and in most
                    recognizable by a society which held to the full Madame de Sévigné’s views of
                    the usefulness of “le prochain” as a butt for satirical observation. But there
                    is something wanting in them. The criticism of Charpentier, who received La
                    Bruyère at the Academy, and who was of the opposite faction, has usually been
                    dismissed as one-sided, but it is in fact fully justified as far as it goes. La
                    Bruyère literally “est [trop] descendu dans le particulier.” He has neither like
                    Molière embodied abstract peculiarities in a single life-like type, nor has he
                    like Shakespeare made the individual pass <hi rend="italic">sub</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">speciem</hi><hi rend="italic">aeternitatis,</hi> and serve as
                    a type while retaining his individuality. He is a photographer rather than an
                    artist in his portraiture. So too his maxims, admirably as they are expressed,
                    and exact as their truth often is, are on a lower level than those of La
                    Rochefoucauld, which, rather unwisely, they sometimes follow very closely.
                    Beside the sculpturesque precision, the Roman brevity, the profoundness of
                    ethical intuition “piercing to the accepted hells beneath,” of the great
                    Frondeur, La Bruyère has the air of a literary <hi rend="italic"
                        >petit-maître</hi> dressing up superficial observation in the finery of <hi
                        rend="italic">esprit.</hi> It is indeed only by comparison that he loses,
                    but then it is by comparison that he is usually praised. There is no doubt that
                    his abundant wit and his personal “malice” have done much to give him his rank
                    in French literature, but much must also be allowed to his purely literary
                    merits. With Racine and Massillon he is probably the very best writer of what is
                    somewhat arbitrarily styled classical French. He is hardly ever incorrect—the
                    highest merit in the eyes of a French academic critic. He is always well-bred,
                    never obscure, rarely though sometimes “precious” in the turns and niceties of
                    language in which he delights to indulge, in his avowed design of attracting
                    readers by form now that in point of matter “tout est dit.” It ought to be added
                    to his credit that he was sensible of the folly of impoverishing French by
                    ejecting old words. His chapter on “Les ouvrages de 1’esprit” contains much good
                    criticism, though it shows that, like most of his contemporaries except Fénelon,
                    he was lamentably ignorant of the literature of his own tongue.</p>
                <p>The editions of La Bruyère, both partial and complete, have been extremely
                    numerous. Les Caractères de Théophraste traduits du Grec, avec les Caractères et
                    les Moeurs de ce Siècle, appeared for the first time in 1688, being published by
                    Michallet, to whose little daughter, according to tradition, La Bruyère gave the
                    profits of the book. Two other editions, little altered, were published in the
                    same year. In the following year, and in each year until 1694, with the
                    exception of 1693, a fresh edition appeared, and, in all these five, additions,
                    omissions, and alterations were largely made. A ninth edition, not much altered,
                    was put forth in the year of the author’s death. The Academy speech appeared in
                    the eighth edition. The Quietist dialogues were published in 1698; most of the
                    letters, including those addressed to Condé, not till 1867. In the last thirty
                    or forty years numerous editions of the complete works have appeared, notably
                    those of Walckenaer (1845), Servois (1867), Asselineau (a scholarly reprint of
                    the last original edition, 1872), and finally Chassang (1876); the last is one
                    of the most generally useful, as the editor has collected almost everything of
                    value in his predecessors. The literature of “keys” to La Bruyère is extensive
                    and apocryphal. Almost everything that can be done in this direction and in that
                    of general illustration was done by the late Μ. Edouard Fournier in his learned
                    and amusing Comédie de La Bruyère. (G. SA. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
