<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0336-0319-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LAS CASAS, Babtolomé de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 319</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g108">Projection</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d79g">Riches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1120522">Slaves</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205154">Guatemala</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205805">Cuba</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1228307">Nicaragua</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n336/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LAS CASAS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Babtolomé de</hi></label>
                    (1474-1566), for some time bishop of Chiapa in Mexico, and known to posterity as
                    “The Apostle of the Indies,” was a native of Seville, where he was born in 1474.
                    His father, one of the companions of Columbus in the voyage which resulted in
                    the discovery of the New World, was rich enough to be able to send him to
                    Salamanca, where he graduated. In 1498 he accompanied his father in an
                    expedition under Columbus to the West Indies, from which he returned in 1500;
                    and in 1502 he went with Nicolas de Ovando, the governor, to Hayti, where eight
                    years afterwards he was admitted to priestly orders, being the first person to
                    receive that consecration in the colonies. In 1511, the conquest of Cuba having
                    been resolved on, he passed over to that island to <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n337/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0337-0320"/> take part in the work of “population and
                    pacification,” and in 1513 or 1514 he witnessed and vainly endeavoured to check
                    the fearful massacre of Indians at Caonao. Soon afterwards there was assigned to
                    him and his friend Renteria a large village in the neighbourhood of Xagua, with
                    a number of Indians attached to it in what was known as “repartimiento”
                    (allotment), and like the rest of his countrymen he sought to make the most of
                    this opportunity for growing rich, but at the same time he occasionally
                    celebrated ma?s and preached. Soon, however, having become deeply convinced of
                    the injustice and other moral evils connected with the repartimiento system, he
                    began to preach against it, at the same time giving up his own slaves. With the
                    consent of his partner he resolved to go to Spain in the cause of the oppressed
                    natives, and the result of his representations was that in 1616 Cardinal Jimenez
                    caused a commission of three Hieronymites to be sent out for the reform of
                    abuses, Las Casas himself, with the title of “protector of the Indians” being
                    appointed, with a salary, to advise and inform them. This commission had not
                    been long at San Domingo, however, before Las Casas became painfully aware of
                    the indifference of his coadjutors to the cause which he himself had so closely
                    at heart, and July 1517 found him again in Spain, where he developed his scheme
                    for the complete liberation of the Indians,—a scheme which not only included
                    facilities for emigration from Spain, but was intended to give to each Spanish
                    resident in the colonies the right of importing twelve negro slaves. The
                    emigration movement proved a failure, and Las Casas lived long enough to express
                    his sorrow and shame for having been so slow to perceive that the Africans were
                    as much entitled to the rights of man as were the natives of the New World.
                    Overwhelmed with disappointment, he retired to the Dominican monastery in Hayti,
                    where he joined the order in 1522, and devoted eight years of extreme seclusion
                    to the acquisition of that store of classical and scholastic learning which
                    appears so curiously in all his writings. About 1530 he appears to have
                    revisited the Spanish court, but on what precise errand or with what result is
                    not known; the vagueness and confusion of the records of this period of his life
                    extends to the time when, after visits to Mexico, Nicaragua, Peru, and
                    Guatemala, in the cause of religion and of his order, he undertook an expedition
                    in 1537 into Tuzulutlan or the Tierra de Guerra (“Land of War”), the inhabitants
                    of •which were, chiefly through his tact and skill, peaceably converted to
                    Christianity, mass being celebrated for the first time amongst them in the newly
                    founded town of Rabinal in 1538. In 1539 Las Casas was sent to Spain to obtain
                    Dominican recruits, and through Loaysa, general of the order, and confessor of
                    Charles V., he was successful in obtaining many royal orders and letters which
                    were supposed to be favourable to his enterprise, among others that which
                    prohibited for the time being the entrance of any lay Spaniard into Tuzulutlan.
                    During this stay in Europe, which lasted more than four years, he more than once
                    visited Germany to see Charles, whom the business of the empire was detaining
                    there; he also (1542) wrote his <hi rend="italic">Veynte Iiazones</hi> (“Twenty
                    Reasons ”) in defence of the liberties of the Indians and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Brevisima lielacion de la Destruycioη des las Indias,</hi> the latter of which
                    was published some twelve years later, and has since been translated into
                    several European languages. In 1543 he refused the Mexican bishopric of Cuzco,
                    but was prevailed upon to accept that of Chiapa, for which he sailed in 1544.
                    Thwarted at every point by the officials, and outraged with passionate hatred by
                    his countrymen in his attempt to carry out the “new laws” which his humanity had
                    procured (see the “Remedios que refirio” in the Seville edition of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Obras,</hi> 1552), he returned to Spain and resigned his dignity
                    three years afterwards (1547). In 1550 he met Sepulveda in public debate on the
                    theses drawn from the recently published <hi rend="italic">Apologia pro</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Libro</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Justis</hi><hi rend="italic">Belli</hi><hi rend="italic">Causis,</hi> in which
                    the latter had maintained the lawfulness of waging unprovoked war upon the
                    natives of the New World. The course of the discussion may still be traced in
                    the account of the “Disputa” contained in the t‰∙αs(1552). In 1555 Las Casas
                    successfully remonstrated with Philip II. against the financial project for
                    selling the reversion of the “encomiendas,”—a project which would have involved
                    the Indians in hopeless bondage. In July of the following year he died at
                    Madrid, whither he had gone to urge (and with success) the necessity of
                    restoring a court of justice which had been repressed in Guatemala.</p>
                <p>A Histοriα de las Iηdias was left by Las Casas to the convent of San Gregorio at
                    Valladolid, with directions that it should not be printed for forty years.
                    Herrera, however, was permitted to consult it for his Historia General (1601).
                    It afterwards lay neglected until the Royal Academy of History took it up with
                    an intention of publishing it. That intention was afterwards abandoned;
                    Prescott, who appears to have seen the MS., hopes that it may yet be given to
                    the world. Sketches of the life of Las Casas have been given by Llorente and by
                    Quintana. The English reader will find adequate notices in the appendix to bk.
                    ii., chap, viii., of Prescott’s Conquest of Mexico, and in the copious monograph
                    of Sir Arthur Helps (Life of Las Casas, 1868).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
