<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0672-0651-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIMOGES (9th edition, volume 14, page 651)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34n208">Vandals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hq83">Visigoths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058861">Persons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n672/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIMOGES</label>, capital of the department of Haute Vienne,
                    France, and the ancient capital of Limousin, lies in the form of an amphitheatre
                    on the right bank of the Vienne, 248 miles by rail south-south-west from Paris,
                    on the Paris and Toulouse Railway, at its junction with the Charente line. It
                    has also direct railway communication by Bellac with Poitiers. The population in
                    1876 was 59,011. In spite of many modern improvements and clearances, commencing
                    with the administration of Turgot in 1762, the city still contains old quarters,
                    which are dark, wretched, and unhealthy.</p>
                <p>The cathedral, the most remarkable building, not only in the town but in the
                    entire province, is in the Parisian Ogival style, and occupies the site of an
                    old heathen basilica, which, according to tradition, was transformed into a
                    Christian church by St Martial. The present edifice was built between 1273 and
                    1327, and has been quite recently restored, the north front of the transept,
                    distinguished by the richness and perfection of its details, having been finally
                    completed in 1851.∙ The campanile is an elegant slightly leaning tower, 204 feet
                    high. The interior of the church is remarkable for the boldness and elegance of
                    its construction. It has a magnificent rood-loft, attributed to Bishop Jean de
                    Langeac (1533); close by the choir screen is the mausoleum of the same prelate.
                    The glass was repaired in the 16th century, but is still undergoing restoration.
                    Under the choir is the crypt of the old Roman church, containing frescos of the
                    11th century. Some of the houses still standing in Limoges date from the
                    Middle</p>
                <p>Ages; and commemorative tablets mark the birthplace of the chancellor D’Aguesseau
                    and of Marshals Jourdan and Bugeaud. There is a museum of painting and
                    sculpture, and, in connexion with the local industry, a very valuable ceramic
                    museum. Limoges is the headquarters of the 12th army corps, and is also the seat
                    of several learned societies, and of a court of appeal.</p>
                <p>The principal industry is the manufacture of porcelain. The kaolin of St Yrieix
                    is of such superior quality that it is exported even to America; the pegmatite
                    used for enamel is obtained at Chanteloube, about 25 miles from Limoges, on the
                    Paris railway. Thirty-five factories with eighty furnaces and fifty-four
                    painting rooms (800 artists) employ 5800 workers of both sexes, and produce
                    goods to the annual value of 12 millions of francs. There are many others in the
                    immediate neighbourhood of the town. Limoges has also wool and cotton
                    spinning-mills, and cloth factories, paper-works, foundries, &lt;fcc. Shoemaking
                    gives employment to 600 persons, and the manufacture of clogs to 250. There is
                    an extensive trade in wine and spirits, cattle, cereals, and wood. The Vienne is
                    navigable for rafts above Limoges, and the logs brought down by the current are
                    stopped at the entrance of the town by the inhabitants of the Naveix quarter,
                    who form a special guild for this industry.</p>
                <p>Limoges was a place of importance even at the time of the Roman conquest, and
                    sent ten thousand soldiers to the defence of Alesia. In 11 B.c. it took the name
                    of Augustus <hi rend="italic">(ΛugustοrRum)</hi>; but in the 4th century it was
                    anew called by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Lcmοviοcs,</hi> whose capital
                    it was. It then contained palaces and baths, had its own senate and the right of
                    coinage. (Till 1837 it had a mint.) Christianity was introduced by St Martial.
                    In the 5th century Limoges was devastated by the Vandals and the Visigoths.
                    Viscounts were set over it by Clovis. It suffered again in the wars between the
                    Franks and the people of Aquitaine, from Norman <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n673/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0673-0652"/> invasion, and from a struggle which arose
                    between two parties into which the city was divided, led by the abbot of St
                    Martial and by the bishop respectively. During the Hundred Years’ War it was
                    taken again and again by the French and English. Confiscated under John
                    Lackland, it was again ceded by Louis IX. In 1370 the Black Prince took it by
                    assault, and gave it up to fire and sword,— a disaster from which it was slow to
                    recover. The religious wars, pestilence, and famine desolated it in turn, but
                    the ravages of all these were surpassed by the plague of 1630-31, which carried
                    off more than twenty thousand persons. The wise administrations of Henri
                    d’Aguesseau, father of the chancellor, and of Turgot enabled Limoges to recover
                    its former prosperity. There have been several noteworthy conflagrations,
                    destroying whole quarters of the city, built, as it then was, of wood. That of
                    1790 lasted for two months, and destroyed one hundred and ninety-nine houses;
                    that of 1864 laid under ashes an area of 10,000 square metres. Limoges
                    celebrates every seven years a curious religious festival (Fête d’Ostension),
                    during which the relics of St Martial are exposed for seven weeks, attracting
                    large numbers of visitors. It dates from the 10th century, and commemorates a
                    pestilence (mal des ardents) which, after destroying forty thousand persons, is
                    believed to have been stayed by the intercession of the saint.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
