<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0360-0343-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LATIUM (9th edition, volume 14, page 343)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bv79x75">Coras</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804171">Albas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n360/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LATIUM</label>, in ancient geography, was the name given to
                    the portion of central Italy which adjoined the Tyrrhenian Sea on the west, and
                    was situated between Etruria and Campania. The name was, however, applied in a
                    very different sense at different times, and the extent of country comprised
                    under this appellation varied materially. Latium originally means the land of
                    the Latini, and in this sense, which is that alone in use historically, it was a
                    tract of comparatively limited extent; but after the overthrow of the Latin
                    confederacy, when the neighbouring tribes of the Hernicans, Volscians, and
                    Auruncans, as well as the Latins properly so called, were reduced to the
                    condition of subjects and citizens of Rome, the name of Latium was extended so
                    as to comprise them all, and include the whole country from the Tiber to the
                    Liris. The change thus introduced was not formally established till the reign of
                    Augustus; but it is already recognized by Strabo (v. p. 228), as well as by
                    Pliny, who terms the additional territory thus incorporated Latium Adjectum,
                    while he designates the original Latium, extending from the Tiber to Circeii, as
                    Latium Antiquum. We shall confine ourselves in the first instance to the
                    description of Latium in this limited sense, in which it figures in Roman
                    history from the foundation of the city to the days of Cicero.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Latium</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Antiquum.</hi> In this
                    original sense Latium was a country of but small extent, and consisted
                    principally of an extensive plain, now known as the Campagna di Roma, bounded
                    towards the interior by the lofty range of the Apennines, which rise very
                    abruptly from the plains at their foot to a height of between 4000 and 5000
                    feet. Several of the Latin cities, including Tibur and Praeneste, were, however,
                    situated on the terrace-like underfalls oι these mountains, while Cora, Norba,
                    and Setia were placed in like manner on the slopes of the Volscian mountains or
                    Monti Lepini, a rugged and lofty range, which branches off from the Apennines
                    near Praeneste, and forms a continuous mountain barrier from thence to
                    Terracina. In the midst of the plain thus limited rises a group of volcanic
                    mountains, of about 30 miles in circuit, and attaining to a height of over 3000
                    feet, now commonly known as the Alban hills, though the designation of Albani
                    Montes is not found in any ancient writer. But the highest summit, now called
                    Monte Cavo, on which stood the temple of Jupiter Latiaris, was known as Mons
                    Albanus; while the north-east summit, which almost equalled it in height, bore
                    the name of Mount Algidus, celebrated in all ages for the dark forests of ilex
                    with which it was covered. No volcanic eruptions are known to have taken place
                    in these mountains within the historic period, but the remains of a crater are
                    distinctly seen near the summit of the Mons Albanus, forming the basin now known
                    as the Campo di Annibale, while the cup-shaped lakes known as the Alban Lake and
                    the Lake of Nemi unquestionably occupy the basins of similar craters at a lower
                    level on the southern slope of the mountain, and the adjacent Lacus Aricinus,
                    now drained, was another vent of a similar character.</p>
                <p>But, besides this distinctly volcanic group, by far the greater part of the plain
                    now called the Campagna di Roma was formed by volcanic deposits, consisting for
                    the most part of the rock called <hi rend="italic">tufo,</hi> an aggregate of
                    volcanic sand, pebbles, and cinders or scoriae, varying greatly in hardness and
                    consistency, from a compact rock well adapted for building stone to a loose
                    disintegrating sand known by the local name of <hi rend="italic">puzzolano.</hi>
                    In a few places only beds of lava are found, the most distinct of which is a
                    continuous stream extending from the foot of the Alban hills to within 2 miles
                    from Rome, along which the line of the Appian Way was carried. These deposits
                    have been formed upon previously existing beds of Tertiary formation, which here
                    and there rise to the surface, and in the Monte Mario, a few miles north of
                    Rome, attain to the height of 400 feet. The surface is by no means an uniform
                    plain, like that of the Terra di Lavoro (the ancient Campania), but is a broad
                    undulating tract, furrowed throughout by numerous depressions, with precipitous
                    banks, serving as water-courses, though rarely traversed by any considerable
                    stream. As the general level of the plain rises gradually, though almost
                    imperceptibly, to the foot of the Apennines, these channels by degrees assume
                    the character of ravines of a formidable description.</p>
                <p>Between the volcanic tract of the Campagna and the sea there intervenes a broad
                    strip of sandy plain, evidently formed merely by the accumulation of sand from
                    the sea, and constituting a barren tract, still covered, as it was in ancient
                    times, almost entirely with wood. This long belt of sandy shore extends without
                    a break for a distance of above 30 miles from the mouth of the Tiber to the
                    promontory of Antium (Porto d’Anzo), which is formed by a low but rocky
                    headland, projecting out into the sea, and giving rise to the only considerable
                    angle in this line of coast. Thence again a low sandy shore of similar character
                    extends for about 21 miles to the foot of the Monte Circello, an isolated
                    mountain mass of limestone of about 9 miles in circumference, and rising to a
                    height of 2000 feet. From the almost insulated character of this remarkable
                    promontory, which is united to the Apennines at Terracina by a similar strip of
                    sandy coast, between the Pontine Marshes and the sea, there can be no doubt that
                    it was once an island, which has been gradually united to the mainland by
                    alluvial deposits. But it is certain that these deposits must have commenced
                    long before the historical period, and the assertion strangely ascribed by Pliny
                    to Theophrastus, that the Circeian promontory was in the days of that
                    philosopher still an island, is certainly erroneous. The region of the Pontine
                    Marshes, which occupies almost the whole tract between the sandy belt on the
                    sea-shore and the Volscian mountains, extending from the southern foot of the
                    Alban hills below Velletri to the sea near Terracina, a distance of about 30
                    miles, is a perfectly level plain, rendered pestilential by the stagnation of
                    numerous streams that descend from the neighbouring mountains, and are unable to
                    find their way through this extremely low and level tract, while their outlet to
                    the sea is barred by the sands of the coast between Monte Circello and
                    Terracina.</p>
                <p>At the earliest period of which we have any historical record the whole of the
                    country that we have thus described, or Latium in the proper sense of the term,
                    was inhabited by the people known to the Romans as Latini. Of their origin or
                    ethnical affinities we have very little information, except that they belonged
                    to the same branch of the Italian races with the Umbrians, Oscans, and
                    Sabellians (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy).</hi> At the same time they
                    constituted, according to the general testimony of ancient writers, a distinct
                    people from their neighbours the Sabines and the Volscians, who held the
                    mountain districts adjoining their territory, as well as (in a much higher
                    degree) from the Etruscans on the other side of the Tiber. There was once,
                    however, a people called the Rutuli, who occupied a small portion of the Latin
                    territory adjoining the sea-coast, and are described as a separate people under
                    their own king,—a tradition familiar to all modern readers from its having been
                    adopted by Virgil. But the name of the Rutuli, as that of an independent people,
                    disappears from history at a very early period, and their capital city of Ardea
                    was certainly one of the thirty cities that in historical times constituted the
                    Latin league. The list of these cities given us by Dionysius of Halicarnassus,
                    which has every appearance of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n361/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0361-0344"/> being derived frnm an authentic document (see
                    Niebuhr’s <hi rend="italic">Roman History,</hi> vol. ii. p. 23), enumerates them
                    as follows: —Ardea, Aricia, Bovillae, Bubentum, Corniculum, Carventum, Circeii,
                    Corioli, Corbio, Cora, Fortinei (?), Gabii, Laurentum, Lavinium, Labicum,
                    Lanuvium, Nomentum, Norba, Praeneste, Pedum, Querquetulum, Satricum, Scaptia,
                    Setia, Tellenae, Tibur, Tusculum, Toleria, Tricrinum (?), Velitrae.</p>
                <p>The list thus given by Dionysius is arranged in an order approximately
                    alphabetical. Omitting the two names which are probably corrupt, and a few of
                    which the site cannot be determined with any certainty, the others may be
                    described according to their geographical arrangement. Laurentum and Lavinium,
                    names so conspicuous in the legendary history of Aeneas, were situated in the
                    sandy strip near the sea-coast,—the former only 8 miles east of Ostia, which was
                    from the first merely the port of Rome, and never figured as an independent
                    city. Farther eastward again lay Ardea, the ancient capital of the Rutuli, and
                    some distance beyond that Antium, situated on the sea-coast, which, though not
                    in the list of Dionysius, was certainly a Latin city. On the southern underfalls
                    of the Alban mountains, commanding the plain at the foot, stood Lanuvium and
                    Velitrae; Aricia rose on a neighbouring hill, and Corioli was probably situated
                    in the plain beneath. The more important city of Tusculum occupied one of the
                    northern summits of the same group; while opposite to it, in a commanding
                    situation on a lofty offshoot of the Apennines, rose Praeneste, now Palestrina.
                    Bola and Pedum were in the same neighbourhood, Labicum on the slope of the Alban
                    hills below Tusculum, and Corbio on a rocky summit east of the same city. Tibur
                    (Tivoli) occupied a height commanding the outlet of the river Anio. Corniculum,
                    farther west, stood on the summit of one of three conical hills that rise
                    abruptly out of the plain at the distance of a few miles from Monte Gennaro, the
                    nearest of the Apennines, and whioh were thence known as the Montes Corniculani.
                    Nomentum was a few miles farther north, between the Apennines and the Tiber, and
                    close to the Sabine frontier. The boundary between the two nations was indeed in
                    this part very fluctuating. Nearly in the centre of the plain of the Campagna
                    stood Gabii; Bovillae was also in the plain, but close to the Appian Way, where
                    it begins to ascend the Alban hills. Several other cities—Tellenae, Scaptia, and
                    Querquetulum—mentioned in the list of Dionysius were probably situated in the
                    Campagna, but their site cannot be determined. Satricum, on the other hand was
                    south of the Alban hills, apparently between Velitrae and Antium; while Cora,
                    Norba, and Setia (all of which retain their ancient names with little
                    modification) crowned the rocky heights which form advanced posts from the
                    Volscian mountains towards the Pontine Marshes.</p>
                <p>It must be borne in mind that the list given by Dionysius belonged to a date
                    about 490 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and a considerable number of the Latin
                    citieshad before that time either been utterly destroyed or reduced to
                    subjection by Rome, and had thus lost their independent existence. Such were
                    Antemnae and Coenina, both of them situated within a few miles of Rome, and the
                    conquest of which was ascribed to Romulus; Fidenae, about 5 miles north of the
                    city, and close to the Tiber; and Crustumerium, in the hilly tract farther north
                    towards the Sabine frontier. Pometia also, on the borders of the Pontine
                    Marshes, to which it was said to have given name, was a city of importance, the
                    destruction of which was ascribed to Tarquinius Superbus. But by far the most
                    important of these extinct cities was Alba, on the lake to which it gave its
                    name, which was, according to the tradition universally received, the parent of
                    Rome, as well as of numerous other cities within the limits of Latium, including
                    Gabii, Fidenae, Collatia, Nomentum, and other well-known towns. Whether or not
                    this tradition deserves to rank as historical, it appears certain that at an
                    early period there existed a confederacy of thirty towns, of which Alba was the
                    supreme head. A list of these is given us by Pliny (iii. 5, 968) under the name
                    of “populi Albenses,” which includes only six of those found in the list of
                    Dionysius; and these for the most part among the more obscure and least known of
                    the names there given; while the more powerful cities of Aricia, Lanuvium, and
                    Tusculum, though situated immediately on the Alban hills, are not included, and
                    appear to have maintained a wholly independent position. This earlιer league was
                    doubtless broken up by the fall of Alba; it was probably the increasing power of
                    the Volsci and Aequi that led to the formation of the later league, including
                    all the more powerful cities of Latium, as well as to the alliance concluded by
                    them with the Romans in the consulship of Sp. Cassius (493 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.c.).</hi></p>
                <p>The cities of the Latin league continued to hold general meetings or assemblies
                    from time to time at the Grove of Ferentina, a sanctuary at the foot of the
                    Alban hills in a valley below Marino, while they had also a common place of
                    worship on the summit of the Alban Mount (the Monte Cavo), where stood the
                    celebrated temple of Jupiter Latiaris. The participation in the annual
                    sacrifices at this sanctuary was regarded as typical of a Latin city; and they
                    continued to be celebrated long after the Latins had lost their independence and
                    been incorporated in the Roman state. This change took place in 338 B.c. During
                    the centuries that followed down to the end of the Roman republic many of the
                    Latin towns sank into a very decayed condition. Cicero speaks of Gabii, Labicum,
                    and Bovillae as places that had fallen into abject poverty, while Horace refers
                    to Gabii and Fidenae as mere “deserted villages.” Many of the smaller places
                    mentioned in the list of Dionysius, or the early wars of the Romans, had
                    altogether ceased to exist, but the statement of Pliny that fifty-three
                    communities <hi rend="italic">(populi)</hi> had thus perished within the
                    boundaries of Old Latium is certainly exaggerated, and his list of the
                    “illustrious cities” <hi rend="italic">(clara oppida)</hi> that had thus
                    disappeared is very confused and unintelligible. Still more erroneous is his
                    statement that there were once twenty-four cities on the site occupied in his
                    time by the Pontine Marshes,—an assertion not confirmed by any other authority,
                    and utterly at variance with the physical conditions of the tract in
                    question.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Latium</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Novum,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Adjectum,</hi> as it is termed by Pliny, comprised the
                    territories occupied in earlier times by the Volscians, Hemicans, and Auruncans.
                    It was for the most part a rugged and mountainous country, extending at the back
                    of Latium proper, from the frontier of the Sabines to the sea-coast between
                    Terracina and Sinuessa. But it was not separated from the adjacent territories
                    by any natural frontier or physical boundaries, and it is only by the
                    enumeration of the towns in Pliny according to the division of Italy by Augustus
                    that we can determine its limits. It included the upper valley of the Anio, with
                    the towns of Sublaqueum and Treba; the Hernican cities of Anagnia, Ferentinum,
                    Alatrium, and Vernlae—a group of mountain strongholds on the north side of the
                    valley of the Trerus or Sacco; together with the Volscian cities on the south of
                    the same valley, and in that of the Liris, the whole of which, with the
                    exception of its extreme upper end, was included in the Volscian territory. Here
                    were situated Signia, Frusino, Fabrateria, Fregellae, Sora, Arpinum, Atina,
                    Aquinum, Casinum, and Interamna; Anxur, or Tarracina, was the only seaport that
                    properly belonged to the Volscians, the coast from thence to the mouth of the
                    Liris being included in the territory of the Auruncans, or Ausouians as they
                    were termed by Greek writers, who possessed the maritime towns of Fundi,
                    Formiae, Caieta, and Minturnae, together with Suessa in the interior, which had
                    replaced their more ancient capital of Aurunca. Sinuessa, on the sea-coast
                    between the Liris (Garigliano) and the Vulturnus, was the last town in Latium
                    according to the official use of the term.</p>
                <p>Thouglι the Apennines comprised within the boundaries of Latium do not rise to a
                    height approaching that of the loftiest summits of the central range, they
                    attain to a considerable altitude, and form steep and rugged mountain masses
                    from 4000 to 5000 feet high. They are traversed by three principal valleys :—(1)
                    that of the Anio, now called Teverone, which descends from above Subiaco to
                    Tivoli, where it enters the plain of the Campagna; (2) that of the Trerus or
                    Sacco, which has its source below Palestrina (Praeneste), and flows through a
                    comparatively broad valley that separates the main mass of the Apennines from
                    the Volscian mountains or Monti Lepini, till it joins the Liris below Ceprano;
                    (3) that of the Liris or Garigliano, which enters the confines of New Latium
                    about 20 miles from its source, flows under the walls of Sora, and has a very
                    tortuous course from thence to the sea at Minturnae; its lower valley is for the
                    most part of considerable width, and forms a fertile tract of considerable
                    extent, bordered on both sides by hills covered with vines, olives, and fruit
                    trees, and thickly studded with towns and villages.</p>
                <p>It may be observed that, long after the Latins had ceased to exist <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0362-0345"/> as a separate people, we meet in Roman
                    writers with the phrase of “nomen Latinum,” used not in an ethnical but a purely
                    political sense, to designate the inhabitants of all those cities on which the
                    Romans had conferred “Latin rights” <hi rend="italic">(fis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Latinum),</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> an inferior form of the Roman
                    franchise, which had been granted in the first instance to certain cities of the
                    Latins, when they became subjects of Rome, and was afterwards bestowed upon many
                    other cities of Italy, especially the so-called Latin colonies. At a later
                    period the same privileges were extended to places in other countries also,—as
                    for instance to most of the cities in Sicily and Spain. All persons enjoying
                    these rights were termed in legal phraseology “Latini” or “Latinae
                    conditionis."</p>
                <p>For the topography of Latium, and the local history of its more important cities,
                    the reader may consult Sir W. GelΓs <hi rend="italic">Topography of Rome and its
                        Vicinity,</hi> 2 vols. 8vo., Lond., 1834, 2d ed., 1 vol., 1846, with a
                    valuable map; Nibby, <hi rend="italic">Analisi Storico-Topografico∙</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Antiquaria</hi><hi rend="italic">della Carta dei Dintorni di
                        Roma,</hi> 3 vols. 8vo, 1837, 2d ed. 1848; Westphal, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Römische Kampagne,</hi> 4to, Berlin, 1829;
                    Bormann, <hi rend="italic">Alt·Latinische Chorographie</hi><hi rend="italic">und
                        Städte-Geschichte,</hi> 8vo, Halle, 1852; Burn’s <hi rend="italic">Rome and
                        the Campagna,</hi> 4to, Lond., 1871; Hare’s <hi rend="italic">Walks around
                        Rome,</hi> 2 vols. 8vo, Lond., 1873. An elaborate antiquarian map of Old
                    Latium has been long in preparation by the Cavaliere De Rossi, but has not yet
                    made its appearance. (E. H. B. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
