<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0482-0463-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LEOPARD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 463</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:999328">Lions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1734554">Lion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1052235">Panthers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1024645">Molars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205459">Algeria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57q1h">Leopard</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s38">Panther</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n17f">Skull</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n482/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LEOPARD</label>, a name now commonly given to a well-known
                    animal, called pard (ττάρδος and τrαpδαλιs) or panther <hi rend="italic"
                    >(πάνθηρ)</hi> by the ancients. Leopard <hi rend="italic">(leo-pardus')</hi> was
                    a later term, originally applied, it is believed, to the animal now known as the
                    cheetah or hunting leopard, upon the supposition that it was a creature
                    intermediate between the lion and the true pard. If so it has been completely
                    transferred to the more common species, and though in this sense a perfectly
                    unnecessary and unmeaning term, has gradually superseded those by which this was
                    originally known. Pard, so commonly used by Elizabethan authors, is now nearly
                    obsolete in the English language, and panther has either become synonymous with
                    leopard, or is used vaguely for any similar large feline animal, even the puma
                    of America.</p>
                <p>Owing to their extensive geographical range, and the great variations, both in
                    size, form, and coloration to which leopards are subject, zoologists have
                    scarcely decided whether all the forms popularly referred to this animal should
                    be regarded as specifically alike, or whether they should constitute several
                    distinct species, but the prevailing opinion at present is in favour of the
                    former view. The attempts to separate a larger and more robust variety, under
                    the name of panther, from a smaller and more graceful form, to which the term
                    leopard might properly be restricted, have failed owing to the existence of
                    intermediate conditions which cannot be assigned definitely to either one or the
                    other form. The most marked anatomical difference yet noted in different
                    varieties of leopard is in the length of the tail as compared with that of the
                    body, even the number of the caudal vertebrae showing variation, though within
                    what limits, and whether correlated with other characters, has not yet been
                    clearly ascertained. The fur of those specimens which inhabit the most northern
                    confines of its range of distribution, as North China, is longer and softer, and
                    the markings are consequently less distinct than on those from more congenial
                    climates, and the well-marked variation thus produced has given rise to the idea
                    of specific distinction.</p>
                <p>Treating the species as one, it is the <hi rend="italic">Felis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ραrdus,</hi> Linn., of most systematic authors, belonging to the
                    family <hi rend="italic">Felidae.</hi> (for the characters of which see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mammalia),</hi> and is one of the most typical members of the
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Felis,</hi> both in its structure and habits. It belongs
                    to that section of the genus (which includes most of its larger members, as the
                    lion and the tiger) in which the hyoid bone is loosely connected with the skull,
                    owing to imperfect ossification of its anterior arch, and in which the pupil of
                    the eye when contracted under the influence of light is circular, not linear as
                    in the smaller cats. The teeth consist on each side of three small incisors, and
                    a formidable large, conical, sharp-pointed canine above and below, and three
                    premolars and one molar above, and two premolars and one molar below, all except
                    the very small upper true molar with sharp compressed trenchant crowns. The
                    skull can scarcely be distinguished, except by its inferior size, from that of
                    the lion. There are seven cervical, thirteen dorsal, seven lumbar, three sacral,
                    and usually twenty-three caudal vertebrae. The toes, five on the forefoot (of
                    which the first or pollex is much shorter than the others) and four on the hind
                    foot, are all armed with powerful, sharp-pointed, much-curved, compressed,
                    retractile claws, The size of different individuals, as before said, varies
                    greatly, the head and body usually measuring from 3∣ to 4⅜ feet in length, and
                    the tail from 2∣ to 3 feet, but specimens have been met with which fall short of
                    or exceed these limits. The ground colour of the fur varies from a pale fawn to
                    a rufous buff, graduating into a pure white on the under parts and inside of the
                    limbs. This is spotted over with dark brown or black; the spots on the back and
                    sides being arranged in rosettes or broken rings, which vary greatly in size and
                    distinctness in different individuals, but are without the central spot seen in
                    those of the jaguar. The spots on the under parts and limbs are simple and
                    blacker than those on the other parts of the body. The bases of the ears behind
                    are black, the tips buff. The upper side of the tail is buff, spotted with
                    broken rings like the back, its under surface white with simple spots. The hair
                    of the cubs is longer than that of the adults, its ground colour less bright,
                    and its spots less distinct. Perfectly black leopards, which, however, in
                    certain lights show the characteristic markings on the fur, are not uncommon.
                    These appear to be examples of <hi rend="italic">melanism,</hi> occurring as
                    individual variations, sometimes in one cub out of a litter of which the rest
                    are normally coloured, and therefore not indicating a distinct race, much less a
                    species. These are met with chiefly in southern Asia. We are not aware of any
                    recorded case from Africa, but the wild animals of that continent are not so
                    well known.</p>
                <p>In habits the leopard resembles the other large cat-like animals, yielding to
                    none in the ferocity and bloodthirstiness of its disposition. It is exceedingly
                    quick and active in its movements, but seizes its prey by waiting in ambush or
                    stealthily approaching to within springing distance, when <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n483/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0483-0464"/> it suddenly rushes upon it and tears it to ground
                    with its powerful claws and teeth. It preys upon almost any animal it can
                    overcome, such as antelopes, deer, sheep, goats, monkeys, peafowl, and is said
                    to have a special liking for dogs. It not unfrequently attacks human beings in
                    India, chiefly children and old women, but instances have been known of a
                    leopard becoming a regular “man-eater.” When favourable opportunities occur, it
                    often kills many more victims than it can devour at once, apparently to gratify
                    its propensity for killing, or only for the sake of their fresh blood. It
                    generally inhabits woody districts, and can climb high trees with facility when
                    necessary for its safety when hunted, but usually lives on or near the ground,
                    among rocks, bushes, and roots and low branches of large trees.</p>
                <p>The present geographical range of the leopard is very extensive, as it is met
                    with in various suitable localities, where not too much interfered with by human
                    cultivation, throughout the greater part of Africa from Algeria to the Cape
                    Colony, and through the whole of the south of Asia from Palestine to China,
                    including all India south of the Himalayas, and the islands of Ceylon, Java,
                    Sumatra, and Borneo. Fossil bones and teeth, indistinguishable from those of
                    existing leopards, have been found in cave de posits of Pleistocene age in
                    Spain, France, Germany, and England. The evidence of the former existence of the
                    leopard in England is described at length by Boyd Dawkins and Sanford in their
                    <hi rend="italic">British Pleistocene Mammalia</hi> ( Palaeontographical
                    Society, 1872). (w. H. F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
