<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0414-0397-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LE CLERC, Jean</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 397</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1026687">Mosaics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c21">Mosaics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n414/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LE CLERC, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean</hi></label> (1657-1736),
                    or <hi rend="smallcaps">Clericus,</hi> theologian and man of letters, was born
                    March 19, 1657 (o.s.), at Geneva, where his father Stephen Le Clerc was
                    professor of Greek. The family had originally belonged to the neighbourhood of
                    Beauvais in France, and several of its members have acquired some name in
                    literature. On the completion of his grammar school course (in which he made
                    himself remarkable for his omnivorous reading), he applied himself to the study
                    of philosophy under Chouet the Cartesian, and from his nineteenth to his
                    twenty-first year he attended the theological lectures of Mestrezat, Turretin,
                    and Louis Tronchin. In 1678-79 he spent some time at Grenoble as tutor in a
                    private family; on his return to Geneva he passed his examinations and received
                    ordination. Soon afterwards he went to Saumur, where in 1679 were published <hi
                    rend="italic">Liberii de Sancto-Amore</hi><hi rend="italic">Epistolae
                    Theologicae</hi> (Irenopoli: Typis Philalethianis), usually attributed to his
                    pen; they deal with such subjects as the doctrine of the Trinity, the
                    hypostatical union of the two natures in Jesus Christ, original sin, and the
                    like, in a manner sufficiently far removed from that of the conventional
                    orthodoxy of the period. From Geneva, which he still continued to regard as his
                    home, Le Clerc in 1682 went to London, where he remained six months, preaching
                    on alternate Sundays in the W alloon church and in the Savoy chapel. Passing
                    over to Amsterdam he was introduced to Locke and Limborch; the acquaintance with
                    the latter soon ripened into a close friendship, which naturally strengthened
                    his preference for the Remonstrant theology, already favourably known to him by
                    the writings of his granduncle Curcellaeus, and by those of Episcopius. A final
                    attempt to live at Geneva, made at the request of his relatives there, satisfied
                    him of the unwholesomeness of its stifling theological atmosphere, and in 1684
                    he finally settled at Amsterdam, first as a moderately successful preacher until
                    ecclesiastical jealousy shut him out from that career, and afterwards as
                    professor of philosophy, belles-lettres, and Hebrew in the Remonstrant seminary.
                    This appointment, which he owed to his friend Limborch, he held from 1684 till
                    1712, when on the death of the latter he was called to occupy the chair of
                    church history also. His suspected Socinianism was the cause, it is said, of his
                    exclusion from the chair of dogmatic theology. Apart from its varied and immense
                    literary labours, his life at Amsterdam was quite uneventful. His marriage to
                    the daughter of Gregorio Leti took place in 1691. In 1728 and following years
                    repeated strokes of paralysis gradually reduced him to a state of mental
                    imbecility, from which he was released by death on January 8, 1736.</p>
                <p>A full catalogue of the publications of Le Clerc will be found, along with
                    adequate biographical material, in Haag’s <hi rend="italic">France</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Protestante</hi> (where seventy-three works are enumerated), or in
                    Chaufle-pié’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire.</hi> Only the most important of
                    these can be mentioned here. In 1685 he published <hi rend="italic"
                    >Scntimens</hi><hi rend="italic">de quelques théologiens</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >de Hollande</hi><hi rend="italic">sur</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire Critique du Vieux Testament composée par le P.
                    Richard</hi><hi rend="italic">Simon,</hi> in which, while pointing out what he
                    believed to be the faults of that author, he undertook to make some positive
                    contributions towards a right understanding of the Bible. Among these last may
                    be noted his argument against the Mosaic authorship of the Pentateuch, his views
                    as to the manner in which the five books actually were composed, his opinions
                    (singularly free for the time in which he lived) on the subject of inspiration
                    in general, and particularly as to the inspiration of Job, Proverbs,
                    Ecclesiastes, Canticles. Simon’s <hi rend="italic">Réponse</hi> (1686) elicited
                    from Le Clerc a <hi rend="italic">Défense</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Scntimens</hi> in the same year, which was followed by a new <hi rend="italic"
                    >Réponse</hi> (1687). In 1692 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Logica</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sire</hi><hi rend="italic">Ars Ratiocinandi,</hi> and also <hi
                    rend="italic">Ontologia</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pneumatologia</hi>; these, with the <hi rend="italic">Physica</hi> (1695), are
                    incorporated with the <hi rend="italic">Opera</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophica</hi> which have passed through several editions. In 1693 his
                    series of Biblical commentaries began with that on Genesis; it was not completed
                    until 1731. The portion relating to the New Testament books included the
                    paraphrase and notes of Hammond. Le Clerc’s commentary had a great influence in
                    breaking up traditional prejudices and opening men’s eyes to the necessity for a
                    more scientific inquiry into the origin and meaning of the Biblical books. It
                    was on all sides hotly attacked,—often for opinions which now seem innocent to
                    the most orthodox. Le Clerc’s new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Apostolic
                    Fathers</hi> of Cotelerius, published in 1698, marked an advance in the critical
                    study of these documents. But the greatest literary influence of Le Clerc was
                    probably that which he exercised over his contemporaries by means of the
                    serials, or, if one may so call them, reviews, of which he was editor. These
                    were the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque universelle et historique</hi>
                    (Amsterdam, 25 vols. 12mo, 1686-93), begun along with De la Croze; the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliothèque choisie,</hi> Amsterdam,</p>
                <p>28 vols. 18mo, 1703-13; and the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque ancienne et
                    moderne,</hi></p>
                <p>29 vols. 18mo, 1714-26. See Le Clerc’s <hi rend="italic">Parrliasiana ou Pensées
                    sur des matières de critique, d’histoire, de morale, et de politique: avec la
                    défense de divers ouvrages de Μ. L. C. par Théodore Parrhase,</hi> Amsterdam,
                    1699; and <hi rend="italic">Vita</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >opera</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">annum MDCCXI.,
                    amici</hi><hi rend="italic">ejus opusculum, philosophicis Clerici operibus
                    subjiciendum,</hi> also attributed to himself. The supplement to Hammond’s notes
                    was translated into English in 1699, <hi rend="italic">Parrliasiana,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">or Thoughts on Several Subjects,</hi> in 1700, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Harmony of the Gospels</hi> in 1701. <hi rend="italic">Twelve
                    Dissertations out of Μ.</hi><hi rend="italic">Le Clercs</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Genesis</hi> appeared in 1696.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
