<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0493-0474-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LESBOS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 474</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1023088">Minorities</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n493/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LESBOS</label> was the name applied by the Greeks to the
                    island now called Metilin—the ancient name of the chief city on the island,
                    Mytilene, having been in the Middle Ages applied to the whole island. It lies
                    along the coast of Mysia, north of the entrance to the Gulf of Smyrna. Strabo
                    estimates its circumference as 1100 stadia, about 138 miles, and Scylax reckons
                    it seventh in size of the islands in the Mediterranean Sea. The narrowest part
                    of the channel which divides it from the Mysian coast, between the promontory of
                    Argennum and the town of Assos, is about 8 miles wide. The island is of
                    irregular shape; it has three prominent points, Argennum on the north-east,
                    Sigrium (now Sigri) on the west, and Malea (now Maria) on the south-east, and a
                    deep gulf, the Euripus Pyrrhaeus, now the port of Calloni, runs far into its
                    western side between Sigrium and Malea. The surface is mountainous, but the soil
                    is in spite of this exceedingly fertile; the wine, oil, and grain of Lesbos were
                    well known in ancient times. The climate is perhaps more delightful than that of
                    any other part of the Aegean; the breezes and the sea temper the heat of summer,
                    and the winter is not severe. Earthquakes were often experienced in the island;
                    the latest, that of 1861, is still remembered as one of the severest known in a
                    country of earthquakes.</p>
                <p>The oldest inhabitants are said to have been Pelasgians; and two generations
                    before the Trojan war came Ionians under Macareus. These two races maybe said to
                    represent respectively the first period of primitive barbarism, and the second
                    period, when navigation brought to the island the commerce and intercourse of
                    more advanced races; it deserves notice that the name Macareus, the Phoenician
                    Melkarth, is taken by Curtius as a sign of the presence of Phoenician traders.
                    But the island begins to be important in history from the time of the Aeolian
                    immigration, which is said to have commenced one hundred and thirty years after
                    the Trojan war; from this time it continued long to be one of the chief homes of
                    Hellenic civilization. Homer refers to its wealth and its populous cities; its
                    chief fame lies in its connexion with the earliest development of Greek poetry
                    and literature. Lesches the cyclic poet, Terpander, Arion, Hellanicus, Pittacus,
                    Alcaeus, and Sappho were all natives of Lesbos. Probably no district of Greece
                    can boast of so many names, most of them associated with some marked advance in
                    literature, as Lesbos can enumerate between 700 and 500 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi></p>
                <p>The chief city of Lesbos was Mytilene or Mitylene, the latter spelling being
                    general in literature while the former is the official spelling used on coins.
                    It was originally built on an island close to the western coast of Lesbos;
                    afterwards when the limits of the island were too narrow it was joined to Lesbos
                    by a causeway, and the city spread out along the coast. On each side of this
                    isthmus was a harbour; not far from the city was a place called Maloeis, but it
                    does not appear that this name was, as some have said, given to the northern
                    harbour. The city has always been known for its delightful and healthy climate.
                    With the advantage of its strong situation and good harbour it soon became one
                    of the most powerful Greek cities of Asia Minor. It was the only Aeolian city
                    that possessed a strong navy. Its colonies were spread along Asia Minor and
                    Thrace, and in the 6th century it maintained a long though finally unsuccessful
                    contest with Athens for the possession of Sigeum. About its internal government
                    little is known. After the kingly period there was a time when oligarchical and
                    democratical factions contended with one another. The noble family of the
                    Penthelidae, descended from Penthilus, son of Orestes, played a great part in
                    these contentions. Its Pelopid descent may be compared with various legends that
                    connect Pelops with the island of Lesbos. The city fell under the Persian power
                    after the defeat of Croesus. A tyrant Coes ruled it soon after, but was expelled
                    when the island joined the Ionic revolt in 500 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> It
                    was freed from the Persian yoke after the battles of Plataea and Mycale, and was
                    a member of the Delian confederacy. It revolted from Athens 429 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and was reduced after a long siege. The story of the
                    cruel revenge which the Athenian assembly at first resolved on, of the second
                    meeting and the more merciful resolution, and of the arrival of the second
                    despatch vessel barely in time to prevent the massacre of the whole male
                    population, has been told by Thucydides. The territory of Mytilene was, however,
                    divided among Athenian <hi rend="italic">κληρούχοι.</hi> The harbour was the
                    scene of a great battle between Callicratidas and Conon in the latter part of
                    the Peloponnesian war; but it is impossible here to trace all the vicissitudes
                    of its history, which are coincident with the history of Greece in the East. It
                    continued to be a rich and prosperous city throughout ancient history, and its
                    name came during the Byzantine period to be applied to the whole island. It was
                    long a stronghold of the Venetians during the Middle Ages, but has belonged to
                    the Turkish empire since 1460.</p>
                <p>The other chief towns besides Mytilene were Methymna, Antissa, Eresus, and
                    Pyrrha; hence the island is sometimes called a Pentapolis. There was also a town
                    called Λrisba, which was destroyed by an earthquake before the time of
                    Herodotus; Conze finds its site inland at Palaiokastro, north-east of the port
                    of Calloni. Pyrrha lay on the south-east coast of this port, at a place also
                    called Palaiokastro. Antissa, near Sigrium, was destroyed by the Romans in 168
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> as having sided with Perseus in the Macedonian
                    war. Eresus, now Eresi, was also near Sigrium. Of these five cities, Mitylene
                    was the chief; Pyrrha, Eresus, and Antissa were under its influence, and seem
                    almost always to have followed its lead. But Methymna on the north coast, though
                    it had not such a fine situation as Mytilene, was a very strong place; it was
                    therefore able to maintain a constant quarrel with the more powerful city, and
                    was always ready to side with its enemies. Mélivo, still the second city of the
                    island, occupies the site of the old Methymna. The name Methymna or Mathymna is
                    derived from the wine for which it was famous (Virg., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Georg.,</hi> ii. 90).</p>
                <p>See Conze, <hi rend="italic">Reise auf der Insel Lesbos</hi>; Plehn, <hi
                    rend="italic">Lesbiaca</hi>; Boutan, <hi rend="italic">Archives</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">cl. Missions Scient, et</hi><hi rend="italic">Liter.,</hi> v.
                    (according to Conze not veιy trustworthy); Zanders, <hi rend="italic">Beitr. z.
                    Kunde d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Insel</hi><hi rend="italic">Lesbos</hi>; Newton,
                    <hi rend="italic">Travels</hi>; and for the geography Cramer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Descr. of Asia Minor,</hi> and Forbiger, <hi rend="italic">Alt. Geogr.</hi> The
                    best maps are the English admiralty charts, and those in Conze’s work.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
