<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0831-0808-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOIRE-INFÉRIEURE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 808</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:829528">Beds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:829474">Bedding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q80j">Ocean</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n831/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOIRE-INFÉRIEURE</label>, a maritime department of western
                    France, is made up of a portion of Brittany on the right and of the district of
                    Retz on the left of the Loire, and lies between 46° 45' and 47° 40' N. lat. and
                    between 55' and 2° 32' W. long., being bounded on the W. by the ocean, on the N.
                    by Morbihan and Ille-et-Vilaine, on the E. by Maine-et-Loire, and on the S. by
                    Vendée. Its greatest length from east to west is 76 miles, its greatest breadth
                    65 miles, and its area 2654 square miles. The surface is very flat, and the
                    highest point, in the north on the borders of Ille-et-Vilaine, is only 377 feet.
                    The line of hillocks skirting the right bank of the Loire, and known as the
                    “sillon de Bretagne,” nowhere attains a height of 265 feet; below Savenay they
                    recede from the river, and the meadows give place to peat bogs. North of St
                    Nazaire the Grande Brière, measuring 9 miles by 6, and rising scarcely 10 feet
                    above the sea-level, still supplies old trees which can be used for joiner work;
                    a few scattered villages occur on the more elevated spots, but communication is
                    effected chiefly by means of the canals which intersect it. The district on the
                    south of the Loire lies equally low; its most salient feature is the lake of
                    Grandlieu, covering an area of 27 square miles, and surrounded by low and marshy
                    ground, but so shallow (6 ’ 5 feet at most) that drainage would be comparatively
                    easy. The Loire has a course of 68 miles within the department; its width above
                    Nantes varies from 1300 to 3280 feet, and its volume at Nantes, where the tide
                    begins to be felt, is never under 700 cubic metres per second. It has numerous
                    islands. At Paimboeuf it is nearly 2 miles broad, but narrows again opposite St
                    Nazaire before finally entering the ocean. The bed is not sufficiently regular
                    to allow easily the passage of vessels drawing more than 10 feet of water. On
                    the left bank a canal of 9 miles is about to be opened between Pellerin, where
                    the dikes which protect the Loire valley from inundation terminate, and
                    Paimboeuf. The principal towns on the river within the department are Ancenis,
                    Nantes, and St Nazaire (one of the most important commercial ports of France) on
                    the right, and Paimboeuf on the left. The chief affluents are on the right the
                    Erdre and on the left the Sèvre, both debouching at Nantes. The Erdre has a
                    succession of broad lakes which give it the appearance of a first class river;
                    it forms part of the canal from Nantes to Brest The Sèvre, on the other hand, is
                    hemmed in by picturesque hills; at the point where it enters the department it
                    flows past the famous castle of Clisson. Apart from the Loire itself, the only
                    navigable channel of importance within the department is the Nantes and Brest
                    canal already referred to, fed by the Isac, a tributary of the Vilaine, which
                    separates Loire-Inférieure from Ille-et-Vilaine and Morbihan. The climate
                    partakes of the general Armorican character in respect of humidity, but is
                    Girondine in its mildness. At Nantes the mean annual temperature is 54 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> o,</hi> 7 Fahr., and there are one hundred and twenty-two
                    rainy days, the annual rainfall being 25 ’ 6 inches. Of the entire area nearly
                    two-thirds is arable; one-seventh is occupied by meadows; and vineyards, woods,
                    heath, lakes, pools, and marshes occupy the remainder.</p>
                <p>The quantity of live stock is considerable:—320,000 horned cattle, 180,000 sheep,
                    80,000 pigs, 38,000 horses, asses, and mules. Poultry also is reared, and there
                    is a good deal of bee-keeping. Wheat, rye, buckwheat, oats, and potatoes are
                    produced in great abundance; leguminous plants are also largely cultivated,
                    especially near Nantes. Beetroot, hemp, and chestnuts represent, along with wine
                    and cider, the chief remaining agricultural products. The woods are of oak in
                    the interior and pine on the coast. The department has deposits of tin, lead,
                    and iron, which are hardly wrought, if at all. North-west from Ancenis a little
                    anthracite is obtained from a coal-bed which is a prolongation of that of Anjou.
                    The salt marshes, about 6000 acres in all, occur for the most part between the
                    mouth of the Vilaine and the Loire, and on the Bay of Bourgneuf. The salt
                    manufacture, which as late as 1874 produced 43,475 tons, is now decaying. There
                    are slate quarries in the north-east of the department, and the granite of the
                    sea-coast and of the Loire up to Nantes is quarried for large blocks, while the
                    limestone about Chateaubriant occupies numerous kilns. The industries of the
                    department are well developed: steam-engines are built for Government at Indret,
                    a few miles below Nantes; the forges of Basse-Indre are in good repute for the
                    quality of their iron; and the production of the lead-smelting works at Couéron
                    amounts to several millions of francs annually. There are also considerable
                    foundries at Nantes, Chantenay, and St Nazaire, and shipbuilding yards at
                    Nantes, St Nazaire, Paimboeuf, and Croisic. Among other industries may be
                    mentioned the preparation of pickles and preserved meats at Nantes, the curing
                    of sardines at Croisic and in the neighbouring communes, salt-refining, the
                    great sugar refinery at Nantes, and the tobacco manufacture also there. Fishing
                    is prosecuted along the entire coast. Nantes, formerly one of the most important
                    of French ports, has now given way before St Nazaire, the trade of which in 1878
                    exceeded 1,500,000 tons. The principal imports are coal, colonial wares, wood,
                    metals,, manure; the exports are wine, salt, preserved meats and pickles, flour,
                    refined sugar, and butter. The department is divided into five
                    arrondissements—Nantes, Ancenis, Chateaubriant, Paimboeuf, and St Nazaire;
                    Nantes is the capital. The population in 1876’ was 612,972, an increase of
                    243,667 since 1801.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
