<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0295-0280-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LANDSEER, Sir Edwin Henry (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    280)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w66">Cat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0743s">Winds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nx59">Gifts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd61">Dog</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:849374">Cats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175820">Winds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817559">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n295/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LANDSEER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Edwin Henry</hi></label>
                    (1802-1873), third son of John Landseer, A.R.A., a well-known engraver and able
                    writer on art, was born in London, March 7, 1802. His mother was Miss Potts, who
                    sat to Reynolds as the gleaner, with a sheaf of corn on her head, in Macklin’s
                    Family Picture, or the Cottagers.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>John Landseer died February 29, 1852, aged ninety-one.
                            Sir Edwin’s eldest brother Thomas, an A.R.A. and a famous engraver,
                            whose interpretations of his junior’s pictures have made them known
                            throughout the world, and will represent them when they have perished,
                            was born in 1796, and died January 20, 1880. Charles Landseer, R.A., and
                            Keeper of the Royal Academy, the second brother, was bom in 1799, and
                            died July 22, 1879. John Landseer’s brother Henry was a painter of some
                            reputation, who emigrated to Australia.</p></note> Edwin Henry Landseer
                    began his artistic education under his father so successfully that in his fifth
                    year he drew fairly well, and was acquainted with animal characters and
                    passions. Etchings of his, at South Kensington, dated by his father, attest that
                    he drew excellently at eight years of age; at ten he was an admirable
                    draughtsman, and his etchings show considerable sense of humour. At thirteen he
                    drew a majestic St Bernard dog so finely that his brother Thomas engraved and
                    published the work. At this date (1815) he sent two pictures to the Academy, and
                    was described in the catalogue as “Master Ε. Landseer, 33 Foley Street.” Youth
                    forbade his being reckoned as an artist in full, and caused him to be considered
                    as the “Honorary Exhibitor” of “No. 443, Portrait of a Mule.” and “No. 584,
                    Portraits of a Pointer Bitch and Puppy.” Adopting the advice of Haydon, whose
                    pupil he was not otherwise, he studied the Elgin Marbles, the “Wild Beasts” in
                    the Tower and Exeter Change, and dissected every animal whose carcase he could
                    obtain. In 1816. in which year he exhibited with the Society of Painters in Oil
                    and Water Colours, Landseer was admitted a student of the Royal Academy. In 1817
                    he sent to the Academy a portrait of Old Brutus, a much-favoured dog, which, as
                    well as his son, another Brutus, often appeared in subsequent pictures. Even at
                    this date Landseer enjoyed considerable reputation, and had more work than he
                    could readily perform, because his renown had been zealously fostered by his
                    father in Elmes’s <hi rend="italic">Annals of Art.</hi> At the Academy he was a
                    diligent student and a favourite of Fuseli’s, who would look about the crowded
                    antique school and ask, “Where is my little <hi rend="italic">dοy</hi> boy!” The
                    prices of his pictures at this time were comparatively small; ten guineas was,
                    in 1818, considered enough for a whole length figure of a horse on a canvas of
                    27 by 35 inches, which now belongs to Lady C. Wellesley.</p>
                <p>In 1818 Landseer exhibited at Spring Gardens Fighting Dogs getting Wind, a
                    picture from which his future might have been predicted. The sale of this work
                    to Sir G. Beaumont vastly enhanced the fame of the painter, who became “the
                    fashion” in a way disclosed by Haydon’s account of his own and Wilkie’s
                    positions under similar circumstances nearly at the same date. This picture is
                    now at Coleorton, and it illustrates the culmination of the studies of
                    Landseer’s youth and the prime strength of his earlier style. Unlike the
                    productions of his later life, this masterpiece of his boyhood exhibits not an
                    iota of sentiment; but it is, in its way, a proof of astonishing vigour in
                    design, and richer in animal character than anything produced since the death of
                    Snyders. Perfectly drawn, solidly and minutely finished, bold in tone, and
                    carefully composed, the execution of this picture attested the skill that had
                    been acquired during ten years’ studies from nature, and the learning with which
                    diligent observation of the best antiques and of Raphael had endowed the
                    painter. Looking at the work as a whole, and valuing it on technical grounds,
                    the critic feels that Landseer never produced anything better or so manly. On
                    this level he stood until 1824, when he removed from his father’s residence, and
                    set up for himself in the house No. 1 (afterwards 18) St John’s Wood Road, where
                    he lived nearly fifty years, and in which he died. In 1818 it was little more
                    than a cottage, with a barn attached, which was converted into a studio. Between
                    1818 and 1825 Landseer did a great deal of work, but on the whole gained little
                    besides facility of technical expression, a greater zest for humour, and a
                    larger style. The work of this stage ended with the production of Lord Essex’s
                    painting called the Cat’s Paw, which is well known by an engraving. It was the
                    price of this picture, £100, that enabled Landseer to set up for himself. He had
                    to borrow a second hundred pounds to pay a premium for the house, and repaid
                    this sum by twenty pounds at a time. Between 1818 and 1825 Landseer’s pictures
                    were such as proved the severity of his studies; among them the principal were
                    the Cat Disturbed, which was lately in the possession of Sir P. de Malpas Grey
                    Egerton; Alpine Mastiffs reanimating a Distressed Traveller, a famous work
                    engraved by John Landseer; the Ratcatchers, which is now at Lambton Castle;
                    Pointers to be; the Larder invaded; and Neptune, the head and shoulders of a
                    Newfoundland dog. The Cat’s Paw was sent to the British Institution in 1824, and
                    made an enormous sensation. In this year Landseer and C. R. Leslie made a
                    journey to the Highlands,—a momentous visit for the former, who thenceforward
                    rarely failed annually to repeat it in search of studies and subjects.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n296/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0296-0281"/>
                <p>In 1826 Landseer was elected an Λ.R.A. In 1827 appeared the Monkey who had seen
                    the World, a picture which marked the growth of a taste for humorous subjects in
                    the mind of the painter, and had been evoked by the success of the Cat’s Paw,
                    Taking a Buck, 1825, was the painter’s first Scottish picture. Its execution
                    marked a change in his style which, in increase of largeness, was a great
                    improvement. In other respects there was a decrease of solid qualities; finish,
                    searching modelling, and elaborate draughtsmanship rarely appeared in Landseer’s
                    work after 1823. The subject, as such, soon after this time became a very
                    distinct element in his pictures; ultimately it dominated, and in effect the
                    popularity of the artist was extended in a greater degree than technical
                    judgment justified. Sentiment gave new charms to his works, which had previously
                    depended on the expression of animal passion and character, and the exhibition
                    of noble qualities of draughtsmanship. Sentimentality ruled in not a few
                    pictures of later dates, and <hi rend="italic">quasi</hi> human humour, or
                    pathos, superseded that masculine animalism which rioted in its energy, and
                    enabled the artist to rival Snyders, if not Velazquez, as a painter of beasts.
                    After High Life and Low Life, pictures of 1831, now in the National Gallery,
                    Landseer’s dogs, and even his lions and birds, were more than half civilized. It
                    was not that these later pictures were less true to nature than their
                    forerunners, but the models were chosen from different grades of animal society.
                    As Landseer prospered he kept finer company, and his new patrons did not care
                    about rat-catching and dog-fighting, however vigorously and learnedly those
                    subjects might be depicted. It cannot be said that the world lost much when, in
                    exchange for the Cat Disturbed and Fighting Dogs getting Wind, came Jack in
                    Office, the Highland Shepherd’s Chief Mourner, and the Swannery invaded by
                    Sea-Eagles, three pictures which are types of as many diverse moods of
                    Landseer’s art, and each a noble one.</p>
                <p>Four years after his election as A.R.A. Landseer was chosen an R.A. (1830). Chevy
                    Chase (1826), which is at Woburn, and the Illicit Whiskey Still (1829), appeared
                    in the interval, and were followed by High Life and Low Life (1831), and
                    Spaniels of King Charles’s Breed (1832); the list is a wonder of brush handling.
                    Landseer had by this time attained such amazing mastery that he painted Spaniel
                    and Rabbit in two hours and a half, and Rabbits, which was at the British
                    Institution, in three-quarters of an hour; and the fine dog-picture Odin (1836)
                    was the work of one sitting, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> painted within twelve
                    hours. He begin and finished a whole-length, life-size study of a fallow deer
                    while Mr Wells of Redleaf was at church. A more remarkable feat consisted in
                    drawing, simultaneously, a stag’s head with one hand and a head of a horse with
                    the other. Harvest in the Highlands, and that masterpiece of humour, Jack in
                    Office, were exhibited in 1833. In 1834 a noble work of sentiment was given to
                    the world in Suspense, which is now at South Kensington, and shows a dog
                    watching at the closed door of his wounded master. Many think this to be
                    Landseer’s finest work, others prefer the Highland Shepherd’s Chief Mourner
                    (1837). The over-praised and unfortunate Bolton Abbey, a group of portraits in
                    character, was shown in the same year, and was the first picture for which the
                    painter received £400. A few years later he sold Peace and War for £1500, and
                    for the copyrights alone obtained £6000. Man Proposes (1864) was resold in 1881
                    for 6300 guineas, and a cartoon for 5000 guineas. A Distinguished Member of the
                    Humane Society, a dog reclining on a quay wall (1838), was succeeded by Dignity
                    and Impudence (1839). The Lion Dog of Malta, and Laying down the Law appeared in
                    1840. The Defeat of Comus was painted in the summerhouse of Buckingham Palace
                    garden in 1842. In this year was finished the capital Highland Shepherd’s Home
                    (Sheepshanks Gift), together with the beautiful Eos, a portrait of Prince
                    Albert’s most graceful of greyhounds, to which Thomas Landseer added an
                    ineffable charm and solidity not in the painting. The Challenge, and Coming
                    Events cast their Shadows before, were accompanied (1844) by Shoeing (Bell
                    Gift), and followed by Peace, and War, and the Stag at Bay (1846). Alexander and
                    Diogenes, and a Random Shot, a kid dead on snow, came forth in 1848. This year
                    Landseer received a national commission to paint in the Houses of Parliament
                    three subjects connected with the chase. Although they would have been worth
                    three times as much money, the House of Commons refused to grant £1500 for these
                    pictures, and the matter fell through, more to the artist’s profit than the
                    nation’s gain. The Sanctuary, and Night and Morning, romantic and pathetic deer
                    subjects, came in due order. For the latter a French jury of experts awarded to
                    the artist the great gold medal of the Exposition Universelle, Paris, 1855.</p>
                <p>The Dialogue at Waterloo (1850) commemorated Landseer’s first visit to the
                    continent, and showed how he, like nearly all English artists of original power
                    and considerable fertility, owed nothing to French or Italian training. In the
                    same year he received the honour of knighthood. The Monarch of the Glen (1851)
                    was succeeded by Geneva, a group of asses, a mule, and a bull; Titania and
                    Bottom, which comprises a charming queen of the fairies; and the dramatic design
                    of the Combat, or Night and Morning, as above. Then came the Children of the
                    Mist (1853), Deer iu Repose, Saved (1856), Braemar, a noble stag, Rough and
                    Ready, Uncle Tom and his Wife for Sale (1857). The Maid and. the Magpie, the
                    extraordinarily large cartoon called Deer Browsing, the Twa Dogs, and one or two
                    minor paintings, were equal if not superior to any previously produced by the
                    artist. Nevertheless, signs of breaking health were remarked in Doubtful Crumbs,
                    and a Kind Star (1859). The immense and profoundly dramatic picture called a
                    Flood in the Highlands (1860) more than reinstated the painter before the
                    public, but friends still saw ground for uneasiness. Extreme nervous
                    excitability manifested itself in many ways, and in the choice (1864) of the
                    dreadful subject of Man Proposes God Disposes, bears clumsily clambering among
                    relics of Sir John Franklin’s party, there was occult pathos, which some of the
                    artist’s intimates suspected, but did not avow. In 1862 and 1863 Landseer
                    produced nothing; but with Man Proposes came a Piper and a Pair of Nutcrackers.
                    The last triumph of Landseer’s career was the Swannery invaded by Sea Eagles
                    (1869). After four years more, mainly of broken art and shattered mental powers,
                    he died 1st October 1873. He was buried in St Paul’s. See <hi rend="italic">Sir
                        E. Landseer,</hi> by F. G. Stephens, 1880. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f. g.
                        s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
