<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0829-0806-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOIRE (9th edition, volume 14, page 806)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p025">Currents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sh83">Diving</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:829774">Bees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:895767">Diving</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n829/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOIRE</label> (Lat., <hi rend="italic">Liger),</hi> the first
                    of the rivers of France in length of course (626 miles) and extent of basin
                    (44,979 square miles), has its headwaters in the great central plateau, and is
                    considered to take its rise in the Gerbier de Jonc, in the department of
                    Ardèche, at a height of 4504 feet above the sea,—though the Allier branch, which
                    has its source about 30 miles west, in the department of Lozère, at the foot of
                    Maure de la Gardille, 4668 feet above the sea, has an almost equal course. The
                    two streams continue to run parallel till the upper Loire turns westward and is
                    joined by the Allier in the neighbourhood of Nevers. All the more important
                    affluents of the upper and middle part of the Loire—as the Cher, the Indre, the
                    Vienne, respectively 198,152, and 231 miles in length—have their gathering
                    grounds in the central plateau. In the north-east the basin of the Seine comes
                    so close (at one place to within 6 or 7 miles) that the versant towards the
                    Loire has hardly anything to contribute; and it is not till within 65 miles of
                    the estuary that we find an important tributary, the Maine, bringing down the
                    drainage of the Brittany plateau. At certain seasons the Loire is navigable for
                    ships as far as Nantes (33 miles), for boats as far as LaNoirie (other 518
                    miles), and for rafts as far as Retournac; but for six months of the year
                    navigation is practically impossible.</p>
                <p>In the volume of water there is all the irregularity of a mountain torrent; at
                    the Bee d’Allier, for instance,—the meeting point of the two head streams,—while
                    the maximum current is 353,200 cubic feet per second, the minimum is 10,600
                    cubic feet, and above Orleans the range lies between 31,800 and 850. During the
                    drought of summer thin and feeble streams thread their way between the sandbanks
                    of the channel; while at other times a stupendous flood pours down and submerges
                    wide reaches of land. In the middle part of its course the Loire traverses the
                    western portion of the undulating Paris basin, with its Tertiary marls, sands,
                    and clays, and the alluvium carried off from these renders its lower channel
                    inconstant; the rest of the drainage area is occupied by crystalline rocks, over
                    the hard surface of which the water, undiminished by absorption, flows rapidly
                    into the streams. A fall of from 3 to 4 inches over the whole river basin is
                    sufficient to pour 35,320,000,000 cubic feet of water into the channels. When
                    the rain is general over the whole area, the floods on the different tributaries
                    reach the main river at different times; but when, through any cause, two or
                    more of them arrive at the same time, inundations of the most serious character
                    result. Attempts to control the river must have begun at a very early date, and
                    by the close of the Middle Ages the bed between Orleans and Angers was enclosed
                    by dykes 10 to 13 feet high. In <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n830/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0830-0807"/> 1783 a double line of dykes or <hi
                        rend="italic">turcies</hi> 23 feet high was completed from Bee d’Allier
                    downwards. This great work had, however, the serious defect that the channel was
                    so much narrowed that the embankments are almost certain to give wayas soon as
                    the water rises 16 feet (the average rise is about 14, and in 1846 it was more
                    than 22). In ιnoremodern times the importance of the water-wayfrom the sea to
                    Nantes led to the embanking of the lower part of the course; but instead of a
                    depth of 16 feet being secured, as the engineers anticipated, there is no more
                    at full tide than 13 feet. One of the practical results of this state of matters
                    has been the commercial development of Saint Nazaire and Paimboeuf, and the
                    comparative decline of Nantes as a great shipping port. Besides the general
                    embankments of the river, several of the towns along the Loire have constructed
                    special works to defend themselves against the floods; Tours, the most exposed
                    of all, is surrounded by a circular dyke. Various schemes for the systematic
                    regulation of the Loire have been discussed. It has been proposed to construct
                    in the upper valleys of the several aflluents a number of gigantic dams or
                    reservoirs from which the water, stored during flood, could be let off into the
                    river as required. A reservoir of this kind, formed by the engineer Mathieu at
                    the village of Pinay, about 18 miles above Roanne, and capable of retaining from
                    3500 to 4500 million cubic feet of water, has greatly diminished the force of
                    the floods at Roanne, and maintained the comparative equilibrium of the current
                    during the dry season. There is a canal (157 miles) along the left bank of the
                    Loire between Roanne and Briare; and the Canal du Bern connects this with the
                    navigable part of the Cher. The Canal du Centre extends from Digoιn on the Loire
                    to Châlon on the Saône; the Canal du Nivernais and the canals starting from
                    Orleans and Briare communicate with the Seine; and the Nantes canal opens up the
                    way to Lorient, Brest, and Dinan. The canals of the Sauldre and the Dive (20 and
                    26 miles respectively) are mainly for irrigation purposes.</p>
                <p>See H. Blerzy, <hi rend="italic">Torrents,</hi><hi rend="italic">fleuves, et
                        canaux de la France</hi> (Paris, 1878), and his papers in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rev. des Deux Mondes,</hi> February and March 1875.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
