<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0433-0416-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LEGHORN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 416</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:999328">Lions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1734554">Lion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n433/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LEGHORN</label> (Italian, <hi rend="italic">Livorno),</hi> a
                    city of Italy, the chief town of the province of Leghorn (which includes the
                    island of Elba), the see of a bishop, and next to Genoa and Naples the greatest
                    commercial port in the kingdom, is situated on the coast of the Ligurian Sea, in
                    43° 33' N. lat. and 10° 16' E. long., 15 miles south-west of Pisa, with which it
                    is connected by a branch from the main west coast line. It is built on low-lying
                    ground backed by a ridge of hills, of which the most striking though not the
                    highest is Monte Nero, with its ancient monastery. In some respects one of the
                    least Italian of Italian cities, Leghorn owes its prosperity as a port not so
                    much to any special advantages of situation as to wise legislation and labour.
                    Broad and well-kept streets, spacious squares, and large substantial houses are
                    the general characteristics of the city, which has room enough within the
                    circuit of its walls (built 1835-37), though it has scattered its villas on the
                    neighbouring hills and coast. Of note among the buildings are the old cathedral
                    (a Latin cross with a single nave—the façade designed by Inigo Jones), the
                    town-hall, the great oil warehouses erected by Cosmo III. in 1705, the reservoir
                    (a subterranean structure dating from the time of Ferdinand III.), and the
                    Jewish synagogue, which ranks next to that of Amsterdam. Near the port stands
                    the statue of Ferdinand I. by Giovanni dell’ Opera, with four slaves in bronze,
                    by Pietro Tacca, chained to the pedestal; and the Piazza Carlo Alberto is
                    adorned with statues of the grand dukes Ferdinand III. and Leopold II. The old
                    English cemetery (closed 1839), which was up to the present century the only
                    Protestant burial-place in Italy, contains the tombs of Smollett and Francis
                    Horner. The Torre del Marzocco, or “Tower of the Sculptured Lion,” is one of the
                    leading landmarks of the city from the sea, and almost the only relic of the
                    republican period. Among the public institutions are the “Chambers of Public
                    Payments,” similar to the London clearing-house, a large naval academy opened in
                    1881, a chamber of commerce dating from 1801, a public library of 40,000
                    volumes, and a technical and nautical institute. Great changes have been
                    effected in the port of Leghorn since the middle of the century. The “new port”
                    is formed by a breakwater finished in 1863, which extends north and south for
                    3300 feet, at a distance of 6 furlongs from the shore. It has a general depth of
                    from 24 to 32 feet. Vessels moored to the breakwater are sheltered from all
                    winds, but those in the open part of the basin are exposed to the southerly
                    gales. The inner or old port, formed by a pier projecting half a mile in a
                    northnorth-west direction from the shore, measures 1800 by 1500 feet, and is
                    perfectly secure on all sides. To the south and east lie a number of docks,
                    which in turn are connected with a system of canals complex enough to justify
                    the name Little Venice applied to part of the city. The Canale dei Navicelli
                    extends north to the Arno. Dredging operations for deepening the harbour having
                    been carried on between 1868 and 1878 with little permanent result, a much more
                    extensive and effective series of improvements (including the construction of a
                    new breakwater from the shore south of the town to the old lighthouse, and the
                    lengthening of the dry dock so as to take in the largest ships now obliged to
                    dock at Marseilles), received the Government sanction in 1881. Shipbuilding is
                    the principal local industry, and even ironclads have been sent out from the
                    dockyards. The following table shows the foreign trade of the port to have
                    declined since 1860, but a counterbalancing increase to have taken place in the
                    coasting trade :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Foreign Trade.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Coasting Trade.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Foreign Trade.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Coasting Trade.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tonnage.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tonnage.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tonnage.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ships.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Tonnage.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1801</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4.597</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>980,357</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10,108</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>’ 692,862</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1871</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,904</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>624,312</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,953</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,218,831</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1862</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5,273</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,056,350</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9,929</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>803,628</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1872</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,891</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>566,284</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8,079</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,248,250</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1863</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,977</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,012,829</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11,597</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,125,176</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1873</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,922</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>616,862</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8,858</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1.205,297</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1864</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,785</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>857,861</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8,562</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,031,054</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1874</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,545</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>382,384</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9,518</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,880,118</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1865</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,800</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>881,805</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9,016</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,111,921</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1875</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,425</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>379,845</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9,105</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,995.324</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1866</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,280</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>800,636</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8,988</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,138,681</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1876</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,448</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>383.493</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,787</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,047.348</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1867</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,357</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>612,135</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,729</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>965,053</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1877</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1.411</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>405,771</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,576</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,866,82!</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1868</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,248</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>587,471</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,865</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>998,955</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1878</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,379</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>386,510</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,125</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,826.18!)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1869</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,858</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>786,535</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,120</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>952,126</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1879</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,481</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>459,884</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,308</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,891.4!0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,151</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>644,897</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,443</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,070,542</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1880</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,361</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>466,313</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,694</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,991.183</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In the early part of the century Leghorn became a great depot of British commerce
                    with the Levant, and about twenty British firms were settled in the town. It was
                    a free port, and had an excellent bonding system. But about 1833 the increase of
                    direct intercourse between Britain and her customers began to tell on the trade,
                    and it gradually disappeared altogether. At present the activity of the port is
                    due to exportation of Italian produce (especially from Tuscany), and the
                    importation of iron, coal, fish, and general goods. Marseilles, Cardiff, and
                    Newcastle are the three ports with which the dealings are most extensive. A
                    considerable trade is also maintained with the United States. The population of
                    Leghorn city increased from 33,000 in 1807 to 83,543 in 1861; but in 1871 it was
                    80,948, and in 1881 only 77,781,—a decrease due mainly to the distribution of
                    the population beyond the city limits, especially along the coast. The communal
                    population was 97,096 in 1871, and 97,615 in 1881. Between the city and the
                    village of Ardenza are many seaside residences, occupied mostly by foreign
                    visitors during the bathing season.</p>
                <p>The earliest mention of Leghorn occurs in a document of the year 891 relating to
                    the first church; in 1017 it is called a castle. In the 13th century the Pisans
                    tried to attract a population to the spot, but it was not till the. 14th that
                    Leghorn began to be the rival of Porto Pisano, which it was destined <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n434/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0434-0417"/> ultimately to supplant. It was at Leghorn that
                    Urban V. and Gregory XL landed on their return from Avignon. When in 1405 the
                    king of France sold Pisa to the Florentines he kept possession of Leghorn; but
                    he afterwards (1407) sold it for 26,000 ducats to the Genoese, and from the
                    Genoese the Florentines purchased it in 1421. In 1496 the city showed its
                    devotion to its new masters by a successful defence against Maximilian and his
                    allies. With the rise of the Medici came a rapid increase of prosperity; Cosmo,
                    Francis, and Ferdinand erected fortifications and harbour works, warehouses and
                    churches, with equal liberality, and the last especially gave a stimulus to
                    trade by inviting ‘ ‘men of the East and the West, Spanish and Portuguese,
                    Greeks, Germans, Italians, Hebrews, Turks, Moors, Armenians, Persians, and
                    others,” to settle and traffic in the city. Declared free and neutral in 1691,
                    Leghorn was permanently invested with these privileges by the Quadruple Alliance
                    in 1718; but in 1796 Napoleon seized all the hostile vessels in its port. It
                    ceased to be a free city by law of 1867.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
