<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0894-0865-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LONG ISLAND (9th edition, volume 14, page 865)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126935">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:898076">Drift</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084913">Quakers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nk36760">Drift</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n894/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LONG ISLAND</label>, an island with an area of 1682 square
                    miles lying off the coast of the United States, between 40° 33' and 41° 10' N.
                    lat,, and forming part of the State of New York. While the length from east to
                    west is about 120 miles, the width nowhere exceeds 24 miles, and in some places
                    falls to 12 or 15. The western end is separated from the city and State of New
                    York by the East River, which is nowhere more than three quarters of a mile in
                    breadth, and has been spanned by a great suspension bridge; but between the main
                    body of the island and the mainland (Connecticut, Rhode Island) lies Long Island
                    Sound, widening out to a breadth of 20 miles. The sound, however, is
                    comparatively shallow, the depth in the eastern and seaward portion being
                    usually under 200 feet, while in the portion west of Connecticut river it is
                    nowhere more than 170 feet, and in general only 75-100 feet. Geologically the
                    island is very interesting, consisting, as it does for the most part, of an
                    immense morainal deposit of glacial drift. A range of hills extends with some
                    interruptions for about 60 miles in the line of its longer axis, varying in
                    height from 150 to 384 feet above sea-level. Fort Pond Hill for instance is 194
                    feet; Neaρeague, 135; Amagansett, 161; Shinecock, 140; Osborn’s Hill, near
                    Riverhead, 293; Ruland’s, south of Coram, 340; West Hills (Jane’s Hill), 354;
                    Layton’s Hill, 380; Westbury, 260; Hempstead</p>
                <p>Harbour Hill, 384; John M. Clarke’s Hill, 326. From the foot of the hills
                    southward stretches a vast nearly level plain, with an average height of 70
                    feet, and consisting of post-glacial stratified sand and gravel; and across this
                    run a large number of shallow parallel watercourses, remarkable mainly for the
                    regularity with which they present an elevated bank on the western side and a
                    long declivity on the eastern. On the northern side of the range the surface is
                    very uneven, some of the elevations exceeding 200 feet, and deep fiord valleys
                    stretching down to the sound, and forming a series of excellent harbours. The
                    glacial drift of Long Island is of immense depth, and contains a wonderful
                    number of boulders. “At the eastern extremity,” says Lyell on the authority of
                    Mather, “they are of such kinds of granite, gneiss, mica, slate, greenstone, and
                    syenite as may have come across the sound from parts of Rhode Island. Opposite
                    the mouth of the Connecticut river they are of such varieties of gneiss and
                    hornblende slate as correspond with the rocks of the region through which that
                    river passes. Still further west they consist of red sandstone and conglomerate
                    and the trap of that country, and lastly, adjoining the city of New York, we
                    find serpentine, red sandstone, and various granitic and crystalline rocks which
                    have come from the district immediately to the north.” One of the boulders near
                    Manhasset measures 54 feet long and 40 feet wide, and rises 16 feet above the
                    level of the soil. Of the numerous lakelets scattered throughout Long Island it
                    is enough to mention Ronkonkoma, near Lakeland, the waters of which are said to
                    decrease and increase in regular periods of four years. Much of the surface of
                    the country is still covered with wood—oak, hickory, and chestnut growing freely
                    on the unmodified drift, and pine forests extending for about fifty miles
                    through the sandy plains. A good rich loam abounds in the northern districts,
                    and the lighter soils of the south are easily rendered productive.
                    Marketgardening especially is carried on with success. The climate is
                    comparatively mild, the mean annual temperature being 49° to 51°, the maximum
                    for the year between 95° and 100°, and the minimum 4° to 8°. The average
                    rainfall is about 421 inches. Towards its western end more especially, the
                    northern coast of Long Island presents a number of important bays—Glen Cove,
                    Oyster Bay, Huntington Bay, Smithtown Bay, &lt;fcc.; the western extremity is
                    deeply bifurcated by a very irregular inlet, broken up by various islands into
                    Gardiner’s Bay, Little Peconic, and Great <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n895/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0895-0866"/> Peconic; and along a large part of the
                    southern coast stretches a remarkable series of lagoons, formed by a line of
                    dunes varying in breadth from ∣ to 1 mile, and connected at various points with
                    the ocean. These last—of which the most important is Great South Bay, 40 miles
                    long by about 5 or 6 miles wide—are of great service to the island, and an Act
                    has been passed to increase their utility by connecting them by canals. Coney
                    Island and Rockaway Beach, the most frequented of the many seaside resorts in
                    the Island, lie near the south-western extremity. As regards both birds and
                    fishes, Long Island seems a kind of meeting place between the arctic and the
                    equatorial species. In winter, for instance, it is visited by the eider-duck,
                    the little white goose, the great cormorant, and the auk, in summer by the
                    turkey buzzard, the swallow-tailed kite, and the fork-tailed flycatcher. A few
                    deer are still to be found; and various tracts of country and islands in the
                    great bays are stocked with game and fish by sportsmen’s clubs. The east portion
                    of the island is one of the chief seats of the menhaden fisheries, and the
                    oyster beds of both the north and the south coast are of great value. Those of
                    the Great South Bay (furnishing, amongst others, the famous “blue points”) alone
                    give employment in the season to 1500 fishermen. (See E. Ingersoll, “The Oyster
                    Industry,” in the <hi rend="italic">Tenth Census</hi> publications of the United
                    States, 1881.)</p>
                <p>Administratively Long Island consists of King’s County (72 square miles), Queen’s
                    County (410), and Suffolk (1200), which·in 1880 bad the following
                    population:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Total.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Male.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Female.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Native.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Foreign.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>white.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Coloured.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>King's</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>599,549</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>289,289</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>310,260</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>411,295</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>188,254</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>590,278</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9,271</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Queen’s</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>90,547</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45,760</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>44,787</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>68,556</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21,991</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>86,707</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,840</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Suffolk</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53,926</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>26,759</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27,167</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48,319</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,607</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>51,473</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,453</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Of the thirteen or fourteen Indian tribes living in the island at the time of its
                    discovery, the only remnants are about fifty Shinecocks and Montauks.</p>
                <p>Besides Brooklyn, which had 566,689 inhabitants, King’s County contained Flatbush
                    town, 7634; Flatlands town, 3127; Gravesend town (including Coney Island
                    village), 3676; New Lots town, 13,681; and New Utrecht town, 4742. In Queen’s
                    county are Flushing town, 15,919; Hempstead town (including East Rockaway,
                    Garden City, and sixteen other villages), 18,160; Jamaica town, 10,089; Long
                    Island City, 17,129; Newtown town, 9798; North Hempstead town, 7562; and Oyster
                    Bay town, 11,923. In Suffolk there are no cities, and none of the villages have
                    500 inhabitants. The “towns” are Babylon, Brookhaven, East Hampton, Huntington,
                    Islip, Riverhead, Shelter Island, Smithtown, Southampton, and Southhold. Garden
                    City was built by A. T. Stewart as a model suburban settlement, and contains a
                    fine cathedral. Hicksville is associated with the memory of Elias Hicks the
                    Quaker missionary. Sag Harbour was formerly a great whaling station, and still
                    maintains a good coasting trade. Five miles from Flushing is Creedmore rifle
                    range, the finest in the United States. On Gardiner’s Island the pirate Kidd
                    concealed the treasures partly recovered by the governor of Massachusetts in
                    1699.</p>
                <p>Long Island was so called by its Dutch discoverers in 1609, and the name Nassau,
                    bestowed in 1693 by the colonial legislature, never found popular acceptance.
                    Breucklen (Brooklyn), Amersfoort (Flatlands), Vlissingen (Flushing), Busdorf
                    (Jamaica), and New Utrecht were founded by the Dutch between 1630 and 1654; and
                    between 1640 and 1665 the English from the New England colonies established
                    Southold, Southampton, Easthampton, Hempstead, Huntington, Oyster Bay,
                    Smithtown, Islip, &amp;c. Though the charter granted by James I. in 1620
                    expressly excluded territory actually possessed or inhabited by any other
                    Christian prince or state, the grantees in 1635 conveyed to the earl of Stirling
                    among other lands the island of Matowacks or Long Island. A treaty concluded
                    between Dutch and English at Hartford (Connecticut) in 1650 suιτendered to
                    England all the land south of Oyster Bay; but, though it was ratified by the
                    states-general of Holland in 1656, no action was taken by the English
                    Government. Long Island was included in the territory assigned to the duke of
                    York in 1663-64, and in 1654 an English squadron conquered the Dutch in time of
                    peace, and set up a government in the duke’s name. When the Dutch governor, who
                    had recovered New York in 1673, issued a proclamation requiring the submission
                    of the Long Island towns, they all obeyed except the three most eastern; but the
                    treaty of Westminster in 1674 left Long Island to the English, and it became a
                    regular colony of the crown. In the beginning of the war of American
                    independence, Long Island naturally played a prominent part. The efforts made by
                    Washington to defend it were frustrated by the British under Cornwallis in 1776,
                    and it remained in their hands till the close of the contest.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
