<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0698-0675-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LINNET (9th edition, volume 14, page 675)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048356">Ornithologists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130935">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1121907">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999274">Linnets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:924818">Finches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rn70">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm43155">Finches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18t15">Seeds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p8d">Breast</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n698/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LINNET</label>, Anglo-Saxon <hi rend="italic">Liηete</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Linet-wige,</hi> whence seems to have been corrupted the
                    old Scottish “Lintquhit,” and the modern northern English
                    “Lintwhite,”—originally a somewhat generalized bird’s name, but latterly
                    specialized for the <hi rend="italic">Fringilla cannabina</hi> of Linnaeus, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Linota</hi><hi rend="italic">cannabina</hi> of recent
                    ornithologists. This is a common and well-known song-bird, frequenting almost
                    the whole of Europe south of lat. 64°, and in Asia extending to Turkestan. In
                    Africa it is known as a winter visitant to Egypt and Abyssinia, and is abundant
                    at all seasons in Barbary, as well as in the Canaries and Madeira. Though the
                    fondness of this species for the seeds of flax <hi rend="italic">(Linum)</hi>
                    and hemp <hi rend="italic">(Cannabis)</hi> has given it its common name in so
                    many European languages,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                                ><p><hi rend="italic">B.g.,</hi> French, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Linotte</hi>; German, <hi rend="italic">Hänfling</hi>; Swedish, <hi
                                rend="italic">Härnpling.</hi></p></note> it feeds largely, if not
                    chiefly, in Britain on the seeds of plants of the order <hi rend="italic"
                        >Composite,</hi> especially those growing on heaths and commons. As these
                    waste places have been gradually brought under the plough, and improved methods
                    of cultivation have been applied to all arable land, in England and Scotland
                    particularly, the haunts and means of subsistence of the Linnet have been slowly
                    but surely curtailed, and hence of late years its numbers have undergone a very
                    visible diminution throughout Great Britain, and its diminution has also been
                    aided by the detestable practice of netting it in spring—for it is a popular
                    cage-bird—so popular indeed as to require no special description. According to
                    its sex, or the season of the year, it is known as the Red, Grey, or Browh
                    Linnet, and by the earlier English writers on birds, as well as in many
                    localities at the present time, these names have been held to distinguish at
                    least two species; but there is now no question among ornithologists on this
                    point, though the conditions under which the bright crimson-red colouring of the
                    breast and crown of the cock’s spring and summer plumage is donned and doffed
                    may still be open to discussion. Its intensity seems due, however, in some
                    degree at least, to the weathering of the brown fringes of the feathers which
                    hide the more brilliant hue, and it is to be remarked that in the Atlantic
                    islands examples are said to retain their gay tints all the year round, while
                    throughout Europe there is scarcely a trace of them visible in autumn and
                    winter; but, beginning to appear in spring, they reach their greatest brilliancy
                    towards midsummer; and it is also to be remarked that they are never assumed by
                    examples in confinement. The Linnet begins to breed in April, the nest being
                    generally placed in a bush at no great distance from the ground. It is nearly
                    always a neat structure composed of fine twigs, roots, or bents, and lined with
                    wool or hair. The eggs, often six in number, are of a very pale blue marked with
                    reddish or purplish brown. Two broods seem to be commonly brought off in the
                    course of the season, and towards the end of summer the birds—the young of
                    course greatly preponderating in number—collect in large flocks and move to the
                    sea-coast, whence a large proportion depart for more southern latitudes. Of
                    these emigrants some return the following spring, and are invariably
                    recognizable by the more advanced state of their plumage, the effect presumably
                    of having wintered in countries enjoying a brighter and hotter sun.</p>
                <p>Nearly allied to the foregoing species is the Twite, so named from its ordinary
                    call-note, or Mountain-Linnet, the <hi rend="italic">Linota fiavirostris,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">L. montium</hi> of ornithologists, which can be at once
                    distinguished by its yellow bill, longer tail, and reddish-tawny throat. This
                    bird never assumes any crimson on the crown or breast, but the male has the rump
                    at all times tinged more or less with that colour. In the breeding-season it
                    seems to affect exclusively hilly and moorland districts from Herefordshire
                    northward, in which it partly or wholly replaces the common Linnet, but is very
                    much more local in its distribution, and, except in the British Islands and some
                    parts of Scandinavia, it only appears as an irregular visitant in winter. At
                    that season it may, however, be found in large flocks in the low-lying
                    countries, and as regards England even on the sea-shore. In Asia it seems to be
                    represented by a kindred form, <hi rend="italic">L. brevirostris.</hi></p>
                <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Redpolls</hi><hi rend="italic">(g.v.)</hi> form a little
                    group placed by many authorities in the genus <hi rend="italic">Linota,</hi> to
                    which they are unquestionably closely allied, but in this work they may be
                    considered later; and, as before stated <hi rend="smallcaps">(Finch,</hi> vol.
                    xi. p. 192), the Linnets seem on the other hand to be related to the birds of
                    the genus <hi rend="italic">Lι mosticte,</hi> the species of which, in number
                    uncertain, inhabit the northern parts of NorthWest America and of Asia. The most
                    recent list of the birds of the former country by Mr Ridgway <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Bull.</hi><hi rend="italic">U.</hi><hi rend="italic">S. Nat. Museum,</hi>
                    No. 21, 1881) includes four species and one local race, of which there is need
                    here to mention, only <hi rend="italic">L. tephrocotis.</hi> It is generally of
                    a chocolate colour, tinged on some parts with pale crimson or pink, and has the
                    crown of the head silvery-grey. Another species, <hi rend="italic">L.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">arctoa,</hi> was formerly said to have occurred in North
                    America, but its proper home is in the Kurile Islands or Kamchatka. This has no
                    red in its plumage. The birds of the genus <hi rend="italic">Leucosticte</hi>
                    seem to be more terrestrial in their habit than those of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Linota,</hi> perhaps from their having been chiefly observed where trees
                    are scarce; but it is possible that the mutual relationship of the two groups is
                    more apparent than real Allied to <hi rend="italic">Leucosticte</hi> is <hi
                        rend="italic">Montifringilla</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> l</hi><pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0699-0676"/> ta which belongs the Snow-Finch of the Alps,
                        <hi rend="italic">Μ. nivalis,</hi> so often mistaken by travellers for the
                    Snow-Bunting, <hi rend="italic">Plectrophanes nivalis.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
