<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0765-0742-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOANGO (9th edition, volume 14, page 742)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032594">Nanga</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847246">Cardisoma</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1051793">Palms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t429">Palms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n765/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOANGO</label>, in the wider signification of the name, is a
                    region on the west coast of southern Africa, which extends from the mouth of the
                    Congo (Zaire) river in 6° S. lat. northwards through about two degrees, with no
                    very definite limit in this direction, unless we adopt the Numbi river which
                    falls into Chilunga Bay in 4° 9' S. lat., and was formerly considered the
                    northern boundary of the Loango kingdom. In a narrower sense it is the country
                    bounded on the S. by the Luemma, and on the N. by the Kuilu,—the district
                    between the Luemma andtheChiloango being known as Chiloango or Little Loango,
                    that between the Chiloango and the Congo as Kakongo and Angoy, and that to the
                    north of the Kuilu as Chilunga. The whole country between 6° and 4° may be
                    described as the lowland portion of the seaward versant of the Serra do Crystal
                    or Serra Complida, a range running almost parallel with the coast, from which
                    its spurs and underfalls are distant only 30 or 40 miles. It has an irregularly
                    undulating or hilly surface, slowly rising in somewhat indefinite terraces, and
                    is traversed from north-east to south-west by a number of considerable streams
                    flowing in well-marked valleys. The coast-line in some stretches is low and
                    swampy, while in others, as along Loango and Kabinda Bays, it presents a series
                    of cliffs 40 to 50 feet high. Behind the region of alluvial deposits which
                    prevails for some distance inland there is a broken belt of Tertiary rocks; but
                    these soon give place to laterite, and beyond the laterite lie the micaschists,
                    talcs, and gneiss of which the mountains are composed. Of the Loango rivers the
                    best explored is the Kuilu or Quillu. At its mouth, in 4° 29' S. lat., it is a
                    noble stream 1100 feet wide, but the bar has hitherto proved an insuperable
                    obstacle to the entrance of sea-going ships; near the Mayombe factory, which may
                    be reached in fifteen hours from the coast, it begins to take the character of a
                    mountain stream. Its principal affluent is the Nanga. Farther south are the
                    Songolo and the Luemma. Of greater importance as a navigable route towards the
                    interior is the Chiloango or Loango Luse (sometimes erroneously called the
                    Kakongo), which disembogues in 5° 12' S. lat. and 12° 5' E. long., and is formed
                    about 15 miles inland by the junction of the Loango and the Lukula, of which the
                    one separates Loango proper from the Osobo country and the other the Osobo
                    country from Kakongo.</p>
                <p>Though a large proportion of the Loango coast region is occupied by primeval
                    forest, with trees rising to a height of 150 and 200 feet, there is considerable
                    variety of scenery—open lagoons, mangrove swamps, scattered clusters of trees,
                    park-like reaches, dense walls of tangled underwood along the rivers, prairies
                    of tall grass through which no pathway can be driven, and patches of
                    cultivation. Among the more characteristic forms of vegetation are baobabs,
                    silkcotton trees, screw-pines, and palms—especially <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hyphaene</hi><hi rend="italic">guineensis</hi> (a fan-palm), <hi
                        rend="italic">Raphia</hi> (the wine-palm), and <hi rend="italic">Elaeis g
                        urne</hi><hi rend="italic">ensis</hi> (the oil-palm). Anonaceous plants
                    (notably <hi rend="italic">Anona senegalensis)</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >↑λιεpallabanda,</hi> an olive-myrtle-like tree, are common in the prairies;
                    the papyrus shoots up to a height of 20 feet along the rivers (particularly the
                    Luemma); the banks are fringed by the cottony <hi rend="italic">Hibiscus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">tiliaceus,</hi> ipomaeas, and fragrant jasmines; and the
                    thickets are bound together in one inextricable mass by lianas of many kinds.
                    Among the fruit trees are the mango and the papaw; the orange has been
                    successfully introduced at Vista and Kabinda; and the lemon continues to
                    flourish well up the country. Negro-pepper (a variety of capsicum) and ginger
                    grow wild; the natives, in addition to manioc (their staple sustenance) and
                    bananas, cultivate groundnuts and tobacco; and the planters have European
                    vegetables in their gardens.</p>
                <p>The crocodile, thehippopotamus, andseveralkindsof apes—including the chimpanzee
                    and the rare gorilla—are the most noteworthy larger animals; the birds are
                    various and beautiful—grey parrots, shrikes, fly-catchers, rhinoceros birds,
                    weaver birds (often in large colonies on the palm-trees), ice-birds, from the
                        <hi rend="italic">Cecyle Sharρii</hi> to the dwarfish <hi rend="italic"
                        >Alcedo cristata,</hi> butterfly-finches, and helmet-birds <hi rend="italic"
                        >CΓuracus giganteus),</hi> not to mention doves, snipes, and other more
                    familiar types. Snakes are extremely common— <hi rend="italic">Caucus
                        rhombeatus, Atractaspis irregularis, Dendraspis Jamesonii, Dasypeltis
                        palmarum,</hi> &amp;c.; but they give comparatively little trouble. The
                    curious climbing-fish, which frequents the mangroves, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pteropterus</hi> or lung-fish, which lies in the mud in a state of lethargy
                    during the dry season, the strange and poisonous <hi rend="italic">Tetrodon
                        guttifer,</hi> and the herring-like <hi rend="italic">Bellona africana,</hi>
                    often caught in great shoals—are the more remarkable of the fishes. Oysters are
                    got in abundance from the lagoons, and the Portuguese fatten the huge <hi
                        rend="italic">Cardisoma</hi><hi rend="italic">armatum</hi> or heart-crab for
                    table. Fireflies and unfortunately also mosquitoes and sandflies are among the
                    most familiar forms of insect life; the bird spider among the rarer. A kind of
                    ant builds very striking pent-house or umbrella-shaped nests rising on the tree
                    trunks one above the other like the roofs of a Chinese pagoda.</p>
                <p>Well-built and tall (average height of the men 5’5 feet, of the women 5 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 2), strongly dolichocephalous and very thick of
                    skull, never black but of various shades of warm brown with the faintest
                    suggestion of purple, the Bafiote (as the natives of the Loango coast call
                    themselves) are on the whole very favourable specimens of the Negro stock to
                    which they belong. Their black curly hair never becomes white with age, and grey
                    only in the case of very old people. Baldness is quite unknown, and many of the
                    men wear beards. Physical deformity is extremely rare. Like the west-coast
                    negroes in general the Bafiote have a ghastly and grotesque belief in fetiches
                    and witchcraft; and their gangas or priests employ the cassa (nkassa) <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n766/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0766-0743"/> ordeal with such recklessness that for every
                    grown-up person who dies a natural death three or four, it is estimated, perish
                    by this judgment of the invisible powers. A custom which readily catches the eye
                    of the foreigner is that of setting their marriageable maidens forth to view in
                    a little bower specially erected in front of the parents’ dwelling—their skins
                    stained red with a peculiar powder. Near Chinchoxo there is a curious tribe, the
                    Mavumbu or Umwambu, known to Europeans as Black Jews on account of their
                    strikingly Semitic features. The coast people proper or Bavilli look down on
                    their more inland neighbours as less civilized; and these in their turn pay the
                    same compliment to those beyond,—the Bayombe and Bayaka, who occupy the
                    mountainous woodland on the borders of Loango, being reckoned as genuine
                    savages.</p>
                <p>The people are scattered throughout the country in small villages; Nkondo,
                    probably the largest, contains only 350 to 400 huts, though it is the seat of
                    one of the most influential “princes.” There is no town or village of
                    Loango,—the place of that name on Loango Bay being a mere group of factories.
                    Buri, Boari, or Boali, was the name of the former capital; Loangiri or Loangele
                    (visited in 1873 by Bastian) was the burial-place of the ancient kings; and
                    Lubu, which is still neutral in war, is that of the “princes.” At one time
                    included in the great Congo kingdom, Loango became independent about the close
                    of the 16th century, and was still of considerable importance in the days of
                    Abbé Proyart (1750), though Kakongo and other districts were practically
                    independent. At present there is no central authority in the country; the petty
                    local chiefs are local chiefs and nothing more; but the members of the blood
                    royal are still honoured with special privileges, a large number of nominal
                    titles remain in use, and a common tradition of greatness gives a sort of
                    cohesion to the political conglomerate.</p>
                <p>The slave trade was longer maintained in Loango than anywhere else on the West
                    African seaboard; and since its extirpation palm oil and india-rubber have been
                    the main objects of commerce. Perfect freedom of trade prevails; and there are
                    Dutch, Portuguese, German, French, and English factories on the coast and up the
                    rivers. The Portuguese have made considerable efforts to secure territorial
                    supremacy; but they have hitherto failed, partly owing to direct French
                    opposition, partly to the state of the country.</p>
                <p>The following are the principal stations of European trade :— Banana at the mouth
                    of the Congo, the central post of the Rotterdam African Trading Company, whose
                    comptoirs are scattered along a vast extent of the west coast; Muanda, with one
                    of the best of the native villages; Vista; Kabinda, the natives of which are
                    known as far south as Mossamedes for their enterprise and skill as car-? enters,
                    tailors, &amp;c.; Landana, the seat of Dutch, French, and 'ortuguese factories,
                    and of a French mission from the Gaboon; and Chincho or Tchinchotcho (5° 9' 14"
                    S. lat., 12°3' 45" E. long.) the post occupied by the German Exploring
                    Expedition in 1873-76.</p>
                <p>See, besides Merolla and Battel (Pinkerton, vol. it), Proyart, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de Loango,</hi> Paris, 1766 (also in
                    Pinkerton); X&gt;egrandprc, <hi rend="italic">Reise nach der westlichen Küste
                        von Afrika,</hi> Weimar, 1801; Bastian, <hi rend="italic">Die deutsche
                        Expedition an der Loango-Küste,</hi> Jena, 1874-75; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Die Loango-Expedition,</hi> by Dr Paul Güssfeldt (1879), Julius Falkenstein
                    (1879), and Pechuel-Loesche (1882).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
