<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0914-0661-0640-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LILBURNE, John (9th edition, volume 14, page
                    640)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084913">Quakers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010806">Martens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1077103">Prisoners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m93h">Martens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q37b">Prisons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n661/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LILBURNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1618-1657),
                    an English sectary and prolific pamphleteer, was the younger son of a gentleman
                    of good family in the county of Durham, and was born in 1618. At the age of
                    twelve he was apprenticed to a clothier in London, but he appears to have paid
                    only slight attention to business, and to have early addicted himself to the
                    “contention, novelties, opposition of government, and violent and bitter
                    expressions” for which he afterwards became so conspicuous as to provoke the
                    saying of Marten that, “if the world was emptied of all but John Lilburn,
                    Lilburn would quarrel with John, and John with Lilburn.” He appears at one time
                    to have been law-clerk to Prynne. In February 1638, for the part he had taken in
                    importing and circulating the <hi rend="italic">Merry Litany</hi> and other
                    publications of Bastwick and Prynne, offensive to the bishops, he was sentenced
                    to be publicly whipped from the Fleet prison to Palace Yard, Westminster, there
                    to stand for two hours in the pillory, and afterwards to be kept in jail until a
                    fine of £500 had been paid. Though gagged at the pillory, and confined in
                    prison, he was not the man to give up his opinions or forego the pleasure of
                    expressing them, and in the following year he did not improve his prospects of a
                    speedy release by the kind of literary activity to which he devoted his enforced
                        leisure.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="italic">Come out of Her, My People: or An Answer to the
                                Questions of α Gentlewoman, a professor in the Anti-Christian Church
                                of England, about Hearing the public Ministers; where it is largely
                                discussed, and proved to be unlawful. Also a Just Apology for the
                                way of Total Separation, commonly but falsely called “Brownisrn”;
                                that it is the truth of God though lightly esteemed in the eyes of
                                the world. With a challenge to dispute them publicly before King and
                                Council, to prove whatsoever I have said at the pillory against
                                them: viz., that the calling of them is</hi> jure Diaboli, <hi
                                rend="italic">even from the Devil himself. By me John Dilburne,
                                close prisoner in the Fleet for the cause of Christ. Printed in the
                                year of hope of England's Purgation and the Prelates'
                                Dissolu-t'on,</hi> 1639.</p></note> In point of fact he did not
                    regain his liberty until November 7, 1640, when one of the earliest recorded
                    speeches of Oliver <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n662/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0914-0662-0641"/> Cromwell was made in support of his petition
                    to the House of Commons. In 1641 he received an indemnity of £3000. He now
                    entered the army, and in 1642 was taken prisoner at Brentford and tried for his
                    life; sentence would no doubt have been executed had not the parliament by
                    threatening reprisals forced his exchange. He soon rose to the rank of
                    lieutenant-colonel, but in April 1645, having become dissatisfied with the
                    general conduct of affairs, and especially with the predominance of
                    Presbyterianism, he resigned his commission, presenting at the same time to the
                    Commons a petition for considerable arrears of pay. His violent language in
                    Westminster Hall about the speaker and other public men led in the following
                    July to his arrest and committal to Newgate, whence he was discharged, however,
                    without trial, by order of the House, in October. In January 1647 he was again
                    committed to the Tower for accusations which he had brought against Cromwell,
                    but was again set at liberty in time to become a disappointed spectator of the
                    failure of the levelling or ultrademocratic party in the army at the Ware
                    rendezvous in the following December. The scene produced a deep impression on
                    his mind, and in February 1649 he along with other petitioners presented to the
                    House of Commons a paper entitled <hi rend="italic">The Serious Apprehensions of
                        a part of the People on behalf of the Commonwealth,</hi> which he followed
                    up with a pamphlet, <hi rend="italic">England's New Chains Discovered</hi>
                    (March 1, 1649), criticizing Ireton, and another exposing the conduct of
                    Cromwell, Ireton, and other leaders of the army since June 1647 <hi
                        rend="italic">{The Hunting of the Poxes from Newmarket and Triploe Heath to
                        Whitehall by Five Small Beagles,</hi> the “beagles” being Lilburne, Overton,
                    Walwyn, Prince, and another). Finally, the <hi rend="italic">Second Part of
                        England's New Chains Discovered,</hi> a violent outburst against “the
                    dominion of a council of state, and a constitution of a new and unexperienced
                    nature,” became the subject of discussion in the House, and led anew to the
                    imprisonment of its author in the Tower on April 11. His trial in the following
                    October, on a charge of seditious and scandalous practices against the state,
                    resulted in his unanimous acquittal, followed by his release in November. In
                    January 1652, for printing and publishing a petition against Sir Arthur Hasilrig
                    and the Haberdasher’s Hall for what he conceived to have been an injury done to
                    his uncle George Lilburne in 1649, he was sentenced to pay fines amounting to
                    £7000, and moreover to be banished the Commonwealth, with prohibition of return
                    under the pain of death. In June 1653 he nevertheless came back from the Low
                    Countries, where he had busied himself during the interval in pamphleteering and
                    such other agitation as was possible, and was immediately arrested; the trial,
                    which was protracted from July 13 to August 20, indeed issued in his acquittal,
                    to the great joy of London, but it was nevertheless thought proper to keep him
                    in captivity for “the peace of the nation.” He was detained successively in the
                    Tower, in a castle at Jersey, and in Dover Castle. At Dover he came under Quaker
                    influence, and signified his readiness at last to be done with “carnal sword
                    fightings and fleshly bustlings and contests”; and in 1656, on giving security
                    for his good behaviour, he was set free. He now settled at Eltham in Kent,
                    frequently preaching at Quaker meetings in the place and neighbourhood during
                    the brief remainder of his troubled life. He died on August 29, 1657.</p>
                <p>See Masson, <hi rend="italic">Life of Milton,</hi> who refers (iv. 120) also to
                    Walker <hi rend="italic">(History of Independency,</hi> ii. 247), Godwin <hi
                        rend="italic">(Commonwealth,</hi> iii. 163-177), and Bisset <hi
                        rend="italic">(Omitted Chapters of the History of England,</hi> 191-251),
                    and adds, “Mr Bisset relates Lilburne’s trial (in 1649) at length, with copious
                    extracts, and makes John more of a hero than Godwin does, though Godwin is not
                    unfavourable. On the whole, I like him myself, and am glad that he is in the
                    history of England, but think he was an ass.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
