<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0785-0762-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOCKHART, John Gibson</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 762</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n785/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOCKHART, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Gibson</hi></label>
                    (1794-1854), was born in the manse of Cambusnethan in Lanarkshire, where his
                    father, Dr Lockhart, was minister. His mother was daughter of the Rev. John
                    Gibson, minister of St Cuthbert’s, Edinburgh. In 1796 his father was transferred
                    to Glasgow, where John Lockhart was reared and educated. He derived his rare
                    abilities from his mother, and his first regular teaching from the High School
                    of Glasgow. He appears to have been from the first distinguished as a clever,
                    but by no means industrious boy. Like most clever boys he read everything that
                    came in his way; and what he had once devoured he never forgot; for his memory
                    was so retentive that, in after life, like Macaulay and Sir George Lewis, he
                    seldom found it necessary to verify a passage for quotation. No livelier boy
                    than John Lockhart ever lived; in or out of school his sense of fun and humour,
                    expressed in joke, sarcasm, and pencil caricatures, was irrepressible. At the
                    same time, however merry and mischievous, he was a proud and reserved boy; and
                    this was the side he mostly turned to the outer world as a man. The struggle
                    between a very affectionate nature and a determination not to show his feelings,
                    or perhaps an incapacity to give way to them, cost him dear. A younger brother
                    and sister were carried off within a few days of each other. John appeared to
                    bear the loss like a stoic, but he fell seriously ill, and had to be removed
                    finally from the High School. On his recovery, though still under twelve years
                    of age, he was entered at college, where he sketched the professor for the
                    amusement of his companions, as he had sketched the masters before. When
                    examination time came, he astonished all by a display of erudition, especially
                    in Greek authors, of the acquisition of which he had given no signs; a Snell
                    exhibition, just vacant at Oxford, was accordingly offered to him and
                    accepted.</p>
                <p>Lockhart was not turned fourteen when he was entered at Balliol. College, but he
                    soon asserted his character and his powers. His fun and satire made him at once
                    popular and formidable, while beyond the regular studies of the place he
                    acquired a great store of extra knowledge. He read French, Italian, German, and
                    Spanish, was curious in classical and British antiquities, and well versed in
                    heraldic and genealogical lore. Lockhart went up to the schools in the Easter
                    term of 1813—not nineteen years of age—and, notwithstanding the most audacious
                    employment of part of his time in caricaturing the examiners, he came out first
                    in classics. The name of Henry Hart Milman, a subsequent friend through life,
                    stood next his. For mathematics he never had the least inclination.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n786/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0786-0763"/>
                <p>He now quitted Oxford, and before settling to the study of Scottish law, for
                    which his father had designed him, he indulged a long cherished wish to visit
                    Germany. His knowledge of German had introduced him to the great band of poets
                    and scholars who had suddenly exalted the fame of German literature. Lockhart
                    had no means to undertake the journey; but here his reputation came to his aid.
                    A proposal to translate Frederick Schlegel’s <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the
                    Study of History</hi> was accepted by Mr Blackwood, and the price of the labour
                    paid before a liue was written. Lockhart always spoke of this as a most generous
                    act on “Ebony’s” part, and his friendship with the liberal publisher lasted
                    through life. He meanwhile paid his visit to Germany, was introduced to Goethe
                    at Weimar, traversed France and the Netherlands, made careful observations on
                    pictures and architecture, and returned to Edinburgh to study law by the time he
                    was twenty-one. In 1816 he was called to the bar. But he had no friends among
                    writers and attorneys, his brilliant powers of conversation did not comprise
                    that of public speaking, and few, if any, briefs came in. His habits of
                    observation, however, turned the time to a use afterwards exemplified in <hi
                    rend="italic">Peter's Letters.</hi></p>
                <p>Edinburgh was then the stronghold of the Whig party. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Edinburgh Review</hi> was their organ, and it was not till 1817 that the Scotch
                    Tories found a national channel of assertion and defence—namely, in <hi
                    rend="italic">Blackwood's Magazine.</hi> This periodical held its way dully
                    enough with its first numbers, when suddenly an outburst of wit and ridicule
                    directed against the hitherto unchallenged writers of the Whig party, surpassing
                    them in cleverness and equalling them in personalities, electrified the
                    Edinburgh world. Wilson (Christopher North), Hogg (the Ettrick Shepherd), and
                    Lockhart had joined the staff, and retaliation for long pent-up wrongs began.
                    Lockhart’s pen contributed scholarly papers on various subjects, including
                    hearty criticism and eulogium on Coleridge, Wordsworth, and other victims of a
                    <hi rend="italic">Review</hi> which could find only scant praise even for Walter
                    Scott. His translations also of the Spanish ballads appeared for the greater
                    part in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood.</hi> But his pen was more often dipped in
                    caustic, dealing out attacks and recriminations which led to regrettable
                    consequences. Meanwhile the gifted and handsome young man, for Lockhart’s head
                    was cast in the highest type of brilliant manly beauty, had attracted the notice
                    of Walter Scott. They met first in 1818. The acquaintance soon ripened into
                    friendship, and that friendship led to the union between Lockhart and Scott’s
                    eldest daughter, Sophia, in April 1820. For more than five years after his
                    marriage Lockhart tasted the best form of domestic happiness. Winters spent in
                    Edinburgh and summers at a cottage fitted up for them at pretty Chiefswood, near
                    Abbotsford, gave the young couple the constant enjoyment of friendship, society,
                    and even worldly distinction, added to the blessing of a perfect home. At
                    Chiefswood Lockhart’s two eldest children, John Hugh and Charlotte, were born;
                    Walter, later, at Brighton.</p>
                <p>Between 1818, when he joined the <hi rend="italic">Blackwood</hi> staff, and 1825
                    Lockhart’s pen was indefatigably at work. As early as 1819 <hi rend="italic"
                    >Peter's Letters to his Kinsfolk</hi> appeared. Like Goldsmith’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Citizen of the World,</hi> these profess to give the impressions
                    of a stranger in a new country. Dr Peter Morris, a Welsh physician, passes some
                    time in Scotland, especially in Edinburgh, and describes the men and manners
                    very freely to his relations at home. His descriptions of the chief notabilities
                    of the day have a certain historical, almost antiquarian interest, though now
                    the least interesting part of the work. What we enjoy most is the reflexion of a
                    young and ardent mind dealing out opinions and estimates far beyond its years,
                    the correctness of which time has singularly verified. The amount of reading too
                    which crops out in every page is amazing; a perpetual play of allusions,
                    quotations, and happy nicknames—for which Lockhart to his last days was
                    famous—is given with a raciness of tone of which the reader might tire, but for
                    the simple, vigorous English in which it is clad. A chapter on dandies is a <hi
                    rend="italic">chef d'oeuvre</hi> in its way. That a work describing the
                    appearance and idiosyncrasies of many living individuals should give offence was
                    a matter of course. His description of the northern universities was not likely
                    to please; while for the unsparing ridicule and ruthless quizzing heaped on the
                    General Assembly—“men,” he is supposed to have said, “of like passions with
                    ourselves, but worse manners” —it would be strange indeed if the author had
                    escaped with impunity.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Valerius, a Roman Story,</hi> followed next (1821). As <hi
                    rend="italic">Valerius</hi> was intended to illustrate the manners and customs
                    of Rome in the time of Trajan, so <hi rend="italic">Reginald Dalton,</hi>
                    published in 1823, aimed at exhibiting the life of an undergraduate at Oxford as
                    he had known it. Lockhart’s strength did not lie in novel writing, and, to those
                    who read <hi rend="italic">Reginald Dalton</hi> now, the digressions of the
                    author are far more interesting than the adventures of the hero. But a plot of
                    simpler construction and intenser passion showed Lockhart’s strength to greater
                    advantage. <hi rend="italic">Adam Blair</hi> (1822) is a tale of temptation,
                    fall, and repentance, each fearful in its way, told with tremendous power, and
                    as far removed from all that is morbid and false in sentiment as the author was
                    himself. It gave great offence to the Scottish Church, for the erring man is a
                    minister, and the scene is laid in a Scottish manse.</p>
                <p>In 1826, on the death of Mr Gifford, the editorship of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quarterly Review</hi> was offered to Lockhart, and accepted. He was singularly
                    free in position, however far from idle. He was next heir to Milton Lockhart,
                    the property of his unmarried half-brother, who eventually survived him; the
                    legal profession to which he had been destined was virtually abandoned; and time
                    had shown him that the party strife which prevailed in Edinburgh was
                    demoralizing to both sides. This last conviction did the most to reconcile him
                    to the separation from all Scottish surroundings. His friends gave him a
                    farewell dinner, when, labouring with strong feelings, and with his habitual
                    dislike or incapacity to express them, he said, on returning thanks, “You all
                    know that I am no speaker; had I been, there would have been no occasion for
                    this parting.”</p>
                <p>The conduct of a great periodical like the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly
                    Review</hi> is the touchstone of a man’s capacity, knowledge, and temper.
                    Looking back to an editorship which lasted twenty-eight years, it must be
                    admitted that Lockhart maintained a high position in all these respects. He
                    contributed largely to the <hi rend="italic">Review</hi> himself, his
                    biographical articles being especially admirable. He also found time, being a
                    very glutton in work, for many a paper in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood</hi>; he
                    wrote what remains the most charming of the biographies of Burns; and he
                    undertook the superintendence of the series called <hi rend="italic">Murray’s
                    Family Library,</hi> which he opened in 1829 with a <hi rend="italic">Life of
                    Napoleon.</hi> But his chief work was the <hi rend="italic">Life of Walter
                    Scott,</hi> a task at once of love and duty. Lockhart knew the great and good
                    man as no one else did, and felt that, whatever the mistakes in judgment, no
                    life from first to last could better afford complete revelation. There have not
                    been wanting those in Scotland who have taxed him with ungenerous exposure of
                    his subject, but to most healthy minds the impression conveyed by the biography
                    was, and is, one of the most opposite kind—namely, that Lockhart has almost
                    deified Scott. The labour incurred was in so far one of love, inasmuch as the
                    writer reaped <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n787/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0787-0764"/> no part of its considerable proceeds, but
                    resigned them absolutely for the benefit of Scott’s creditors.</p>
                <p>Lockhart’s life in London was a long succession of constant work, of dignified
                    social success, and of heavy bereavements. His eldest boy, the suffering “Hugh
                    Littlejohn” of the <hi rend="italic">Tales of a, Grandfather,</hi> died in 1831.
                    Sir Walter died in 1832; Anne Scott, the second daughter, who had come to live
                    with the Lockharts in London, in 1833; Mrs Lockhart in 1837. The love for his
                    children was for long the one bright element in his life. But the death in 1852,
                    and, sadder still, the previous life, of his surviving son Walter, a fine youth,
                    who had entered the army under unfortunate auspices, broke down all that
                    remained of health and spirit in the father.</p>
                <p>Failing health compelled Lockhart to resign the editorship of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Quarterly Review</hi> in 1853. He spent the next winter in Rome,
                    but returned to England with no restoration of vital power. He was conveyed to
                    Abbotsford, where, under the tender care of his daughter Mrs Hope Scott, and
                    cheered by the prattle of his granddaughter, now the possessor of Abbotsford, he
                    lingered till his death, November 25, 1854. He was buried in Dryburgh Abbey, at
                    the feet of Walter Scott. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. e.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
