<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0671-0650-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">LIMITATION, Statutes of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 14, page 650</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90227c">Rent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j33z">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1094658">Rent</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n671/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LIMITATION, <hi rend="smallcaps">Statutes of</hi></label>,
                    are Acts of Parliament by which rights of action are limited to a fixed period
                    after the occurrence of the events giving rise to the cause of action. This is
                    one of the devices by which lapse of time is employed to settle disputed claims.
                    There are mainly two modes by which this may be effected. We may say that the
                    active enjoyment of a right—or possession—for a determined period shall be a
                    good title against all the world. That is the method known generally as <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Prescription</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.vf</hi> It looks to the
                    length of time during which the defendant in a disputed claim has been in
                    possession or enjoyment of the matter in dispute. On the other hand, the
                    principle of the statutes of limitation is to look to the length of time during
                    which the plaintiff has been out of possession. The point of time at which he
                    might first have brought his action having been ascertained, the lapse of the
                    limited period after that time bars him for ever from bringing his action. In
                    both cases the policy of the law is expressed by the maxim <hi rend="italic"
                    >Interest</hi><hi rend="italic">reipublicae</hi><hi rend="italic">ut sit
                    finis</hi><hi rend="italic">litium.</hi></p>
                <p>The principle of limitation was first adopted in English law in connexion with
                    real actions, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> actions for the recovery of real
                    property. At first a fixed date was taken, and no action could be brought of
                    which the cause had arisen before that date. By the Statute of Westminster the
                    First (3 Edward I. c. 39), the beginning of the reign of Richard I. was fixed as
                    the date of limitation for such actions. This is the well known “period of legal
                    memory” recognized by the judges in a different class of cases to which a rule
                    of prescription was applied. Possession of rights in <hi rend="italic"
                    >alieno</hi><hi rend="italic">solo</hi> from time immemorial was held to be an
                    indefeasible title, and the courts following the statutes above mentioned held
                    time immemorial to begin with the first year of Richard I.</p>
                <p>A. period absolutely fixed became in course of time useless for the purposes of
                    limitation, and at last the method of counting back a certain number of years
                    from the date of the writs was adopted in the Statute 32 Henry VIII. c. 2, which
                    fixed periods of thirty, fifty, and sixty years for various classes of actions
                    named therein. A large number of statutes since that time have established
                    periods of limitation for different kinds of actions. Of those now in force the
                    most important are 21 James I. c. 16 for personal actions in general, and 3
                    &amp; 4 Will. IV. c. 27 relating to actions for the recovery of land. The latter
                    statute has been repealed and virtually re-enacted by the Real Property
                    Limitation Act, 1874, which reduced the period of limitation from twenty years
                    to twelve, for all actions brought after the 1st January 1879. The principal
                    section of the Act of Will. IV. will show the <hi rend="italic">modus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">operandi</hi>:—“After the 31st December 1833, no person shall make
                    an entry or distress, or bring an action to recover any land or rent <hi
                    rend="italic">but within twenty years next after the time</hi> at which the
                    right to make such entry or distress or to bring such action shall have first
                    accrued to some person through whom he claims, or shall have first accrued to
                    the person making or bringing the same.” Another section defines the times at
                    which the right of action or entry shall be deemed to have accrued in particular
                    cases; <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> when the estate claimed shall have been an
                    estate or interest in reversion, such right shall be deemed to have first
                    accrued at the time at which such estate or interest became an estate or
                    interest in possession. Thus suppose lands to be let by A to B from 1830 for a
                    period of fifty years, and that a portion of such lands is occupied by C from
                    1831 without any colour of title from B or A—C’s long possession would be of no
                    avail against an action brought by A for the recovery of the land after the
                    determination of B’s lease. A would have twelve years after the determination of
                    the lease within which to bring his action, and might thus, by an action brought
                    in 1891, disestablish a person who had been in quiet possession since 1831. What
                    the law looks to is not the length of time during which C has enjoyed the
                    property, but the length of time which A has suffered to elapse since he might
                    first have brought his action.</p>
                <p>It is to be observed, however, that the Real Property Limitation Act does more
                    than bar the remedy. It extinguishes the right, differing in this respect from
                    the other Limitation Acts, which, while barring the remedy, preserve the right,
                    so that it may possibly become available in some other way than by action.</p>
                <p>By section 14 of the Act of Will. IV., “when any acknowledgment of the title of
                    the person entitled shall have been given to him or his agent in writing signed
                    by the person in possession, or in receipt of the profits or rent, then the
                    right of the person (to whom such acknowledgment shall have been given) to make
                    an entry or distress or bring an action shall be deemed to have first accrued at
                    the time at which such acknowledgment, or the last of such acknowledgments, was
                    given. By section 15, persons under the disability of infancy, lunacy, or
                    coverture, or beyond seas, and their representatives, are to be allowed ten
                    years from the termination of this disability, or death (which shall have first
                    happened), notwithstanding that the ordinary period of limitation shall have
                    expired.</p>
                <p>By 21 James I. c. 16, actions of trespass, detinue, trover, replevin, or account,
                    actions on the case (except for slander), actions of debt arising out of a
                    simple contract, and actions for arrears of rent not due upon specialty, shall
                    be limited to six years from the date of the cause of action. Actions for
                    assault, menace, battery, wounds, and imprisonment are limited to four years,
                    and actions for slander to two years. Persons labouring under disabilities are
                    allowed the same time after the removal of the disability. When the defendant is
                    “beyond seas” <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> outside the United Kingdom and the
                    adjacent islands) a similar extension of time is allowed.</p>
                <p>An acknowledgment, whether by payment on account or by mere spoken words, was
                    formerly sufficient to take <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n672/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0672-0651"/> the case out of the statute. The Act 9 Geo. IV.
                    c. 14 (Lord Tenterden’s Act) requires any promise or admission of liability to
                    be in writing and signed by the party to be charged, otherwise it will not bar
                    the statute.</p>
                <p>Contracts under seal are governed as to limitation by 3 &amp; 4 William IV. c.
                    42, which provides that actions for rent upon any indenture of demise, or of
                    covenant, or debt, or any bond or other specialty, and on recognizances, must be
                    brought within twenty years after cause of action. Actions of debt on an award
                    (the submission being not under seal), or for a copyhold fine, or for money
                    levied on a writ <hi rend="italic">oi fieri facias,</hi> must be brought within
                    six years.</p>
                <p>Of the miscellaneous limitations fixed by various Acts, the following may be
                    noticed. Suits and indictments under penal statutes are limited to two years if
                    the forfeiture is to the crown, to one year if the forfeiture is to the common
                    informer. Penal actions by persons aggrieved are limited to two years (3 &amp; 4
                    Will. IV. c. 42). Actions brought against a justice of the peace for acts done
                    in the execution of his office are limited to six calendar months (11 &amp; 12
                    Vict. c. 44). Acts done under any local or personal Act of Parliament can only
                    be sued upon within two years (5 &amp; 6 Vict. c. 97).</p>
                <p>A defence under the statutes of limitations must in general be specially pleaded.
                    Limitation is regarded strictly as a law of procedure. The English courts will
                    therefore apply their own rules to all actions, although the cause of action may
                    have arisen in a country in which different rules of limitation exist. This is
                    also a recognized principle of private international law.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States.—</hi> The principle of the statute of
                    limitations has passed with some modification into the statute-books of every
                    State in the Union except Louisiana, whose laws of limitation are essentially
                    the prescriptions of the civil law drawn from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Partidas,</hi> or “Spanish Code.” As to personal actions, it is generally
                    provided that they shall be brought within a certain specified time—usually six
                    years or less—from the time when the cause of action accrues, and not after,
                    while for land the “general if not universal limitation of the right to bring
                    action or to make entry is to twenty years after the right to enter or to bring
                    the action accrues” (Bouvier’s <hi rend="italic">Law Dictionary,</hi> art.
                    “Limitations ”). The constitutional provision prohibiting States from passing
                    laws impairing the obligation of contracts is not infringed by a law of
                    limitations, unless it bars a right of action already accrued without giving a
                    reasonable term within which to bring the action. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e.
                    e.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
