<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-5247-0168-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOYSE, Boys, or Bois</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881352">Countesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1144715">Tears</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193735247?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BOYSE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Boys</hi>, or
                        Bois</label>, <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> one of the translators of the
                    Bible in the reign of James I. was son of William Bois, rector of West Stowe,
                    near St Edmundsbury, Suffolk, and born at Nettlestead in Suffolk on the 3d of
                    January 1560. He was taught the first rudiments of learning by his father; and
                    his capacity was such, that at the age of five li£ was able, it is said, to read
                    the Bible in Hebrew. He went afterwards to Hadley school; and at fourteen was
                    admitted of St John’s College, Cambridge, where he distinguished himself by his
                    skill in Greek. Happening to catch the small-pox when he was cleeted fellow, he
                    caused himself to be carried for admission in blankets, in order to preserve his
                    seniority. He applied himself for some time to the study of medicine; but,
                    fancying himself affected with every disease he read of, he quitted that
                    science. He was during ten years principal Greek lecturer in his college, and
                    read every day. Hc voluntarily read a Greek lecture for some years at four in
                    the morning, in his own chamber, which was frequented by many of the fellows. On
                    the death of his father, he succeeded to the reetory of West Stowe. At the age
                    of thirty-six he married the daughter of Mr Holt, rector of Buxworth, in
                    Cambridge-shire, whom he succeeded in that living in October 1596. On his
                    quitting the university, the college gave him L.100. But his young wife, who had
                    been bequeathed to him with the living, which was an advowson, having proved a
                    bad economist, and he himself being wholly addicted to his studies, he soon
                    became so mueh involved in debt that he was obliged to sell his choice
                    collection of books, consisting of almost every Greek author then extant. When a
                    new translation of the Bible was directed to be made, Mr Bois was elected one of
                    the Cambridge translators. He performed not only his own, but also the part
                    assigned to another, with great reputation. He was also one of the six who had
                    met at Stationers’ Hall to revise the whole; whieh task they performed in nine
                    months, having each, from the company of stationers, during that time, thirty
                    shillings a week. He afterwards assisted Sir Henry Savile in publishing the
                    works of St Crysostom. In 1615 Dr Lancelot Andrews, bishop of Ely, bestowed on
                    him, unasked, the prebend in his church. He died on the 14th of January 1643, in
                    the eighty-fourth year of his age, and left a great many manuscripts behind him,
                    particularly a Commentary on almost all the books of the New Testament. When
                    Bois was a young student at Cambridge, he received from the learned Dr Whitaker
                    three rules for avoiding those distempers whieh usually attend a sedentary life,
                    to which he adhered with equal constancy and success. The first was, To study
                    always standing; the second, Never to study in a window; and the third, Never to
                    go to bed with his feet cold.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Boyse,</hi><hi rend="italic">Samuel,</hi> a man
                    remarkable for the fineness of his genius, the lowness of his manners, and the
                    wretchedness of his life. He was born in 1708, and received the rudiments of his
                    education at a private school in Dublin. When he was but eighteen years old, his
                    father, a non-conformist clergyman, sent him to the university of Glasgow, that
                    he might finish his education there. But he had not been a year at the
                    university, when he fell in love with the daughter of a tradesman in that city,
                    and was imprudent enough to interrupt his education by marrying her before he
                    had entered into his twentieth year. The natural extravagance of his temper soon
                    exposed him to want; and as he had now the additional charge of a wife, his
                    redueed eircumstances obliged him to quit the university, and go over with his
                    wife (who also carried a sister along with her) to Dublin, where they relied on
                    the old clergyman for support. Young Boyse w as of all men the farthest removed
                    from the charaeter of gentleman. He had no graces of person, and still fewer of
                    manners or conversation. Never were three people of more libertine habits than
                    young Boyse, his wife, and his sister-in-law; yet the two women wore sueh
                    amaskof decency before the old non-conformist gentleman, that his fondness was
                    never abated. The estate which he possessed in Yorkshire was sold to discharge
                    his son’s debts; and his means were utterly wasted, so that, when seized with
                    his last sickness, he was entirely supported by presents from his eongregation,
                    and at length buried at their expense. We have no further account of Boyse till
                    we find him soon after his father’s death at Edinburgh. At this place his
                    poetical genius raised him many friends, and some patrons of eminence. He
                    published a volume of poems in 1731, to which are subjoined 7‰ <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tablature of Cebes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A Letter upon Liberty,</hi>
                    inserted in the <hi rend="italic">Dublin Journal,</hi> 1726, by which he
                    obtained considerable reputation. These poems arc addressed to the Countess of
                    Eglintoun. This amiable lady was the patroness of all men of wit, and greatly
                    distinguished Boyse <pb break="no" facs="nls:193735260?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0705-5260-0169"/> while he resided in Scotland. Upon the death
                    of the Viscountess Stormont, Boyse wrote an elegy, which was much applauded by
                    her ladyship’s relations. This elegy he entitled <hi rend="italic">The Tears of
                        the Muses,</hi> as the deceased lady was a woman of the most refined taste
                    in the sciences, and a great admirer of poetry. The Lord Stormont was so much
                    pleased with this mark of attention paid to the memory of his lady, that he
                    ordered a handsome present to be o∙iven to Boyse by his attorney at Edinburgh.
                    The notice which Lady Eglintoun and the Lord Stormont took of our poet
                    recommended him likewise to the patronage of the Duchess of Gordon, who was so
                    solicitous to raise him above necessity, that she employed her interest in
                    procuring the promise of a place for him. She gave him a letter, which he was
                    next day to deliver to one of the commissioners of the customs at Edinburgh. But
                    it happened that he was then some miles distant from the city; and th&lt; ’)t
                    the morning on which he was to have proceeded to town with her Grace’s letter of
                    recommendation proved rainy. This slender circumstance was enough to discourage
                    Boyse, who never looked beyond the present moment. He declined going to town on
                    account of the rainy weather; and thus letting slip the opportunity, the place
                    was bestowed upon another, which the commissioner declared he kept for some time
                    vacant in expectation of seeing a person recommended by the Duchess of Gordon.
                    Having defeated all the kind intentions of his patrons towards him, Boyse at
                    last fell into contempt and poverty, which obliged him to quit Edinburgh. He
                    coinţnunicated his design of going to London to the Duchess of Gordon, who,
                    having still a high opinion of his poetical abilities, gave him a letter of
                    recommendation to Mr Pope, and obtained another for him to Sir Peter King, the
                    lord chancellor of England. Lord Stormont recommended him to the solicitor
                    general his brother, and many other persons of the first fashion. Upon receiving
                    these letters he quitted Edinburgh with great caution, despised by all, and
                    regretted by none but his creditors. Upon his arrival in London, he went to
                    Twickenham in order to deliver the Duchess of Gordon’s letter to Mr Pope; but
                    that gentleman not being at home, Mr Boyse never gave himself the trouble to
                    repeat his visit. He wrote poems; but these, though possessing some intrinsic
                    merit, were lost to the world, by being introduced with no advantage. He had so
                    great a propensity to low company, that his acquaintance were generally of such
                    a cast as could be of no service to him; and those in higher life he addressed
                    by letters, not having sufficient breeding or common good manners to converse
                    familiarly with them. Thus unfit to support himself in the world, he was exposed
                    to a variety of distresses, from which he could invent no means of extricating
                    himself except by writing mendicant letters. Yet this man, of so abject a
                    spirit, was voluptuous and luxurious; he had no taste for any thing elegant, but
                    was to the last degree expensive. Often when he had received a guinea in
                    consequence of a supplicating letter, he would go into a tavern, order a supper
                    to be prepared, drink of the richest wines, and spend all the money that had
                    just been given him in charity, without having any one to participate the regale
                    with him, and whilst his wife and child were starving at home.</p>
                <p part="N">About the year 1740, Boyse, reduced to the last extremity of human
                    wretchedness, had not a shirt, a coat, nor any kind of apparel, to put on; the
                    sheets in which he lay were carried to the pawn-broker’s, and he was obliged to
                    be confined to his bed with no other covering than a blanket. He had little
                    support except what he got by writing letters in the most abject style; and he
                    remained for six weeks in the situation we have described. During this time he
                    had some employment in writing verses for the Magazines. PIe sat up in bed with
                    the blanket wrapt about him, through which he had cut a hole large enough to
                    admit his arm, and placing the paper upon his knee, scribbled in the best manner
                    lie could the verses he was obliged to write; whatever he got by these, or by
                    begging letters, being barely sufficient for the preservation of life. And
                    perhaps he would have remained much longer in this distressful condition, had
                    not a compassionate gentleman, upon hearing the circumstance related, ordered
                    his clothes to be taken out of pawn, and enabled him to appear abroad again.</p>
                <p part="N">About the year 1745 Boyse’s wife died. He was then at Reading, and
                    pretended much concern when he heard of her death. His business at Reading was
                    to compile a review of the most material transactions at home and abroad during
                    the war; and in this he has included a short account of the rebellion. Upon his
                    return from Reading, his behaviour was more decent than it had ever been before;
                    and hopes were entertained that a reformation, though late, might be wrought
                    upon him. He was employed by a bookseller to translate <hi rend="italic">Fenelon
                        on the Existence of a God;</hi> and during the time he was occupied in this
                    he married a second wife, a woman in low circumstances, but well enough suited
                    to his taste. He now began to live with more regard to character, and supported
                    a better appearance than usual; but whilst his circumstances were mending, and
                    his irregular appetites losing their hold, his health visibly declined. While
                    suffering from a lingering illness, he had the satisfaction to observe a poem of
                    his, entitled <hi rend="italic">The Deity,</hi> recommended by two writers of
                    very opposite principles and talents, Mr Fielding the novellist, and the
                    Reverend James Harvey, author of <hi rend="italic">The Meditations.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Boyse’s mind was often religiously disposed; he frequently talked upon
                    this subject, and probably suffered a great deal from remorse of conscience. The
                    early impressions of his education were never entirely obliterated; and his
                    whole life was a continued struggle between his reason and his passions, as he
                    was always violating the dictates of the one, while he fell under the dominion
                    of the other. It was in consequence of this war in his mind that he wrote his
                    poem entitled <hi rend="italic">The Recantation.</hi> In May 1749 he died in
                    obscure lodgings near Shoe-lane, under the influence, it is believed, of
                    sentiments very different from those in which he had spent the greater part of
                    his life. An old acquaintance of his endeavoured to collect money to defray the
                    expenses of his funeral, and spare his remains the dishonour of being buried by
                    the parish; but his efforts were vain, and the corpse of this son of the Muses
                    was, with very little ceremony, hurried away by the parish-officers.</p>
                <p part="N">Never was a life spent with less grace than that of Boyse, and never
                    were good abilities given to less purpose. His genius was not confined to poetry
                    alone. He had a taste for painting, music, and heraldry; with the last of which
                    he was very well acquainted. His poetical pieces, if collected, would form six
                    moderate volumes. Many of them are scattered in <hi rend="italic">The Gentleman
                        s Magazine,</hi> marked with the letter <hi rend="italic">Y,</hi> and the
                    signature <hi rend="italic">Akens.</hi> Two volumes were published in London.
                    Anode of his in the manner of Spenser, entitled <hi rend="italic">The
                        Olive,</hi> was addressed to Sir Robert Walpole, which procured him a
                    present of ten guineas. He translated a poem from the High Dutch of Van Haren,
                    in praise of peace, upon the conclusion of that of Aix-la-Chapelle; but the poem
                    which procured him the greatest reputation was that upon the attributes of the
                    Deity. He was employed by Mr Ogle to translate some of Chaucer’s tales into
                    modern English, which he executed with great spirit, and received at the rate of
                    threepence a line for his, trouble. Mr Ogle published a <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193735273?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0705-5273-0170"/>complete
                    edition of <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales modernized',</hi> and Boyse’s name
                    is put to such tales as were done by him. ’In 1743 Boyse published, without his
                    name, an ode on the battle of Dettingen, entitled <hi rend="italic">Albion's
                        Triumph.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
