<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-3375-0024-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOSSUET, James Benigne</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p104">Messiah</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193733375?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BOSSUET, <hi rend="smallcaps">James
                        Benigne</hi></label>, one of the most illustrious prelates which the church
                    of France, so fruitful in great men, has ever produced, was born at Dijon on the
                    27th September 1627. He was descended from an ancient and noble family in
                    Burgundy. On the establishment of the parliament of Metz, his father was
                    appointed one of its counsellors. Being destined by his parents for the church,
                    the young Bossuet took the <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> clerical tonsure
                    before he had completed his eighth year. At first he was placed under the care
                    of his uncle, the first president of the parliament of Metz; and he used to
                    relate that, while a mere boy, under his uncle’s roof, he read the Old Testament
                    with a relish and delight far exceeding any pleasure he afterwards felt on the
                    perusal of any other work. His uncle afterwards placed him at the college of the
                    Jesuits at Dijon, where he applied himself to his studies with such labour and
                    success that they desired to attach him to themselves; but in 1642 his uncle
                    sent him to Paris to the college of Navarre. Here, under the direction of the
                    celebrated Nicholas Cornet the principal, Bossuet made rapid progress in Greek
                    and philosophy, relieving his studies from time to time by reading the best
                    works of antiquity; but the Scriptures and religious books always occupied a
                    large share of his time. At the age of sixteen he supported his first thesis in
                    a manner which gave indications of his future greatness, and which caused him to
                    be already regarded as a prodigy. An extempore sermon which he shortly
                    afterwards delivered, at the Hotel of Rambouillet, in presence of an assembly
                    partly composed of the most celebrated men of the time, excited general
                    admiration.</p>
                <p part="N">He was admitted into the corporation of the college at the age of
                    twenty, on which occasion he chose for the subject of his thesis a comparison
                    between the glory of this world and that which awaits the just in the next.
                    During the delivery of this discourse, the great Condé, who had just dazzled
                    France by the splendour of his victories, suddenly entered the hall, surrounded
                    by a number of his companions in arms. The orator, without interrupting his
                    harangue, immediately addressed himself to the young conqueror, and, in the name
                    of France, paid him a just and appropriate tribute of admiration and praise; but
                    he told him at the same time how vain and perishable was the glory which he had
                    acquired. Forty years after, Bossuet repeated the same truths over the bier of
                    the princely warrior. During the whole of that long period he had enjoyed his
                    friendship and esteem.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1652 Bossuet took the degree of doctor, and received also the order
                    of priesthood. In thus devoting himself to the cause of religion, he exclaimed,
                    “Under thy auspices, 0 sacred Truth, I will joyfully approach those altars,
                    which are to witness the oath I am about to take; an oath which our ancestors
                    have often heard; that most pleasing and most sacred oath, by which I am to bind
                    myself, even to death, to the holy cause of truth.” After passing some time in
                    the retreat at St Lazarus, under the discipline of Sť Vincent de Paul, whose
                    friendship he had obtained, he went to Metz, in the cathedral church of which
                    city he had previously obtained the preferment of a canonicatc, and where he was
                    successively raised to the rank of archdeacon and dean. He now applied himself
                    wholly to the duties of his ministry, edifying those who surrounded him by the
                    puricy of his life, and astonishing them by the splendour of his talents. His
                    first appearance as an author was in 1655, when he published his Refutation of
                    the Catechism of Paul Ferry, a Protestant minister highly esteemed for his
                    learning and talents. This work advanced his reputation greatly with his own
                    party, and, it is said, gained him even the respect of the Protestants. The
                    affairs of the cathedral rendering his presence necessary in Paris, he often
                    preached there; and his sermons were so universally applauded, that he was
                    appointed to preach in the chapel of the Louvre before Louis XIV. during the
                    Lent of 1663. His Majesty signified the pleasure he derived from his sermons in
                    a letter which his private secretary wrote by his desire to Bossueťs father.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1669 he was nominated to the bishopric of Condom, but being appointed
                    preceptor to the Dauphin the following year, he resigned his see, because he
                    considered his new charge as inconsistent with the duty he owed to his diocese.
                    For the instruction of the Dauphin he composed his work on universal history,
                    which he divided into three parts. The first part is purely chronological; but
                    it has been well observed that it scarcely contains a sentence in which there is
                    not some noun or verb that conveys an image or suggests a sentiment of the
                    noblest kind. The third part, which is historical, contains the most profound
                    reflections on the rise and fall of empires. “But in the second part of it,” as
                    one of his biographers observes, “the genius of Bossuet takes its highest
                    flight. He never appears on the stretch of exertion; he is never lost in the
                    mazes of argumentation; but, in a continued strain of sublime eloquence, he
                    displays the truths and proofs of the Christian religion with a grandeur of
                    thought, a magnificence of language, and a force of evidence, which nothing can
                    withstand. A nobler work in support of Christianity has never issued from the
                    press.” This work was first published in 1681. Ten years before, he had
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Exposition of the Doctrine of the Catholic
                        Church in Matters of Controversy,</hi> which was speedily translated into
                    all the living languages of Europe. Pope Innocent XI. formally approved of it by
                    two successive briefs on the 22d November 1678 and the 12th July 1679; and the
                    Gallican clergy in their assembly of 1682 gave it also the seal of their
                    approbation. It has therefore, we believe, been regarded as a correct exposition
                    of the tenets of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
                <p part="N">The publication of the Exposition gave rise to the famous conference
                    between Bossuet and Μ. Claude, one of the ablest divines of the reformed church
                    in France. As a specimen of the argumentative powers of both champions, we shall
                    select a few sentences from that part of <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193733388?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0705-3388-0025"/>the
                    conference which relates to the right of private judgment in matters of faith.
                    On the one hand, Bossuet contended for an unconditional submission to the
                    authority of the church; while, on the other, M. Claude only admitted a
                    conditional submission to the decrees of the national assembly of his own, or
                    those of any other church, or, in other words, that a conscientious submission
                    could only be required if the party thought their determinations were
                    conformable to the word of God. “Surely,” said Bossuet, <hi rend="superscript">
                        ii</hi> this right of individual examination, which you recognise in each
                    individual, must be accompanied with the highest individual presumption.” “That
                    by no means follows,” replied M. Claude; “when the synagogue declared that Jesus
                    Christ was not the Messiah promised by the prophets, and condemned him to death,
                    would not an individual who believed him to be the true Christ have judged
                    better than the synagogue? Could you accuse such an individual of <hi
                        rend="italic">presumptuously</hi> believing that he understood the
                    Scriptures better than all the synagogue ?” It is impossible to conceive a more
                    able reply than this. It produced, as it ought, a powerful impression on the
                    audience, and even staggered the great champion of the Catholic church. After a
                    short pause, during which he says he offered up a mental prayer for light and
                    direction from above, he thus addressed Μ. Claude: “You say that my assertion,
                    that the individual who sets up his private opinion in opposition to that of the
                    whole church must be guilty of intolerable presumption, fixes the charge of
                    equal presumption on those who believed in Jesus Christ in opposition to the
                    sentence of the synagogue which had pronounced him guilty of blasphemy. Most
                    certainly my assertion proves nothing of the kind. When an individual <hi
                        rend="italic">now</hi> sets up his own private opinion in opposition to that
                    of the whole church, he sets it up against the highest authority on earth, as
                    the earth contains no authority to which an appeal from that authority can be
                    made. But when the synagogue condemned Jesus Christ, there was on earth a much
                    higher authority than the synagogue; to that authority the individual who
                    reprobated the proceedings of the synagogue might appeal. Truth herself <hi
                        rend="italic">then</hi> visibly existed among men—the Messiah, the eternal
                    Son of God,—He to whom a voice from above had rendered testimony, by proclaiming
                    before the whole people that he was the well-beloved Son of God,—He who restored
                    the dead to life, gave sight to the blind, and did so many miracles, that the
                    Jews themselves-confessed no man had done the like before him,—He, the Jesus
                    himself, then existed among men, and was the visible external authority to whom
                    there was a lawful appeal from the synagogue. His authority was infallible. I
                    hear you say that it was a contested authority. I know that it was contested;
                    but, as a Christian, <hi rend="italic">you</hi> are bound to say that no
                    individual could reasonably or conscientiously contest it. It was not,
                    therefore, presumption—it was duty to disobey the synagogue and believe in
                    Christ. Bring back to me Jesus Christ in person; bring him teaching, preaching,
                    and working miracles—I no longer want the church: but don’t take the church from
                    me, unless you give me Jesus Christ in person. You say you have his word. Yes,
                    certainly, we have his holy, adorable word; but what is to be done with those
                    who understand it in a wrong sense? Jesus Christ is not present in person to set
                    them right: they must therefore obey the church. Before Jesus Christ appeared
                    among the Jews, they were bound to obey the synagogue. When the synagogue
                    failed, Jesus Christ came among men to teach them all truth, and they were bound
                    to obey his voice. When he returned to his Father, he left us his church, and we
                    are bound to obey her voice. There is not—no, there is not on earth any visible
                    higher authority to which you can appeal from her.” This is, no doubt, very
                    ingeniously argued; but, considered as a piece of mere reasoning, it proceeds
                    upon an assumption which cannot be admitted without separate proof, and it
                    evades the case so forcibly put, by introducing the subject of <hi rend="italic"
                        >time,</hi> which, in truth, formed no element in the question at issue.
                    Further, it is evident that, <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis,</hi> the same
                    reasoning might have been employed by the Rabbin of the synagogue, who, on
                    grounds precisely identical, might have argued in favour of the divine authority
                    of the church established by Moses.</p>
                <p part="N">Having finished the education of the Dauphin in 1681, the king nominated
                    Bossuet to the bishopric of Meaux, and he entered with zeal upon the duties of
                    his new episcopate. He took a very active part in the general assembly of the
                    church of France held the following year, and drew up the celebrated declaration
                    of 1682 against the attempted encroachments of the see of Rome. Bossuet now
                    directed all the energies of his powerful mind to the most important of all his
                    controversial works, the <hi rend="italic">History of the Variations of the
                        Protestant Churches,</hi> which was first published in 1688. Gibbon in his
                    younger years was converted to the Roman Catholic faith by perusing this work,
                    retiring for a while, like Chillingworth, to use the expression of Dr Johnson in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Life of Dryden,</hi> into the bosom of an infallible
                    church. It has been remarked as a singular coincidence, that although no writers
                    were ever more opposed in sentiment than Bossuet and the author of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Decline and Fall of the Iłoman Empire,</hi> yet the latter (c.
                    54) adopts and aggravates the charges made by Bossuet, in his History of the
                    Variations, of the alleged Socinian tendency of the principles of the
                    Reformation.</p>
                <p part="N">During the last years of hi⅜ <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> life Bossuet
                    was much occupied in the hopeless scheme of effecting a union between the Roman
                    Catholic and Protestant churches. The négociation was first carried on with
                    Molanus, who limited his views to a junction between the Roman Catholic and
                    Lutheran churches, a plan which many persons considered by no means
                    impracticable. But Leibnitz, who succeeded Molanus on the part of the
                    Protestants, being desirous of including the whole Protestant churches in the
                    arrangement, the négociation failed, as might have been expected, after a
                    correspondence of ten years.</p>
                <p part="N">It was the fate of Bossuet to be involved in religious controversy
                    during the greater part of his life. He entered the arena at the age of
                    twenty-eight, and during the fifty years which followed, his pen was in constant
                    requisition. He composed with ease, but, like Burke, he laboured hard to improve
                    his writings, and did not cease to alter them till they issued from the press;
                    yet the style of both is as free as if it had been quite spontaneous. Some of
                    Bossueťs principal writings against the Protestants have been mentioned. He was
                    also engaged in controversies with persons of his own communion. That with the
                    amiable Fenelon is the most conspicuous. The mystical speculations of Madame
                    Guyon of Port Roval having found an abettor in the person of the author of <hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">Γelemaehus,</hi> in a
                    work on the maxims of the saints, Bossuet drew up his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pelationdu Quiétisme,</hi> in which the archbishop was attacked with great
                    severity. Fenelon published a reply, in which meekness, simplicity, and grandeur
                    of mind were admirably blended. The writings in this controversy are amongst the
                    finest in French literature; but Quietism being a perishable topic, these
                    writings are now seldom read. In this contest the eagle of Meaux carried off the
                    palm of victory.</p>
                <p part="N">Among the writings of Bossuet, his sermons and funeral orations are
                    particularly to be distinguished. Of the latter, the finest is that on the death
                    of Henrietta-Anne, the daughter of our Charles I. and wife of the duke of
                    Orleans. As his funeral orations place him in the first class of orators, so his
                    sermons unquestionably rank him <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193733401?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0705-3401-0026"/>in the
                    first line of preachers. It has been observed that Bourdaloue and Massillon
                    alone can dispute his pre-eminence. In the opinion of Voltaire, the eloquence of
                    Bossuet stands unrivalled. This great prelate died on the 12th of April 1704, in
                    the 77th year of his age. Massillon and other French writers have eulogised the
                    talents and virtues of Bossuet in terms of the highest admiration; and he is
                    thus noticed by the Reverend Mr Eustace, in his <hi rend="italic">Classical
                        Tour:</hi> “Bossuet was indeed a great man, and one of those extraordinary
                    minds which, at distant intervals, seem as if deputed from a superior region to
                    enlighten and to astonish mankind. With all the originality of genius, he was
                    free from its eccentricity and intemperance. Sublime, without obscurity—bold,
                    yet accurate—splendid, and yet simple at the same time,—he awes, elevates, and
                    delights his readers, overpowers all resistance, and leads them willing captives
                    to join and to share his triumph. The defects of his style arise from the
                    imperfection of his dialect. And perhaps he could not have given a stronger
                    proof of the energies of his mind than in compelling the French language itself
                    to become the vehicle of sublimity. His works, therefore, are superior to all
                    other controversial writings in his own or any other language.” His works were
                    collected and published soon after his decease in twelve volumes quarto. The
                    Benedictines of St Maur published another edition; but a more complete edition,
                    in forty-three volumes octavo, was published in 1815-20. Cardinal de Bausset
                    wrote a history of the life of Bossuet, which was published in four volumes
                    octavo. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
