<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-1357-0638-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUDGELL, Eustace</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829774">Bees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01649">Creation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193741357?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BUDGELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Eustace</hi></label>,
                    an ingenious writer, was the son of Gilbert Budgell, doctor of divinity, and was
                    born at St Thomas, near Exeter, about the year 1685. He was educated at Christ
                    Church College, Oxford, from which he removed to the Inner Temple, London; but
                    instead of studying the law, for which his father intended him, he applied to
                    polite literature, kept company with.the genteelest persons in town, and in
                    particular contracted a strict intimacy with Mr Addison, who was first cousin to
                    his mother, and who, on his being appointed secretary to Lord Wharton,
                    lord-lieutenant of Ireland, took Budgell with him as one of the clerks of his
                    office. Mr Budgell, who was then about twenty years of age, and had read the
                    classics and the works of the best English, French, and Italian authors, now
                    became concerned with Sir Richard Steele and Mr Addison in writing the <hi
                        rend="italic">Tatler,</hi> as he had soon afterwards a share in writing the
                        <hi rend="italic">Spectator,</hi> where all the papers furnished by him are
                    marked with an X; and when that work was completed, he had likewise a hand in
                    the Guardian, where his performances are marked with an asterisk. He was
                    subsequently made under secretary to Mr Addison, chief secretary to the lords
                    justices of Ireland, and deputy clerk of the council. Soon afterwards he was
                    chosen a member of the Irish parliament; and in 1717, Mr Addison, having become
                    principal secretary of state in England, procured him the place of accountant
                    and comptrollergeneral of the revenue in Ireland. But the next year, the ÌDuke
                    of Bolton being appointed lord-lieutenant, Mr Budgell wrote a lampoon against Mr
                    Webster, his secretary, in which his Grace himself was not spared; and upon all
                    occasions he treated that gentleman with the utmost contempt. This imprudent
                    step became the primary cause of his ruin; for the Duke of Bolton, in support of
                    his secretary, got him removed from the post of accountant-general; upon which,
                    returning to England, he, contrary to the advice of Mr Addison, published his
                    case in a pamphlet. Mr Addison had now resigned the seals, and retired into the
                    country for the sake of his health; Mr Budgell had also lost several other
                    powerful friends, who had been removed by death, particularly the Earl of
                    Sunderland and Lord Halifax. He, however, made several attempts to succeed at
                    court, but was constantly kept back by the Duke of Bolton. In the year 1720 he
                    lost L.20,000 by the South Sea scheme, and afterwards spent L.5000 more in
                    unsuccessful attempts to get into parliament. This completed his ruin. He at
                    length employed himself in writing pamphlets against the ministry, and published
                    many papers in the <hi rend="italic">Craftsman.</hi> In 1733 he began a weekly
                    pamphlet called the <hi rend="italic">Bee,</hi> which he continued for above a
                    hundred numbers, and which is printed in eight volumes 8vo. During the progress
                    of this work occurred the death of Dr Tindal, by whose will Mr Budgell had
                    L.2000 left him; and the world being surprised at such a gift from a man
                    entirely unrelated to him, to the exclusion of the next heir, a nephew, and the
                    continuator of Rapĩn’s history of England, immediately imputed it to his having
                    made the will himself. Lienee the satirist:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Let Budgell charge low Grub-street on my quill, </l>
                    <l part="N"> And write whate’ei he please except my will. </l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">It was thought that he had soîne hand in publishing Dr Tindaľs <hi
                        rend="italic">Christianity as old as the Creation</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> for he often talked of an additional volume on the subject, but
                    never published it. After the cessation of the <hi rend="italic">Bee,</hi> Mr
                    Budgell became so involved in law-suits, that he was reduced to a very unhappy
                    situation. He was indeed called to the bar, and attended for some time in the
                    courts of law; but finding himself unable to make any progress, and being
                    distressed to the utmost, he determined at length to put an end to his life.
                    Accordingly, in the year 1736, he took a boat at Somerset-stairs, after filling
                    his pockets with stones; ordered the waterman to shoot the bridge; and, whilst
                    the boat was passing under, threw himself into the river. He had several days
                    before been visibly distracted in his mind. Upon his bureau was found a slip of
                    paper, on which were these words:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> What Cato did, and Addison approv’d, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Cannot be wrong. </l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">Besides the above works, he wrote a Translation of the Characters of
                    Theophrastus. He was never married, but .left one natural daughter, who
                    afterwards assumed his name, and became an actress in Drury-lane.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
