<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-5975-0224-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRECHIN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154ds5t">Friars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152704">Tops</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193735975?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BRECHIN</label>, a town of Scotland, in the county
                    of Forfar and parish of Brechin, is situated on the face of a hill about the
                    centre of the parish, on the left bank of the River South Esk, which is crossed
                    below the town by a stone bridge of two arches. Brechin consists of one main
                    street running north and south, with several smaller streets. On the south, the
                    town is continued by two suburbs named the Upper and Nether Tenements, which
                    hold in feu of the families of South Esk and Panmure.</p>
                <p part="N">This town is said to have been the capital of Pictavĩa, and the royal
                    seat of the Pictish kings; and the hill of Caterthun, about four miles north of
                    the town, surrounded with an immense coronal of loose stones, is supposed to
                    have been a fortification belonging to that ancient nation. In the earliest
                    record extant, the name of the town is spelt as at present; but as in the days
                    of St Columba there was a noted Druid of the name of “Broichan,” probably the
                    town may have derived its appellation from some such source. The Culdees are
                    reported to have had a convent here; and their abbot Leod was witness to the
                    grant made by King David to his new abbey of Dunfermline. In after-times the
                    Culdees gave way to the Mathurines or Red Friars, the ruins of whose house,
                    according to Maitland, are still to be seen in the College or Chandry W <hi
                        rend="superscript"> τ</hi> ynd.</p>
                <p part="N">Brechin was founded into a bishopric by David I. about 1150. At the
                    Reformation its revenues amounted in money and kind to L.700 per annum; but
                    after that event they were miserably reduced by various grants, and mainly by
                    the alienation of lands and tithes, by Alexander Campbell, the first Protestant
                    bishop, to his chieftain the Earl of Argyll. In 1572 James VI. with consent of
                    John Earl of Morton, Regent, founded an hospital in the burgh. “Mr George
                    Buchanan, pensioner of Crossragwell,” is one of the witnesses to the grant,
                    which was ratified by his majesty in 1587, when he attained majority. The
                    magistrates and council are patrons of this charity, from which they give a
                    small weekly allowance to the poor, no hospital apparently having ever been
                    erected. William de Brechin founded a chapel in 1256, called Maison de Dieu.
                    Albinus, bishop of Brechin in the reign of Alexander II. was witness to the
                    grant. Parts of the walls of the chapel still remain in the Maison Dieu Vennel,
                    a little west of the High Street, and prove that the chapel had originally been
                    an elegant little building. The house itself, and the property about it, with
                    the superiority of some other lands, are generally gifted by the crown to the
                    rector of the grammar-school during his incumbency, who hence takes the title of
                    preceptor of Maison-dieu. The cathedral, which is now used as the parish church,
                    was originally a handsome Gothic building; but its appearance has been much
                    injured by modern “improvements.” The steeple attached is a noble-looking square
                    tower, with an octagon spire, rising to the height of 128 feet. Close to the
                    church stands the round tower, one of those singular structures which are
                    generally supposed to have been places of look-out belonging to the Picts,
                    although their real use has long baffled the research of antiquaries. These
                    towers are peculiar to North Britain and Ireland; in the latter they are
                    frequent, in the former only two at this time exist, one at Brechin and another
                    at Abernethy. There is no stair in the Brechin tower, and the only access to the
                    top is· by means of six ladders placed on wooden semicircular floors,' which
                    rest on circular projections within the tower. The height from the ground to the
                    roof is eighty-five feet, the inner diameter within a few feet of the bottom is
                    eight feet, and the thickness of the wall at that part four feet two inches, so
                    that the whole diameter is nearly sixteen feet; the circumference is very near
                    forty-eight feet; the inner diameter at top is six feet seven inches, the
                    thickness of the wall two feet ten inches, and the circumference thirty-eight
                    feet eight inches. These proportions give the building an inexpressible
                    elegance. The top is roofed with an octagonal spire eighteen feet high, which
                    makes the whole height of the building 103 feet. Certain it is, that during
                    strong winds this tower has often been observed to vibrate. A stone built into
                    the wall of the church-yard, evidently modernized, but most probably copied from
                    an older stone, records, in not inelegant Latin, that during 1647 six hundred
                    persons died of the plague in Brechin in the course of four months.</p>
                <p part="N">Within the burgh there is a house said to have been a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hospitium</hi> of the knights templars, now appropriately used as an inn.
                    These knights seem to have had some lands in the neighbourhood, as there is a
                    piece of ground close by Brechin bearing the title of Temple Hill of Bothers. A
                    little to the north of this last-mentioned place is Huntly Hill, remarkable for
                    the battle fought there between ’ the Earls of Huntly and Crawford, in
                    consequence of the rebellion raised in 1452, on account of the murder of the
                    Earl of Douglas in Stirling Castle. The victory fell to the royalists under
                    Huntly, who has hence given his name to the ground/</p>
                <p part="N">Brechin Castle, the seat of Lord Panmure, stands on the brink of a
                    perpendicular rock overhanging the South Esk, a ’ little to the south of the
                    town. This castle was <pb break="no" facs="nls:193735988?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0705-5988-0225"/>besieged by the English under Edward I. in
                    1303, and was for twenty days gallantly defended by Sir Thomas Maule, ancestor
                    of the family of Panmure, who was slain by a stone thrown from an engine placed
                    on the opposite rising ground, when the castle was instantly surrendered. The
                    south front of the castle above the river presents a romantic mixed mass of
                    buildings, covered with ivy, and showing some remains of the original structure.
                    The west front forms a regular building, in the style of the seventeenth
                    century.</p>
                <p part="N">Brechin was burnt by the Danes in 1012, and by the Marquis of Montrose
                    in 1645. At present it has a neat appearance, the excellent free-stone quarries
                    in the vicinity giving every opportunity for substantial erections. The chief
                    manufactures of this place consist of various branches of the linen trade. There
                    is also an extensive distillery in the town, and a smaller one in the immediate
                    vicinity; and at the mills of Brechin a good deal of wheat is ground for distant
                    markets. Brechin has a market every Tuesday, which is well frequented by dealers
                    in grain. About a mile from the town, on the Trinity Muir, four annual fairs are
                    held, the principal of which takes place in June. The town is governed by a
                    provost, two bailies, a dean of guild, seven merchant and two trades’
                    counsellors. This burgh is the seat of a presbytery, and, besides the
                    Presbyterian church, it contains a neat Episcopal chapel, two meeting-houses
                    belonging to the United Associate Synod, one belonging to the Original Seceders,
                    and a Relief chapel. There is an endowed grammarschool under a rector, and a
                    parochial school under two teachers besides assistants, with several private
                    schools, in the town.</p>
                <p part="N">Maitland, the laborious historian of Edinburgh and London, and Dr John
                    Gillies, the historian of Greece, were natives of this place. James Tytler, an
                    eccentric and unfortunate personage, one of the contributors to the early
                    editions of the Encyclopaedia Britannica, was born in the immediate
                    neighbourhood. The population of the town and Tenements in 1831 was 5060.
                    Brechin is eight miles from Montrose, thirteen from the county town of Forfar,
                    forty-two from Aberdeen, and the same distance from Perth. Long. 2. 18. W*. Lat.
                    56. 40. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
