<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-5416-0181-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRAMAH, Joseph</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm13w80">Patents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pj93">Keys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h6f">Inventors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1054862">Patents</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978052">Inventors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064480">Pipe</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193735416?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BRAMAH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi></label>, a
                    practical engineer and machinist, was born at Stainborough, in Yorkshire, on the
                    13th of April 1749. His father rented a farm on the estate of Lord Strafford;
                    and, being the eldest of five children, he was intended for the same employment.
                    He exhibited at a very early age an unusual talent for the mechanical arts, and
                    succeeded, when he was quite a boy, in making two violoncellos, which were found
                    to be very tolerable instruments; as well as in cutting a single block of wood
                    into a violin, chiefly by means of tools which were forged for him by a
                    neighbouring smith, whom, at a subsequent period of his life, he induced to
                    assist him in London as one of his principal workmen. Notwithstanding the
                    ingenuity which he had thus displayed, his destination in life might have
                    precluded its further cultivation, had he not, fortunately for himself and for
                    the public, been incapacitated, when he was about sixteen, by an accidental
                    lameness in his ancle, for the pursuit of agricultural labour. He was then
                    apprenticed to a carpenter and joiner, who seems, however, to have contributed
                    but little towards his improvement in mechanical knowledge.</p>
                <p part="N">When the term of his engagement had expired, he obtained employment for
                    some time in the workshop of a cabinet-maker in London, and soon after
                    established himself as a principal in that business. Another accidental
                    confinement left his mind at liberty for a time to occupy itself with reflection
                    and invention; and he employed his involuntary leisure in the improvement of
                    some of the most humble, but not the least useful, of domestic conveniences. He
                    obtained a patent for his inventions, and established a manufacture of these and
                    other similar articles in Denmark Street, Soho, where he continued to simplify
                    and improve the arrangement of the pumps and pipes subservient to his principal
                    purpose. He procured in 1783 a patent for a water-cock, intended to allow the
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193735429?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0705-5429-0182"/>fluid a more uninterrupted passage through it
                    than was practicable in the ordinary construction. He afterwards removed to
                    Piccadilly, and established the various branches of his manufactory in some
                    extensive premises at Pimlico.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1784 Mr Bramah took out a patent for his improvement in locks, which
                    certainly appear to bc of very material importance. Their peculiar character
                    depends on the arrangement of a number of levers or sliders, in such a manner as
                    to preserve, when at rest, a uniform situation, and to be only pressed down by
                    the key to certain unequal depths, which nothing but the key can ascertain; the
                    levers not having any stop to retain them in their required situation, except
                    that which forms a part of the key. The construction is more particularly
                    detailed in the specification of the patent <hi rend="italic">(Repertory of
                        Arts,</hi> vol. v. p. 217), as well as in the inventor’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dissertation on Lochs,</hi> 8vo; and some additional modifications,
                    allowing the key to be varied at pleasure, are described in a patent, dated in
                    1798. It is not easy to say why the application for an act of parliament to
                    prolong the privilege proved unsuccessful, unless it was supposed that the
                    inventor had been already sufficiently remunerated for the share of ingenuity
                    which his contrivance exhibited; but the report, that one of these locks had
                    been readily opened, before a committee of the House of Commons, by means of a
                    common quill, was a gross misrepresentation of the fact; the quill having in
                    reality been previously cut into the required shape from the true key. The
                    experiment, in fact, only served to show the perfection of the workmanship, so
                    little force being required to overcome the resistance when properly
                    applied.</p>
                <p part="N">For different modifications of pumps and fire-engines Mr Bramah took out
                    three successive patents, the two last being dated in 1790 and 1798. <hi
                        rend="italic">(Repertory,</hi> vols. ii. iii.) His “rotative principle”
                    consists in making the part which acts immediately on the water in the form of a
                    slider, sweeping round a cylindrical cavity, and kept in its place by means of
                    an eccentric groove; a construction which was very possibly suggested by his own
                    inventive mind, but which had been before described, in a form nearly similar,
                    by Ramclli, Cavalleri, Amontons, Prince Rupert, and Dr Hooke. The third patent
                    related chiefly to the attachment of a considerable reservoir of water to the
                    fire-engine in a cylindrical form, and to the furnishing of it with wheels of
                    its own, of a proper size and strength to allow it to be conveniently
                    worked.</p>
                <p part="N">There was somewhat more of originality in the idea of applying
                    practically, to the purpose of a press, the well-known principle of the
                    hydrostatic paradox, by which, as by a lever with arms capable of infinite
                    variation, the smallest imaginable weight is made capable of holding in
                    equilibrium a force incomparably greater. Mr Bramah’s patent for the invention
                    is dated in the year 1796 <hi rend="italic">(Repertory,</hi> vol. vi. p. 289),
                    and it has been one of the most successful of his numerous speculations. He
                    added to it, in a subsequent patent, the contrivance of a “retainer,” for
                    keeping goods in a constant state of pressure for an unlimited time after their
                    removal from the press. The apparatus has certainly a considerable advantage in
                    the great steadiness with which the force can be applied, in the facility with
                    which it can be regulated, and the convenience with which it can be continued
                    without alteration; and it has been extensively applied, both on a small and on
                    a large scale, for copying writings, for pressing gunpowder, for proving cables
                    and chains, for raising weights of various kinds, and for drawing piles, and
                    pulling up trees by the roots.</p>
                <p part="N">A simple but a very convenient arrangement of little pumps and pipes has
                    been very generally employed in public-houses under the name of the
                    beer-machine: for this Mr Bramah took out a patent in 1797, describing it as
                    part of an apparatus for retaining, drawing, and clarifying liquors <hi
                        rend="italic">(Repertory,</hi> vol. ix. p. 361). He prefaces his
                    specification with some general observations on the right of an inventor to a
                    property, both in the objects which he selects for his improvements, and in the
                    means which he employs for the attainment of them; and demands of the public
                    justice an ample security for both these rights, grounding this claim on his
                    resolution to make a clear and unreserved disclosure of all his inventions.
                    Besides the method of pumping up the liquors from the various casks through
                    flexible pipes, without the necessity of entering the cellar, he describes a
                    mode of converting every cask into a forcing pump, excluding the air, and
                    raising the liquor to any part of the house, by a load on its head, which is to
                    bc converted into a piston. He mentions also a filtering machine, a vent peg, a
                    method of making pipes, and a new form of stop-cocks.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1801 he obtained a patent for some improvements in the construction
                    of steam-engines, particularly relating to the boilers; and in 1802, one for a
                    very elaborate and accurate machine for producing smooth and parallel surfaces
                    on wood and other materials. The tools of different kinds employed in this
                    machine, such as gouges, spokeshaves, and planes, are carried with a
                    considerable velocity by a rotatory motion, and come successively in contact
                    with the wood, which is placed on a movable carriage gradually advancing. The
                    centre or gudgeon of the axis or shaft, instead of a common step, is supported
                    by a barrel of oil, to which it is fitted by a collar; and this arrangement not
                    only diminishes the friction very considerably, but allows the height of the
                    shaft also to be very easily and accurately regulated by means of a small
                    forcing pump. The inventor thinks this liquid support likely to be as permanent
                    as it is advantageous; but it may be apprehended, that the constant friction of
                    such a collar would cause it to require frequent repairs, in order to prevent
                    the escape of the oil so powerfully compressed. The machine has been erected on
                    a large scale in the arsenal at Woolwich, and is employed with perfect success.
                    The specification includes the description of a mode of turning spherical
                    surfaces, either convex or concave, by the simple contrivance of a tool, movable
                    on an axis precisely perpendicular to that of the lathe; and of cutting out
                    concentric shells, by fixing, in the same manner, a curved tool, nearly of the
                    same form as that which is employed by the common turners for making wooden
                    bowls.</p>
                <p part="N">An improvement in the processes for making paper, with the assistance of
                    new machinery, in large sheets, was secured to the inventor by a patent in 1805
                        <hi rend="italic">(Repertory,</hi> second series, vol. viii. p. 1). The
                    description is accompanied by that of a mode of drying the paper on sliding
                    frames, hung on lines like sashes, and of keeping it in a state of compression
                    by retainers adapted to the hydrostatic press; but Mr Bramah had not leisure to
                    introduce these arrangements into actual practice, although he had been at a
                    considerable expense in preparing the apparatus.</p>
                <p part="N">His next invention was, however, very effectually carried into execution
                    in a particular department, notwithstanding its unpromising appearance, as
                    generally stated in the specification of the patent, which he obtained in 1806
                        <hi rend="italic">(Repertory,</hi> second scries, vol. x. p. 329). He
                    proposes to facilitate the process of printing by means of a roller, composed of
                    a number of circular plates, closely fitted together, and turning on the same
                    axis, each bearing twenty-six letters, with figures, spaces, and various marks,
                    cither engraved or projecting, and capable of being shifted at pleasure, so as
                    to express any single line by a proper combination of the plates. This is
                    described as a substitute for common printing, copperplate engraving, <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193735442?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0705-5442-0183"
                    />and calico printing; and the ink is intended to be supplied by a trough fixed
                    above, and in contact with the cylinder. Now it is obvious that such a machine
                    would be insufferably tedious and inconvenient for every purpose of common
                    printing, which it would be scarcely possible to perform by its means; but when
                    we discover that the inventor had probably in view the apparatus which hc
                    constructed the next year for the Bank of England, for numbering and dating
                    their, notes, we shall be awarc that the means were admirably adapted to the
                    end; a single line only being here wanted at once, in which a single figure was
                    to be changed at each step, and that in a regular order. In fact, during the
                    immense temporary circulation of one and two pound notes, the Bank has been
                    able, by this machinery, under the management of about twenty clerks, to perform
                    the labour of 120, who were before required for the purpose.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Bramah procured a patent in 1809 for a mode of making and holding
                    pens for writing, calculated to save the substance of the quill, by cutting a
                    number of pens out of it, instead of a single one; and those who are not in the
                    habit of making their own pens may often find a convenience in the portable form
                    in which this and other similar “pterophori” are arranged. In 1812 he brought
                    forward his patent for the construction of main pipes, to be carried through the
                    principal streets of a metropolis, of sufficient thickness to withstand a great
                    force, to which the water within them is intended to be subjected, by proper
                    pumps, furnished with air-vessels; so that the water may not only be ready for
                    the immediate extinction of fires, without the necessity of bringing an engine
                    to the spot, but may also furnish a convenient moving power for various
                    mechanical purposes, such as raising weights, by means of tubes sliding out of
                    each other, like those of a telescope. He observes that hc has frequently had
                    occasion to employ a hydrostatic pressure, in many of his operations, equivalent
                    to that of a column of water 20,000 feet high, which is about four tons for
                    every square inch. He also asserts that he can form 500 tubes, each five feet
                    long, capable of sliding within each other, and of being extended, in a few
                    seconds, by the pressure of air forced into them, to a length of 2500 feet; and,
                    with a power of this kind, he seems to have imagined that he could raise wrecks,
                    and regulate the descent of weights of various descriptions.</p>
                <p part="N">His improvements in wheel-carriages, for which he obtained a patent in
                    1814, consisted in fixing each wheel to a separate movable axis, having its
                    bearings at two distinct points of its length, but loosely inclosed between
                    these points in a cylinder filled with oil; and, in some cases, he proposes to
                    fix the opposite wheels to the same axis, though with a power of turning very
                    stiffly round it, in order to lessen the lateral motion of the shafts in very
                    rough roads. Hc also suggests the use of pneumatic springs, formed by pistons,
                    sliding in cylinders, as a substitute for common springs of metal.</p>
                <p part="N">The purpose of Mr Bramah’s last patent was the prevention of the dry
                    rot, by laying on the timber meant to be preserved from it, a thin coat of
                    Parker’s Roman cement, much diluted with water; but he does not appear to have
                    pursued this experiment, having transferred his right in the invention to other
                    hands.</p>
                <p part="N">In addition to the seventeen patents which have been mentioned, he took
                    out two or three others of less importance, at different times; besides a
                    variety of contrivances, which he did not think it necessary to appropriate to
                    himself by a legal privilege. Mr Nicholson has mentioned a double plunger for a
                    forcing pump, as described to him by Mr Bramah <hi rend="italic">(Nich.
                        Jour.</hi> vol. vii. p. 50), which, m the form he has delineated, is
                    certainly possessed of <hi rend="superscript"> no</hi> particular advantage,
                    producing only with a large apparatus the effect of a much smaller. Mr Bramah
                    had erected, in the latter years of his life, some large machines at the Thames
                    bank for sawing stones and timber; he had begun to devise some improvements in
                    bridges and in locks for canals; and he had at one time been actually employed
                    in the execution of some water-works belonging to the department of the civil
                    engineer, which lie completed with ability and with success. His great and
                    various exertions appear in some measure to have exhausted the strength of his
                    constitution; and his last illness was immediately occasioned by a severe cold,
                    taken in the prosecution of his experiments on the tearing up of trees, made in
                    Holt Forest. He died in his sixty-sixth year, on the 9th of December 1814.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Bramah was a sincere believer in the doctrines of the Christian
                    religion; and, notwithstanding his diversified avocations, he left several
                    manuscript essays on religious subjects. In his moral character hc was cheerful,
                    benevolent, and affectionate; in his habits he was neat and methodical; and he
                    knew well how to temper liberality with economy. He often kept his workmen
                    employed more for their sake than his own, when the stagnation of trade deprived
                    him of the means of disposing of the products of their labour. It is surely on
                    the characters of such individuals that the wealth and prosperity of the British
                    empire most essentially depend; an inventive imagination controlled by a sound
                    judgment, an incessant activity of mind and body, a head that can direct, and a
                    heart that can feel, are the genuine sources of that practical superiority which
                    is well known to distinguish the productions of our national industry. <hi
                        rend="italic">(Life of Mr Bramah, by Dr Brown, in the New Monthly Magazine
                        for April</hi> 1815.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(l. l.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
