<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-2255-0707-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURCKHARDT, John Ludwig</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155558">Travel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355164">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193742255?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BURCKHARDT, <hi rend="smallcaps">John
                        Ludwig</hi></label>. This traveller, celebrated for his extensive journeys
                    in the East, was descended from an ancient family in Switzerland, who had been
                    long established at Kirchgarten, near Lausanne. His father, John Rudolph, had
                    been tried by a French military commission on a charge of having delivered up
                    the <hi rend="italic">tête du</hi><hi rend="italic">pont</hi> at Hunningen to
                    the Austrians, and, though acquitted, received such treatment from the French
                    republican authorities as made a lasting impression on his mind, and induced him
                    to remove his family from the territories, where their power predominated, and
                    to establish them at Basle. He then entered into a Swiss corps in the service of
                    England.</p>
                <p part="N">John Ludwig was the eighth son, and born about the year 1785. Having
                    acquired the usual classical instruction at Basle, he was placed at the
                    university of Leipsic; and, after a residence there of two years, according to a
                    custom very usual with German students, of dividing the time of their academical
                    course among several universities, he concluded his studies, and took his
                    degree, at Göttingen. During his residence at the latter seat of learning, his
                    talents, application, and good conduct had gained him the esteem and respect of
                    the professors, but especially of the celebrated Blumenbach. When he resolved on
                    proceeding to England, Blumenbach gave him a letter of introduction to Sir
                    Joseph Banks, who, with the other members of the African Association, to whom he
                    was introduced, accepted his offer of travelling to explore the interior of
                    Africa. After the plan of his journey had been settled, he diligently prepared
                    himself for it by application to those studies which were most appropriate. He
                    passed his time partly in London and partly at Cambridge in acquiring a
                    knowledge of astronomy, chemistry, mineralogy, medicine, and surgery. He
                    suffered his beard to grow, accustomed himself to the dress and manners of the
                    East, and diligently learned to read, write, and speak the Arabic language; in
                    all which pursuits he was much assisted by Browne, who during his travels in
                    Africa had acquired not merely a knowledge of, but an ardent attachment to, the
                    languages and customs of Mahommedan nations.</p>
                <p part="N">After these preparations, and receiving his instructions from the
                    society, he left England, and in April 1809 reached Malta, whence he proceeded
                    to Aleppo in the following October. Being determined to acquire the Arabic
                    language in perfection, he appeared there as a Mussulman under the name of
                    Ibrahim Ibn Abdallah; and, during more than two years passed in that part of
                    Asia, he had so perfected himself in the language as not to be distinguished
                    from the natives, and acquired such accurate <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193742268?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2268-0708"/>knowledge
                    of the contents of the Koran, and of the commentaries upon its religion and
                    laws, that after a critical examination, the most learned Mussulmen entertained
                    no doubts of his being really what he professed to be, a learned doctor of their
                    law.</p>
                <p part="N">During his residence in Syria he visited Palmyra, Damascus, Lebanon, and
                    the other parts of that interesting country, and thence repaired to Cairo in
                    Egypt, with the intention of joining a caravan, and travelling to Fezzan, in the
                    north of Africa. In 1812, whilst waiting for the departure of the caravan, he
                    was induced to maκe a journey to the Nile, as far up as Mahass; and then, in the
                    character of a poor Syrian merchant, he made a journey through the Nubian desert
                    which Bruce had traversed, passing by Berber and Shendy to Suakim, on the Red
                    Sea; whence he performed the pilgrimage to Mecca by way of Jidda. In this
                    journey his privations and sufferings seem to have been of the severest kind. He
                    returned thence to Cairo in a state of great exhaustion, but in 1815 travelled
                    to Mount Sinai, whence he returned again to Cairo in June 1816, and there made
                    preparations for his intended journey to Fczzan, and to explore the sources of
                    the Niger.</p>
                <p part="N">Several hindrances prevented his prosecuting this intention, till at
                    length, in April 1817, when the long-expected caravan prepared to depart, he was
                    seized with an illness which ended his life. He had from time to time carefully
                    transmitted his journals and remarks, and a very copious series of letters; so
                    that nothing which appeared to him to be interesting in the various journeys he
                    made has been lost. But it is much to be lamented that the life of a man so well
                    qualified as Burckhardt should not have been prolonged, till he had been enabled
                    to solve many of the doubts respecting the interior of Africa, which has excited
                    the curiosity of mankind from the most remote ages.</p>
                <p part="N">The communications from Burckhardt have at several periods been
                    furnished to the public in very ample forms, with appropriate maps; and much
                    light has been thrown by them on the geography of the countries he visited, and
                    on the manners, laws, religion, and commerce of their inhabitants. His Journey
                    along the Banks of the Nile from Assouan to Mahass, on the Frontier of Dongola,
                    was published in 1819, in 4to; and the volume contained also a description of a
                    Journey from Upper Egypt through the Deserts of Nubia to Jidda in Arabia. To
                    this is added an Appendix, with an Itinerary from the Frontiers of Bornou by
                    Bahr el Ghazal and Darfour to Shendy; and also notices of the country of Soudan,
                    west of Darfour, and vocabularies of the several languages.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1822 a volume was published containing a Tour from Damascus in the
                    countries of Libanus and Anti-Libanus; a Journal of an Excursion into the
                    Haouran in 1810; a Journey from Aleppo to Damascus in 1812; a Journey from
                    Damascus into the Haouran in 1811; a Journey from 1 )amascus through the
                    Mountains of Arabia Petrae'n in 1812; and a Journal of a Tour in the Peninsula
                    of Mount Sinai in 1816.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1829 was published a posthumous volume <hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                    Travels in Arabia, in 4to (2 vols. 8vo). This is a very interesting work,
                    containing the narrative of a Journey to Mecca and Medina during the time when
                    the former city was the scene of the great Hadj or pilgrimage, as also the best
                    account yet given of the Wahabee power.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1830 appeared another volume, entitled Manners and Cus toms of the
                    Egyptians, 4to; but this, consisting chiefly of the proverbs current among the
                    people of Cairo, is not of equal value with his former publications. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
