<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-2164-0700-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BULGARIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841374">Bulgarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159314">Turkeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28g7v">Cloth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc91">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193742164?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">BULGARIA</label>, a province of European Turkey,
                    extending from the mouth of the Danube, along that river till it meets the Timok
                    above Widdin, on the borders of Servia. The Danube forms the whole of its
                    northern, and the parallel chain of the Balkan its southern boundary. It is
                    about three hundred and fifty miles long, extending from the Black Sea to
                    Servia, by fi <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> om forty to fifty broad.</p>
                <p part="N">This province was the <hi rend="italic">Moesia Inferior</hi> of the
                    Romans, and derives its present name from the Bulgarii or Bulgares, one of the
                    northern hordes who abandoned their dreary plains to seek a more propitious
                    climate in the south. They left the Wolga in the sixth century, and crossing the
                    Danube near its mouth, established themselves in the inviting country which lies
                    between that river and the mountains, extending westward from the shore of the
                    Euxine. Here they defied all the efforts of the Greeks of the lower empire to
                    dispossess them; and their various and sanguinary conflicts form a considerable
                    portion of the history of that period. They carried on many contests with the
                    emperors of the East; but in the eleventh century they were at length confined
                    within certain limits, and the country was reduced to the state of a province.
                    On the decline of the Greek empire, however, it was finally brought <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193742177?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2177-0701"/>
                    under the Turkish yoke by Bajazet, when the Turks had established themselves in
                    the neighbouring province of Rumelia, the ancient Thrace.</p>
                <p part="N">The country, except in the neighbourhood of the Danube and the Euxine,
                    is mountainous; but the sides of the smaller hills afford excellent pasture, and
                    the soil is exceedingly rich and fertile. It is irrigated by a number of rivers
                    and streams, the tributaries of the Danube. The climate is mild, and the
                    productions accordingly are various and abundant. There is a profusion of grain,
                    cattle, wine, wood, iron, &amp;c.; and the province is looked upon by the Turks
                    as the granary of Constantinople. The people have entirely laid aside the
                    warlike character which distinguished their ancestors. The avocations of the
                    greater number of them are pastoral, and their character corresponds with that
                    which is always identified with this mode of life. Mr Walsh, the most recent
                    traveller who has visited the province, gives the following graphic and
                    interesting description of the appearance and character of the people. “Of all
                    the peasantry I have ever met with,” says he, <hi rend="superscript"> ti</hi>
                    the Bulgarians seem the most simple, kind, and affectionate; forming a striking
                    contrast with the rude and brutal Turks, who are mixed among them, but
                    distinguished by the strongest traits of character. On the road we frequently
                    met groups of both, always separate, but employed in the same avocations; the
                    Turks were known by turbans, sashes, pistols, andyatigans; but still more by a
                    ferocity of aspect, a rude assumption of demeanour, and a careless kind of
                    contempt, that at once repulsed and disgusted us. They never turned their
                    buffaloes or arubas out of the way to let us pass, or showed the smallest wish
                    to be civil or obliging: on the contrary, they were pleased if they pushed us
                    into a bog in the narrow road, or entangled us among trees or bushes. Any
                    accommodation in houses was out of the question; if we approached one for a
                    drink of milk or water, we ran the hazard of being stabbed or shot. The
                    Bulgarians were distinguished by caps of brown sheepskin; jackets of cloth, made
                    of the wool undyed of dark brown sheep, which their wives spin and weave; white
                    doth trousers, and sandals of raw leather, drawn under the sole, and laced with
                    thongs over the instep; and they carried neither pistol or yatigan, nor any
                    other weapon of offence; but they were still more distinguished by their
                    countenance and demeanour The first is open, artless, and benevolent; and the
                    second is so kind and cordial, that every one we met seemed to welcome us as
                    friends. Whenever their buffaloes or arubas stopped up the way, they were prompt
                    to turn them aside; and whenever they saw us embarrassed, or obliged to get out
                    of the road, they were eager to show us it was not their fault. Their houses
                    were always open to us, and our presence was a kind of jubilee to the family;
                    the compensation we gave scarcely deserved the name, and, I am disposed to
                    think, if not offered, would not have been asked for. Turkish women we never
                    saw; the Bulgarian women mixed freely with us in the domestic way, and treated
                    us with the unsuspecting cordiality they would show to brothers. Their dress was
                    neat, clean, and comfortable; it generally consisted of a jacket and petticoat
                    of dark blue cloth, with a bright border of list round the edges or down the
                    seams; and a shift of hemp and cotton, very large, hanging far below the
                    petticoat, and gathered in full folds round the neck and arms, and worked or
                    wove with lace-like borders. Married women wear handkerchiefs on their heads,
                    with a long lap-pel hanging on the back behind; girls have their heads
                    uncovered, with their hair braided and ornamented with different coins. All wear
                    ear-rings, bracelets, and rings on their fingers, even girls of three and four
                    years old, and all go barefooted. They are exceedingly industrious, and are
                    never for a moment without their spindle and distaff; they frequently asked for
                    needles, and I greatly regretted I had not brought a few scissors and other
                    female implements, which would have been highly acceptable to them. Their
                    villages generally consist of forty or fifty houses, scattered without order or
                    regularity. Their houses are built of wicker-work plastered, and are clean and
                    comfortable on the inside.”</p>
                <p part="N">The Bulgarians fabricate to a great extent several articles which are
                    famous in Turkey; one is a coarse woollen cloth, and another rifle gun-barrels.
                    But that which is most congenial to their rural habits is the preparation of the
                    otto or attar of roses, a great part of which comes to England. Rose trees are
                    very plentiful, and gardens are laid out for the purpose of cultivating them.
                    The language of the people is a dialect of the Sclavonian, and bears a
                    resemblance to the Russian. Only a few elementary books have been printed in
                    this language, and it has never been reduced to grammatical rules. The books
                    introduced are in Greek, but that language has made .no progress amongst the
                    people, and the consequence is that they are entirely illiterate. Their religion
                    is Christianity, which they embraced on their arrival in the district. They
                    belong to the Greek church, subject to the Greek patriarch of Constantinople,
                    who appoints their bishops. There is generally attached to every two or three
                    villages a priest, who performs the duties of his vocation in each occasionally;
                    but, unless in a very few places, they are destitute of churches, schools, and
                    books. The principal towns, such as Sophia, Shumla, Ternevo, &amp;c., will be
                    described as they occur alphabetically.</p>
                <p part="N">The Bulgarians have extended themselves beyond the limits defined at the
                    commencement. They have crossed the chain of mountains, and now occupy almost
                    exclusively a considerable portion of Rumelia. They are gradually advancing, and
                    in course of time, if their barbarous neighbours allow them to proceed, they are
                    likely to cultivate the almost solitary desert which lies between the Balkan and
                    the sea. The population of Bulgaria is estimated at about 1,800,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
