<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0180-0165-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AYTOUN, William Edmonstoune (9th edition, volume 3,
                    page 165)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825857">Ballade</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825864">Ballads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825860">Ballades</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc29">Ballads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cj85">Signets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n180/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AYTOUN, <hi rend="smallcaps">William
                    Edmonstoune</hi></label>, a Scottish poet, humourist, and miscellaneous writer,
                    was born at Edinburgh, 21st June 1813. He was the only son of Roger Aytoun, a
                    writer to the Signet, and the family was of the same stock as Sir Robert Ayton
                    noticed above. From his mother, a woman of marked originality of character and
                    considerable culture, he derived his distinctive qualities, his early tastes in
                    literature, and his political sympathies, his love for ballad poetry, and his
                    admiration for the Stuarts. At the age of eleven he was sent to the Edinburgh
                    Academy, whence he passed in due time to the University, studied the classics
                    under Professors Pillans and Dunbar, and attended the course of Professor John
                    Wilson on Moral Philosophy. In 1833 he spent a few months in London for the
                    purpose of studying the law; but in September of that year he went to study
                    German at Aschaffenburg, where he remained till April 1834. He then resumed his
                    legal pursuits in his father’s chambers, was admitted a writer to the Signet in
                    1835, and five years later was called to the Scottish bar. But, by his own
                    confession, though he “followed the law, he never could overtake it.” He
                    disliked his profession, and allowed his literary tastes to predominate. His
                    first publication—a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Poland, Homer, and other
                    Poems,</hi> in which he gave expression to his eager interest in the state of
                    Poland—appeared in 1832. While in Germany he made a translation in blank verse
                    of the first part of <hi rend="italic">Faust;</hi> but, forestalled by other
                    translations, it was never published. In 1836 he made his earliest contributions
                    to <hi rend="italic">Blackwood’s Magazine,</hi> in translations from Uhland; and
                    from 1839 till his death he remained on the staff of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blackwood.</hi> About 1841 he became acquainted with Mr Theodore<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n181/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0181-0166"/> Martin, and in association with him wrote a
                    series of light humorous papers on the tastes and follies of the day, in which
                    were interspersed the verses which afterwards became popular as the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bon</hi><hi rend="italic">G</hi><hi rend="italic">ualtιer
                    Ballads.</hi> 1 he work on which his reputation as a poet chiefly rests is the
                    <hi rend="italic">Lays of the Scottish Cavaliers.</hi> The first of these
                    appeared in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi> in April 1843, and the
                    whole were published in a collected edition in 1848. They became very popular,
                    and have passed through nineteen editions, the last of which has spirited and
                    beautiful illustrations by Sir J. Noel Paton and W. H. Paton. Meanwhile, he
                    obtained, in 1845, the chair of Rhetoric and Belles Lettres at Edinburgh
                    University, which he filled honourably and successfully till 1864. He devoted
                    himself conscientiously to the duties of the office, and his pupils increased in
                    number from 30 to 150. In 1849 he married the youngest daughter of Professor
                    John Wilson (Christopher North), whose death, in 1859, was the great calamity of
                    his life. His services in support of the Tory party, especially during the
                    Anti-Corn-Law struggle, received official recognition in his appointment (1852)
                    as sheriff of Orkney and Zetland. In 1854 appeared <hi rend="italic">Firmilian,
                    a Spasmodic Tragedy,</hi> in which he attacked and parodied the writings of
                    Bailey, Sydney Dobell, and Alexander Smith; and two years later he published his
                    <hi rend="italic">Bothwell, a Poem.</hi> Among his other literary works are a
                    <hi rend="italic">Collection of the Ballads of Scotland,</hi> a translation of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Poems and Ballads of Goethe,</hi> executed in co-operation
                    with his friend Theodore Martin, a small volume on the <hi rend="italic">Life
                    and Times of Richard I.,</hi> written for the <hi rend="italic">Family
                    Library,</hi> and a novel entitled <hi rend="italic">Norman Sinclair,</hi> many
                    of the details in which are taken from incidents in his own experience. In 1860
                    Aytoun was elected honorary president of the Associated Societies of Edinburgh
                    University. The death of his mother took place in November 1861, and his own
                    health was failing. In December 1863 he married Miss Kinnear, and health and
                    happiness for a time revived; but his malady recurred, and he died at
                    Blackhills, near Elgin, 4th August 1865. His remains were interred at Edinburgh.
                    A memoir of Aytoun by Theodore Martin, with an appendix containing some of his
                    prose essays, was published in 1867. (w. L. R. c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
