<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0512-0109-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HALE, Sir Matthew</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830288">Benches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026097">Moralities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026093">Morale</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m3b">Moralities</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k55d">Morals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640512?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">HALE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Matthew</hi></label>,
                    the lord chief justice of the King’s Bench in the reign of Charles II., was the
                    son of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640525?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0711-0525-0110"/>Robert Hale, Esq. a barrister of Lincoln’s
                    Inn, and was born in 1609. He was educated at Oxford, where he made considerable
                    progress in learning; but he was afterwards diverted from his studies by the
                    levities of youth. From these, however, he was recalled by Mr John Glanvill,
                    serjeant-at-law; and having applied to the study of the law, he entered himself
                    of Lincoln’s Inn. Noy the attorneygeneral took early notice of him, and directed
                    him in his studies. Selden also distinguished him; and it was this acquaintance
                    which first led Hale to a more enlarged pursuit of learning, having before
                    confined his studies to his own profession. During the civil wars he behaved so
                    well as to gain the esteem of both parties. He was employed in practice by all
                    the king’s party; and he was also appointed by the parliament as one of the
                    commissioners to treat with the king. The murder of King Charles gave him very
                    sensible regret. However, he took the engagement, and was appointed, with
                    several others, to consider of the reformation of the law. In 1653 he was by
                    writ made serjeant-at-law, and soon afterwards appointed one of the justices of
                    the Common Pleas. Upon the death of Oliver Cromwell, he refused to accept of the
                    new commission offered him by Richard, his successor. He was returned as one of
                    the knights of Gloucestershire in the parliament which recalled Charles II. Soon
                    afterwards he was made lord chief baron of the Exchequer; but he declined the
                    honour of knighthood, till Lord Chancellor Hyde, sending for him upon business
                    when the king was at his house, told his majesty that there was his modest chief
                    baron; upon which he was unexpectedly knighted. He was one of the principal
                    judges who sat in Clifford’s Inn about settling the difference between landlord
                    and tenant, after the fire of London; in which capacity he behaved to the
                    satisfaction of all parties concerned. As chief baron he likewise acted with
                    inflexible integrity. A peer of the highest rank went once upon a time to his
                    chamber, and told him, that having a suit in law to be tried before him, he was
                    then to acquaint him with it, that he might the better understand it when it
                    should come to be tried in court. Upon this the lord chief baron interrupted
                    him, and said that his grace (for he was a duke) did not deal fairly to come to
                    his chambers about such affairs, for he never received information of such
                    causes but in open court, where both parties were to be heard alike. His grace
                    then went away not a little dissatisfied, and complained of it to the king as a
                    rudeness which was not to be endured; but his majesty bid him content himself
                    that he was not worse used, adding, that he verily believed Hale would have used
                    him no better if he had gone to solicit him in any of his own causes. Another
                    remarkable incident happened in one of his circuits. A gentleman who had a trial
                    at the assizes had sent him a buck for his table. When Judge Hale heard his
                    name, he asked if he was not the same person who had sent him the venison; and
                    being answered in the affirmative, told him that he could not suffer the trial
                    ιu go on till he had paid him for his buck. The gentleman answered, that he
                    never sold his venison, and that he had done nothing to him which he did not do
                    to every judge who had gone that circuit; which was confirmed by several
                    gentlemen present. The lord chief baron, however, would not suffer the trial to
                    proceed till he had paid for the present, upon which the gentleman withdrew the
                    record. This upright judge was in 1671 advanced to be lord,, chief justice of
                    the King’s Bench; but about four years after this promotion his health declined,
                    and he resigned his high office in February 1676, and died in December
                    following. This excellent man, who was an ornament to the bench, to his country,
                    and to human nature, was the author of, 1. An Essay touching the Gravitation or
                    Non-Gravitation of Fluid Bodies; 2. <hi rend="italic">Difficiles</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Nugoe, or</hi> Observations on the Torricellian
                    Experiment;</p>
                <p part="N">3. Observations on the Principles of Natural Motion; 4. Contemplations
                    Moral and Divine; 5. An English Translation of Nepos’s Life of Pomponius
                    Atticus; and, 6. The Primitive Origination of Mankind. At the time of his
                    decease he also left other works, which were afterwards published, viz. 1.
                    Judgment of the Nature of True Religion; 2. Several Tracts, including a
                    Discourse of Religion, under three heads; 3. A Letter to his Children;</p>
                <p part="N">4. A Letter to one of his Sons on his recovery from the small-pox; 5. A
                    Discourse of the Knowledge of God and of Ourselves, first, by the Light of
                    Nature, and secondly, by the Sacred Scriptures. All these, under the title of
                    Hale’s Moral and Religious Works, were published by Thirlwall in 1805, in two
                    volumes 8vo, with a life of the author by Bishop Burnet. Of his Law Tracts one
                    only appeared in his lifetime, viz. London Liberty, or an argument of Law and
                    Reason, 1650, reprinted in 1682. After his death were published, 1. Pleas of the
                    Crown, or a Methodical. Summary, 1678, in 8vo, continued by Jacob, and reprinted
                    in 1716; 2. Treatise on the enrolling and registering of all Conveyances of
                    Land, 1694, in 4to, reprinted with additions in 1756; 3. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Tractatus</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">successionibus
                        apud</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglos,</hi> or a Treatise on Hereditary
                    Descents, 1700 and 1735, in 8vo; 4. A Treatise on the original Institution of
                    Parliaments, 1707, republished by Hargrave in 1796, 4to; 5. Analysis of the Law,
                    without date; 6. History of the Common Law of England, in twelve chapters, 1713,
                    in 8vo; 7. <hi rend="italic">Historia Placitorum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Coronae,</hi> or History of the Pleas of the Crown, 1739, in two volumes
                    folio, edited by Emelyn. There are a few other tracts and opinions of his, which
                    have been published by Hargrave and succeeding writers on law in their
                    collections. Sir Matthew Hale, by his will, bequeathed to the society of
                    Lincoln’s Inn his collection of manuscripts, which he had been nearly forty
                    years in making, and on which he had spared neither labour nor expense.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
