<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-1786-0207-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEINECCIUS, John Gottlieb</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193641786?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">HEINECCIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John
                        Gottlieb</hi></label> (Theophilus), one of the most celebrated jurisconsults
                    Germany has produced, was born at Eisenberg, in the principality of Altenburg,
                    on the 21 st of September 1681. His father, who was regent of the school of that
                    place, and a man of talents superior to his situation, made him early acquainted
                    with the masterpieces of antiquity, and thus inspired him with a decided taste
                    for study. Heineccius (or more properly <hi rend="italic">Heinecke)</hi> was
                    still very young when he had the misfortune to lose his father; but in his elder
                    brother, who was pastor at Goslar, he found a monitor and guide, who, by his
                    care and instructions, in some measure supplied the place of his deceased
                    parent. From Goslar he proceeded to Leipsic, where he attended the prelections
                    of the illustrious professor who then adorned the university of that place. In
                    1702 he published there a thesis <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >insignibus sacerdotalibus Apostolorum</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> a
                    subject which might have afforded scope for a great display of erudition, but
                    which, as treated by Heineccius, did not indicate the real talent of the author.
                    In this thesis he attempted to combat some assertions of Baronius. Heineccius,
                    the following year, took his degree in arts, and then returned to his brother,
                    who wished him to enter the ecclesiastical profession. But having satisfied his
                    brother as to the reasons which induced him to decline taking orders, he soon
                    afterwards accompanied the latter to Halle, where he became tutor to the sons of
                    Count Golofkin. In 1708 he was admitted into the philosophical faculty of that
                    city, and there published an academical dissertation <hi rend="italic"
                        >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Genuina</hi><hi rend="italic">Christi AEra</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">e Nummis et Inscriptionibus illustrata,</hi> in 4to,
                    republished in 1735, with notes by Liebknecht. Two years afterwards he obtained
                    a chair, which he filled with ability, but without any material increase of
                    reputation. All his studies, however, he regarded as merely preparatory to that
                    of jurisprudence; but it was not until 1716, when he was admitted into the
                    faculty of law, being then in the thirty-sixth year of his age, that he
                    disclosed his designs. His inaugural thesis <hi rend="italic">De Origine
                        et</hi><hi rend="italic">Indole</hi><hi rend="italic">Jurisdictionis
                        Patrimonialis,</hi> which was considered as a masterpiece, procured him the
                    esteem of his judges; and his Abridgment of the Antiquities of the Roman law
                    confirmed the high idea which had been formed of his merit, whilst it extended
                    his reputation throughout all Germany. In 1721 he was appointed to the chair of
                    law, a situation which he filled with an ability and success that reflected
                    credit on the university; and new works, which succeeded one another with
                    inconceivable rapidity, added daily to his reputation. But although he enjoyed
                    the highest consideration, yet finding his allowances insufficient to enable him
                    to bring up his family, he was obliged, in 1724, to accept a chair which had
                    been offered him, with suitable appointments, in the university of Franeker.
                    Three years afterwards, on the invitation of the king of Prussia, he repaired to
                    Francfort-on-the-Ođer, whence this prince obliged him, in 1733, to return to
                    Halle. Everywhere his prelections were attended by an extremely numerous
                    concourse of pupils, attracted by the solid instruction, the luminous method,
                    and the clear and elegant die* tion, for which this illustrious professor was
                    distinguished. His life, barren of incidents, was passed in the prosecution of
                    useful labours; yet notwithstanding his continual occupation, he discharged in
                    an exemplary manner all the duties of society. But sedentary habits and
                    unremitting application at length ruined his health, and he died generally
                    regretted, on the 31st of August 1741, at the age of sixty. A list of his
                    numerous works will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque
                        Germanique,</hi> tom. ii. part 1st. The principal are, 1. Fundamenta styli
                    cultioris una cum Sylloge exemplorum, Halle, 1719, in 8vo; 2. Elementa
                    Philosophiae Rationalis et Moralis, quibus praemissa Historia Philosophica,
                    Francfort, 1728, in 8vo; 3. Antiquitatum Romanarum Jurisprudentiam illustrantium
                    Syntagma juxta seriem Institutionum Justiniani, Halle, 1718, in 8vo; 4. Elementa
                    Juris Naturae et Gentium, Halle, 1738, in 8vo; 5. Praelectiones Academicae in H.
                    Grotii <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Jure Belli ac Pacis</hi>
                    libros, Berlin, 1744, in 8vo; 6. Praelectiones Academicae in Sam. Puffendorf <hi
                        rend="italic">de Officio Hominis et Civis,</hi> ibid. 1742, in 8vo; 7.
                    Historia Juris Civilis Romani ac Germanici, Halle, 1735, in 8vo; 8. Elementa
                    Juris Civilis secundum ordinem Institutionum, Franeker, 1725, in 8vo; 9.
                    Elementa Juris Civilis secundum ordinem Pandectarum, Francfort, 1756, in two
                    vols. 8vo; 10. Elementa Juris Cambiales, Amsterdam, 1743, in 8vo. The works of
                    Heineccius were collected and published by Uhl, professor at
                    Francfort-on-the-Ođer, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Opera ad</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Universam Jurisprudentiam, Philosophiam, et Litteras
                        humaniores pertinentia,</hi> Geneva, 1744-1748, in eight vols. 4to,
                    reprinted in the same city, with additions, 1771, in nine vols. 4to; and to
                    these two editions a supplementary volume was at the same time added. After the
                    works of Cujas, this collection is perhaps the most valuable and necessary to a
                    student of jurisprudence. The commentary of Heineccius on the Julian and Papian
                    laws would alone suffice to place him in the rank of the greatest jurisconsults;
                    and if his authority has decreased somewhat in Germany, which we believe to be
                    the case, it is because his successors, profiting by his researches, have been
                    enabled to surpass him. We are also indebted to Heineccius for editions of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Jurisprudentia Romana</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Attica,</hi> Leyden, 1738, in three vols, folio, with a
                    learned preface prefixed to the first volume. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
