<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0759-0128-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAMPSHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952109">Hay</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pf6k">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640759?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">HAMPSHIRE</label>, or, as it is sometimes called,
                    the county of <hi rend="smallcaps">Southampton,</hi> or of <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Hants,</hi> a shire of England, on the British Channel. It is bounded on
                    the east by Surrey and Sussex, on the north by Berkshire, on the west by
                    Wiltshire and Dorsetshire, and on the south by the sea. Its extreme length is
                    fifty-five miles, but, owing to a projection at its south-west extremity, its
                    mean length is not more than forty-four miles, and its breadth thirty-nine
                    miles. Its area, including the Isle of Wight, which is at the extreme points
                    twenty-three miles long and thirteen broad, is 1645 square miles, or 1,052,800
                    statute acres.</p>
                <p part="N">The whole population amounted in 1801 to 219,656, in 1811 to 245,080, in
                    1821 to 283,208, and in 1831 to 314,700. It appears, by the registers of
                    burials, that the deaths between 1801 and 1811, were one in forty-six of the
                    whole number of inhabitants, that from 1811 to 1821 they were one in fifty-four,
                    and from 1821 to 1831, notwithstanding an increase of mortality by the cholera,
                    they were only one in fifty-six; thus a great and regular increase of the
                    longevity of the population has become apparent. The occupations, at the last
                    census, were as follow: Occupiers of land employing labourers, 2774; occupiers
                    of land not employing labourers, 1234; labourers employed in agriculture,
                    24,675; persons employed in manufactures, 292; employed in retail trade or
                    handicraft, 23,164; capitalists, bankers, and others, 3784; labourers not
                    agricultural, 10,348; other males twenty years of age, 10,348; male servants,
                    3295; female servants, 12,724.</p>
                <p part="N">As a whole, few counties in England are superior to this, or have a less
                    proportion of uncultivated land. But at the western extremity, bordering on
                    Dorsetshire, a small por- ' tion of sandy heath is scarcely productive of any
                    thing but pasture for sheep, or honey. A considerable tract, extending from
                    Winchester to the northern extremity of the county, is down land, principally
                    used for sheep-pasture, but, when brought under the plough, is very fertile in
                    barley, turnips, clover, and sainfoin. Another portion is forest land, including
                    the <hi rend="italic">New Forest</hi> of about 92,000 acres, but within whose
                    boundary a great part of the land is highly cultivated, and very fertile. The
                    abundance of timber trees of large dimensions, the open glades between, and the
                    variety of foliage, as well of the trees as of the underwood, render the scenery
                    of the district highly delightful. The oaks are the principal beauty of this
                    forest; they do not grow to a great height, but swell to large dimensions in the
                    trunk, and shoot out strong crooked branches, which give them a very picturesque
                    appearance, and add to their value as naval timber, by being well adapted to be
                    used as knees for ships of the largest size. The beech trees also grow to a very
                    great size, and contribute to the beauty as well as the profits of the forest.
                    The other forests are Alice, Holt, and Woolmer, extending over about 15,500
                    acres, of which nearly one half belongs to the crown, and affords excellent oak
                    timber; and Bere Forest, of 16,000 acres, whose timber has been much neglected.
                    In these forests there are abundance of deer belonging to the crown, some of
                    which are annually killed, and distributed, according to ancient prescription,
                    to the various officers of the government and the royal household. The greater
                    part of the county is enclosed, and even the down lands are so in a great
                    measure.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal rivers are the Itchen, which forms a part of the estuary
                    of Southampton Water; the Avon, which falls into the sea at Christchurch Bay;
                    the Boldre, which empties itself at Lymington. The Anton, which falls into the
                    Tees, receives many small brooks before it reaches Southampton, where it is lost
                    in that arm of the sea. The canals of the county are but two. The Bassingstoke
                    was begun in 1778, to communicate between that town and London. It is
                    thirty-seven miles in length, and terminates near Guildford, in the river Wey,
                    which falls into the Thames. It passes through a tunnel, near three quarters of
                    a mile in length, under Grewell Hill, near Odiham. This canal was not completed
                    till 1794⅛ when it had cost L.100,000; and the tolls are not yet sufficient to
                    pay the interest. The Andover Canal was begun in 1789 at that town, and
                    terminates at Redbridge; and is useful to con ∙ vey coals and other heavy
                    commodities to the centre of the county.</p>
                <p part="N">The soil of this county is very various, but, in almost every part, it
                    rests on a calcareous subsoil. The uplands are generally appropriated to
                    breeding sheep, and hence the culture of turnips has been much extended. After
                    the turnips are fed on the land, barley is usually sown, and with it clover, or
                    other artificial grass-seeds. To the clover succeeds sometimes wheat or oats,
                    and, when the land is somewhat heavier in texture, occasionally beans; but in
                    few parts of England are the rotations of crops more diversified. The average
                    produce of corn on these high lands is not more than sixteen bushels of wheat,
                    twenty-two of barley, and twenty-four of oats to the acre. The, ploughing is
                    almost universally performed by horses, which are of a very excellent race. On
                    much of the stiffer lands four of these strong horses are thought necessary; but
                    on lighter lands, and with a single-wheeled plough, sometimes two or three are
                    used, and very rarely are harnessed abreast of each other. On the higher lands,
                    the hay for winter consumption is generally made from sainfoin, a plant which
                    peculiarly flourishes when the subsoil is calcareous. It is <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193640772?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0772-0129"/>laid down
                    with much care in extirpating all weeds, and every other description of grasses,
                    and will usually continue for ten years to be fit for mowing; and on some soils
                    it has been found to last even twenty years, and yield abundant crops of hay.
                    There is no part of England in which this valuable grass is so well or so
                    extensively cultivated.</p>
                <p part="N">The corn lands on the lower levels of the county are much more
                    productive; but on those districts they have no occasion for sainfoin, and
                    scarcely for clover, as their rich water meadows supply them with a sufficiency
                    of hay. Some of these meadows are perhaps the most valuable of any lands in this
                    island, and are managed with great skill and attention. Where a rapid stream of
                    water can be passed over them during the whole winter, it seldom becomes frozen;
                    and the grasses grow during the cold weather, so as to be fit for pasture at an
                    early period in the spring, before any traces of vegetation appear in the
                    surrounding fields. This young grass is a provision for the sheep, when no other
                    green food is to be found, and supplies them to the beginning of May, when it is
                    laid up, and in six or eight weeks it is fit to be mowed, and yields most
                    abundant quantities of hay. There is much of this valuable description of land
                    in the fertile valley that extends from Overton to Redbridge, by
                    Stockbridge.</p>
                <p part="N">In the eastern part of the county, bordering on Surrey, there are
                    extensive hop plantations, the produce of which is equal in flavour to those in
                    the adjoining villages of that country near Farnham.</p>
                <p part="N">The original race of Hampshire sheep were white faced, with horns; but
                    these have been so often crossed with other races, that few of an unmixed breed
                    are left. Most of the flocks now are of the Southdown kind; they are found to be
                    more beneficial, both on account of the superior quality of their wool, and the
                    tendency to fatten with a less quantity of food than any others. The cows are
                    not much attended to, and are not generally of the best kind. The introduction
                    of the Welsh breed has made some improvement, but there is room for much
                    more.</p>
                <p part="N">The breeding and fattening of pigs has long been a most important part
                    of Hampshire husbandry. The bacon from them is the principal animal food of the
                    rural inhabitants. In the vicinity of the forests they are fed on acorns and
                    beech-mast; and those so fattened are considered as the best, either as pickled
                    pork, or when converted into bacon. The average weight of these animals, when
                    deemed fit for slaughter, is abóut 440 or 450 pounds, but many of them weigh 800
                    pounds.</p>
                <p part="N">The manufactures of this county are neither numerous nor extensive,
                    except those carried on at Portsmouth, for warlike purposes. Besides the
                    ship-building in the royal yard, there are many vessels, both for war and trade,
                    built on the river Itchen at Buckler’s Hard, on the river Boldre, and on the
                    banks of Southampton Water. The manufacturing of their woollen goods upon a
                    small scale is carried on at Andover, Romsey, Alton, and Basingstoke. Paper is
                    made at Romsey and at Overton. The mills at the latter place have supplied the
                    whole of the thin paper used by the Bank of England for their notes, ever since
                    the reign of George I. Ringwood has been long celebrated for the excellence of
                    the strong beer brewed there, but the quantity has declined of late years. On
                    the sea-shore at Lymington, and on the island of Hayling, near Havant, some salt
                    is made by the evaporation of sea-water. The quantity depends on the degree of
                    heat which prevails during the summer season, as the first part of the process
                    of evaporation is performed by the heat of the sun alone; the brine is
                    afterwards conveyed to iron pans, and the process completed by artificial heat,
                    which, as coals, the only fuel, are dear, makes the whole expensive, and
                    prevents the proprietors from competing with the northern manufacturers of
                    salt.</p>
                <p part="N">The foreign commerce of the county is inconsiderable. Many merchant
                    ships repair to Portsmouth with stores for the naval arsenal; and, in time of
                    war, many prizes are carried thither for sale, which creates some extensive
                    trade. Southampton imports much wine from Portugal, which, before the
                    introduction of the bonding system, used to be deposited in the islands of
                    Guernsey and Jersey, to save the interest upon the amount of the duties. At
                    Christ-church there are a few vessels fitted for the Newfoundland fishery.</p>
                <p part="N">The most populous town in the county is Portsmouth, which, with its
                    adjuncts, Portsea and Gosport, with the adjacent villages, contains between
                    fifty and sixty thousand inhabitants. The far greater part of these are the
                    families oí officers of the navy, army, and marines, and of the arsenal, with
                    the various artificers.</p>
                <p part="N">The harbour of Portsmouth is perhaps one of the best in the world. Its
                    entrance is narrow, and therefore easily defended. The approach to that entrance
                    is defended by batteries, that can rake any ship before it reaches the fire of
                    the castles, at the two narrowest points. The depth of water is sufficient for
                    the largest ships, and the interior spreads out into an extensive basin of still
                    water, in which there is room for all the British fleet to anchor. The system of
                    building no ships of war in private yards has much increased the number of
                    artificers of every description. The mast-making, anchor-making, cable-making,
                    and particularly the making of blocks, are all conducted within the. walls of
                    the arsenal, which, as a whole, is a most astonishing combination of vast powers
                    simply and economically directed to naval purposes. The gun-wharf, victualling
                    office, the king’s mill, and many other public buildings, merit rather a
                    detailed description than such brief notices as our limits allow. One of the
                    finest objects depending on the naval establishment is the hospital for sick and
                    wounded seamen at Haslar. It is 567 feet in length. It is divided into 100
                    wards, each sixty feet long and twenty-four broad, calculated to receive twenty
                    patients, with apartments adjoining for nurses and attendants.</p>
                <p part="N">Southampton is celebrated for the beauty of its environs, the elegance
                    of the streets and buildings, and the purity and salubrity of its air; and it is
                    much frequented for salt-water bathing, as well as on account of a chalybeate
                    spring of considerable repute. In the'summer season it is a place of fashionable
                    resort to those who wish to enjoy rides amongst the pleasing scenery of the New
                    Forest.</p>
                <p part="N">Winchester, a city of ancient date, has fallen into decay, and now
                    depends on its being the county town, the see of the bishop of an extensive
                    diocese, the station of his courts, and a collegiate place, in which many youths
                    of the first families in the kingdom receive their classical education. The
                    cathedral and the castle are venerable piles of antiquity, though the former was
                    much damaged and the latter blown up by the soldiers of Cromwell, after his
                    capture of the city.</p>
                <p part="N">The antiquities of this county are very numerous, and may be
                    contemplated in the ruins of numerous castles, abbeys, and shattered towers,
                    which add not a little to the beauty of the scenery. The most remarkable of
                    these are Calshot Castle, Netley Abbey, Hurst Castle, Porchester Castle, and
                    Beaulieu Abbey. Antiquities of more early date, of ancient British or of Roman
                    origin, are scattered over the county. The numerous barrows are ascribed to the
                    former, and many vestiges of intrenched camps and castles to the latter.</p>
                <p part="N">The beauty of the country has attracted to it a greater number of
                    families of rank and fortune than almost any other county can enumerate, the
                    bare list of which would fill a page.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640785?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0785-0130"/>
                <p part="N">The most considerable towns, with their population, according to the
                    census of 1831, were,</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Portsmouth and
                            Portsea</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">50,389</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Southampton</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">19,324</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Gosport, with
                            Alverstoke</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">12,636</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Winchester</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">9,012</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Romsey</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5,432</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Fareham</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4,402</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Andover</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4,843</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Ringwood</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,434</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Titchfield</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,712</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Basingstoke</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,581</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Lymington</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,361</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Alton</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2,742</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Fordinabridge</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2,611</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">By the law of 1832 this county has, for election purposes, been divided
                    into the northern and southern parts, each of which returns two members to the
                    House of Commons. The northern division contains about 2400 voters. The place of
                    election is Winchester, and the other polling places are, Alton, Andover,
                    Basingstoke, Kingsclere, Droxforđ, Odiham, and Petersfield. The southern
                    division has about 3150 voters; the election is held at Southampton, and the
                    other polling places are Fareham, Lymington, Ringwood, and Romsey. By the same
                    law the boroughs of Whitchurch, Stockbridge, Yarmouth, and Newton have been
                    disfranchised, and the boroughs of Petersfield and Chrlst-church, which used to
                    elect two members, now choose only one each. The towns which now return two
                    members each are, Winchester, Southampton, Andover, Lymington, Newport, and
                    Portsmouth, with which has been incorporated the adjacent large town of
                    Portsea.</p>
                <p part="N">See Brayley and Britton’s <hi rend="italic">Beauties of England and
                        Wales</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Driver’s <hi rend="italic">Exports to the
                        Board of Agriculture ,∙</hi> Milner’s <hi rend="italic">Winchester</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Hampshire Pepository</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> Warner’s <hi rend="italic">Walks through
                        Southampton</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Worsley’s <hi rend="italic">Isle of
                        Wight.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
