<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-2774-0283-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERTFORD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827603">Barley</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936106">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p69w">Barley</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90257q">Servants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193642774?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">HERTFORD</label>, a town, the capital of the county
                    of the same name, twenty-one miles from London, on the river Lea. It is supposed
                    to have been a town as early as the time of the Britons. The Saxon kings held
                    their court at this place; and Alfred, to check the irruptions of the Danes,
                    constructed a castle, the remains of which are still to be seen. It is a
                    corporate town, governed by a mayor or high steward, a recorder, and nine
                    aidermen, and two members are returned to parliament. Christ Hospital in London
                    has here a branch of its establishment, in which 400 boys and sixty girls are
                    educated. There are two parish churches, and several places of worship for the
                    different dissenters from the establishment. The assizes and sessions being held
                    here, brings some trade to the town; and there is a good market on Saturday, at
                    which much corn, especially barley, is sold. The chief trade consists in
                    converting barley into malt for the great breweries in the metropolis. The
                    inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 3360, in 1811 to 3900, in 1821 to 4265, and in
                    1831 to 5247.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Hertford College.</hi> The design of this
                    institution is to train up and qualify a race of youths, for filling in
                    succession the various and important offices of government in our Indian empire.
                    “To dispense justice to millions of people of various languages, manners,
                    usages, and religions; to administer avast and complicated system of revenue,
                    through districts equal in extent to some of the most considerable kingdoms in
                    Europe; to maintain civil order in one of the most populous and litigious
                    regions in the world; these,” says Marquis Wellesley, “are now the duties of the
                    larger portion of the civil servants of the Company. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >senior merchants,</hi> composing the courts of circuit and appeal under the
                    presidency of Bengal, exercise in each of these courts a jurisdiction of greater
                    local extent, applicable to a larger population, and occupied in the
                    determination of causes infinitely more intricate and numerous, than that of any
                    regularly constituted courts of justice in Europe. The senior or junior
                    merchants employed in the several magistracies and courts, the writers or
                    factors filling the stations of registrars, and assistants to the several courts
                    and magistrates, exercise, in different degrees, functions of a nature purely
                    judicial, or intimately connected with the administration of the police, and
                    with the maintenance of the peace and good order of their respective districts.”
                    The marquis points out, in the same strong manner, the arduous duties of the
                    several departments which the Europeans are required to perform in India; and
                    sums up by saying, “that the civil servants of the East India Company can no
                    longer be considered as the agents of a <hi rend="italic">commercial
                        concern</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> they are in fact the ministers and
                    officers of a <hi rend="italic">powerful</hi> sovereign; they must be viewed in
                    that capacity with a reference, not to their nominal, but to their real
                    occupations. They are required to discharge the functions of magistrates,
                    judges, ambassadors, and governors of provinces, in all the complicated and
                    extensive relations of those sacred trusts and exalted stations, and under
                    peculiar circumstances, which greatly enhance the solemnity of every public
                    obligation, and the difficulty of every public charge. Their duties are those of
                    statesmen in every other part of the world; with no other characteristic
                    differences than the obstacles opposed by an unfavourable climate, a foreign
                    language, the peculiar usages and laws of India, and the manners of its
                    inhabitants.”</p>
                <p part="N">The system of education adopted holds a due medium between the
                    strictness of our public schoolsand the laxity of the English universities. Upon
                    being appointed, each youth must undergo an examination in Greek and Latin, and
                    arithmetic, before the principal professors. This previous examination at once
                    prevents persons from offering themselves who have not received the usual school
                    education of the higher classes of society; and those who offer themselves, and
                    are found deficient, are remanded till another period of admission. The lectures
                    of the different professors in the college are given in a manner to make
                    previous preparation necessary, and to encourage most effectually habits of
                    industry and application. In their substance they embrace the important subjects
                    of Classical Literature, the Oriental Languages, the elements of Mathematics and
                    Natural Philosophy, the Laws of England, General History, and Political
                    Economy.</p>
                <p part="N">On all the important subjects above enumerated, examinations take place
                    twice in the year. These examinations are conducted upon the plan of the great
                    public and collegiate examinations in the universities, particularly of
                    Cambridge, with such improvements as experience has suggested. The questions
                    given are framed with a view to ascertain the degree of progress and actual
                    proficiency in each particular department on the subjects studied during the
                    preceding term; and the answers, in all cases which admit of it, are given in
                    writing, in the presence of the professors, and without the possibility of a
                    reference to books. After the examination in any particular department is
                    concluded, the professor in that department reviews, at his leisure, all the
                    papers that he has received, and places, as nearly as he can, each individual in
                    the numerical order of his relative merit, and in certain divisions implying his
                    degree of positive merit. These arrangements are all subject to the control of
                    the whole collegiate body. They require considerable time and attention, and
                    they are executed with scrupulous care and strict impartiality.</p>
                <p part="N">The course of study continues two years, and commences at such an age
                    that the students may be qualified to proceed to India by the time they are
                    eighteen or nineteen years old; and having begun the study of the oriental
                    languages, they are prepared to prosecute them in Calcutta, so as to proceed to
                    their official appointments by the time they have attained the age of twenty or
                    twenty-one.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193642787?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-2787-0284"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
