<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-1045-0150-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARMONY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c946">Sphere</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1245970">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193641045?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">HARMONY</label>, according to the modern definition
                    of the word, is a succession of chords, written according to the laws of
                    fundamental progression and modulation. Harmony is a generic term when it
                    signifies the doctrine of chords; but we also make use of the expression to
                    indicate the effect of a combination of sounds on the ear.</p>
                <p part="N">The history of harmony forms an interesting branch of musical knowledge.
                    In tracing its progress, we observe an almost uninterrupted succession of
                    discoveries in the aggregate properties of sounds. These discoveries are
                    referrible to the early felt and increasing desire to create novelty of effect;
                    to the boldness of human skill and invention, to the improvement of instrumental
                    music, and, without doubt, also to the results of chance. The history of the
                    theory is necessarily dependent upon that of the practice of harmony; for, in
                    proportion as composers have attempted new combinations, it becomes more
                    difficult to trace their origin and reduce them to a general system. The
                    innumerable modifications which chords undergo so essentially change their
                    primitive forms, that we can scarcely wonder at the multiplicity of errors which
                    have been committed in endeavouring to classify them.</p>
                <p part="N">We could almost persuade ourselves that harmony, from its being so
                    natural to man, must have been universally understood in all ages. We learn,
                    however, that the ancients had scarcely any idea of it; and even now the
                    oriental nations are ignorant of harmonic relations, and our music affects them
                    with disagreeable sensations. The knowledge which the Greeks and Romans had of
                    harmony has been the subject of much controversy, but to little purpose. Some
                    treatises on music, written since the time of Alexander the Great, and towards
                    the decline of the Grecian empire, have come down to us; but in none of them do
                    we find the word <hi rend="italic">harmony</hi> employed in the sense in which
                    we now understand it. The chant or song of an ode by Pindar, a hymn to Nemesis,
                    and a few other fragments, without chords of any kind, are all that have been
                    preserved as specimens of ancient Greek music. Moreover, the form of ancient
                    instruments, and the small number of their strings, all tend to render probable
                    the opinion of those who doubt the employment of harmony in the music of the
                    ancients. Their opponents contend that harmony exists <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193641058?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-1058-0151"/>as an
                    elementary part of our nature, and must have been comprehended in the most
                    primitive times; but this opinion we are strongly induced to disregard, from the
                    fact, that to this day the Turks, Arabians, and Chinese are unacquainted with
                    the simplest union of harmonies.</p>
                <p part="N">The first indications of an approach to harmony appeared among the
                    writers of the middle ages, towards the ninth century; but it remained in a
                    state of barbarism till about the middle of the fourteenth century, when some
                    Italian musicians began to mould it into a somewhat agreeable form. Amongst
                    those who distinguished themselves at this remote epoch were, Francesco Cieco,
                    so called from his blindness, and Francesco degli Organi, so designated from his
                    skill in organ-playing, and Jacomo da Bologna. Harmony was still further
                    elucidated by two French musicians, Guillaume Dufay and Giles Binchois, and by
                    John Dunstable, an Englishman, who lived about the early part of the fifteenth
                    century. The advancement of this science must, however, for a long period have
                    been of small extent, and still less interest; for, up to the close of the
                    sixteenth century, we find that consonant chords, and certain discordant
                    prolongations, or suspensions as they are now called, were all that were known
                    and used in music. Composed of such elements, harmony was too limited in its
                    operation to become the groundwork of any intelligible science. It appears
                    indeed probable, that at this dark period of musical history, no systematic
                    connection was even supposed to exist between the chords, or the tones of which
                    they consisted. The intervals were considered only in a double relation; and the
                    art of writing them, according to certain conditions, comprehended the whole
                    doctrine of the schools.</p>
                <p part="N">Towards the year 1590, a Venetian called Monteverde introduced the
                    fundamental discord, and immediately a new impulse was given to the art, which
                    attracted the attention of musicians. About fifteen years after this period,
                    Monteverde’s invention was disputed by Viadana and some Germans, who represented
                    harmony by figures, and considered the nature of musical sounds separately. It
                    was then that the term <hi rend="italic">chord</hi> was introduced into the
                    vocabulary of music; and harmony, or the <hi rend="italic">basso</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">continuo</hi> as it was styled, became a branch of scientific
                    study. For nearly a century, no further advances were made, although a number of
                    elementary works had been published during that interval, to explain the
                    intricacies of the new science.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1699, Sauveur, a French geometrician, entertained such a passion for
                    music, that it became the object of all his pursuits. The doctrine of sounds
                    appeared to him worthy of mathematical analysis, and his researches were so
                    successful, that he founded the science called Acoustics. Availing himself of
                    the labours of Father Mersenne, Sauveur also found that every sound, however
                    simple, was always accompanied with other sounds less sensible. With this
                    experiment Rameau set out, and upon it formed the basis of his harmonic system,
                    which he demonstrated in a series of works published in the early part of the
                    last century. Tartini, although following a different mode of investigation,
                    arrived at conclusions similar to those of Rameau. The latter supposes the
                    treble to be generated by the bass; the former makes the bass result from the
                    treble. Rameau deduces harmony from melody; Tartini, on the contrary, derives
                    melody from harmony. To determine from which of the two schools the best
                    performances are likely to proceed, no more is necessary than to investigate the
                    end of the composer, and discover whether the air is made for the accompaniment,
                    or the accompaniment for the air. Rousseau, in his <hi rend="italic">Musical
                        Dictionary,</hi> gives a decided preference to the system of Tartini; but
                    this celebrated author was not very profoundly versed in these matters.
                    D’Alembert gave a familiar explanation of the doctrines of Rameau, and in 1752
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi><hi rend="italic">of the Theory and
                        Practice of Music,</hi> in which an apparent order and clearness is imparted
                    to a system essentially defective. Marpurg attempted to introduce these
                    doctrines into Germany without success. It is almost unnecessary to add, that
                    they are now universally rejected by all modern theorists.</p>
                <p part="N">It was reserved for Kirnberger, a learned musician, to discover the
                    theory of suspensions, and explain, in his <hi rend="italic">Wahren
                        Grundsätze</hi><hi rend="italic">sum</hi><hi rend="italic">gebrauch der
                        Harmonie,</hi> published in 1773, the laws of harmony, in a manner at once
                    natural and satisfactory. Catcl has reproduced this system in a clear and simple
                    form, in his treatise on harmony, written for the conservatory of music in
                    France. Albretz-berger, Reicha, and several other eminent theorists, have
                    propagated and elucidated the doctrines of Kirnberger with ingenuity and
                    ability, and by their elaborate works have largely promoted the practical uses
                    of harmony. In England the science has been as yet very imperfectly explained.
                    One of the best works we have met with in our language is by Kollmann, whose <hi
                        rend="italic">Treatise on Harmony</hi> displays admirable systematic
                    arrangement, although his ex« positions are rather dry and verbose. See Music,
                    (z. z.)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Harmony</hi><hi rend="italic">of the
                        Spheres,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Celestial Harmony,</hi> a sort of music
                    much talked of by many of the ancient philosophers and fathers, and supposed to
                    have been produced by the sweetly-tuned motions of the stars and planets. This
                    harmony they attributed to the various proportionate impressions of the heavenly
                    globes upon one another, acting at proper intervals. It is impossible, according
                    to them, that such prodigiously large bodies, moving with so much rapidity,
                    should be silent. On the contrary, the atmosphere, continually impelled by them,
                    must yield a set of sounds proportionate to the impression it receives; and as
                    they do not all run the same circuit, nor revolve with the same velocity, the
                    different tones arising from the diversity of motions, directed by the hand of
                    the Almighty, must form an admirable symphony or concert. They therefore
                    supposed that the moon, as being the lowest of the planets, corresponded to <hi
                        rend="italic">mi,</hi> Mercury to <hi rend="italic">fa,</hi> Venus to <hi
                        rend="italic">sol,</hi> the Sun to <hi rend="italic">la,</hi> Mars to <hi
                        rend="italic">si,</hi> Jupiter to <hi rend="italic">ut,</hi> Saturn to <hi
                        rend="italic">re,</hi> and the orb of the fixed stars, as being the highest
                    of all, to <hi rend="italic">mi,</hi> or the octave.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
