<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0664-0643-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ECLECTIC</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 643</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fj36">Platonists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:901409">Eclecticism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:867118">Collards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n664/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ECLECTIC</label> (from ∈κλeγω, I select), a term of which the
                    most important application is in philosophy, denotes a thinker whose views are
                    borrowed partly from one, partly from another, of his predecessors. It perhaps
                    requires to be noted that, where the characteristic doctrines of a philosophy
                    are not thus merely adopted, but are the modified products of a blending of the
                    systems from which it takes its rise, the philosophy is not properly
                    eclectic.</p>
                <p>The history both of ancient and of modern eclecticism shows that eclecticism
                    naturally springs up when, while literary culture makes the doctrines of the
                    chief philosophies familiar and preserves an interest in philosophy, the first
                    pursuit of thinkers is not purely speculative truth.</p>
                <p>In the 2d century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> a remarkable tendency toward
                    eclecticism began to manifest itself. The longing to arrive at the one
                    explanation of all things which had inspired the older philosophers became less
                    earnest; the belief, indeed, that any such explanation was attainable began to
                    fail; and thus men, not feeling the need of one complete logical system, came to
                    adopt from all systems the doctrines which best pleased them. In Panaetius we
                    find one of the earliest examples of the modification of Stoicism by the
                    eclectic spirit; and about the same time the same spirit displayed itself among
                    the Peripatetics.</p>
                <p>The philosophy that took root in Rome, where philosophy never became other than a
                    secondary pursuit, was naturally for the most part eclectic; of this Cicero is
                    the most striking illustration,—his philosophical works consisting of a mixture,
                    with little or no blending, of doctrines borrowed from Stoicism, Peripateticism,
                    and the scepticism of the Middle Academy. And, not to mention numerous names of
                    minor importance, eclecticism had another representative at Rome in the school
                    of Sextius and Sotion, who were half Stoic, half Pythagorean.</p>
                <p>In the last stage of Greek philosophy the eclectic spirit produced remarkable
                    results outside the philosophies of those properly called eclectics. Thinkers
                    chose their doctrines from many sources—from the venerated teaching of Aristotle
                    and Plato, from that of the Pythagoreans and of the Stoics, from the old Greek
                    mythology, and from the Jewish and other Oriental systems. Yet, it must be
                    observed that neo-Platonism, Gnosticism, and the other systems which are grouped
                    under the name Alexandrian, were not truly eclectic, consisting, as they did,
                    not of a mere syncretism of Greek and Oriental thought, but of a mutual
                    modification of the two. It is true that several of the neo-Platonists professed
                    to accept all the teaching both of Plato and of Aristotle, but, in fact, they
                    arbitrarily interpreted Aristotle so as to make him agree with Plato, and Plato
                    so as to make his teachings consistent with the Oriental doctrines which they
                    had adopted, in the same manner as the schoolmen attempted to reconcile
                    Aristotle with the doctrines of the church. Among the early Christians, Clement
                    of Alexandria, Origen, and Sinesius were eclectics in philosophy.</p>
                <p>The eclectics of modern philosophy are too numerous to name. Of Italian
                    philosophers the eclectics form a large proportion. Among the German we may
                    mention (though details cannot here be given) Wolf and his followers, as well as
                    Mendelssohn, Eberhard, Platner, and to some extent Schelling, whom, however, it
                    would be incorrect to describe as merely an eclectic. In the first place he
                    cannot be denied the praise of originality; and, in the second place, it is not
                    so much that his views of anytime were borrowed from a number of philosophers,
                    as that his thinking was influenced first by one philosopher then by
                    another.</p>
                <p>But, during the present century, the term eclectic has come to be specially
                    applied to a number of French philosophers who-differ considerably from one
                    another. Of these the earliest were Royer-Collard, who was mainly a follower of
                    Reid, and Maine de Biran; but the name is still more appropriately given to the
                    school of which the most distinguished members are Victor Cousin, Théodore
                    Jouffroy, Damircn, St Hilaire, Rémusat, Garnier, and Ravaisson. Cousin, whose
                    views varied considerably at different periods of his life, not only adopted
                    freely what pleased him in the doctrines of Laromiguière, Royer-Collard, and
                    Maine de Biran, of Kant, Schelling, and Hegel, and of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n665/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0665-0644"/> the ancient philosophies, but expressly
                    maintained that the eclectic is the only method now open to the philosopher,
                    whose function thus resolves itself into critical selection and nothing more.
                    “Each system,” he asserted, “is not false, but incomplete, and in reuniting all
                    incomplete systems, we should have a complete philosophy, adequate to the
                    totality of consciousness.” But this assumes that every philosophical truth is
                    contained somewhere in the various philosophies; and if, as it would be surely
                    rash to deny, there still remains philosophical truth undiscovered, but
                    discoverable by human intelligence, it is evident that eclecticism is not yet
                    the only philosophy. For a discussion of tho question how far the above dicta of
                    Cousin represent his own method of philosophizing we must refer the reader to
                    the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Cousin.</hi> Eclecticism gained great
                    popularity, and, partly owing to Cousin’s position as minister of public
                    instruction, became the authorized system in the chief seats of learning in
                    France, where it has given a most remarkable impulse to the study of the history
                    of philosophy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
