<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0673-0652-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EDESSA (9th edition, volume 7, page 652)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n673/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EDESSA</label>, or, as it is now called, Urfa or Orfa, a city
                    of Northern Mesopotamia, on the Daisun, a left-hand tributary of the Euphrates,
                    75 miles W. of Diarbekir and 59 E. of Biredjik, in 37° 2Γ N. lat. and 39° 6' E.
                    long. It is surrounded with walls and towers, well preserved on the northern
                    side, has narrow but comfortable and cleanly <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n674/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0674-0653"/> streets, and displays in its bazaar not only
                    the native woollen stuffs, pottery, and silver work, but also a considerable
                    variety of European goods. In the principal square there is a large mosque
                    dedicated to Abraham, who, according to Mahometan legend, was slain in the city;
                    and in its immediate vicinity is a pond shaded by fine pomegranate, plain, and
                    cypress trees, and tenanted from time immemorial by sacred fish. The only
                    ancient remains are those of a tower ascribed by tradition to Nimrod; but in the
                    neighbourhood there exist extensive catacombs with numerous inscriptions of an
                    early date. The prevailing language is Turkish, though more than three-fourths
                    of the inhabitants are Christian. The population was estimated about 1796 by
                    Olivier as from 20,000 to 24,000; by Buckingham at 50,000; and, in 1873, by
                    Chernik at 40,000. There are two mission establishments, an American and a
                    French, and in connection with the former a school with about 250 pupils. The
                    outskirts are occupied by melongardens, vineyards, and mulberry plantations.</p>
                <p>Nothing is known of the origin of Edessa. It has been suggested that probably the
                    early inhabitants were Sabaeans, and that the sacred fish originally belonged to
                    the worship of Atergatis. According to the Targum of the pseudo-Jonathan,
                    Jerome, and Ephraem Syrus, the city is to be identified with the Erech of
                    Genesis x.</p>
                <p>10, and the local tradition of the Arabs and Jews makes it the same as Ur of the
                    Chaldees; but there is no historical basis for either identification, though the
                    former has received the support of Michaelis, Buttmann, and Von Bohlen. The
                    first authentic mention of the city connects it with Seleucus, who appears to
                    have greatly increased its prosperity, and was probably the bestower of the name
                    by which it is best known in history. This, according to Stephanus, was taken
                    from the Macedonian Edessa, from the abundance of the water in both cities, but
                    a modern etymologist recognizes the Syrian Haditha or New Town. Another
                    designation, Callirhoe, found in the ancient writers, undoubtedly alludes to its
                    fountain; and it is at least possible that this may be the derivation of its
                    modern name—Urlιoi among the Syrians, Er Roha among the Arabs, and Orfa among
                    the Turks and Christians. In the time of Antiochus VII., about 135 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.o.,</hi> the city became the seat or centre of the
                    Osrhoenic kingdom, founded by Orhoi-Bar-Khevyo, and governed for centuries by a
                    series of elective monarchs. Of these the eighth in succession, Abgar Bar-Abgar,
                    fought against Lucullus, but afterwards sided with the Romans; the fifteenth
                    Abgar Uchomo is famous for the legendary correspondence with Christ reported by
                    Eusebius. The city was plundered by Trajan’s general Lusius Quietus, and the
                    kingdom became tributary in 116. Restored by Hadrian it was finally abolished by
                    Caracalla in 217, and a Roman military colony was established with the title of
                    Colonia Marcia Edessorum. Meanwhile Christianity had been taking fast root in
                    the city, the first church having been built as early at least as 202. By the
                    time of Julian, the wealth of the Christians was sufficient to attract his
                    revengeful cupidity; and in the course of the following century, the number of
                    monasteries alone .is said to have exceeded 300. Great theological schools were
                    established, and the city, in fact, became one of the chief seats of Oriental
                    learning. Most famous of all was the <hi rend="italic">Schola Persica</hi> or
                    Persian School; but its professors having adopted the Nestorian heresy were
                    expelled by Martyrus the bishop, and the building was destroyed in 489, and
                    replaced by St Mary’s Church. The prosperity of the city gradually disappeared
                    during the next five centuries, as it passed successively into the hands of the
                    Arabs and the Seljuks. From the latter it was captured in 1097 by Baldwin de
                    Bouillon, and for the next fifty years it continued an independent Christian
                    countship. Baldwin’s successors were his cousin Baldwin</p>
                <p>11. (1100-1118), Jocelin de Courtenay, surnamed the Great (1118- 1131), and
                    Jocelin II. (1131-1144). The negligence of this last count permitted the city to
                    fall into the hands of Zengi of Mosul, and in 1466, the attempt of the
                    inhabitants to recover their independence brought down the vengeance of Zengi’s
                    successor Nur-eddin. The sultans of Egypt and Syria obtained possession in 1181,
                    the Byzantines in 1234, the Mongolians under Tamurlane about 1393, the Turkomans
                    and the Persians at a later date, and finally the Turks in 1637.</p>
                <p>See Assernani <hi rend="italic">Bibliοth. Orient.,</hi> vol. I, where the “Chron.
                    Edessenum" is reprinted; Th. L. Bayer, <hi rend="italic">Uistoria
                        Osrheena</hi><hi rend="italic">et Edessena</hi><hi rend="italic">ex</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">nummis illustrata,</hi> St Petersburg, 1734.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
