<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0663-0642-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ECKHART, Johannes</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 642</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1092260">Redemptioners</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n663/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ECKHART, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johannes</hi></label>, or,
                    according to the general designation, Meister Eckhart, the first of the great
                    speculative mystics, flourished during the latter part of the 13th century and
                    the early part of the 14th. Extremely little is known of his life; the date and
                    place of his birth are equally uncertain. According to some accounts, he was a
                    native of Strasburg, a town with which he was afterwards closely connected;
                    according to others, he was born in Saxony. Trithemius, one of the best
                    authorities, speaks of him merely as “Teutonicus.” 1260 has frequently beeD
                    given as the date of his birth; it was in all probability some years earlier,
                    for we know that he was advanced in age at the time of his death, about 1327. He
                    appears to have entered the Dominican order, and to have acted for some time as
                    professor at one of the colleges in Paris. His reputation for learning was very
                    high, and in 1302 he was summoned to Rome by Boniface VIΠ., to assist in the
                    controversy then being carried on with Philip of France. From Boniface he
                    received the degree of doctor. In 1304 he became provincial of his order for
                    Saxony, and in 1307 was vicar-general for Bohemia. In both provinces he was
                    distinguished for his practical reforms and for his power in preaching. In what
                    manner he ceased to hold his high office we do not know; indeed, several years
                    of his life about this time are a complete blank. Towards 1325 we hear of him as
                    preaching with great effect at Cologne, where he gathered round him a numerous
                    band of followers. Before this time, and in all probability at Strasburg, where
                    he appears to have been for some years, he had come in contact with the <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Beghards</hi><hi rend="italic">(g. v.)</hi> and Brethren of the
                    Free Spirit, whose fundamental notions he may indeed be said to have
                    systematized and expounded in the highest form to which they could attain. In
                    1327 the opponents of the Beghards laid hold of certain propositions contained
                    in Eckhart’s works, and he was summoned before the Inquisition at Cologne. The
                    history of this accusation is by no means clear. Eckhart appears, however, to
                    have made a conditional recantation—that is, he professed to disavow whatever in
                    his writings could be shown to be erroneous. Further appeal, perhaps at his own
                    request, was made to the Pope, and in 1329 a bill was published condemning
                    certain propositions extracted from Eckhart’s works. But before its publication
                    Eckhart was dead. The exact date of his death is unknown. Of his writings,
                    several of which are enumerated by Trithemius, there remain only the Sermons and
                    a few tractates. Till recently the majority of these were attributed to Tauler,
                    and it is only from Pfeiffer’s careful edition <hi rend="italic">{Deutsche
                    Mystiker</hi><hi rend="italic">d. XIV.</hi><hi rend="italic">Jahrhunderts,</hi>
                    vol. ii., 1857) that one has been able to gather a true idea of Eckhart’s
                    activity. From his works it is evident that he was deeply learned in all the
                    philosophy of the time. He was a thorough Aristotelian, but by preference
                    appears to have been drawn towards the mystical writings of the neo-Platonists
                    and the pseudoDionysius. His style is unsystematic, brief, and abounding in
                    symbolical expression. His manner of thinking is clear, calm, and logical, and
                    he has certainly given the most complete exposition of what may be called
                    Christian pantheism.</p>
                <p>Eckhart has been called the first of the speculative mystics; but such a
                    designation requires some qualification. Within the Christian church from the
                    time of Erigena there had been a constant stream of what must be called
                    mysticism, originating for the most part from the writings of the neo-Platonists
                    and of Dionysius the Areopagite. This tendency may be noted in Bonaventura, in
                    Albert (under whom Eckhart is said to have studied), and in Aquinas; it is more
                    prominent in Hugo and Richard of St Victor, though with them it took a practical
                    rather than a speculative direction. But in all these writers, with the partial
                    exception of Erigena, who occupies a quite peculiar position, the mystical
                    element was in strict subordination to the church doctrines, which might be
                    speculatively <hi rend="italic">symbolized,</hi> but were not thereby explained
                    or rationalized. In Eckhart’s writings and preaching, on the other hand, the
                    element of mystical speculation for the first time comes to the front as
                    all-important. By its means the church doctrines are made intelligible to the
                    many, and from it the church dogmas receive then· true significance. It was but
                    natural that he should gradually diverge more and more widely from the
                    traditional doctrine, so that at length the relation between his teaching and
                    that of the church appeared to be one of opposition rather than of
                    reconciliation. Eckhart is thus in truth the first who attempted with perfect
                    freedom and logical consistency to gi∖3 a speculative basis to religious
                    doctrines.</p>
                <p>It is not possible to expound in detail how Eckhart endeavours to explain the
                    main principles of the Christian faith, but it is necessary to note the two most
                    important points in his as in all mystical theories. These are first, his
                    doctrine of the divine nature, and second, his explanation of the relation
                    between God and human thought. The two are logically connected, and a complete
                    exposition of his theory might start from either his theology or his psychology.
                    Lasson, the author of a most valuable monograph on Eckhart, adopts the latter
                    course, but for many reasons the other appears the most systematic.</p>
                <p>The fundamental thought from which Eckhart’s theology starts is that of the
                    Absolute or Abstract Unity as the only real existence. Apart from God no thing
                    has real being. But this Absolute is, for Eckhart, the Zteu·s <hi rend="italic"
                    >absconditus,</hi> the 0eδs <hi rend="italic">άγνωστοί</hi> of the neo-Platonic
                    theology. With Dionysius the Areopagite, Eckhart describes this divine essence,
                    the Godhead, as absolutelywithoutpredicates; all determinations are limitations
                    which destroy its infinite being. The Godhead is incomprehensible,
                    inexpressible. It is in truth nothing; yet as the most real of beings it must be
                    conceived as absolutely potential, as containing in itself the origin and final
                    end of all things. This Godhead is not God as known to us. From the Godhead the
                    triune God <hi rend="italic">proceeds</hi> or is evolved. At this point, at the
                    transition between the divine absolute and the personal deity, Eckhart is face
                    to face with the crucial difficulty of all speculative mysticism, and it is of
                    interest to compare his method of solution with that adopted by later thinkers
                    of like tendencies, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> Boehme and Baader. In the
                    Godhead, as in everything, according to Eckhart, there must be distinguished
                    matter and form, or, as they are here called, essence and nature. The matter or
                    essence is the potentiality, what the thing is in itself; the form or nature is
                    that which it becomes as an object for others. The Godhead reveals itself in the
                    personal God, the Father. For the Godhead is a spiritual substance, and as such
                    can only become real by consciousness, by reflection on self, by
                    self-expression. That which reflects and expresses is the Father. The Son is the
                    Word, or expression through and in which the Father becomes self-conscious. As
                    there is here no distinction of time or space, Father and Son are in very truth
                    one. The Father eternally begets the Son, and the return of the Son into the
                    Father in love and mutual will is the Spirit. The Father is not before the Son;
                    only through the begetting of the Son, only through arriving at
                    self-consciousness, does He become the Father.</p>
                <p>The genesis of the Son from the Father involves also, according to Eckhart, the
                    production of the world of things. For God is reason, and in reason is contained
                    the ideal world, the world of creatures, not in time and space, which becomes
                    materialized. In the Son are all things made, but only, Eckhart is careful to
                    point out, in ideal form. He holds strongly to the so-called Platonic view that,
                    over and above sensible things, there exists a realm of ideal forms or
                    exemplars, to be apprehended by pure thought, through thought freed from the
                    limitations of space and time. How this ideal world is related to the world of
                    real things he does not show, nor does he explain the apparent independence of
                    the material universe. When, therefore, Eckhart speaks of the world as necessary
                    to the divine existence, of God as loving Himself in created things, and of all
                    things being God, he must be understood to speak of this ideal world, not of
                    things as known to us.</p>
                <p>As all things have arisen from God, so all things desire to return into the unity
                    of the divine being. Repose in God is the final end of all things. In man, the
                    noblest of created things, this return is brought about. In man, specially,
                    there is the faculty of supra-rational cognition, the power of reaching to the
                    absolute, the ground both of God and of the universe. This peculiar power,
                    called <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n664/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0664-0643"/> by Eckhart the spark <hi rend="italic">{Fhnklcin,
                    Scintilla),</hi> is in truth God working in man. In cognition of God, God and
                    man are one; there is no distinction of knower and known, and hence, as opposed
                    to empirical knowledge, it may be called faith. In such faith, there is involved
                    not only reason, but will, for the divine illumination becomes operative or
                    takes real effect through the will.</p>
                <p>To attain to full union with God is the final end of activity, and the means, it
                    is clear, must be the resignation of all individuality. Absolute quietism
                    appears to be the only method whereby the birth of the Son in the soul may be
                    brought about. When this state has been reached, then the human soul is one with
                    God; its will is God’s; no evil can be wrought by it; it cannot sin. The
                    practical consequences which would flow from such a doctrine, and which did
                    appear among the Brethren of the Free Spirit, were evaded, rather than overcome,
                    by Eckhart. For, according to his teaching, all the above applies only to the
                    “spark” in the soul; the other faculties may be reasonably and legitimately
                    employed about other and temporal matters. By this loop-hole, also, he escapes
                    the doctrine that works are entirely inefficacious. He is careful to hold the
                    balance between inward feeling and outward action, and on this point his
                    teaching is important in relation to the later Reformation thinkers.</p>
                <p>On the specifically theological doctrines of Eckhart, such as Grace, Incarnation,
                    the Fall, Redemption and Sin, it is not possible to enter in brief compass. A
                    most adequate account of them will be found in Lasson’s monograph above referred
                    to.</p>
                <p>The most important of the many works upon Eckhart, are—Pfeiffer, <hi
                    rend="italic">Deutsche</hi><hi rend="italic">Mystiker,</hi> vol. ii.; Martensen,
                    <hi rend="italic">Meister Eckhart,</hi> 1842; Bach, <hi rend="italic">Meister
                    Eckhart</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic">Vater</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">der Deutschen</hi><hi rend="italic">Speculation,</hi> 1864;
                    Lasson, <hi rend="italic">Meister Eckhart</hi><hi rend="italic">der
                    Mystiker,</hi> 1868; Ullmann, <hi rend="italic">Reformatoren vor der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Reformation,</hi> 1842; Preger, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte d.
                    Deutschen Mystik,</hi> i., 1874.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
