<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0618-0597-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EARTH, Figure of the (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    597)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243607">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s24s">Mass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0660t">Ellipsoid</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1011191">Mass</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1011506">Masses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908167">Ellipsoid</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n618/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EARTH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Figure of the</hi></label>. The
                    determination of the figure of the earth is a problem of the highest importance
                    in astronomy, inasmuch as the diameter of the earth is the unit to which all
                    celestial distances must be referred. Reasoning, doubtless, from the uniform
                    level appearance of the horizon in any situation in which a spectator can be
                    placed—the variations in altitude of the circumpolar stars as one travels
                    towards the north or south, the disappearance of a ship standing out to sea, and
                    perhaps other phenomena— the earliest astronomers universally regarded this
                    earth as a sphere, and they endeavoured to ascertain its dimensions. Aristotle
                    relates that the mathematicians had found the circumference to be 400,000
                    stadia. But Eratosthenes appears to have been the first who entertained an
                    accurate idea of the principles on which the determination of the figure of the
                    earth really depends, and attempted to reduce them to practice. His results were
                    very inaccurate, but his method is the same as that which is followed at the
                    present day—depending, in fact, on the comparison of a line measured on the
                    earth’s surface with the corresponding arc of the heavens. He observed that at
                    Syene in Upper Egypt, on the day of the summer solstice, the sun was exactly
                    vertical, whilst at Alexandria at the same season of the year its zenith
                    distance was 7° 12', or one-fiftieth of the circumference of a circle. He
                    assumed that these places were on the same meridian; and, reckoning their
                    distance apart as 5000 stadia, he inferred that the circumference of the earth
                    was 250,000 stadia. A similar attempt was made by Posidonius, who adopted a
                    method which differed from that of Eratosthenes only in using a star instead of
                    the sun. He obtained 240,000 stadia for the circumference. But it is impossible
                    to form any correct opinions as to the degree of accuracy attained in these
                    measures, as the length of the stadium is unknown. Ptolemy in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Geography</hi> assigns the length of the degree as 500
                    stadia.</p>
                <p>The Arabs, who were not inattentive to astronomy, did not overlook the question
                    of the earth’s magnitude. The caliph Almamoum, 814 A.D., having fixed on a spot
                    in the plains of Mesopotamia, despatched one company of astronomers northwards
                    and another southwards, measuring the journey by rods, until each found the
                    altitude of the pole to have changed one degree. But the result of this
                    measurement does not appear to have been very satisfactory. From this time the
                    subject seems to have attracted no attention until about 1500, when Fern el, a
                    Frenchman, measured a distance in the direction of the meridian near Paris by
                    counting the number of revolutions of the wheel of his carriage as he travelled.
                    His astronomical observations were made with a triangle used as a quadrant, and
                    his resulting length of a degree was by a happy chance very near the truth.</p>
                <p>The next geodesist, Willebrυrd Snell, took an immense step in the right direction
                    by substituting a chain of triangles for actual linear measurement. The account
                    of this operation was published at Leyden in 1617. He measured his base line on
                    the frozen surface of the meadows near Leyden, and measured the angles of his
                    triangles, which lay between Alkmaar and Bergen-op-Zoom, with a quadrant and
                    semicircles. He took the precaution of comparing his standard with that of the
                    French, so that his result was expressed in toises (the length of the toise is
                    about 6 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 39 English feet). The work was recomputed
                    and reobserved by Muschenbroek in 1729.</p>
                <p>In 1637 an Englishman, Richard Norwood, published his own determination of the
                    figure of the earth in a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">The Seaman's
                        Practice, cοntayniηg</hi><hi rend="italic">a Fundamentali</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Probleme</hi><hi rend="italic">in Navigation experimentally
                        verified, namely, touching the</hi><hi rend="italic">Compasse</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">of the Earth and Sea and the quantity of a Degree in our
                        English Measures.</hi> It appears that he observed on the 11th June 1633 the
                    sun’s meridian altitude in London as 62° Γ, and on June 6, 1635, his meridian
                    altitude in York as 59° 33 ’. He measured the distance between these places
                    along the public road partly with a chain and partly by pacing. By this means,
                    through compensation of errors, he arrived at 367,176 feet for the degree—a very
                    fair result.</p>
                <p>The application of the telescope to circular instruments was the next important
                    step in the science of measurement. Picard was the first who in 1669, with the
                    telescope, using such precautions as the nature of the operation requires,
                    measured an arc of meridian. He measured with wooden rods a base line of 5663
                    toises, and a second or base of verification of 3902 toises; his triangulation
                    extended from Mal voisine, near Paris, to Sourdon, near Amiens. The angles of
                    the triangles were measured with a quadrant furnished with a telescope having
                    cross-wires in its focus. The difference of latitude of the terminal stations
                    was determined by observations made "with a sector on a star in Cassiopeia,
                    giving 1° 22' 55'' for the amplitude. The terrestrial measurement gave 78,850
                    toises, whence he inferred for the length of the degree 57,060 toises.</p>
                <p>Hitherto geodetic observations had been confined to the determination of the
                    magnitude of the earth considered as a sphere, but a discovery made by Richer
                    turned tho attention of mathematicians to its deviation from a spherical form.
                    This astronomer, having been sent by the Academy of Sciences of Paris to the
                    island of Cayenne, in South America, for the purpose of determining the amount
                    of terrestrial refraction and other astronomical objects, observed that his
                    clock, which had been regulated at Paris to beat seconds, lost about two minutes
                    and a half daily at Cayenue, and that in order to bring it to measure mean solar
                    time it was necessary to shorten the pendulum by more than a line. This fact,
                    which appeared exceedingly curious, and was scarcely credited till it had been
                    confirmed by the subsequent observations of Varin and Deshayes on the coasts of
                    Africa and America, was first explained in the third book of Newton’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Principia,</hi> who showed that it could only be referred to a
                    diminution of gravity arising either from a protuberance of the equatorial parts
                    of the earth and consequent increase of the distance from the centre or from the
                    counteracting effect of the centrifugal force. About the same time, 1673,
                    appeared the work of Huyghens entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Horologio</hi><hi rend="italic">Oscillator™,</hi> in which for
                    the first time were found correct notions on the subject of centrifugal force.
                    It does not, however, appear that they were applied to the theoretical
                    investigation of the figure of the earth before the publication of Newton's <hi
                        rend="italic">Principia.</hi> In 1690 Huyghens, following up the subject,
                    published his treatise entitled <hi rend="italic">De Causa</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Gravitatis,</hi> which contains an investigation of the figure of the earth
                    on the supposition that the attraction of every particle is towards the
                    centre.</p>
                <p>Between 1684 and 1718 J. and D. Cassini, starting from Picard’s base, carried a
                    triangulation northwards from Paris to Dunkirk and southwards from Paris to
                    Collioure. They measured a base of 7246 toises near Perpignan, and a somewhat
                    shorter base near Dunkirk; and from the northern portion of the arc, which had
                    an amplitude of 2’ 12' 9", obtained for the length of a degree 56,960 toises;
                    while from the southern portion, of which the amplitude was 6° 18' 57'', they
                    obtained 57,097 toises. The immediate inference from this was that, the degree
                    diminishing with increasing latitude, the earth must be a prolate spheroid. This
                    conclusion was totally opposed to the theoretical investigations of Newton and
                    Huyghens, and created a great sensation among the scientific men of the day. The
                    question was far too important to be allowed to remain unsettled, and
                    accordingly the Academy of Sciences of Paris determined to apply a decisive test
                    by the measurement of arcs at a great distance from each other. For this purpose
                    some of the most distinguished <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n619/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0619-0598"/> members of their body undertook the
                    measurement of two meridian arcs—one in the neighbourhood of the equator, the
                    other in a high latitude; and so arose the celebrated expeditions of the French
                    Academicians. In May 1735, MM. Godin, Bouguer, and De la Condamine, under the
                    auspices of Louis XV., proceeded to Peru, where, assisted by two Spanish
                    officers, after ten years of laborious exertion they measured an arc of 3° 7'
                    intersected by the equator. The second party consisted of Maupertuis, Clairaut,
                    Camus, Lemonnier, and Outhier, who reached the Gulf of Bothnia in July 1736;
                    they were in some respects more fortunate than the first party, inasmuch as they
                    completed the measurement of an arc near the polar circle of 57'amplitude and
                    returned to Europe within sixteen months from the date of their departure.</p>
                <p>The measurement of Bouguer and De la Condamine was executed with great care, and
                    on account of the locality, as well as the manner in which all the details were
                    conducted, it has always been regarded as a most valuable determination. The
                    southern limit was at a place called Tarqui, the northern at Cotchesqui. A base
                    of 6272 toises was measured in the vicinity of Quito, near the northern
                    extremity of the arc, and a second base of 5260 toises near the southern
                    extremity. The mountainous nature of the country made the work very laborious,
                    in some instances the difference of heights of two neighbouring stations
                    exceeding a mile. The difficulties with which the observers had to contend were
                    increased by the opposition of the more ignorant of the inhabitants, and they
                    were at times in danger of losing their lives. They had also much trouble with
                    their instruments, those with which they were to determine the latitudes proving
                    untrustworthy. But their energy and ingenuity were equal to the occasion, and
                    they succeeded by simultaneous observations of the same star at the two
                    extremities of the arc in obtaining very fair results. The whole length of the
                    arc amounted to 176,945 toises, while the difference of latitudes was 3° 7' 3”.
                    In consequence of a misunderstanding that arose between De la Condamine and
                    Bouguer, their operations were conducted separately, and each wrote a full and
                    interesting account of the operation. Bouguer’s book was published in 1749; that
                    of De la Condamine in 1751. The toise used in this measure was ever after
                    regarded as <hi rend="italic">the</hi> standard toise, and is always referred to
                    as the <hi rend="italic">Toise of Peru.</hi></p>
                <p>The party of Maupertuis, though their work was quickly despatched, had also to
                    contend with great difficulties. They were disappointed in not being able to
                    make use of the small islands in the Gulf of Bothnia for the trigonometrical
                    stations, and were forced to penetrate into the forests of Lapland. They
                    commenced operations at Tornea, a city situated on the mainland near the
                    extremity of the gulf. From this, the southern extremity of their arc, they
                    carried a chain of triangles northward to the mountain Kittis, which they
                    selected as the northern terminus. In the prosecution of this work they suffered
                    greatly from cold and the bites of flies and gnats. The latitudes were
                    determined by observations with a sector (made by Graham) of the zenith distance
                    of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and δ Draconis. The base line was measured on the
                    frozen surface of the river Tornea about the middle of the arc; two parties
                    measured it separately, and they differed by about 4 inches. The result of the
                    whole was that the difference of latitudes of the terminal stations was 57' 29"
                    ’ 6, and the length of the arc 55,023 toises. In this expedition, as well as in
                    that to Peru, observations were made with a pendulum to determine the force of
                    gravity; and these observations coincided with the geodetical results in proving
                    that the earth was an oblate and not prolate spheroid.</p>
                <p>In 1740 was published in the Paris <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> an account, by
                    Cassini de Thury, of a remeasurement by himself and Lacaille of the meridian of
                    Paris. With a view to determine more accurately the variation of the degree
                    along the meridian, they divided the distance from Dunkirk to Collioure into
                    four partial arcs of about two degrees each, by observing the latitude at five
                    stations. The anomalous results previously obtained by J. and D. Cassini were
                    not confirmed, but on the contrary the length of the degree derived from these
                    partial arcs showed on the whole an increase with increasing latitude. In
                    continuation of their labours, Cassini and Lacaille further measured an arc of
                    parallel across the mouth of the Rhone. The difference of time of the
                    extremities was determined by the observers at either end noting the instant of
                    a signal given by flashing gunpowder at a point near the middle of the arc.</p>
                <p>While at the Cape of Good Hope in 1752, engaged in various astronomical
                    observations, Lacaille measured an arc of meridian of 1° 13' 17'', which gave
                    him for the length of the degree 57,037 toises—an unexpected result, which has
                    led to the modern remeasurement of the arc by Sir Thomas Maclear.</p>
                <p>Passing over the measurements made between Rome and Rimini and on the plains of
                    Piedmont by the Jesuits Boscovich and Beccaria, and also the arc measured with
                    deal rods in North America by Messrs Mason and Dixon, we come to the
                    commencement of the English triangulation. In 1783, in consequence of a
                    representation from Cassini de Thury on the advantages that would accrue to
                    science from the geodetic connection of Paris and Greenwich, General Roy was
                    with the king’s approval appointed by the Royal Society to conduct the
                    operations on the part of this country,—Count Cassini, Mechain, and Delambre
                    being appointed on the French side. And now a precision previously unknown was
                    brought into geodesy by the use of Ramsden’s splendid theodolite, which, was the
                    first to make the spherical excess of triangles measurable. The wooden rods with
                    which the first base was measured were speedily replaced by glass rods, which
                    again were rejected for the steel chain of Ramsden. The details of this
                    operation are fully given in the <hi rend="italic">Account of the
                        Trigonometrical Survey of England and Wales.</hi> Shortly after this, the
                    National Convention of France, having agreed to remodel their system of weights
                    and measures, chose, as applicable to all countries, for their unit of length
                    the ten-millionth part of the meridian quadrant. In order to obtain this length
                    precisely, the remeasurement of the French meridian was resolved on, and deputed
                    to Delambre and Mechain. The details of this great operation will be found in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Base</hi><hi rend="italic">du Système Métrique
                        Décimale.</hi> The arc was subsequently extended by MM. Biot and Arago to
                    the island of Iviza.</p>
                <p>The appearance in 1838 of Bessel’s classical work entitled <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gradmessung</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">Ostpreussen</hi>
                    marks an era in the science of geodesy. Here we find the method of least
                    squares, a branch of the theory of probabilities, applied to the calculation of
                    a network of triangles and the reduction of the observations generally. This
                    work has been looked on as a model ever since, and probably it will not soon be
                    superseded as such. The systematic manner in which all the observations were
                    taken with the view of securing final results of extreme accuracy is admirable.
                    The triangulation, which is a small one, extends about a degree and a half along
                    the shores of the Baltic in a N.N.E. direction. The compound bars with which he
                    measured his base line may be understood by the following brief description. On
                    the surface of an iron bar two toises in length is laid a zinc bar, both being
                    very perfectly planed and in free contact— the zinc bar being slightly shorter
                    than the iron bar. They are united at one end only, and as the temperature
                    varies the difference of length of the bars as seen at the other end varies;
                    this difference of length is a thermometrical indication<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n620/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0620-0599"/> whereby a correction for temperature can be
                    applied to the bars so as to reduce their length to that at the standard
                    temperature. The bars in measuring were not allowed to come into contact, but
                    the intervals left were measured by the interposition of a glass wedge. The
                    results of all the comparisons of the four measuring rods with one another, and
                    with the standards, are elaborately worked out by least squares. The angles were
                    observed with theodolites of 12 and 15 inches diameter, and the latitudes
                    determined by means of the transit instrument in the prime vertical—a method
                    much used in Germany. The formulae employed in the reduction of the astronomical
                    observations are very elegant. The reduction of the triangulation waβ carried
                    out in the most thorough manner,—the sum of the squares of all the actual
                    theodolite observations being made a minimum. As it is usual now to follow this
                    method (sometimes only approximately) in all triangulations where great
                    precision is required, we here give a brief description of the method. The
                    equations of condition of a triangulation are those which exist between the
                    supernumerary observed quantities and their calculated values, for, after there
                    are just sufficient observations to fix all the points, then any angle that may
                    be subsequently observed can be compared with its calculated value. If a
                    triangulation consist of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> + 2 points, two of which are
                    the ends of a base line, then to fix the <hi rend="italic">n</hi> points 2n
                    angles suffice; so that if <hi rend="italic">m</hi> be the actual number of
                    angles really observed, the triangulation must afford <hi rend="italic">m -
                        2n</hi> equations of condition. To show how these arise, suppose that from a
                    number <hi rend="italic">m</hi> of fixed points A, B, C . . . a new point P is
                    observed, which <hi rend="italic">m</hi> points are again observed from P, then
                    there will be formed <hi rend="italic">m</hi>- 1 triangles, in each of which the
                    sum of the observed angles is = 180° + the spherical excess; this gives at once
                        <hi rend="italic">m</hi>- 1 equations of condition. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >m</hi> — 2 distances will each afford an equation of the form</p>
                <p>PC PB PA</p>
                <p>PB ’ PA PC ’</p>
                <p>not, however, limited to three factors. Should P observe the <hi rend="italic"
                        >m</hi> points and not be observed back, there will be <hi rend="italic"
                        >m</hi>- 3 equations of the above form (they are called side equations). In
                    a similar manner other cases can be treated. In practice the ratios of sides are
                    replaced by the ratios of the sines of the corresponding opposite angles. To
                    each observed angle a symbolical correction is applied, so that if α be an
                    observed angle and <hi rend="italic">a + x</hi> the true or most probable angle,
                    sin (α + z) = sin α(1 <hi rend="italic">+ x cot a), x</hi> being a small angle
                    whose square is neglected. Thus the side equation takes the form <hi
                        rend="italic">β + β</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> λ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> χ</hi><hi rend="italic">+ β</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ . . .
                        β</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> = 0. In the case of equations formed by
                    adding together the three observed angles of a triangle the co-efficients are of
                    course unity. The problem then is this: Given <hi rend="italic">n</hi>
                    equations</p>
                <p>β + 3 <hi rend=" subscript"> r</hi> r <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> + β. <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> x <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + . . . β <hi
                        rend="subscript"> m</hi> r <hi rend="subscript"> m</hi> = 0 β' + <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> j</hi> 3 <hi rend=" subscript">
                        1</hi> 'z <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> + β <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> 'x
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + . . . βfx <hi rend="subscript"> m</hi> = 0
                    β"+ βfx <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> + β <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> "x <hi
                        rend="subscript"> a</hi> + . . . β <hi rend="subscript"> m</hi> "r <hi
                        rend="subscript"> m</hi> = 0</p>
                <p>between <hi rend="italic">m(m&gt;n)</hi> unknown quantities <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">. . .x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> m</hi>, which are the corrections (expressed in
                    seconds of arc) to the observed angles, it is required to determine these
                    quantities so as to render the function <hi rend="italic">w</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">+ tv</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ w.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> 0</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> 3</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">+ . . . w</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> m</hi><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> m</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> a
                    minimum, where <hi rend="italic">w</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">. . . w</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> m</hi> are the <hi
                        rend="italic">weights</hi> of the determinations of the angles to which the
                    corresponding corrections belong. The corrections <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">. . . x</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> η</hi> fulfilling this
                    condition of minimum have, according to the theory of least squares, a higher
                    probability than any other system of corrections that merely satisfy the
                    equations of condition. Multiply the <hi rend="italic">n</hi> equations by
                    multipliers λ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, λ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, . .
                    . λ <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi>, and we obtain by the theory of maxima and
                    minima <hi rend="italic">m</hi> equations w <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> x <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ≈ β <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> λ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> + β <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ’ λ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> i</hi> + βfλ <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> + . . .</p>
                <p><hi rend=" superscript"> =</hi> 3aM ^t h 2 + β∙&gt; λj + . <hi rend=" subscript">
                        l j</hi> wmrm — 3∙tλj + βmλ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + ß <hi
                        rend="subscript"> M</hi> λ-3 + . .</p>
                <p>The values of <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">. . . x</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> m</hi> obtained from
                    these equations are to be substituted in the original equations of condition,
                    and then there will be <hi rend="italic">n</hi> equations between the <hi
                        rend="italic">n</hi> multipliers λ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. . . λ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> n</hi>. These being solved, the numerical values of λ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi>. . . λ <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> will be
                    obtained, and on substituting these in the last equations written down, the
                    values of aq . . . ir <hi rend="subscript"> ιn</hi> will follow. The process is
                    a long and tedious one; but it is inevitable if we wish very good results.</p>
                <p>The great meridian arc in India was commenced by Colonel Lambton at Punnoe in
                    latitude 8° 9'. Following generally the methods of the English survey, he
                    carried his triangulation as far north as 20° 30'. The work then passed into the
                    able hands of Sir George (then Captain) Everest, who continued it to the
                    latitude of 29° 30'. Two admirably written volumes by Sir George Everest,
                    published in 1830 and in 1847, give all the details of the vast undertaking. The
                    great trigonometrical survey of India is now being prosecuted with great
                    scientific skill by Colonel Walker, R.E., and it may be expected that we shall
                    soon have some valuable contributions to the great problem of geodesy. The
                    working out of the Indian chains of triangle by the method of least squares
                    presents peculiar difficulties, but enormous in extent as the work is, it is
                    being thoroughly carried out. The ten base lines on which the survey depends
                    were measured with Colby’s compensation bars.</p>
                <p>These compensation bars were also used by Sir Thomas Maclear in the measurement
                    of the base line in his extension of Lacaille’s arc at the Cape. The account of
                    this operation will be found in a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Verification
                        and Extension of Lacaille’s Arc of Meridian at the Cape of Good Hope,</hi>
                    by Sir Thomas Maclear, published in 1866. Lacaille ’ 3 amplitude is verified,
                    but not his terrestrial measurement.</p>
                <p>The number of stations in the principal triangulation of Great Britain and
                    Irelaud is about 250. At 32 of these the latitudes were determined with
                    Ramsden’s and Airy’s zenith sectors. The theodolites used for this work were, in
                    addition to the two great theodolites of Ramsden which were used by General Roy
                    and Captain Kater (and which are now in as good condition as when they came from
                    the hands of the maker), a smaller theodolite of 18 inches diameter by the same
                    mechanician, and another of 24 inches diameter by Messrs Troughton and Simms.
                    Observations for determination of absolute azimuth were made with these
                    instruments at a large number of stations; the stars α, δ, and λ Ursae Minoris
                    and 51 Cephei being those observed, always at the greatest azimuths. At six of
                    these stations the probable error of the result is under 0" <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 4, at twelve under 0" ’ 5, at thirty-four under
                    0" <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 7: so that the absolute azimuth of the whole
                    network is determined with extreme accuracy. Of the seven base lines w hich have
                    been measured, five were by means of steel chains and two with Colby’s
                    compensation bars. This is a system of six compound bars self-correcting for
                    temperature. The compound bar may be thus described. Two bars, one of brass and
                    the other of iron, are laid side by side, parallel, and firmly united at their
                    centres, from which they are free to expand or contract; at the standard
                    temperature they are of the same length. Let AB be one bar, A ’ B' the other;
                    draw a line through the corresponding extremities A, A' to P, aud a line through
                    the other extremities B, B' to Q, make A'P = B'Q, AA' being = BB'. Now if A'P is
                    to AP as the rate of expansion of the bar A'B' to the rate of expansion of the
                    bar AB, then clearly the distance PQ will be invariable, or very nearly so. In
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0621-0600"/> the actual instrument P and Q are finely
                    engraved dots at the distance of 10 feet apart. In the measurement the bars when
                    aligned do not come into contact; an interval of six inches is left between each
                    bar and its neighbour. This small space is measured by an ingenious
                    micrometrical arrangement constructed on exactly the same principle as the bars
                    themselves. The triangulation was computed by least squares. The total number of
                    equations of condition for the triangulation is 920; if therefore the whole had
                    been reduced in one mass, as it should have been, the solution of an equation of
                    920 unknown quantities would have occurred as a part of the work. To avoid this
                    an approximation was resorted to; the triangulation was divided into twenty-one
                    parts or figures; four of these, not adjacent, were first adjusted by the method
                    explained, and the corrections thus determined in these figures carried into the
                    equations of condition of the adjacent figures. The average number of equations
                    in a figure is 44; the largest equation is one of 77 unknown quantities.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See the volume of the
                            Ordnance Survey, entitled <hi rend="italic">Account of the Principal
                                Triangulation of Great Britain and Ireland,</hi> by Captain A. R.
                            Clarke, R.E., F.R.S., 1858.</p></note></p>
                <p>Airy’s Zenith Sector is too well known to need description. The vertical limb is
                    read by four microscopes; altogether, in the complete observation of a star
                    there are 10 micrometer readings and 12 level readings. In some recent
                    observations in Scotland for latitude the Zenith Telescope has been used with
                    very great success; it is very portable; and a complete determination of
                    latitude, affected with the mean of the declination errors of two stars, is
                    effected by two micrometer readings and four level readings. The observation
                    consists in measuring with the telescope micrometer the <hi rend="italic"
                        >difference</hi> of zenith distances of two stars which cross the meridian,
                    one to the north and the other to the south of the observer at zenith distances
                    which differ by not much more than 10' or 15', the interval of the times of
                    transit being not less than one nor more than twenty minutes. The advantages are
                    that, with simplicity in the construction of the instrument and facility in the
                    manipulation, refraction is eliminated (or nearly so, as the stars are generally
                    selected within 25° of the zenith), and there is no large divided circle. The
                    telescope, which is counterpoised on one side of the vertical axis, has a small
                    circle for finding, and there is also a small horizontal circle. This instrument
                    is universally used in American geodesy.</p>
                <p>The United States Coast Survey has a principal triangulation extending for about
                    9° 30' along the coast, but the final results are not yet published.</p>
                <p>In 1860 was published F. G. Struve’s <hi rend="italic">Arc</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >du Méridien</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi> 25° 20' <hi rend="italic">entre
                        le</hi><hi rend="italic">Danube</hi><hi rend="italic">et la Mer Glaciale
                        mesuré depuis</hi> 1816 <hi rend="italic">jusqu'en</hi> 1855. This work is
                    the record of a vast amount of scientific labour and is the greatest
                    contribution yet made to the question of the figure of the earth. The latitudes
                    of the thirteen astronomical stations of this arc were determined partly with
                    vertical circles and partly by means of the transit instrument in the prime
                    vertical. The triangulation, a great part of which, however, is a simple chain
                    of triangles, is reduced by the method of least squares, and the probable errors
                    of the resulting distances of parallels is given; the probable error of the
                    whole arc in length is ± 6 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 2 toises. Ten base
                    lines were measured. The sum of the lengths of the ten measured bases is 29,863
                    toises, so that the average length of a base line is 19,100 feet. The azimuths
                    were observed at fourteen stations. In high latitudes the determination of the
                    meridian is a matter of great difficulty; nevertheless the azimuths at all the
                    northern stations were successfully determined,—the probable error of the result
                    at Fuglenoes being ÷ 0" ’ 53.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mechanical Theory.</hi></p>
                <p>Newton appears to have been the first to apply his own newly-discovered doctrine
                    of gravitation, combined with the so-called centrifugal force, to the question
                    of the figure of the earth. Assuming that an oblate ellipsoid of rotation is a
                    form of equilibrium for a homogeneous fluid rotating with uniform angular
                    velocity, he obtained the ratio of the axes 229: 230, and the law of variation
                    of gravity on the surface. A few years later Huyghens published an investigation
                    of the figure of the earth, supposing the attraction of every particle to be
                    towards the centre of the earth, obtaining as a result that the proportion of
                    the axes should be 578:579. In 1740 Maclaurin wrote his celebrated essay on the
                    tides, one of the most elegant geometrical investigations ever made. He
                    demonstrated that the oblate ellipsoid of revolution is a figure which satisfies
                    the conditions of equilibrium in the case of a revolving homogeneous fluid mass
                    whose particles attract one another according to the law of the inverse square
                    of the distance; he gave the equation connecting the ellipticity with the
                    proportion of the centrifugal force at the equator to gravity, and he determined
                    the attraction on a particle situated anywhere on the surface of such a body.
                    Some few years afterwards Clairaut published (1743) his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Théorie</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Figure de la Terre,</hi> which
                    contains, among other results, demonstrated with singular elegance, a very
                    remarkable theorem which establishes a relation between the ellipticity of the
                    earth and the variations of gravity at different points of its surface. Assuming
                    that the earth is composed of concentric ellipsoidal strata having a common axis
                    of rotation, each stratum homogeneous in itself, but the ellipticities and
                    densities of the successive strata varying according to any law, and that the
                    superficial stratum has the same form as if it were fluid, he proves the very
                    important theorem contained in the equation <hi rend="italic">f-g .</hi> 5</p>
                <p>-—- <hi rend="superscript"> i,</hi> + e = <hi rend="subscript"> δ</hi> ∙m, <hi
                        rend="italic">g</hi> 2</p>
                <p>Where <hi rend="italic">g, f</hi> are the amouhts of gravity at the equator and
                    at the pole respectively, <hi rend="italic">e</hi> the ellipticity of the
                    meridian, and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> the ratio of the centrifugal force at the
                    equator to <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> Clairaut also proved that the increase of
                    gravity in proceeding from the equator to the poles is as the square of the sine
                    of the latitude. This, taken with the former theorem, gives the means of
                    determining the earth ’ 3 ellipticity from observation of the comparative force
                    of gravity at any two places. Clairaut would seem almost to have exhausted the
                    subject, for although much has been written since by mathematicians of the
                    greatest eminence, yet, practically, very little of importance has been added.
                    Laplace, himself a prince of mathematicians, who had devoted much of his own
                    time to the same subject, remarks on Clairaut’s work that “the importance of all
                    his results and the elegance with which they are presented place this work
                    amongst the most beautiful of mathematical productions” (Todhunter’s <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the Mathematical Theories of Attraction and the
                        Figure of the Earth,</hi> vol. i. p. 229).</p>
                <p>The problem of the figure of the earth treated as a question of mechanics or
                    hydrostatics is one of great difficulty, and it would be quite impracticable but
                    for the circumstance that the surface differs but little from a sphere. In order
                    to express the forces at any point of the body arising from the attraction of
                    its particles, the form of the surface is required, but this form is the very
                    one which it is the object of the investigation to discover; hence the
                    complexity of the subject, and even with all the present resources of
                    mathematicians only a partial and imperfect solution can be obtained, and that
                    not without some labour. We may, however, here briefly indicate the line of
                    reasoning by which some of the most important of the results we <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0622-0601"/> have alluded to above may be obtained. The
                    principles of hydrostatics show us that if X, Y, Z be the components parallel to
                    three rectangular axes of the forces acting on a particle of a fluid mass at the
                    point <hi rend="italic">x, y,</hi> z, then, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> being the
                    pressure there, and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> the density, dp = p(Xdx + Υdy+
                    Zdz); and for equilibrium the necessary conditions are, that <hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> p</hi><hi rend="italic">(Xdx +
                        Υdy + Zdx)</hi> be a complete differential, and at the free surface <hi
                        rend="italic">Xdx + Υdy</hi> + Zcfz = 0. This equation implies that the
                    resultant of the forces is normal to the surface at every point, and in a
                    homogeneous fluid it is obviously the differential equation of all surfaces of
                    equal pressure. If the fluid be heterogeneous then it is to be remarked that for
                    forces of attraction according to the ordinary law of gravitation, if X, Y, Z be
                    the components of the attraction of a mass whose potential is V, then <hi
                        rend="subscript"> v</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> vj</hi>- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 7j</hi> &lt;ilV <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi> dV, , &lt;ZV,
                    ∖dx + Υdy÷7idz — <hi rend="superscript"> t ,</hi> which is a complete
                    differential. And in the case of a fluid rotating with uniform velocity, in
                    which the so-called centrifugal force enters as a force acting on each particle
                    proportional to its distance from the axis of rotation, the corresponding part
                    of <hi rend="italic">Xdx + Sidy</hi> + Z&lt;fe is obviously a complete
                    differential. Therefore for the forces with which we are now concerned Xcfø
                    +Y&lt;⅞∕ + ZcZz = &lt;7U, where U is some function of <hi rend="italic">x, y,
                        z,</hi> and it is necessary for equilibrium that <hi rend="italic">dp =</hi>
                    pdU be a complete differential; that is, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> must be a
                    function of U or a function of <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> and so also p a
                    function of U. So that tZU = 0 is the differential equation of surfaces of equal
                    pressure and density.</p>
                <p>We may now show that a homogeneous fluid mass in the form of an oblate ellipsoid
                    of revolution having a uniform velocity of rotation can be in equilibrium. It
                    may be proved that the attraction of the ellipsoid z <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> +y <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    (1 + ∈ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) = c <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (1 + ∈
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) upon a particle P of its mass at <hi
                        rend="italic">x, y,</hi><hi rend="italic">z</hi> has for components</p>
                <p>X = <hi rend="italic">Ax,</hi> Y = <hi rend="italic">Ay, Z = Cz,</hi> where <hi
                        rend="superscript"> a</hi> = <hi rend="superscript"> 2π</hi> ∕ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> (⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> ^ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> tan</hi> ~ <hi rend="superscript"> le</hi> “ «0
                    C=4τp(^-l±≤ t <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> m" <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                    e)</p>
                <p>Besides the attraction of the mas3 of the ellipsoid, the eentrifugal force at P
                    has for components - <hi rend="italic">xω</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi>- yω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, 0; then
                    the condition of fluid equilibrium is</p>
                <p>(A - ω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)xcfo + (A - <hi rend="italic">ω</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">')ydy + Czdz</hi> = 0,
                    which by integrating gives</p>
                <p>(A - ω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)(aj <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + y <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) + C≈ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =
                    constant.</p>
                <p>This is the equation of an ellipsoid of rotation, and therefore the equilibrium
                    is possible. The equation coincides with that of the surface of the fluid mass
                    if we make <hi rend="smallcaps">a</hi><hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> _ C</p>
                <p>A - w- - —„ ,</p>
                <p>1 + e- ’ which gives</p>
                <p>ω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 3 + e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, 3</p>
                <p>ö— ——3~ tan e - .</p>
                <p>2πρ e <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>If we would determine the maximum value of ω from tiιis equation, we find that it
                    corresponds to the value of e determined by the condition <hi rend="subscript">
                        +</hi>-1 _ 9e + 7e <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi></p>
                <p>* “ (l+e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> X9 + e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)
                    ’</p>
                <p>hence it may be shown that if the angular velocity exceed <hi rend="subscript">
                        ω</hi> 2</p>
                <p>that calculated from = 0'2247, equilibrium is impossible for the form of an
                    ellipsoid of revolution. If ω fall short of this limit, there are two ellipsoids
                    which satisfy the condition of equilibrium; in one of these the eccentricity is
                    greater and in the other less than 0 ’ 93. In the case of the earth, which is
                    nearly spherical, we get by expanding the expression for ω <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> in powers of e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,
                    rejecting the higher powers, and remarking that the ellipticity e = ∣e <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, jΔ-± <hi rend=" subscript"> e2</hi> =A <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> β</hi> 2∙∏ <hi rend=" subscript">
                        7</hi> &gt; 15 15 ‘</p>
                <p>Now, if <hi rend="italic">m</hi> be the ratio of the centrifugal force at the
                    equator to gravity there, cω <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> . ω <hi
                        rend="                     superscript"> 2</hi> _ 2 m <hi rend="superscript"
                        > m</hi> ⅜τrpc - Cω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ’ 2ιrp 3 1 + <hi
                        rend="italic">m</hi></p>
                <p>In the case of the earth it is a matter of observation that <hi rend="italic"
                        >m</hi> = - <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>-g- <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>-,
                    hence the ellipticity</p>
                <p> 5 1</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> i-</hi> 4 <hi rend="superscript"> w</hi> ~ 2312 so that
                    the ratio of the axes on the supposition of a homogeneous fluid earth is 230:
                    231, as announced by Newton.</p>
                <p>Now, to come to the case of a heterogeneous fluid, we shall assume that its
                    surfaces of equal density are spheroids, concentric and having a common axis of
                    rotation, and that the ellipticity of these surfaces varies from the centre to
                    the outer surface, the den⅛ty also varying. In other words, the body is composed
                    m homogeneous spheroidal shells of variable density and ellipticity. On this
                    supposition we shall express the attraction of the mass upon a particle in its
                    interior, and then, taking into account the centrifugal force, form the equation
                    expressing the condition of fluid equilibrium. The attraction of the homogeneous
                    spheroid rc <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + y <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +
                    2 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (1 + <hi rend="italic">2e) =</hi> c <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (1 + 2e), where <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is the
                    ellipticity, of which the square is neglected, on an internal particle, whose
                    co-ordinates are <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic">—f,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> 0, <hi rend="italic">z =
                        h,</hi> has for its <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z</hi>
                    components <hi rend="superscript"> x</hi>-l' <hi rend="superscript"> pz</hi>
                        (<hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>-∣ <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi>)' <hi
                        rend="superscript"> z</hi> '=√' <hi rend="superscript"> ,i</hi> (<hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1+</hi> ι <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi>)' th¾Y
                    component being of course zero. Hence we infer that the attraction of a shell
                    whose inner surface has an ellipticity <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and its outer
                    surface an ellipticity <hi rend="italic">e + de,</hi> the density being <hi
                        rend="italic">p,</hi> is expressed by</p>
                <p> &lt;ZX' = -5- · 7 τrpfde, dZ'=θ · J τrphde.</p>
                <p>3 5 3 5</p>
                <p>To apply this to our heterogeneous spheroid; if we put <hi rend="italic"
                        >c</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> for the semiaxis of that surface
                    of equal density on which is situated the attracted point P, and <hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 0</hi> for the semiaxis of
                    the outer surface, the attraction of that portion of the body which is exterior
                    to P, namely, of all the shells which inclose P, has for components both <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> being functions of <hi
                        rend="italic">c.</hi> Again the attraction of a homogeneous spheroid of
                    density <hi rend="italic">p</hi> on an <hi rend="italic">external</hi> point <hi
                        rend="italic">f, h</hi> has the components</p>
                <p>X"= j <hi rend="superscript"> c3</hi> &lt; <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> + <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2e</hi>) - <hi rend="superscript"> λec5</hi> J</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> z</hi> "= ~-P <hi rend=" superscript"> c</hi> ∖ l + 2e) -
                    λ'ec <hi rend=" superscript"> 5</hi><hi rend=" subscript"> 1 x</hi> 3 4h <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>-f <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. <hi
                        rend="subscript"> l</hi> 3 2h <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- 3∕ <hi
                        rend="                     superscript"> 2</hi> , <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> o λo</hi> „</p>
                <p>where λ = 5 · —74— ’ <hi rend="superscript"> λ =</hi> 5 * —74~, <hi
                        rend="superscript"> αnd</hi> ** <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =∕ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + ^ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Now <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> being considered a function of c, we can at once
                    express the attraction of a shell (density p) contained between the surface
                    defined by <hi rend="italic">c + dc, e + de</hi> and that defined by c, <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> upon an external point; the differentials with respect
                    to c, viz. &lt;7X" &lt;7Z", must then be integrated with <hi rend="italic"
                        >p</hi> under the integral sign as being a function of <hi rend="italic"
                        >c.</hi> The integration will extend from c≈0 to c = c <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi>. Thus the components of the attraction of the heterogeneous spheroid
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n623/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0623-0602"/> upon a particle within its mass, whose
                    co-ordinates are ∕, 0, <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> are <hi rend=" superscript">
                        x</hi> ~l <hi rend=" superscript"> 7rp</hi> ≠ ⅛ + <hi rend="superscript">
                        2e</hi> '&gt;- <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> μ∕' ⅛ <hi rend=" superscript">
                        c</hi> ≡) -1 ∕ <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> p° <hi rend="superscript">
                        de</hi> J</p>
                <p>o o <hi rend="subscript"> q</hi> z = ∣ <hi rend="subscript"> τp</hi> h j 1 y <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> p</hi> d.c <hi rend=" superscript"> 3</hi> (l + 2e)-^
                    J'pd(ed} + ^Jpde I</p>
                <p> o θ q</p>
                <p>We take into account the rotation of the earth by subtracting the centrifugal
                    force ∕ω <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = F from X. Now, the surface of constant
                    density upon which the point <hi rend="italic">f,</hi> 0, <hi rend="italic"
                        >h</hi> is situated gives (1 - <hi rend="italic">2e)fdf + hdh = Q ∙,</hi>
                    and the condition of equilibrium is that (X - F)&lt;7∕^+ <hi rend="italic"
                        >T</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">dh</hi> = 0.
                    Therefore,</p>
                <p>(X-F)Λ = Z∕(l-2e), which, neglecting small quantities of the order e <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> and putting ω¾ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =
                    4τr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, gives</p>
                <p>*yi'&lt;i.c&gt;d+!⅛)-⅛√7⅛∙)-∣-∕⅛-⅛</p>
                <p>0 0 &lt;∙,</p>
                <p>Here we must put now <hi rend="italic">c</hi> for c <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi> for r, and 1 + 2e under the first integral sign may
                    be replaced by unity. Two integrations lead us to the following very important
                    differential equation :—</p>
                <p>d <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> e 2pc <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> de ∕ 2pc 6
                    ∖ de <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> fpc <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> dc de <hi
                        rend="superscript"> +</hi> ∖fpc <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> dc c <hi
                        rend="subscript"> i</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> ~^ θ ‘</p>
                <p>When <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is expressed in terms of <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>
                    this equation can be integrated. We infer then that a rotating spheroid of very
                    small ellipticity, composed of fluid homogeneous strata such as we have
                    specified, will be in equilibrium; and when the law of the density is expressed,
                    the law of the corresponding ellipticities will follow. If we put M for the mass
                    of the spheroid, then</p>
                <p> M = y^∕*pd.c <hi rend=" superscript"> 3</hi> (l + 2e); and</p>
                <p>0</p>
                <p>and putting c = c <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> in the equation expressing the
                    condition of equilibrium, we find</p>
                <p> M(2e -TO) = iτr.Ay <hi rend=" superscript"> r</hi><hi rend=" subscript"> p</hi>
                    rf( <hi rend=" subscript"> cc</hi> 5) <hi rend=" subscript"> f</hi> o</p>
                <p>Making these substitutions in the expressions for the ∕ <hi rend="subscript">
                        j</hi> 2 forces at the surface, and puttingr=1+6-e-, we get</p>
                <p> Gcos&lt;∕&gt; = - ( l-e-^-m + (½m- 2e) ⅞- j — αc ∣ , 2 ∖ 2 ∕c <hi
                        rend="                     superscript"> 2</hi> Jc</p>
                <p> Gsinφ = - ( l + e~lm+(lm-2ey ’ L I A.</p>
                <p>ac I 2 ∖ 2 ∕c <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> Jc</p>
                <p>Here G is gravity in the latitude &lt;∕&gt;, and <hi rend="italic">a</hi> the
                    radius of</p>
                <p>• C ∕ lb^ ∖</p>
                <p>the equator. Since sec <hi rend="italic">φ</hi><hi rend="italic">=</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">(l+e + e-^</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >∖</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 0=</hi> “ { <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 4" <hi rend="superscript"> ,+</hi> (f~^ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> e</hi>) <hi rend="superscript"> siπiφ</hi>} ’ which
                    expression contains the theorems we have referred to as discovered by
                    Clairaut.</p>
                <p>The theory of the figure of the earth as a rotating ellipsoid has proved an
                    attractive subject to many of the greatest ma themati cans, Laplace especially,
                    who has devoted a large portion of his <hi rend="italic">Mécanique</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Celeste</hi> to it. In English the principal existing works on
                    the subject are Sir George Airy’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Tracts,</hi>
                    where the subject is treated in the lucid style so characteristic of its author,
                    but without the use of Laplace’s coefficients, Archdeacon Pratt’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Attractions and Figure of the Earth,</hi> and O’Brien’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Mathematical Tracts;</hi> in the last two Laplace’s
                    coefficients are used. In the <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Transactions,</hi>
                    vol. viii., is a valuable essay by Professor Stokes, in which he proves, without
                    making any assumption whatever as to the ellipticity of internal strata, or as
                    to the past or the present fluidity of the earth that if the external form of
                    the sea—imagined to percolate the land by canals—be a spheroid with small
                    ellipticity, then the law of gravity will be that found above.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See also a paper by
                            Professor Stokes, in the <hi rend="italic">Cambridge and Dublin
                                Mathematical Journal,</hi> vol. iv. 1849.</p></note></p>
                <p>An important theorem by Jacobi must not be overlooked. He proved that for a
                    homogeneous fluid in rotation a spheroid is not the only form of equilibrium; an
                    ellipsoid rotating round its least axis may with certain proportions of the axes
                    and a certain time of revolution be a form of equilibrium.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See a paper in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Proceedings of</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> D&gt;λ</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Rοual Society,</hi> No. 123 1870, by I. Todhunter,
                            Μ.A., F.R.S.</p></note><hi rend="italic">Local Attraction.</hi></p>
                <p>In speaking of the figure of the earth, we mean the surface of the sea imagined
                    to percolate the continents by canals. That this surface should turn out, after
                    precise measurements, to be exactly an ellipsoid of revolution is <hi
                        rend="italic">a priori</hi> improbable. Although it may be highly probable
                    that originally the earth was a fluid mass, yet in the cooling whereby the
                    present crust has resulted, the actual solid surface has been left in form the
                    most irregular. It is clear that these irregularities of the visible surface
                    must be accompanied by irregularities in the mathematical figure of the earth,
                    and when we consider the general surface of our globe, its irregular
                    distribution of mountain masses, continents, with oceans and islands, we are
                    prepared to admit that the earth may not be precisely any surface of revolution.
                    Nevertheless, there must exist some spheroid which agrees very closely with the
                    mathematical figure of the earth, and has the same axis of rotation. We must
                    conceive this figure as exhibiting slight departures from the spheroid, the two
                    surfaces cutting one another in various lines; thus a point of the surface is
                    defined by its latitude, longitude, and its height above the spheroid of
                    reference. Call this height for a moment <hi rend="italic">η-,</hi> then of the
                    actual magnitude of this quantity we can generally have no information, it only
                    obtrudes itself on our notice by its variations. In the vicinity of mountains it
                    may change sign in the space of a few miles; <hi rend="italic">n</hi> being
                    regarded as a function of the latitude and longitude, if its differential
                    coefficient with respect to the former be zero at a certain point, the normals
                    to the two surfaces then will lie in the prime vertical; if the differential
                    coefficient of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> with respect to the longitude be zero,
                    the two normals will lie in the meridian; if both coefficients are zero, the
                    normals will coincide. The comparisons of terrestrial measurements with the
                    corresponding astronomical observations have ever been accompanied with
                    discrepancies. Suppose A and B to be two trigonometrical stations, and that at A
                    there is a disturbing force drawing the vertical through an angle δ, then it is
                    evident that the apparent zenith of A will be really that of some other place
                    A', whose distance from A is rδ, when <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is the earth’s
                    radius; and similarly if there be a disturbance at B of the amount δ', the
                    apparent zenith of B will be really that of some other place B', whose distance
                    from B is rδ'. Hence we have the discrepancy that, while the geodetical
                    measurements deal with the points A and B, the astronomical observations belong
                    to the points A', B'. Should δ, δ' be equal and parallel, the displacements AA',
                    BB' will be equal and parallel, and no discrepancy will appear. The
                    nonrecognition of this circumstance often led to much perplexity in the early
                    history of geodesy. Suppose that, through the unknown variations of <hi
                        rend="italic">n,</hi> the probable error of an observed latitude (that is,
                    the angle between the normal to the mathematical surface of the earth at the
                    given point and that of the corresponding point on the spheroid of reference) be
                    e, then if we compare two arcs of a degree <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n624/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0624-0603"/> each in mean latitudes, and near each other,
                    say about five degrees of latitude apart, the probable error of the resulting
                    value of the ellipticity will be approximately ± κ⅜σ&lt;, « being expressed in
                    seconds, so that if ∈ be so great as 2" the probable error of the resulting
                    ellipticity will be greater than the ellipticity itself. It is not only
                    interesting, but necessary at times, to calculate the attraction of a mountain,
                    and the consequent disturbance of the astronomical zenith, at any point within
                    its influence. The deflection of the plumb-line, caused by a local attraction
                    whose amount is Aδ, is measured by the ratio of <hi rend="italic">AS</hi> to the
                    force of gravity at the station. Expressed in seconds, the deflection Δ is</p>
                <p> Δ = 12".447.-A ,</p>
                <p>P</p>
                <p>where <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is the mean density of the earth, δ that of the
                    attracting mass,—the linear unit in expressing A being a mile. Suppose, for
                    instance, a table-land whose form is a rectangle of twelve miles by eight miles,
                    having a height of 500 feet and density half that of the earth; let the observer
                    be two miles distant from the middle point of the longer side. The deflection
                    then is Γ' ’ 472; but at one mile it increases to 2"∙20. At sixteen astronomical
                    stations in the English Survey the disturbance of latitude due to the form of
                    the ground has been computed, and the following will give an idea of the
                    results. At six stations the deflection is under 2", at six others it is between
                    2" and 4'', and at four stations it exceeds 4". There is one very exceptional
                    station on the north coast of Banffshire, near the village of Portsoy, at which
                    the deflection amounts to 10'', so that if that village were placed on a map in
                    a position to correspond with its astronomical latitude, it would be 1000 feet
                    out of position! There is the sea to the north and an undulating country to the
                    south, which, however, to a spectator at the station does not suggest any great
                    disturbance of gravity. A somewhat rough estimate of the local attraction from
                    external causes gives a maximum limit of 5", therefore we have 5" unaccounted
                    for, or rather which must arise from unequal density in the underlying strata in
                    the surrounding country. In order to throw light on this remarkable phenomenon,
                    the latitudes of a number of stations between Nairn on the west, Fraserburgh on
                    the east, and the Grampians on the south, were observed, and the local
                    deflections determined. It is somewhat singular that the deflections diminish in
                    all directions, not <hi rend="italic">very</hi> regularly certainly, and most
                    slowly in a south-west direction, finally disappearing, and leaving the maximum
                    at the original station at Portsoy.</p>
                <p>The method employed by Dr Hutton for computing the attraction of masses of ground
                    is so simple and effectual that it can hardly be improved on. Let a horizontal
                    plane pass through the given station; let <hi rend="italic">r, θ</hi> be the
                    polar coordinates of any point in this plane, and <hi rend="italic">r, θ,
                        z,</hi> the coordinates of a particle of the attracting mass; and let it be
                    required to find the attraction of a portion of the mass contained between the
                    horizontal planes 2 = 0, <hi rend="italic">z — h,</hi> the cylindrical surfaces
                        <hi rend="italic">r = r</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">, r = r</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">,</hi> and the vertical planes <hi rend="italic">θ≈θ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">, θ =
                        θ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> The
                    component of the attraction at the station or origin along the line <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> = 0 is <hi rend=" subscript"> s</hi> ∕* <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> r2</hi> ∕^¾ ∕* <hi rend=" superscript"> λ</hi> r <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="                     superscript">
                        cos</hi> θdrclθdz J J J 0∙ <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> + z <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> )l n <hi rend=" superscript"> 0</hi> ι o = bh
                    (sin 0 <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> - sin 0 <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> ) log
                    , <hi rend=" superscript"> r</hi> 2 <hi rend=" superscript"> +</hi> ^ <hi
                        rend="                     superscript"> 2</hi> ⅛ , r <hi rend=" subscript">
                        1</hi> + (r <hi rend="                     superscript"> 2</hi> +Λ <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> )i'</p>
                <p>By taking r <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>-r <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>
                    sufficiently small, and supposing <hi rend="italic">h</hi> also small, as it
                    usually is, compared with r <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> + <hi rend="italic"
                        >r</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> the
                    attraction is</p>
                <p> 7</p>
                <p> =- δ(r <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> - r <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> )(sin 0
                        <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> - sin θ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>) - , <hi
                        rend="italic">r</hi> where <hi rend="italic">r =</hi> ⅛(r <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> + r <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>). This form
                    suggests the following procedure. Draw on the contoured map a series of
                    equidistant circles, concentric with the station, intersected by radial lines so
                    disposed that the sines of their azimuths are in arithmetical progression. Then,
                    having estimated from the map the mean heights of the various compartments, the
                    calculation is obvious.</p>
                <p>In mountainous countries, as near the Alps and in the Caucasus, deflections have
                    been observed to the amount of as much as 29". On the other hand, deflections
                    have been observed in flat countries, such as that noted by Professor
                    Schweitzer, who has shown that, at certain stations in the vicinity of Moscow,
                    within a distance of 16 miles the plumb-line varies 16" in such a manner as to
                    indicate a vast deficiency of matter in the underlying strata. But these are
                    exceptional cases.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In
                            the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for 1855 and 1859
                            will be found Archdeacon Pratt’s calculations of the attractions of the
                            Himalayas and the mountain region beyond them, and the consequent
                            deflection of the plumb-line at various stations in India; the subject,
                            which presents many anomalies and difficulties, is very fully gone into
                            in his treatise on the figure of the earth. His computed deflections are
                            vastly greater than anything brought to light by observation.</p></note>
                    Since the attraction of a mountain mass is expressed as a numerical multiple of
                    δ: <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> the ratio of the density of the mountain to that of
                    the earth, if we have any independent means of ascertaining the amount of the
                    deflection, we have at once the ratio <hi rend="italic">p</hi>: δ, and thus we
                    obtain the mean density of the earth, as, for instance, at Schiehallion, and
                    more recently at Arthur’s Seat. A compact mass of great density at a small
                    distance under the surface of the earth will produce an elevation of the
                    mathematical surface which is expressed by the formula i (1 +⅛ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> s</hi>- <hi rend="italic superscript"> ς</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">λk</hi> cos 0)⅛ L· where <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is the
                    radius of the (spherical) earth, α(1 - Ä) the distance of the disturbing mass
                    below the surface, <hi rend="smallcaps">∕λ</hi> the ratio of the disturbing mass
                    to the mass of the earth, and <hi rend="italic">aθ</hi> the distance of any
                    point on the surface from that point, say Q, which is vertically over the
                    disturbing mass. The maximum value of <hi rend="italic">y</hi> is at Q, where it
                    is</p>
                <p>The deflection at the distance <hi rend="italic">aθ</hi> is <hi rend="subscript">
                        δ</hi> _ μk sin θ</p>
                <p> (1 j-fc <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> - 2k cos Θ)⅜ '</p>
                <p>or since <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> is small, putting <hi rend="italic">h +
                        lc—</hi> 1,</p>
                <p> ∆=- .</p>
                <p> (A <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> + θ <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> )l</p>
                <p>The maximum deflection takes place at a point whose distance from Q is to the
                    depth of the mass as 1: 2, and its amount is</p>
                <p> 2 M 8√3Λ <hi rend=" superscript"> s</hi> '</p>
                <p>Tf, for instance, the disturbing mass were a sphere a mile in diameter, the
                    excess of its density above that of the surrounding country being equal to half
                    the density of the earth, and the depth of its centre half a mile, the greatest
                    deflection would be 5", and the greatest value of <hi rend="italic">y</hi> only
                    two inches. Thus a large disturbance of gravity may arise from an irregularity
                    in the mathematical surface whose actual magnitude, as regards height at least,
                    is extremely small.</p>
                <p>The effect of the disturbing mass <hi rend="italic">y</hi> on the vibrations of a
                    pendulum would be a maximum at Q; if <hi rend="italic">ν</hi> be the number of
                    seconds of time gained per diem by the pendulum at Q, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >σ</hi> the number of seconds of angle in the maximum deflection, then it
                    may be shown that</p>
                <p>V _ 7ΓV ’ 3 σ 1CΓ ’ <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0625-0604"/> so that the number of seconds of time by
                    which at the maximum the pendulum is accelerated is about half the number of
                    seconds of angle in the maximum deflection.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Principles of Calculation.</hi></p>
                <p>Let α, «' be the mutual azimuths of two points P, Q on a spheroid, <hi
                        rend="italic">k</hi> the chord line joining them, <hi rend="italic">μ,
                        μ'</hi> the angles made by the chord with the normals at P and Q, <hi
                        rend="italic">φ, φ', ω</hi> their latitudes and difference of longitude, and
                        <hi rend="italic                     superscript strikethrough"> x +</hi><hi
                        rend="italic strikethrough"> J-</hi> + ⅛ -1 = 0 the equation of the surface;
                    α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">o</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> l</hi> then if the plane <hi rend="italic"
                        >xz</hi> passes through P the co-ordinates of P and Q will be tX tx ’ *</p>
                <p>X = — COS <hi rend="italic">φ ,</hi> » ≈ T7 <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Φ</hi> CO3 <hi rend="italic superscript"> ω</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">9</hi></p>
                <p>Δ Δ</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">y=ο y</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">-^g</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                        cos</hi> &lt;J&gt; ’ sm « »</p>
                <p>z=^(l-e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) sin <hi rend="italic">φ, z'</hi> =J^(l -e
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>) sin <hi rend="italic">φ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >,</hi> where ∆ = (l -e <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ≠)i, ∆' = (1 -e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    siu <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">φ</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >)f</hi> and e is the eccentricity. Let <hi rend="italic">f,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">g,</hi><hi rend="italic">h</hi> be the direction cosines of
                    the normal to that plane which contains the normal at P and the point Q, and
                    whose inclinations to the meridian plane of P is = <hi rend="italic">a</hi>; let
                    also ζ <hi rend="italic">m, η</hi> and <hi rend="italic">V, m</hi> ’ <hi
                        rend="italic">, n</hi> ’ be the direction cosines of the normal at P, and of
                    the tangent to the surface at P which lies in the plane passing through Q, then
                    since the first line is perpendicular to each of the other two and to the chord
                        <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> whose direction cosines are proportional to <hi
                        rend="italic">x'-x, y</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">-y, z</hi> ’ <hi
                        rend="italic">-z,</hi> we have these three equations</p>
                <p>∕(a∕ <hi rend="italic">-x) + gf + h(z</hi> ’- z) - 0 <hi rend="italic">fl +gm
                        +hn</hi> = 0 <hi rend="italic">fl</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+ gm' + hn'
                        —</hi> 0 .</p>
                <p>Eliminate ∕, <hi rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">h</hi> from these equations, and substitute <hi rend="italic"
                        >l =</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">φ l'=- sin φ</hi> cos α</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">m</hi> = 0 <hi rend="italic">m'</hi> = sin <hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi> = sin <hi rend="italic">φ n'</hi> = cos <hi
                        rend="italic">φ</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> and we get</p>
                <p>(a/- <hi rend="italic">x)</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">φ + y'</hi> cot <hi
                        rend="italic">a- &lt;f-z)</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> = 0 .</p>
                <p>The substitution of the values of <hi rend="italic">x, z, x', y</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> z' in this
                    equation will give immediately the value of cot «; and if we put £, <hi
                        rend="italic">C</hi> for the corresponding azimuths on a sphere, or on the
                    supposition <hi rend="italic">e —</hi> 0, the following relations exist cot α -
                    cot C = e <hi rend="superscript"> 2 c</hi>-^-, Q</p>
                <p>cos <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> Δ</p>
                <p>cot a'- cot f'= -e <hi rend="superscript"> 2 cos</hi>.^ ’- 51</p>
                <p>cos <hi rend="italic">φ</hi><hi rend="italic">Δ.</hi></p>
                <p>∆' sin <hi rend="italic">φ-Δ</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">φ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >=</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">ω</hi> Q .</p>
                <p>If from Q we let fall a perpendicular on the meridian plane of P, and from P let
                    fall a perpendicular on the meridian plane of Q, then the following equations
                    become geometrically evident:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">, . .</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >»</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic">k</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="italic">μ</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">a = —,</hi> cos <hi rend="italic"
                        >φ</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">ω</hi><hi rend="italic">t~</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> δ</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">z</hi> r <hi
                        rend="italic">k</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> sin α = — cos <hi
                        rend="italic">φ</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">ω .</hi></p>
                <p>Now in any surface u = 0 we have</p>
                <p>⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =(a∕-x) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + (y <hi
                        rend="superscript"> z</hi>-ι∕) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + (z <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi>-z) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>- COS μ - ∕⅛√∙ <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        k</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">dz</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> i+</hi><hi rend="italic">df</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic">dz</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >)</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> c03μ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        k</hi><hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> da</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Ι</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> +</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        du</hi><hi rend="italic">^</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> +</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> d</hi><hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >∖</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dz</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">* df</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> dz <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,2</hi> 7</p>
                <p>in the present case, if we put <hi rend="italic">xx' zz</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >_</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="italic">-</hi> α <hi
                        rend="superscript"> i</hi> " F ’ then i cos μ=^∆U; cos∕Z=^-∆'U,</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">u</hi> be such an angle that</p>
                <p>(1 - e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)⅛ sin <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> = ∆ sin <hi
                        rend="italic">u</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> = ∆ cos <hi rend="italic"
                        >u,</hi> then on expressing <hi rend="italic">x, x', z,</hi> z' in terms of
                        <hi rend="italic">u</hi> and u',</p>
                <p>U = 1 ~ cos <hi rend="italic">u</hi> cos «' cos « - sin <hi rend="italic">u</hi>
                    sin <hi rend="italic">u!;</hi> also, if <hi rend="italic">V</hi> be the third
                    side of a spherical triangle, of which two sides are ∣π - <hi rend="italic"
                        >u</hi> and ⅛π - <hi rend="italic">u</hi> ’ and the included angle <hi
                        rend="italic">a&gt;,</hi> using ‰ subsidiary angle ψ such that <hi
                        rend="italic">. , V u' -u u</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">+ u</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sin ψ</hi> sin — <hi rend="italic">= e</hi> sin cos —-— , <hi
                        rend="superscript"> τ</hi> 2 2 2 ’ we obtain finally the following equations
                    :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">k</hi> = 2α cos <hi rend="italic">ψ</hi> sin -</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> 2</p>
                <p>cos <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> = Δ sec ψ sin ∣∙</p>
                <p>cos <hi rend="italic">μ —Λ</hi> sec ψ sm —</p>
                <p>sin <hi rend="italic">μ</hi> sin <hi rend="italic">a =</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> c</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >L</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi>
                    sin <hi rend="italic">ω</hi> sin √ sin <hi rend="italic">a =</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="italic">u</hi> sin « .</p>
                <p>These determine rigorously the distance, and the mutual zenith distances and
                    azimuths, of any two points on a spheroid whose latitudes and difference of
                    longitude are given.</p>
                <p>By a series of reductions from the equations containing f, it may be shown that
                    z&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi></p>
                <p>α + α'=f + <hi rend="italic">ζ'</hi> + — ω(φ'-φ) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    cos <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> φ <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> sin &lt;∕&gt;
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> + ....</p>
                <p>4</p>
                <p>where <hi rend="italic">φ</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 0</hi> is the mean of
                        <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> and <hi rend="italic">φ',</hi> and the higher
                    powers of <hi rend="italic">e</hi> are neglected. A short computation will show
                    that the small quantity on the right-hand side of this equation can never amount
                    even to the ten thousandth part of a second, which is, practically speaking,
                    zero; consequently the sum of the azimuths <hi rend="italic">a + a</hi> on the
                    spheroid is equal to the sum of the spherical azimuths, whence follows this very
                    important theorem (known as Dalby’s theorem). If <hi rend="italic">φ, φ'</hi> be
                    the latitudes of two points on the surface of a spheroid, <hi rend="italic"
                        >ω</hi> their difference of longitude, <hi rend="italic">a, a</hi> their
                    reciprocal azimuths, <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">- φ</hi> cos^-
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>- <hi rend="superscript"> ι</hi>- , <hi
                        rend="italic">ω</hi> 2 <hi rend="italic">a + a</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                        t,</hi> T . ,-+» <hi rend="superscript"> cot</hi>- <hi rend="subscript">
                        2</hi> ~∙</p>
                <p>2</p>
                <p>The vertical plane at P passing through Q and the vertical plane at Q passing
                    through P cut the surface of the spheroid in two distinct curves. The greatest
                    distance apart of these curves is, if α <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> = the mean
                    azimuth of PQ, e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> s <hi rend="superscript">
                    3</hi></p>
                <p>— - <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> φ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 0</hi> sin 2α <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi>.</p>
                <p>This is a very small quantity; for even in the case of a line of 100 miles in
                    length having a mean azimuth α= 45° in the latitude of Great Britain, it will
                    only amount to half an inch, whilst for a line of fifty miles it cannot exceed
                    the sixteenth part of an inch. The geodesic line joining P and Q lies wholly
                    between these two curves.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>See a paper “On the course of Geodesic Lines on the Earth’s Surface”
                            in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Magazine</hi> for
                        1870.</p></note> If we designate by P', Q' the two curves (the former being
                    that in the vertical plane through P), then, neglecting quantities of the order
                    e <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 0 <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, where <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> is the angular distance of P and Q at the centre of the
                    earth, the geodesic curve makes with P' at P an angle equal to the angle it
                    makes with Q ’ at Q, each of these angles being a . third of the angle of
                    intersection of P ’ and Q'. The difference of length of the geodesic line and
                    either of the curves P', Q' is, s being the length of either, e <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 4</hi> 0 <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> cos <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 4</hi> φ <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 2α <hi rend="subscript"> u</hi>.</p>
                <p>At least this is an approximate expression. Supposing the angle PQ to be as much
                    as 10°, this quantity would be less than one hundredth of au inch.</p>
                <p>An idea of the course of a geodesic line may be gathered from the following
                    example. Let the line be that joining Cadiz and St Petersburg, whose approximate
                    positions are</p>
                <p>Cadiz. St Petersburg.</p>
                <p>Lat. 36“ 22' N 59“ 56' N.</p>
                <p>Long. 6° 18' w 30“ 17' <hi rend="smallcaps">e.</hi></p>
                <p>If G be the point on the geodesic corresponding to F on that one of the plane
                    curves which contains the normal at</p>
                <p>Cadiz (by “corresponding” we mean that F and G are on a meridian) then G is to
                    the north of F; at a quarter of the whole distance from Cadiz GF is 458 feet, at
                    half the distance<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0626-0605"/> it is 637 feet, and at three quarters it is
                    473 feet. The azimuth of the geodesic at Cadiz differs 20" from that of the
                    vertical plane, which is the astronomical azimuth. The azimuth of a geodesic
                    line cannot be observed, so that the line does not enter of necessity into
                    practical geodesy, although many formjulae connected with its use are of great
                    simplicity and elegance. The geodesic line has always held a more important
                    place in the science of geodesy among the mathematicians of France, Germany, and
                    Russia than has been assigned to it in the operations of the English and Indian
                    triangulations. Although the observed angles of a triangulation are not geodesic
                    angles, yet in the calculation of the distance and reciprocal bearings of two
                    points which are far apart, and are connected by a long chain of triangles, we
                    may fall upon the geodesic line in this manner :—</p>
                <p> If A, Z be the points, then to start the calculation from A, we obtain by some
                    preliminary calculation the approximate azimuth of Z, or the angle made by the
                    direction of Z with the side AB or AC of the first triangle. Let P <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> be the point where this line
                    intersects BC; then, to find P,, where the line cuts the next triangle side CD,
                    we make the angle BP <hi rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> P <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> such that BP <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> P <hi rend=" subscript">
                        2</hi> + BP <hi rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> A = 180 <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> o</hi> . This fixes P <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> ,
                    and P <hi rend=" subscript"> 3</hi> is fixed by a repetition of the same
                    process; soforP <hi rend=" subscript"> 4</hi> , P <hi rend=" subscript"> 8</hi>
                    . . . · Now it is clear that the points P <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> , P <hi rend=" subscript">
                        2</hi> , P <hi rend=" subscript"> 3</hi> so computed are those which would
                    be actually fixed by an observer with a theodolite, proceeding in the following
                    manner. Having set the instrument up at A, and turned the telescope in the
                    direction of the computed bearing, an assistant places a mark P <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> on the line BC, adjusting it till bisected by the
                    cross-hairs of the telescope at A. The theodolite is then placed over P <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> , and the telescope turned to A; the horizontal
                    circle is then moved through 180°. The assistant then places a mark P <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> on the line CD, so as to be bisected by the
                    telescope, which is then moved to P <hi rend="                     subscript">
                        2</hi> , and in the same manner P <hi rend=" subscript"> 3</hi> is fixed.
                    Now it is clear that the series of points P <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> , P
                        <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> , P <hi rend=" subscript"> 3</hi> approaches
                    to the geodesic line, for the plane of any two consecutive elements P <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> n</hi> -ι P <hi rend=" subscript">
                        n</hi> , P <hi rend=" subscript"> n</hi> P«+i contains the normal at P <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> n</hi> .</p>
                <p>From the formulae which we have given above, expressing the mutual relations of
                    two points P, Q on a spheroid, we may obtain the following solution of the
                    problem: Given the latitude &lt;∕&gt; of P, with the azimuth α and distance s of
                    Q, to determine the latitude and longitude of Q and the back azimuth <hi
                        rend="italic">a.</hi></p>
                <p> Let β = -∆</p>
                <p>a <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> lQH</p>
                <p>C= <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> TΓλ</hi> κ <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi> * <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ψ <hi rend="superscript"> sin 2α</hi></p>
                <p> 4(1 -e <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> )</p>
                <p> ⅝∙f⅛'' <hi rend=" superscript"> ,s,vrιi</hi></p>
                <p>£, ζ' are always veryminute quantities even for the longest distances; then,
                    putting κ = 90 <hi rend=" superscript"> o</hi> - φ, tan &lt;+&lt;- <hi
                        rend="                     superscript"> ft,</hi> . <hi rend=" superscript">
                        si</hi> " ⅜( <hi rend="                     superscript"> ,t</hi> - <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> g</hi> -Ω cot “</p>
                <p> 2 sm⅜(κ + 0 + O 2</p>
                <p> tan ≤+i±g <hi rend=" subscript"> g</hi><hi rend=" superscript"> cos</hi> ⅜(&lt;-
                        <hi rend=" superscript"> fl</hi> -^ cot “</p>
                <p> 2 cos ⅜(κ + θ-r C) 2</p>
                <p><hi rend=" subscript"> φ</hi> -&lt; <hi rend=" subscript"> t</hi> &gt;= l.
                    sin⅜(√+&lt;- <hi rend=" subscript"> g</hi> ) ∕ √- <hi rend=" subscript"> g</hi>
                    ∖ .</p>
                <p><hi rend=" superscript"> ψ ψ</hi> psin⅛(α'+^ <hi rend=" subscript"> +β</hi> )V 12
                    2 )’</p>
                <p> here p is the radius of curvature of the meridian for the mean latitude ⅜(φ +
                    φ'). These formulae are approximate only, but they are sufficiently precise even
                    for very long distances.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Meridian Arcs.</hi></p>
                <p> The length of the arc of meridian between the latitudes φ <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi> and φ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> is <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> =
                    f <hi rend="superscript"> φ</hi> * <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> d <hi
                        rend="subscript"> φ</hi> = <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi></p>
                <p>J <hi rend="superscript"> Ρφ</hi> J (1-e <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> sin <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> &lt;∕&gt;)⅜ ’</p>
                <p>Φι Φι</p>
                <p> instead of using the excentricity, put the ratio of the axes = 1 - η: 1 + n ,
                    then <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> ∕'Φ2 ⅞(l+nχi-⅞ <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi>
                    )</p>
                <p>f (1 + 2n cos 2φ + n <hi rend=" superscript"> a</hi> )⅜</p>
                <p>Φl</p>
                <p> This, after integration, gives</p>
                <p> 5 = (1 + n + ( ¼ ∣ ( 3» + 3»&gt; + ?‘»s) «, + (£»’+ ⅛⅛) <hi rend=" subscript">
                        α</hi> , where <hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> 0 = ≠2 <hi rend="superscript">
                        -</hi> Φl a <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> = sin (φι~φ <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi>) cos (≠ <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> + ≠ι) a <hi rend=" subscript">
                        2</hi> = sin 2(ψ <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> - ’ ≠ <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> ) cos 2(&lt;f&gt; <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> ÷φ <hi rend="                     subscript">
                        1</hi> ) a <hi rend=" subscript"> 3</hi> = sin 3(&lt;⅛&gt; <hi
                        rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> -&lt;j&gt; <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> ) cos
                    3(&lt; ∣ ⅛ <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> +φ <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> ) The
                    part of s which depends on n <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> is very small; in
                    fact, if we calculate it for the longest arc measured, the Bussian arc, it
                    amounts to only an inch and a half, therefore we omit this term, and put for ⅜
                    the value o</p>
                <p> (1 +n + ∣ n <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> ) α <hi rend=" subscript"> 0</hi> -
                    (3n + 3?i <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> ) a <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> +
                    (^n <hi rend=" superscript"> 2</hi> )a <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p> Now, if we suppose the observed latitudes to be affected with errors, and that
                    the true latitudes are φ <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> + x <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi>, φ <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> + x <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi>;
                    and if further we suppose that n <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> + dn is the true
                    value of a-b: a + b, and that n <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> itself is merely a
                    very approximate numerical value, we get, on making these substitutions and
                    neglecting the influence of the corrections x on the position of the arc in
                    latitude, i.e., on φ <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> + φ <hi rend=" subscript">
                        2</hi> ,</p>
                <p> I - (1 + n <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> + I ¾) α <hi rend=" subscript"> 0</hi>
                    - ( 3n <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> +3nJ) α <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> +
                    (^nj)α <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi><hi rend=" superscript"> +</hi> {(l+ ∣ <hi
                        rend=" superscript"> n</hi> ι) <hi rend=" superscript"> a</hi> o <hi
                        rend="                     superscript"> -</hi> ( <hi rend=" superscript">
                        3</hi> + <hi rend=" superscript"> 6,ι</hi> ι) <hi rend=" superscript">
                        a</hi> ι+(ι ’ h)&lt;⅛ } <hi rend="                     superscript"> dn</hi>
                    + I l+n <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> -3w <hi
                        rend="                     subscript"> 1</hi> ⅛pa <hi rend=" subscript">
                        0</hi>; here da^~x <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>- x <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi>; and as b is only known approximately, put b <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi>- b{l + u)∙, then we get, after dividing through by the coefficient of
                    da <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> , which is = 1 + π <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi>
                    - 3n <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> cos (φ <hi rend=" subscript"> 2</hi> -
                    &lt;f&gt; <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> ) cos (φ <hi rend=" subscript"> 4</hi> -
                    φ <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> ), an equation of the form x <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =x <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> + h+fu + gυ, where
                    for convenience we put v for dn.</p>
                <p> Now in every measured arc there are not only the extreme stations determined in
                    latitude, but also a number of intermediate stations, so that if there be i +1
                    stations there will be i equations</p>
                <p> α⅛=a⅛+∕ <hi rend=" subscript"> 1</hi> tt+gqv + A <hi rend=" subscript">
                        1</hi><hi rend=" smallcaps"> ¾ = ≈1+Λ</hi><hi rend=" superscript smallcaps">
                        w</hi><hi rend=" smallcaps"> + ^ +</hi><hi rend=" superscript smallcaps">
                        λ</hi><hi rend=" smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic">Xi = X</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">+fiU +
                        giv + hi .</hi></p>
                <p>In combining a number of different arcs of meridian, with the view of determining
                    the figure of the earth, each arc will supply a number of equations in <hi
                        rend="italic">u</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and the corrections to its
                    observed latitudes. Then, according to the method of least squares, those values
                    of <hi rend="italic">u</hi> and <hi rend="italic">υ</hi> are the most probable
                    which render the sum of the squares of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the errors <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi> a minimum. The corrections <hi rend="italic">x</hi>
                    which are here applied arise not from errors of observation only. The mere
                    uncertainty of a latitude, as determined with modern instruments, does not
                    exceed a very small fraction of a second as far as errors of observation go, but
                    no accuracy in observing will remove the error that may arise from local
                    attraction. This, as we have seen, may amount to some seconds, so that the
                    corrections <hi rend="italic">x</hi> to the observed latitudes are attributable
                    to local attraction. Archdeacon Pratt, in his treatise on the figure of the
                    earth, objects to this mode of applying least squares first used by Bessel; but
                    certainly Bessel was right, and the objection is groundless.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Comparisons of Standards.</hi></p>
                <p>In determining the figure of the earth from the arcs of meridian measured in
                    different countries, one source of uncertainty was, until the last few years,
                    the want of comparisons between the standards of length in which the arcs were
                    expressed. This has been removed by the very extensive series of comparisons
                    recently made at Southampton (see <hi rend="italic">Comparisons of Standard of
                        Length oj England, France, Belgium, Prussia, Russia, India, and Australia,
                        made at the Ordnance Survey Office, Southampton,</hi> 1866, and a paper in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for 1873, by Lieut.-Col.
                    A. R. Clarke, C.B., R.E., on the further comparisons of the standards of
                    Austria, Spain, the United States, Cape of Good Hope, and Russia). These direct
                    comparisons, which were carried out with the highest attainable precision, are
                    of very great value. The length of the toise has three independent
                    determinations, viz., through the Russian standard double toise, the Prussian
                    toise, and the Belgium toise,—giving for the length of the toise, expressed in
                    terms of the standard yard of England <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n627/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0627-0606"/> through the Russian standard 6 39453216
                    ft.</p>
                <p>„ ,, Prussian ,, . 6 39453703 ft.</p>
                <p>„ „ Belgian „ 6 39453215 ft.</p>
                <p>By combining all the different comparisons made in England and on the Continent
                    on these bars, by the method of least squares, the final value of the toise is
                    6∙39453348 ft (log = 0‘8058088656), from which the greatest divergence of the
                    three separate results specified above is only half a millionth of a toise,
                    corresponding to ten feet in the earth’s radius. From the known ratio of the
                    toise and the metre, 864000: 443296, we get for the metre</p>
                <p>3∙28086933 ft. (log = 0'5159889356).</p>
                <p>That the close agreement between the determinations of the toise is not due to
                    chance will be seen from the fact that the comparisons of the Prussian toise
                    with the English standard involved 2340 micrometer readings and 520 thermometer
                    readings, extending over twenty-five days, the probable error of the resulting
                    length of the toise being ±0'00000015 yard. The probable error of the
                    determination of the Belgian toise is ÷ 0Ό0000027; that of the Russian double
                    toise ±0O0000031. With regard to tne metre, there is an independent
                    determination resulting from the comparison of the platinum metre of the Royal
                    Society,— a large number of observations giving for the length of the metre 3 ’
                    28087206 feet, which differs from the former result by about one millionth part.
                    But this determination, involving the expansion of the bar for 30° of
                    temperature, and being dependent on some old observations of Arago, cannot be
                    allowed any weight in modifying the result obtained through the toises. The
                    Russian standard, compared at Southampton, was that on which the length of their
                    base lines and therefore their whole arc depends.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Calculation of the Semiaxes.</hi></p>
                <p>We now bring together the results of the various meridian arcs, omitting many
                    short arcs which have been used in previous determinations, but which on account
                    of their smallness have little influence in the result aimed at.</p>
                <p>The data of the French arc from Formentera to Dunkirk are—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stations.</p><p>Formentera</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3"><p>Astronomical</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Distance of Parallels.</p><p>Feet.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>b</p><p>38</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Latitudes.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>39</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53∙17</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mountjouy</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>.... 41</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>44∙96</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>982671’04</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Barcelona</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>.... 41</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>22</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>47∙90</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>988701 ∙92</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Carcassonne</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>43</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54∙30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1657287'93</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Pantheon</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>.... 48</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>47’98</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3710827 ’ 13</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Dunkirk</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>51</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8∙41</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4509790'84</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The latitude of Formentera as here given is taken from the observations of Μ.
                    Biot, recorded and computed in the third volume of his <hi rend="italic">Traité
                        Élémentaire</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >Astronomie</hi><hi rend="italic">physique.</hi></p>
                <p>The latitude of the Pantheon, given in the <hi rend="italic">Base</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">du Système Métrique</hi><hi rend="italic">Decimal</hi> (ii.
                    413), is 48° 50' 48"∙86. In the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >de l'</hi><hi rend="italic">Observatoire</hi><hi rend="italic">Imperial de
                        Paris,</hi> vol. viii. page 317, we find the latitude of south face of the
                    observatory determined as 48° 50' 11"‘71. The Pantheon being 35" <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 38 north of this, we thus get a second
                    determination of its latitude. The mean is that given above.</p>
                <p>The distance of the parallels of Dunkirk and Greenwich, deduced from the recent
                    extension of the triangulation of England into France, in 1862, is 161407 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 3 feet, which is 3 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                    9 feet greater than that obtained from Captain Kater’s triangulation, and 3'2
                    feet less than the distance calculated by Delambre from General Roy’s
                    triangulation. The following table shows the data of the English arc with the
                    distances in standard feet from Formentera.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Formentera</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Greenwich</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>51</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>38∙30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4671198-3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Λrbury</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>26∙59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4943837’6</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Clifton</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29∙50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5394063∙4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Kellie Law</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53’60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6413221 ∙7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stirling</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>57</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>49∙12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6857323’3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Saxavord</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>49</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>37∙21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8086820-7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The latitude assigned in this table to Saxavord is not the directly observed
                    latitude, which is 60° 49' 38" ’ 58, for there are here a cluster of three
                    points, whose latitudes are astronomically determined; and if we transfer, by
                    means of the geodesic connection, the latitude of <hi rend="italic">Gerlh of
                        Scaw</hi> to Saxavord, we get 60° 49' 36" ’ 59; and if we similarly transfer
                    the latitude of <hi rend="italic">Balta,</hi> we get 60° 49' 36" ’ 46. The mean
                    of these three is that entered in the above table.</p>
                <p>For the Indian arc in long. 77° 40' we have the following data :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Punnoe</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31T32</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Putchapolliam</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>42-276</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1029174-9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Dodagoontah</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52-165</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1756562-0</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Namthabad</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 15</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53-562</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2518376-3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Daumergida</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15-292</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3591788-4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Takalkhera</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>51-532</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4697329-5</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Kalianpur</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 24</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11-262</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5794695’7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Kaliana</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>... 29</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48'322</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7755835-9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The data of the Russian arc (long. 26° 40') taken from M. Struve’s work are as
                    below :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Staro Nekrassowka..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>2-94</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Wodolui</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>47</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24-98</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>616529-81</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ssuprunkowzi</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3 04</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1246762-17</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Kremenetz</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>49’95</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1737551∙48</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Belin</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>42-16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2448745-17</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Nemesch</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>39</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4-16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3400312-63</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Jacobstadt</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4-97</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4076412-28</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Dorpat</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>58</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>22</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>47’56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4762421-43</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Hogland</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9-84</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5386135-39</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Kilpi-maki</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>38</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5-25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6317905∙67</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tornea</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>65</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>49</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>44-57</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7486789-97</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Stuor-oivi</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>68</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>58-40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8530517-90</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fuglenoes</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>70</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11-23</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9257921-06</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>From the arc measured by Sir Thomas Maclear in long. 18° 30', we have</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>North End</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>17∙66</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Heerenlogement Berg.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>58</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9-11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>811507‘7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Koyal Observatory....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>33</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3-20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1526386-8</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Zwart Kop</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>34</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>32 13</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1632583∙3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cape Point</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>34</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6-26</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1678375-7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>And, finally, for the Peruvian arc, in long. 281° 0',</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tarqui</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>-3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4 32-068</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feet.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cotchesqui</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2 3Γ387</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1131036-3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Having now stated the data of the problem, we may either seek that ellipsoid
                    which best represents the observations, or we may restrict the figure to one of
                    revolution. It will be convenient to commence with the supposition of an
                    ellipsoidal figure, as on so doing we can, by a slight alteration in the
                    equations of minimum, obtain also the required figure of revolution. It may be
                    remarked that, whatever the real figure may be, it is certain that if we
                    presuppose it an ellipsoid, the arithmetical process will bring out an
                    ellipsoid, which ellipsoid will agree better with all the observed latitudes
                    than any spheroid would, therefore we do not <hi rend="italic">prove</hi> that
                    it is an ellipsoid; to prove this, arcs of longitude would be required. There is
                    no doubt such arcs will be shortly forthcoming, but as yet they are not
                    available.</p>
                <p>The first thing that occurs to one in considering an ellipsoidal earth is the
                    question, What is a meridian curve 1 It may be defined in different ways: a
                    point moving on the surface in the direction astronomically determined as
                    “north” might be said to trace a meridian; or we may define it as the locus of
                    those points which have a constant longitude, whose zeniths lie in a great
                    circle of the heavens, having its poles in the equator; we adopt this
                    definition. Let <hi rend="italic">a, b, c</hi> be the semiaxes, c being the
                    polar semiaxis. The equation of the ellipsoid being</p>
                <p>α <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> 5≡ <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> c <hi
                        rend="superscript"> a</hi> ’</p>
                <p>if P be any point on the surface, the direction cosines of the normal at P are
                    proportional to <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n628/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0628-0607"/><hi rend="italic">du du (lu</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> λt</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >,</hi><hi rend="italic">« y_</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">∙</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic">dx’ Ty’
                        te’</hi> α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ’ P ’ c <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> ’ and if ⅜π - <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> be the angle between this
                    normal and the •minor axis, so that <hi rend="italic">φ</hi> is the latitude of
                    P, we have z <hi rend="superscript"> βin</hi> ≠ = ∕x <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> y <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ⅛∖⅜' ∖α <hi rend="superscript">
                        4</hi> 6 <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> c <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi>
                    √</p>
                <p>Hence the equation to a “parallel” in which the latitude <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>
                    is constant is</p>
                <p>⅞ + g-C∞t≡ <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> &gt; = O. .</p>
                <p>α <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >c</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi></p>
                <p>So that in an ellipsoidal earth the parallel is no longer a plane curve. Let
                    longitude be reckoned from the plane of <hi rend="italic">xz.</hi> As there are
                    two species of latitude, astronomical and geoeentric, so there are in the
                    ellipsoidal earth two species of longitude, geocentric (called «) and
                    astronomical (called ω). Conceive a line passing through the origin in the plane
                    of the equator and directed to a point whose longitude is ⅛π + ω. The direction
                    cosines of that line are—sin ω, cos <hi rend="italic">ω,</hi> and 0. Those
                    points of the surface whose normals are at right angles to this line are in the
                    meridian whose longitude is ω; the condition of perpendicularity is expressed by
                        <hi rend="italic">X</hi> ein <hi rend="italic">ω</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >y</hi> cos <hi rend="italic">ω _</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> n</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">~aΓ~</hi><hi rend="superscript"> +-</hi> P ’</p>
                <p>and this, in fact, is the equation of the meridian, which is still on the
                    ellipsoidal hypothesis a plane curve. The geocentric and astronomical longitudes
                    are connected by the relation</p>
                <p>α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> tan u= <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> i</hi> tan <hi rend="italic"
                        >a&gt;.</hi></p>
                <p>This meridian curve is an ellipse whose minor semi-axis is c, and of which the
                    semi-axis major is some quantity <hi rend="italic">r</hi> intermediate between
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> such that</p>
                <p>1 _ cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"> u</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi><hi rend="italic"> u</hi> r <hi rend="superscript"
                        > 2</hi> α <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ~ ~⅛ <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> ~ *</p>
                <p>Take two quantities <hi rend="italic">i, k,</hi> such that α <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (l -i) = δ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (l <hi
                        rend="italic">+ i')-k</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">,</hi> then ⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> =r <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (l - <hi rend="italic">i</hi> cos 2w); and take
                        <hi rend="italic">n</hi> such that</p>
                <p>„_r-c</p>
                <p>-—- , <hi rend="italic">r + e</hi> and substitute the value of <hi rend="italic"
                        >r,</hi> neglecting the square of <hi rend="italic">i</hi>; this gives</p>
                <p>»“V—- + v <hi rend="superscript"> cos</hi> 2ω .</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">k + c 4</hi></p>
                <p>Now we have to determine not only the three semi-axes <hi rend="italic">a, b,
                        e,</hi> but the longitude of <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> Let w <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 1</hi> be the longitude of one of the measured meridian
                    arcs, <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 0</hi> the longitude
                    of <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> then, for that arc,</p>
                <p>⅛-c i <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> λ</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> n =</hi> *Tc <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> 4 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> C0S</hi><hi rend="italic">=JHM-+p</hi> cos 2w <hi
                        rend="subscript"> j</hi> +o sin 2u <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">k + c</hi> where <hi rend="italic">4p = i</hi> cos 2u <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 0</hi>, <hi rend="italic">4q-i</hi> sin 2w <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 0</hi>.</p>
                <p>The normal at P does not pass through the axis of rotation, so that the observed
                    latitudes on an ellipsoid are not exactly the quantities which should be used in
                    the ordinary method of expressing the length of a meridian arc in terms of the
                    latitudes. But it may be shown that this consideration may be neglected.</p>
                <p>The data we have collected form 35 equations between the 40 «-corrections to the
                    observed latitudes, and the four unknown quantities determining the elements of
                    the ellipsoid. Suppose n <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> to be an approximate value
                    of the ratio <hi rend="italic">fc - c: lc</hi> + c, so that <hi rend="italic"
                        >k-c</hi> vrr" <hi rend="superscript"> ι+r</hi> ∙</p>
                <p>where <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is a small correction to n <hi rend="subscript">
                        1</hi> and suppose <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                        1</hi> to be an approximate value of <hi rend="italic">c so</hi> that <hi
                        rend="italic">c = c</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >(</hi> 1 + <hi rend="italic">t),</hi> then the four unknown quantities are
                        <hi rend="italic">p, q, r, t.</hi> The result of making the sum of the
                    squares of the 40 corrections a minimum is</p>
                <p>Feet. Metres.</p>
                <p>α =-∙ 20926350 = 6378294 0 <hi rend="italic">b =</hi> 20919972 = 6376350'4 <hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi> =20853429 = 6356068’1</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">a — c</hi> 1 6—c 1</p>
                <p>^^c~ 285 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 97 ’ <hi rend="italic">~c</hi> ' <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 313∙38</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">a — b</hi> J</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> c <hi rend="superscript"> --</hi> 3269 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> τ</hi> 5 Longitude of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> 15° 34'
                    East.</p>
                <p>The meridian of the greater axis passes, in the Eastern Hemisphere, through
                    Spitzbergen, the Straits of Messina, Lake Chad in North Africa, and along the
                    west coast of South Africa,—nearly corresponding to the meridian which passes
                    over the greatest quantity of land in that hemisphere. In the Western Hemisphere
                    it passes through Behring’s Straits and through the centre of the Pacific Ocean.
                    The meridian (105° 34' E.) of the minor axis of the equator passes near
                    North-east Cape on the Arctic Sea, through Tong-king and the Straits of Sunda,
                    and corresponds nearly to the meridian which passes over the greatest amount of
                    land in Asia; and in the Western Hemisphere it passes through Smith Sound, the
                    west of Labrador, Montreal, between Cuba and Hayti, and along the west coast of
                    South America, nearly coinciding with the meridian that passes over the greatest
                    amount of land in that hemisphere.</p>
                <p>The length of the meridian quadrant passing through Paris, in the ellipsoidal
                    figure given above, is 10001472 ’ 5 metres, showing that the length of the ideal
                    French standard is considerably in error as representing the ten-millionth part
                    of the quadrant. The minimum quadrant, in longitude 105° 34', has a length of
                    10000024 ’ 5 metres. The probable error of the longitude of the major axis of
                    the equator given above is of course large, as much perhaps as ±15°.</p>
                <p>It has been objected to this figure of three unequal axes that it does not
                    satisfy, in the proportions of the axes, the conditions brought out in Jacobi’s
                    theorem. Admitting this, it has to be noted, on the other hand, that Jacobi’s
                    theorem contemplates a homogeneous fluid, and this is certainly far from the
                    actual condition of our globe, indeed, the irregular distribution of continents
                    and oceans suggests as possible a sensible divergence from a perfect surface of
                    revolution.</p>
                <p>If we limit the figure to being an ellipsoid of revolution, we get rid in our
                    equations of two unknown quantities, and the result may be expressed thus :—</p>
                <p>Feet. Metres.</p>
                <p>α = 20926062 = 6378206∙4</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">c</hi> =20855121 = 6356503 8 c: α = 293 ’ 98 :294 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 98.</p>
                <p>As might be expected, the sum of the squares of the 40 latitude corrections,
                    viz., 153’99, is greater in this figure than in that of three axes, where it
                    amounts to 138 ’ 30. In the Indian arc the largest corrections are at
                    Dodagoontah, + 3"∙87, and at Kalianpur, -3" ’ 68. In the Russian arc the largest
                    corrections are + 3" ’ 76, at Tornea, and - 3" <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                    31, at Staro Nekrassowka. Of the whole 40 corrections, 16 are under 1"O,10
                    between 1" ’ 0 and 2".0, 10between 2"O and 3"O, and 4 over 3"O. For the
                    ellipsoidal figure the probable error of an observed latitude is ± 1" ’ 42; for
                    the spheroidal it would be very slightly larger. This quantity may be taken
                    therefore as approximately the probable amount of local deflection.</p>
                <p>In 1860, the Russian Government, at the instance of M. Otto Struve, imperial
                    astronomer at St Petersburg, invited the co-operation of the Governments of
                    Prussia, Belgium, France, and England, to the important end of connecting their
                    respective triangulations so as to form a continuous chain under the parallel of
                    52° from the island of Valentia on the south-west coast of Ireland, in longitude
                    10° 20' 40" W., to Orsk on the river Ural in Russia. This grand undertaking was
                    at once set in action, but up to the present <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n629/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0629-0608"/> time there are portions of the work still
                    incomplete. On the part of England the triangulation was, in 1862, carried
                    through France into Belgium; and the difference of longitude of Greenwich and
                    Valentia was determined by the Astronomer Royal by means of electric telegraph
                    signals.</p>
                <p>Although in theory the determination of differences of longitude by electric
                    telegraph signals may appear ext remely simple, yet practically there are very
                    many sources of error which have to be sought out and eliminated by a proper
                    arrangement of the observations. The system has now been brought to such
                    perfection that the astronomical amplitude of arcs of longitude can be
                    determined with nearly as much accuracy as those of latitude, and in a few years
                    the data of the problem of the figure of the earth will thus receive many
                    additions. As an example of the precision arrived at, the difference of
                    longitude of Greenwich Observatory and Harvard Observatory, U.S.A., has been
                    three times determined with the following results :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1866 by Anglo-American Cable</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>h.</p><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>m.</p><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31 00</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1870 by French Cable to Duxbury</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30 99</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1872 by French Cable to St Pierre</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30∙96</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>But the different determinations of the velocity of transmission of signals
                    present great anomalies.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pendulum Observations.</hi></p>
                <p>In Clairaut’s theorem we have seen that if <hi rend="italic">f</hi> be gravity in
                    the latitude of &lt;∕&gt;, <hi rend="italic">g</hi> its value at the equator,
                    then ∕ = &lt;7(1+ &lt;7 sin <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> φ). If the same
                    pendulum be swung in different latitudes then the square of the number of
                    vibrations will be proportional to gravity. Hence, if N be the number of
                    vibrations of an invariable pendulum per diem at the equator, N' the number in
                    latitude &lt;∕&gt;, then N' <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = N <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> (1 + <hi rend="italic">q</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> φ). Thus <hi rend="italic">q</hi> can be obtained
                    by observations on the same pendulum in different latitudes, and since <hi
                        rend="italic">q — ^m-e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is known, <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> will at once follow. The pendulum which makes 86400
                    oscillations per diem in London is observed to lose 136 vibrations at the
                    equator and gain 79 at Spitzbergen.</p>
                <p>The limits of space at our disposal here prevent our going into the subject of
                    pendulum experiments, and it seems unnecessary to repeat the investigations that
                    have already been based upon the older pendulum observations. See Airy’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Figure of the Earth,</hi> Baily’s paper in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Memoirs of the Royal Astronomical Society,</hi> General
                    Sabine’s <hi rend="italic">Account of Experiments to determine the Figure of the
                        Earth by means of the Pendulum vibrating seconds in Different
                        Latitudes,</hi> 1825, and a valuable paper in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cambridge Philosophical Transactions,</hi> 1849, by Professor Stokes. The
                    pendulum gives an ellipticity certainly somewhat greater than that resulting
                    from arcs of meridian, viz., - <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>-g⅛.- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> s</hi>-. An immense number of pendulum observations are
                    now being made at the astronomical stations of geodesical surveys in Germany,
                    Russia, and India, which, when fully published, will throw light more perhaps
                    upon the local variations of gravity than on the figure of the earth. The
                    observations made at the various stations of the Indian meridian arc bring to
                    light a physical fact of the very highest importance and interest, namely, that
                    the density of the strata of the earth’s crust under and in the vicinity of the
                    Himalayan Mountains is less than that under the plains to the south, the
                    deficiency increasing as the stations of observation approach the Himalayas, and
                    being a maximum when they are situated on the range itself. This accounts fer
                    the non-appearance of the large deflections which the Himalayas, according to
                    Archdeacon Pratt’s calculations, ought to produce. The Indian pendulum
                    observations also throw some light on the relative variations of gravity at
                    continental, coast, and island stations, showing that, without a single
                    exception, gravity at the coast stations is greater than at the corresponding
                    continental stations, and greater at island stations than at coast stations. The
                    ellipticity of the earth has also been deduced from the motion of the moon, the
                    quantity <hi rend="italic">e-⅛m</hi> entering as a coefficient_in the expression
                    for the moon’s latitude. The resulting value of the ellipticity is ∙ <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>-⅜ <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> th (Airy’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Tracts,</hi> p. 188). A value of the ellipticity may also be
                    derived from the precession of the equinoxes, but as this depends on the assumed
                    law of density in the interior of the earth it is not of much importance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Elements of the Figure as a Solid of Revolution.</hi>
                    α=20926062: δ=20855121 .</p>
                <p>If <hi rend="italic">p</hi> be the radius of curvature of the meridian in
                    latitude <hi rend="italic">φ, p'</hi> that perpendicular to the meridian, D the
                    length of a degree of the meridian, D' the length of a degree of longitude, <hi
                        rend="italic">r</hi> the radius drawn from the centre of the earth, V the
                    angle of the vertical, then</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="3"><p>Feet.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 20890606’6 -10641Γ5 cos 2≠</p><p><hi
                                    rend="italic">p’</hi> = 20961607’3 - 35590’9 cos
                                2&lt;∕&gt;</p><p>D = 364609∙87 - 1857’14 cos 2&lt;f&gt;</p><p>D' =
                                365538’48 cos <hi rend="italic">φ —</hi> 310Ί7 cos 3φ</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>+ 225’8 cos <hi rend="italic">4φ</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>+ + +</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45’2 cos <hi rend="italic">4φ</hi></p><p>3 <hi rend="superscript">
                                    -</hi> 94 cos <hi rend="italic">4φ</hi></p><p>0'39 cos <hi
                                    rend="italic">5φ</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Log- = 9’9992645 + Ό007374 cos 2&lt;∕&gt;</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>-</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 0000019 cos <hi rend="italic"
                                    >4φ</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>V =700"∙44 sin 2φ- 1" ’ 19 sin <hi rend="italic"
                            >4φ.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>(A. R. C.)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
