<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0703-0682-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">EDWARD I</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 682</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:800130">Age</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:800293">Aging</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n703/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EDWARD I</label>. (1239-1307), king of England, was the son
                    of Henry III. of England, and of Eleanor, daughter of the count of Provençe, and
                    was born at Westminster, June 16, 1239. In 1252 he was named governor of Gascony
                    in room of Simon de Montfort, with whom Henry was dissatisfied; and in 1254, by
                    his marriage with Eleanor, daughter of Alphonso X. of Castile, he secured to the
                    English for a time undisputed possession of that province. At the battle of
                    Lewes, 13th May 1264, Edward, by the impetuosity of his attack, at first
                    defeated the barons with great slaughter, but by his too great rashness in
                    pursuit failed to give the king proper support in another part of the field, and
                    was thus the cause ultimately of the utter rout of the royal forces. He was
                    taken prisoner, but escaping by a clever stratagem, he joined with the earl of
                    Gloucester, and inflicted a disastrous defeat on De Montfort and his sons at
                    Evesham, August 3, 1265. In 1269, at the request of the Pope, he undertook a
                    crusade to the Holy Land. He reached it in 1270, and in 1271 he captured
                    Nazareth and massacred all the Turks found within its walls. In revenge,
                    perhaps, for this act, an assassin, on June 12, 1272, stabbed him in three
                    places with a poisoned arrow; but his vigorous constitution triumphed over his
                    injuries and he completely recovered. In the same year his father died, and he
                    was proclaimed king. He had arrived at Sicily when the news reached him, but
                    instead of going direct to England, he crossed over to Italy, and thence into
                    France, where in a tournament his followers quarrelled with those of the count
                    of Chalons, and he slew the count in single combat. He landed in England August
                    2, 1274, and was crowned on the 19th. In October of the same year he issued
                    writs to inquire into the state of the realm, and the next year there were
                    passed the laws called the Statutes of Westminster, which reformed many of the
                    abuses of the feudal system, secured freedom from undue influence in the
                    election of sheriffs and other justices, and threatened with penalties certain
                    oppressive acts on the part of the barons. In 1277 he conquered Wales and caused
                    Llewelyn to sue for peace; but in 1280, a Welsh war again broke out, which
                    continued till the death of Llewelyn in 1282. Edward’s plan to obtain money for
                    the expenses of this <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> war, by summoning for
                    consultation in 1283 representatives of the shires, the boroughs, and the
                    church, was the germ of the English House of Commons, although the first
                    properly constituted Parliament did not meet till 1295. A less creditable method
                    of raising money was the banishment, in 1280, of the Jews from England, on
                    condition that the clergy and laity submitted to a tax of a fifteenth. Two other
                    important decisions were the consequence of his money difficulties :—in 1297 he
                    refused submission to the bull of Boniface VIII. forbidding the clergy to be
                    taxed on their ecclesiastical revenue, and in 1299 he was obliged to confirm the
                    charters conferring on the people the right to fix their own taxation. In 1290
                    Queen Eleanor died, and in 1293 Edward entered into negotiations for a marriage
                    with Margaret, sister of Philip TV. of France; but on account of an act of
                    treachery on the part of the French, these negotiations were broken off for a
                    time, and the marriage did not take place till 1299. From 1295 the affairs of
                    Scotland occupied his chief attention. In 1292 he had decided the claims of the
                    candidates for the Scottish crown <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n704/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0704-0683"/> in favour of Baliol, on condition that the latter
                    acknowledged him as lord paramount, and on the breaking out of war with France
                    he demanded his assistance. On Baliol’s refusal, and on learning that he had
                    entered into a treaty with France, Edward in 129G captured Berwick, defeated the
                    Scots at Dunbar, took the castles of Roxburgh, Jedburgh, Edinburgh, Dumbarton,
                    and Stirling, and, receiving at Perth Baliol’s unconditional surrender, sent him
                    prisoner to the Tower. In 1297 Wallace headed a rebellion of the Scots, and
                    defeated the English with great slaughter at the battle of Stirling bridge; but
                    next year the Scots suffered an overwhelming defeat at Falkirk, and only
                    prevented the further success of the English by laying waste their own country.
                    In 1299 and 1300 Edward’s attempts at invasion met with little success on
                    account of opposition from his barons. In 1301 he invaded Scotland for the fifth
                    time, but at the request of the king of France granted it a truce. In 1304 he
                    compelled its submission, and excepted from the amnesty granted to the Scotch
                    nobles Sir William Wallace, who was captured and executed in 1305. In 1307, to
                    avenge Bruce’s murder of Cornyn and his attacks on the English, Edward resolved
                    on a seventh invasion, and, though in great bodily λveak-ness, determined to
                    lead his army in person; but his almost unexampled labours had already
                    undermined his vigorous health, and he died 7th July 1307, at the village of
                    Burgh-on-the-Sands, on the fifth day of his march northwards from Carlisle. He
                    had given orders that his dead body should be carried before the army until his
                    enemies were conquered; but his son Edward made no endeavour to fulfil his wish.
                    The body was escorted to Waltham, and was buried at Westminster on the 27th
                    October. In Edward were united in a rare degree both the physical and mental
                    qualities of a great general; and he is one of the few English kings, and
                    perhaps the first, who can lay claim to the higher qualities of statesmanship.
                    The measures which he passed for the government of his own kingdom, and the
                    concessions he made to the demands of his subjects, almost entitle him to be
                    called the founder of England’s constitutional freedom; while the far-seeing
                    wisdom of his foreign policy was shown by his sacrificing his influence in
                    France in order to quell the opposition to his authority in Scotland. That his
                    claims on Scotland were altogether just can scarcely be affirmed; but that he
                    clearly saw the necessity of a union of Scotland and England, and devoted his
                    whole efforts to the attainment of this end, is perhaps his highest title to
                    honourable remembrance. His harsh manner of attaining his end, and the cruel
                    punishments he exercised on those who sought to thwart his efforts, may be
                    excused partly on account of the times in which he lived, and partly as arising
                    from the just vexation of a stern and eager nature; and they are somewhat
                    counter-balanced by the righteousness and clemency with which he governed
                    Scotland at the periods when it was under his rule.</p>
                <p>See Hallam’s <hi rend="italic">Middle Ages;</hi> Pearson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of England during the Early and Middle Ages,</hi> vol. ii.; Longman’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the History of England,</hi> vol. i.; Stubbs’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Early Plantagenet Kings;</hi> Hill Burton’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Scotland,</hi> vol. ii.; and Green’s <hi rend="italic">Short History
                    of the English People.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
