<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0644-0623-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ECCLESIASTES, The Book of (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    623)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176240">Wisdom</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sf6k">Talmud</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n644/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ECCLESIASTES, <hi rend="smallcaps">The Book of</hi></label>,
                    has been handed down by Hebrew tradition as one of the three canonical books of
                    Solomon, son of David, the other two being Proverbs and the Song of Songs, or
                    Canticles.</p>
                <p>Two different practices have obtained from time immemorial as to the position of
                    this book in the Bible. According to one, which is preserved in the MSS. and
                    editions of the Septuagint, and is followed by the MSS. and editions of the
                    Vulgate, Ecclesiastes is the second in the order of the five books which,
                    according to the Alexandrian Jews and the Greek and Latin churches, was written
                    by Solomon. The order of these five books in the Alexandrian and Sinai tic
                    Codices and in the MS. Bible of Charles the Bold, <hi rend="italic">circa</hi>
                    850 (British Museum) is Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, Canticles, Wisdom, and
                    Ecclesiasticus. According to the other practice the book in question is
                    separated from those which are supposed to belong to the same author, and is
                    joined for liturgical purposes to the other four <hi rend="italic"
                        >Megilloth.</hi> Thus in the oldest dated MS. of the entire Hebrew Bible yet
                    known (1009), now in the imperial library of St Petersburg, it is the <hi
                        rend="italic">third</hi> of the five Megilloth, viz., Ruth, Canticles,
                    Ecclesiastes, Lamentations, and Esther. Though this order is also to be found in
                    the Spanish and Italian MSS., it is by no means universal. Additional MS. 15,250
                    of the British Museum not only puts Ecclesiastes before Canticles, but places
                    Ruth before the Psalms. In the fourteen pre-Reformation German translations of
                    the Bible (1462-1518), and in Wycliffe’s English version, where the five
                    Solomonic books are still kept together, the order of the Septuagint and Vulgate
                    is followed, as is also the case in the English Catholic version (Douai, 1610).
                    Luther, who was the first to remove Wisdom and Ecclesiasticus from this group,
                    and place them with the other so-called Apocryphal books at the end of the Old
                    Testament, has left Ecclesiastes as second in the order of the Solomonic
                    writings. In our first English translation of the entire Bible (1535) Coverdale
                    followed the example of the great Continental Reformer. Hence this narrower
                    group and this position of Ecclesiastes in the succeeding English Bibles, and in
                    the present Authorized Version.</p>
                <p>There is hardly another book in the Bible which has called forth so many
                    commentaries and suffered as much at the hands of expositors as Ecclesiastes.
                    Nearly 350 years ago Luther remarked,—“Difficult as this book is, it is almost
                    more difficult to clear the author of the visionary fancies palmed upon him by
                    his numerous commentators than to develop his meaning.” What w ould this
                    sagacious Reformer have said if he could have seen the countless speculations of
                    which it has been the subject since his days <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> We
                    are positively assured that the book contains the holy lamentations of Solomon,
                    together with a prophetic vision of the splitting up of the royal house of
                    David, the destruction of the Temple, and the Captivity; and we are equally
                    assured that it is a discussion between a refined sensualist and a sober sage.
                    Solomon publishes in it his repentance, to glorify God and to strengthen his
                    brethren; he wrote it “when he was irreligious and sceptical during his amours
                    and idolatry.” “The Messiah, the true Solomon, who was known by the title of son
                    of David, addresses this book to the saints ;” a profligate who wanted to
                    disseminate his infamous sentiments palmed it upon Solomon. It teaches us to
                    despise the world with all its pleasures, and flee to monasteries; it shows that
                    sensual gratifications are men’s greatest blessing upon earth. It is a
                    philosophic lecture delivered to a literary society upon topics of the greatest
                    moment; it is a medley of heterogeneous fragments belonging to various authors
                    and different ages. It describes the beautiful order of God’s moral government,
                    showing that all things work together for good to them that love the Lord; it
                    proves that all is disorder and confusion, and that the world is the sport of
                    chance. It is a treatise on the <hi rend="italic">summum bonum;</hi> it is “a
                    chronicle of the lives of the kings of the house of David from Solomon down to
                    Zedekiah.” Its object is to prove the immortality of the soul; its design is to
                    deny a future existence. Its aim is to comfort the unhappy Jews in their
                    misfortunes; and its sole purport is to pour forth the gloomy imaginations of a
                    melancholy misanthrope. It is intended “to open Nathan’s speech (1 Chron. xvii.)
                    touching the eternal throne of David;” and it propounds by anticipation the
                    modern discoveries of anatomy and the Harveian theory of the circulation of the
                    blood. “It foretells what will become of man or angels to eternity ;” and,
                    according to one of the latest and greatest authorities, it is a keen satire on
                    Herod, written 8 B.c., when the king cast his son Alexander into prison.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For an historical account
                            of the interpretation of Ecclesiastes, with detached, specimens of these
                            conflicting views, see Ginsburg, <hi rend="italic">Commentary on
                                Ecclesiastes,</hi> pp. 27-293, London, 1861.</p></note></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n645/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0645-0624"/>
                <p>One of the causes which have contributed to obscure the design of this book is
                    the name <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastes.</hi> This title Preacher, which
                    ascribes to Solomon an office foreign to the Old Testament, has been given to it
                    by the Septuagint and Vulgate in accordance with a Jewish tradition, and has
                    been adopted alike by the pre-and post-Reformation authorized versions of the
                    Scriptures. The Jewish tradition in question is to be found in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Midrash Pabba</hi> on Eccl. i. 1, where we are told that
                    “Solomon was called <hi rend="italic">Coheleth</hi> = Ecclesiastes, because hi3
                    discourses were delivered in the <hi rend="italic">Cαhαl =</hi> Ecclesia.” Hence
                    the title in the Alexandrian version, which was followed by the Latin Authorized
                    Version, and is reproduced in Wycliffe’s Bible “the boc of Ecclesiastes, that is
                    to sey, boc of talker to the people.” Hence, too, Luther’s title <hi
                        rend="italic">Prediger,</hi> which is followed in our first printed English
                    Bible “the boke of the Preacher, otherwyse called Ecclesiastes” (Coverdale,
                    1535), and which is perpetuated in our Authorized Version. This title, however,
                    is contrary to the grammatical form of the word <hi rend="italic">Coheleth,</hi>
                    as well as to the usage of the root from which it is derived. It has arisen from
                    a desire on the part of the Jewish synagogue to exhibit Solomon in the garb of a
                    penitent confessing his sins, and, by detailing his bitter experience, warning
                    the people publicly to avoid the thorny path he has pursued and walk in the ways
                    of righteousness. Laudable as this desire is, it perverts the
                    historico-exegetical import of the book, and is contradicted by the
                    signification of the name.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Coheleth</hi> is the participle feminine Kai of <hi
                        rend="italic">kdhal,</hi> which primarily means <hi rend="italic">to call,
                        to call together, to collect, to assemble.</hi> The verb 0ccur3 about forty
                    times in the Hebrew Bible, and is invariably used for assembling or gathering
                    people together, especially for religious worship. Hence the name means <hi
                        rend="italic">α collectress,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">an assembleress of
                        people into the presence of God, a female gatherer of an assembly to
                        God,</hi> This meaning of the name is fully confirmed by another Jewish
                    tradition, which 13 embodied in the <hi rend="italic">Midrash Yalkut</hi> (Eccl.
                    i. 1), and is exhibited in the ancient Greek versi0n3 of Aquila and Symmachus.
                    Chapter i. 12 tells us that Solomon is meant by this designation, since he was
                    the only son of David who was king over Israel in Jerusalem. The feminine and
                    symbolic appellation arises from the fact that in chapter vii. 27 of this very
                    book Solomon is depicted as <hi rend="italic">personified Wisdom,</hi> who
                    appears herself in Prov. i. 10, viii. 1, &amp;c., as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Coheleth,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">the female gatherer of the people.</hi>
                    This symbolic name is, moreover, intended to indicate the design of the book
                    itself, and to connect Solomon’s endeavours here with his work recorded in 1
                    Kings viii. Solomon, who in 1 Kings viii. is described as <hi rend="italic"
                        >gathering</hi> (^∏p') the people to hold communion with the Most High in
                    the place which he erected for this purpose, is here again represented as <hi
                        rend="italic">the gatherer</hi> (∏S∏p) θf the far-off people of God. As he
                    retains his individuality, he sometimes describes his own experience, and
                    sometimes utters the words of Wisdom, whose organ he is.</p>
                <p>The design of this book, as indicated in the symbolic title of its hero, is to
                    gather God’s people, who were led astray by the inexplicable difficulties in the
                    moral government of the world, iuto the community of God. Coheleth shows them
                    the utter insufficiency of all human efforts to obtain real happiness—that it
                    cannot be secured by wisdom, pleasure, industry, wealth, and prudence, but that
                    it consists in the calm enjoyment of our lot, in resignation to the dealings of
                    Providence, in the service of the Most High, and in looking forward to a future
                    state of retribution, when all the present mysteries shall be solved, and when
                    the Righteous Judge shall render to every man according to his deeds, whether
                    they be good or evil.</p>
                <p>Instead of writing an elaborate metaphysical disquisition to refute the various
                    systems of happiness which the different orders of mind and the different
                    temperaments had constructed for themselves, Solomon is introduced as narrating
                    his painful experience in all his attempts. He shows how he had vainly striven
                    to divert the longings of his soul by various experiments, and the only solution
                    which can pacify the perplexed mind when contemplating the unfathomable dealings
                    in the moral government of the world.</p>
                <p>The theme or problem of the book is given in chapter i. 2-11. On the assumption
                    that there is <hi rend="italic">no hereafter,</hi> and that the longing soul is
                    to be satisfied with the things <hi rend="italic">here,</hi> Coheleth declares
                    all human efforts to satisfy the longings of the soul to be utterly vain (chap.
                    i. 1, 2), since conscious man is more deplorable than unconscious nature, for he
                    must speedily quit this life, whilst the earth abides for ever (4): the objects
                    of nature depart and retrace their course again, but man disappears and is for
                    ever gone (5-11).</p>
                <p>In corroboration of the allegation in the prologue, and to show the utter failure
                    to satisfy the cravings of the soul with mere temporal pleasures, Coheleth tells
                    us that, with all the resources of a great monarch at his command (chap, i. 12),
                    he applied himself assiduously to discover by the <hi rend="italic">aid of
                        wisdom</hi> the nature of earthly pursuits, and found that they were
                    fruitless (13-14), since they could not alter destinies. Hence, when he
                    reflected upon the large amount of wisdom which he had acquired, he came to the
                    conclusion that it is utterly useless (16-17), for the accumulation of it only
                    increased his sorrow and pain (18). Wisdom having failed, Coheleth resolved to
                    try <hi rend="italic">pleasure,</hi> to see whether it would yield the desired
                    happiness, but he soon found that this too w as vain (chap. ii. 1), and hence
                    denounced it (2). After procuring every imaginable pleasure (3-10) he found that
                    it was utterly insufficient to impart lasting good (11). He then compared wisdom
                    with pleasure, the two experiments he had made (12); and though he saw that the
                    former had a decided advantage over the latter (13, 14α), still he also saw that
                    it does not except its possessor from death and oblivion, but that the wise man
                    and the fool must both die alike and be forgotten (146—16). This melancholy
                    thought made him hate both life and the wealth which he had acquired by wisdom
                    and industry, and which, to aggravate matters, he perchance might leave to a
                    reckless fool (17-21). It convinced him that man has nothing from his toil but w
                    earisome days and sleepless nights (22, 23), and that there is therefore nothing
                    better for man than to enjoy himself (24α). Soon, however, he found that this
                    too is not in the power of man (245, 25). God gives this power to the righteous
                    and withholds it from the wicked, and it is after all only transitory (2).</p>
                <p>Having shown the failure of wisdom, knowledge, and enjoyment to calm the
                    distracted mind which broods over the problem that, whilst the objects of nature
                    depart and retrace their steps, again man vanishes and is for ever forgotten,
                    Coheleth now shows the vain efforts of industry to satisfy the restless longings
                    of the soul. All the events of life are immutably fixed (chap. iii. 1-8); labour
                    is therefore fruitless (9). Even the regulations to human labour which God has
                    prescribed in harmony with this fixed order of things man in his ignorance often
                    mistakes (10, 11). Nothing is therefore left but the enjoyments as one finds
                    them. But this, too, as has already been shown, is a gift of God (12, 13), who
                    has fixed everything to make man feel his utter dependence on and fear the Lord
                    (14, 15). The success of the wicked does not militate against this conclusion,
                    for there is a day fixed for righteous retribution (16, 17). But even if all
                    terminates <hi rend="italic">here,</hi> and man and beast have the same destiny
                    (17-21), this only shows all the more that the enjoyment of life is our only
                    portion <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n646/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0646-0625"/> (22). Such a desperate conclusion, however,
                    makes death preferable to a toilsome life (iv. 1-3),—a life spent in exertions
                    to battle with the pre-ordained order of things, a life expended in labours
                    which either arise from jealousies and fail in their end (4-6), or are prompted
                    by avarice and defeat themselves (9-16). But as God has thus ordained the order
                    of things, we ought to serve him (17-v. 6), trust to his protection under
                    oppression (7, 8), and remember that the rich oppressor has not even the comfort
                    of the poor labourer (9-11), and often bι'.ngs misery upon his children and
                    himself (12-16). This again brings Coheleth to the mournful conclusion that
                    nothing is left but to enjoy the few fleeting years of life, which is a gift of
                    God (17-19).</p>
                <p>Coheleth now shows that neither the much-coveted wealth nor the highly-praised
                    prudence suffices to secure the desired happiness and solve the melancholy
                    problem of life that the same failure attends wealth (vi. 1—9), for the rich man
                    cannot over-rule the order of Providence, nor forecast what will be for his
                    happiness (10-12). The same is the case with the prudential or common sense view
                    of life. Coheleth thought to secure happiness by acquiring and leaving a good
                    name (vi. 1-4), by listening to merited rebuke (5-9), not indulging in a
                    repining spirit. He would also submit to Divine Providence (10-14), be moderate
                    in his religious practices (15-20), not meddle with the opinions of others (21,
                    22), seeing that higher wisdom is unattainable (23, 24), and submit to the
                    oppressive powers that be, convinced that the mightiest tyrant will ultimately
                    be punished (viii. 1-9), for, though righteous retribution is momentarily
                    suspended which causes wickedness to triumph, God will eventually administer
                    justice (10-13). But as he found that the fortunes of the righteous and the
                    wicked <hi rend="italic">are often reversed all their lifetime,</hi> he had to
                    relinquish this common-sense view of life as utterly insufficient to calm the
                    longings of the soul, and recurred to his repeated conclusion that there is
                    nothing left for man but to enjoy the fleeting things of this life (14, 15).</p>
                <p>Before propounding his final conclusion, Coheleth gives a <hi rend="italic"
                        >resume</hi> of his investigations. Since it is impossible to fathom the
                    work of God by wisdom, seeing that even the righteous and wise are subject to
                    this inscrutable Providence just as are the wicked (viii. 16-ix. 2) ;—for all
                    must die alike and be forgotten, and have no more participation in what takes
                    place here (3-6), and we are therefore to indulge in pleasures here, since there
                    is no hereafter (7-10); success does not always attend the strong and the
                    skilful (11, 12); wisdom, though advantageous in many respects, is often
                    despised and defeated by folly (13-x. 3); we are to be patient under sufferings
                    from rulers who by virtue of their power often pervert the order of things
                    (4-7), since opposition may only increase our sufferings (8-11); the exercise of
                    prudence will in the long run be more advantageous than folly (12-20); we are to
                    be charitable, though the recipients of our charity often appear ungrateful,
                    since some of them may after all requite us (xi. 1, 2); we are always to be at
                    work, not allowing ourselves to be deterred by imaginary failures, since we know
                    not which of our efforts may prove successful (3-6), and thus make life as
                    agreeable as we can, since this is the only scene of enjoyment, and the future
                    is all vanity (7, 8);—yet, seeing that even all this does not satisfy the higher
                    craving of the soul, and still leaves conscious man in a more deplorable state
                    than unconscious nature, for the objects of nature depart, retrace their course
                    again, while man disappears and is for ever forgotten—Coheleth at last comes to
                    the conclusion that the enjoyment of this life, combined with a belief in a
                    future judgment, does secure real happiness for man (9, 10). We are therefore to
                    live from our early years in the fear of God and of a final judgment, when the
                    Righteous Judge will rectify all present inequalities (xii. 1-7).</p>
                <p>The wisest and most painstaking Coheleth found by experience that all human
                    efforts to obtain real happiness are vanity of vanities (xii. 8-10), that the
                    sacred writings alone contain the clue to it (11, 12), that there is a Righteous
                    Judge who takes cognizance αf all we do, that He will in the great Day of
                    Judgment try the conduct of us all, and that we are therefore to fear Him and
                    keep His commandments (13, 14).</p>
                <p>From this analysis of its contents it will be seen that the book consists of four
                    parts, with a prologue and epilogue. The prologue and epilogue are distinguished
                    by respectively beginning with the same phrase (i. 1, xii. 8) and ending with
                    two marked sentences (i. 11, xii. 14). The prologue, which consists of chapter
                    i. 1-11, propounds the grand problem of the book; whilst the epilogue, which
                    consists of chapter xii. 8-12, gives the solution proposed by Coheleth. The four
                    sections, which are respectively indicated by the recurrence of the same formula
                    or refrain, viz., ii. 26, V. 19, and viii. 15, give the result of each
                    experiment or group of efforts to satisfy the cravings of the longing soul,
                    apart from the conclusion at which Coheleth arrived.</p>
                <p>Coheleth fills up a gap in the Old Testament lessons. Throughout the Hebrew
                    Scriptures virtue and vice are spoken of as being visibly rewarded on earth. God
                    declares at the very giving of the law that He will show mercy to thousands of
                    those who love Him and keep His commandments, and visit the iniquity of those
                    who hate Him to the third and fourth generation (Exod. xx. 5, 6). The whole of
                    Lev. xxvi. and of Deut, xxviii. are replete with promises of earthly blessings
                    to those who will walk i n the way of the Lord, and threatenings of temporal
                    afflictions upon those who shall transgress His law. The faithful fulfilment of
                    these promises and threatenings in the early stages of the J ewish history
                    convinced every Israelite that “God judgeth the righteous, and God is angry with
                    the wicked <hi rend="italic">every dayf</hi> and afforded a source of
                    consolation to which the righteous resorted when the power of the wicked
                    threatened destruction (1 Sam. xxiv. 13-16, xxvi. 23; Pss. vii., ix., lii.).
                    Like a net of fine threads is this doctrine spread over the entire Old Testament
                    (comp. Pss. xvii. 1, 2; xxvi. 1, 2; xxviii. 1-3; xxxv.; liv. 7-9; Iv. 20-24;
                    xc.; cxii.; cxxv. 3; cxxvii.; cxl.; cxli. 10; Prov. X. 6; xi. 5-8, 19; xii. 7;
                    Hag. ii. 15-20; Zech. i. 2-6; viii. 9-17; Malachi ii. 17). By limiting the bar
                    of judgment to this side of the grave, the Old Testament yielded no explanation
                    of, or succour under, the distracting sight of the righteous suffering <hi
                        rend="italic">all their life,</hi> and then dying for their righteousness,
                    and of the wicked prospering and prolonging their days through their wickedness.
                    It was under such despairing circumstances that Psalms xxxvii., xlix., and
                    lxxiii were written. But these very Psalms endeavour to allay the prevailing
                    scepticism in the moral government of God, by declaring that the righteous shall
                    ultimately prosper and prolong their days <hi rend="italic">upon the earth,</hi>
                    and that the wicked shall suddenly be cut off in great misery. Hence the
                    recurrence of this perplexity passing over into despair when these reassurances
                    and consolations were not realized by experience, and when the sufferers,
                    however conscious of their innocence, were looked upon as rejected of God in
                    consequence of some secret sin. The book of Job, which so successfully combats
                    the latter notion by showing that afflictions are not always a proper test of
                    sin committed, only confirms the old opinion that the righteous are visibly
                    rewarded here, inasmuch as it represents their calamities as transitory, and Job
                    himself as restored to double his original wealth and happiness <hi
                        rend="italic">in this life.</hi></p>
                <p>Under the Persian aud Ptolemeian dominion over Palestine, the political affairs
                    of the Jews -were such as to render the incongruity between the destinies of men
                    and <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n647/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0647-0626"/> their morals still more striking. Hence
                    people began to arraign the character of God.</p>
                <p>“Every one that doeth evil</p>
                <p>Is good in the sight of Jehovah, he delighteth in them,</p>
                <p>Or where is the God of justice ?”—Mai. ii. 17.</p>
                <p>“It is vain to serve God,</p>
                <p>And what profit is it that we keep his ordinance</p>
                <p>And walk mournfully before Jehovah of Hosts? For now we pronounce the proud
                    happy;</p>
                <p>They also that work wickedness are built up;</p>
                <p>They even tempt God, yet they are delivered. ”—Mai. iii. 17, 18.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances, when the inheritance of the Lord, which was to be the
                    praise and the ruler of all the earth, was reduced and degraded to the rank of a
                    mere province; when her inhabitants were groaning under the extortions and
                    tyranny of hirelings; when her seats of justice were filled by the most venial
                    and corrupt men (Eccl. iii. 16); when might became right, and the impunity and
                    success with which wickedness was practised swelled most alarmingly the ranks of
                    the wicked (viii. 10, 11); when the cherished faith in temporal retribution was
                    utterly subverted by the melancholy experience of the reversion of destinies;
                    when the longing minds of the desponding people, released from the terrors of
                    the law, began to import as well as to construct philosophic systems to satisfy
                    their cravings (xii. 12), and to resort to various other experiments to obtain
                    happiness, Coheleth disclosed a new bar of judgment in the world to come. There
                    the Judge of the quick and the dead will rectify all the inequalities which take
                    place here.</p>
                <p>On the Continent, where Biblical criticism has been cultivated to the highest
                    degree, and where Old Testament exegesis has become an exact science, the
                    attempt to prove that Solomon is not the author of Ecclesiastes would be viewed
                    in the same light as adducing facts to demonstrate that the earth does not stand
                    still. In England, however, some scholars of acknowledged repute still adhere to
                    the Solomonic authorship. Their principal argument is that the unanimous voice
                    of tradition declares it to be so. We at once concede the fact. The Jewish
                    synagogue undoubtedly believed that Solomon wrote Canticles when young, Proverbs
                    when in middle life, and Ecclesiastes in his old age <hi rend="italic">(Midrash
                        Yαlkut,</hi> Eccl. i. 1), and the Christian church has simply espoused the
                    Jewish tradition. But with all due deference, we submit that tradition has no
                    authority whatever to determine points of criticism. It is an acknowledged fact
                    that the ancients, both Jews and Christians, and indeed the leaders of thought
                    to the beginning of the 16th century, had not the slightest appreciation of
                    peculiarities of style. The different shades of meaning in which the same
                    expression is used by different authors, the variations in forms, phrases,
                    constructions, and sentences which obtained at diverse periods, and which supply
                    definite data to philologists, and have been reduced to a science in modern
                    days, began only to be noticed at the time of the Reformation, when the vital
                    power of criticism was first applied to traditional dogmas. The spell of
                    tradition once broken, thinking men soon began to recognize the literary style
                    and the respective artistic merits of the component parts of the Bible. Hence
                    Luther already declared, “Solomon did not write the book of Ecclesiastes; it was
                    compiled by Sirach, at the time of the Maccabees It is, like the Talmud, made up
                    of many books, which perhaps belonged to the library of King Ptolemy Euergetes
                    in Egypt.” No impartial student, with even a moderate knowledge of the genius of
                    the Hebrew language, can fail to see the striking difference in the style of the
                    pre-and post-exile books of the Old Testament. In the case of Ecclesiastes the
                    difference is still more unmistakable. Of the vocabulary and phrases in
                    Ecclesiastes a part is to be found in the post-Babylonian biblical writings, and
                    that only in the Chaldee portions , whilst another part has no parallel in the
                    Bible, but is only to be met with in the Mishna, the Talmud, and other post
                    biblical productions. Unless, therefore, it is maintained that the Hebrew of the
                    Bible, which extends over a period of several thousand years, and purports to
                    exhibit the styles of a number of writers who lived in different districts, is
                    unlike any other known literary language, that it had no development and no
                    epochs in its literature, the striking Rabbinic complexion of Ecclesiastes must
                    assuredly stamp it as the latest composition in the Old Testament. Those who
                    know the ultra-orthodoxy of the eminent Hebrew scholar, Professor Delitzsch,
                    will feel the convincing power of this fact when they find that he assigns to
                    Ecclesiastes the latest date of any book in the Hebrew Bible, because it is
                    written in this unquestionably late language. We have abstained from adducing
                    any other arguments derived from its contents, because this appears superfluous.
                    An intelligent reader even in the English translation can see that the
                    representation of Coheleth as indulging in sensual enjoyments and acquiring
                    riches and fame in order to ascertain what is good for the children of men
                    (chap. ii. 3-9; iii. 12, 22, &amp;c.), making philosophical experiments to
                    discover the <hi rend="italic">summum bonum,</hi> is utterly at variance with
                    the conduct of the historical Solomon, and is an idea of a much later period;
                    that the recommendation to individuals not to resent a tyrannical sovereign, but
                    to wait for a general revolt (chap, viii. 2-9), would not proceed from King
                    Solomon; that the complaint about the multiplication of profane literature
                    (chap. xii. 12) could only have been made at a time when the Jews became
                    acquainted with the Greek writings and Alexandrian philosophy. The book,
                    however, is of Palestinian origin, as is evident from the frequent allusion to
                    rain (xi. 3, xii. 2), which does not fall in Egypt; the reference to the Temple
                    and its worship (iv. 7); and the mention of “the city” (viii. 10), though, from
                    the remark ∏∏O3, <hi rend="italic">in the city</hi> (v. 7), it would seem that
                    the writer did not live in Jerusalem itself but in the neighbourhood.</p>
                <p>From the records we possess of the discussions on thθ Hebrew canon we see that at
                    the synod at Jerusalem, <hi rend="italic">circa</hi> 65 A.D., and at a
                    subsequent synod in Yabne, <hi rend="italic">circa</hi> 90 A.D., the question
                    was still an open one whether Ecclesiastes was canonical. The school of Shammai
                    then decided against its canonicity, whilst the school of Hillel passed it as
                    canonical <hi rend="italic">(Mishna Yadaim,</hi> iii. 5, iv. 6; <hi
                        rend="italic">Eduyoth,</hi> v. 3). The reasons assigned for its rejection,
                    as given in the Talmud, are that chap. ii. 2, vii. 3, and viii. 5 contradict
                    each other, and that the book does not exhibit any signs of its being inspired
                        <hi rend="italic">(Sabbath</hi> 30 <hi rend="italic">b, Megilla</hi> 7 «).
                    According to the <hi rend="italic">Midrash Rabba</hi> on Eccl. xi. 9, the advice
                    to enjoy sensual pleasures was considered as contradicting the law of Moses
                    (comp. Eccl. xi. 9 with Numb. xv. 39) and inclining to heresy. The admonition,
                    however, to fear God and the doctrine of a future judgment were urged in its
                    favour and ultimately prevailed. The sages showed that the contradictions were
                    apparent only, and the book was declared canonical <hi rend="italic">(Aboth d’
                        R. Nathan,</hi> cap. i.). Hence it passed over into the Christian church as
                    a part of the canon.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> The most important commentaries on
                    Ecclesiastes which furnish the best materials for forming an in&lt;lependent
                    opinion on this avowedly difficult bookare—Knobel, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Commentar</hi><hi rend="italic">überdas Buch</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Koheleth,</hi> Leipzig, 1836; Ewald, <hi rend="italic">Q6hilet,</hi> in <hi
                        rend="italic">Oie Dichter des Alten Bundes,</hi> 2d ed. vol. ii. 267,
                    &amp;c., Göttingen, 1867; Hitzig, <hi rend="italic">Der Prediger Salomo im
                        Kurzgefassten exegetischen Handbuch zum alten Testament,</hi> vol. vii.,
                    Leipzig, 1877; Stuart, <hi rend="italic">A Commentary on Ecclesiastes,</hi> New
                    York, 1851; Elster, <hi rend="italic">Commentar</hi><hi rend="italic">über den
                        Prediger,</hi> Gottingen, 1855; Graetz, <hi rend="italic">Koheleth,</hi>
                    Leipzig, 1871; Delitzsch, <hi rend="italic">Hohcslied</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >und</hi><hi rend="italic">Koheleth,</hi> Leipzig, 1875. The last two give
                    complete vocabularies of the post-Babylonian diction of the book. For the
                    history of the interpretation see Ginsburg, <hi rend="italic">Coheleth, commonly
                        called the Book of Ecclesiastes,</hi> London, 1861. (C. D. G.) <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n648/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0648-0627"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
