<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0907-0848-0825-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELBE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 7, page 825</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1043442">Ocean</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6bb1s">Tolls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q80j">Ocean</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n848/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELBE</label>, the Albis of the Romans and the Labe of the
                    Bohemians, a large river of Germany, with a total length of 705 miles, and a
                    drainage area of about 55,000 square miles. It rises in Bohemia not far from the
                    frontiers of Silesia, on the southern side of the Riesengebirge or Giants’
                    Mountains, in 50° 46' N. lat. and 15° 32' E. long. Of the numerous small streams
                    (Seifen or Flessen, as they are named in the district) whose confluent waters
                    compose the infant river, the most important are the Weisswasser, or White
                    Water, and the Elbseifen; the former rises to the S.W. of the Schneekuppe in the
                    White Meadow, and the latter in a stone fountain in the Elb Meadow. Augmented
                    successively by the Adler, the Iser, the Moldau, and the Eger, it cuts its way
                    through the Mittelgebirge of Bohemia, traverses the sandstone mountains of Saxon
                    Switzerland, and with a general N.W. direction continues to meander through
                    Saxony, Anhalt, and Hanover, until at length it falls into the German Ocean
                    about 53° 5' N. lat. and 8° 50' E. long. The principal towns on its banks are
                    Leitmeritz, Pirna, Dresden, Meissen, Torgau, Wittenberg, Magdeburg, Wittenberge,
                    Harburg, Hamburg, and Altona. A short distance above Hamburg the stream divides
                    into a number of branches, but they all reunite before reaching the ocean. At
                    its source the Elbe is about 4600 feet above the level of the sea; after the
                    first 40 miles of its course it is still 658 feet; but at Dresden it is only
                    279, and at Arneburg in Brandenburg only 176. At Königgratz the width is about
                    100 feet, at the mouth of the Moldau about 300, at Dresden 960, and at Magdeburg
                    over 1000. The tide is perceptible as far up as Geesthacht. Of the fifty and
                    more tributaries belonging to the system the most important are the Moldau, the
                    Eger, the Mulde, and the Saale,—the Moldau having a course of 267 miles, the
                    Eger of 235, the Mulde of 185, and the Saale of 220. Though the channel in some
                    places, and especially in the estuary, is encumbered with sandbanks and
                    shallows, the Elbe is of great importance as a means of communication,
                    steamboats being able to ascend the main stream as far as Melnick, and to reach
                    Prague by means of the Moldau. Some idea of the extent of its traffic may be
                    obtained from the statement that in 1870 at Schandau 489 passenger-steamers and
                    2658 vessels and barges of various kinds passed up the stream, and 489 passenger
                    steamers, 2865 ships, and 1505 rafts down the stream. By one line of canal it
                    communicates with Lübeck, by another with Bremen, and by others with the great
                    network of Mecklenburg and Brandenburg; and several new lines are projected, by
                    which a direct way will be opened up to Hanover, Leipsic, and various other
                    important cities.—For details see Dr Th. H. Schunke’s “Die Schifffahrts-Kanäle
                    im Deutschen Reiche,” in Petermann’s <hi rend="italic">Mittheil.,</hi> 1877.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n849/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0907-0849-0826"/>
                <p>Formerly 3 entrepots (Pirna, Dresden, and Magdeburg), 35 tolls, and numerous
                    corporations of privileged watermen, opposed almost insurmountable obstacles to
                    the navigation; the Austrians and the Saxons alone could navigate the Upper
                    Elbe, that is, from Magdeburg to where it ceases to be navigable, and the
                    Prussians and Hamburgers had the sole privilege of navigating the Lower Elbe.
                    But new regulations were introduced by a convention concluded on the 13th June
                    1821 between all the bordering states, viz., Austria, Saxony, Prussia, Hanover,
                    Denmark (for Holstein and Lauenburg), the grand duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin,
                    and the three principalities of Anhalt. Every merchant, to whatever bordering
                    state he might belong, was allowed with his own vessel and crew to navigate the
                    whole course of the river without interruption; the 35 tolls were reduced to 14;
                    the heavy dues which were levied upon goods of the first necessity were reduced
                    to one for the cargo <hi rend="italic">{Elbe Toll)</hi> and another for the ship
                    <hi rend="italic">{Recogni∙ tionsgebiihren)</hi>; and each state was bound to
                    watch over the portion of river which passed through their territories, and to
                    preserve it from everything injurious to commerce or navigation. It was also
                    arranged that a commission should meet from time to time for the revision of the
                    tariff, &amp;c., and the investigation of all matters connected with the
                    utilization of the river. By the second of these commissions, which met at
                    Dresden in 1842, an additional Navigation Act was published in 1844; in the
                    third, at Magdeburg in 1850, it was proposed by Austria to remove the Elbe tolls
                    altogether, but Hanover and some other states refused; in the fourth, at
                    Hamburg, 1858, the same objections still carried the day; but in 1861 the fifth
                    commission decided that only one common toll for all the riparian states should
                    be left at Wittenberge; and after numerous difficulties, the federative council
                    of the German empire succeeded in securing the complete freedom of the river in
                    1870. A compensation of 1,000,000 thalers was granted to Mecklenburg-Schwerin,
                    and of 85,000 to Anhalt.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
