<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0907-0648-0627-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ECCLESIASTICAL LAW (9th edition, volume 7, page
                    627)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vf0v">Jaws</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n648/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ECCLESIASTICAL LAW</label> generally means the law of the
                    church, in countries where an established religion is recognized by the state,
                    but in a more general sense it would include the whole body of the law relating
                    to religion. It is in this sense that the phrase is used by American lawyers,
                    and it is only in this sense that it can be used of Ireland since the
                    disestablishment of the state church in that country. The relation of the
                    ecclesiastical law to the rest of the law, especially in respect of legislation
                    and judicature, is one of the most important points in the constitution of a
                    country. Where the Roman Catholic religion is recognized by the state the
                    jurisprudence of the canon law prevails, but the relations between the Papal See
                    and the state are governed by special conventions, or concordats. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Canon Law.</hi></p>
                <p>The ecclesiastical law of England is remarkable for its complete dependence upon
                    the authority of the state. The Church of England cannot be said to have a
                    corporate existence nor even a representative assembly. The Convocation of York
                    and the Convocation of Canterbury are provincial assemblies possessing no
                    legislative or judicial authority. The ecclesiastical judicatories are for the
                    most part officered by laymen, and the last court of appeal is the Judicial
                    Committee of the Privy Council. In like manner changes in the ecclesiastical law
                    are made directly by Parliament in the ordinary course of legislation, and in
                    point of fact a very large portion of the existing ecclesiastical law consists
                    of Acts of Parliament.</p>
                <p>The sources of the ecclesiastical law of England are thus described by the
                    leading text-writer on this subject:<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical Law,</hi> by
                            Richard Burn, LL.D.</p></note> — “The ecclesiastical law of England is
                    compounded of these four main ingredients—the civil law, the canon law, the
                    common law, and the statute law. And from these, digested in their proper rank
                    and subordination, to draw out one uniform law of the church is the purport of
                    this book. When these laws do interfere and cross each other, the order of
                    preference is this :—‘ The civil law submitteth to the canon law; both of these
                    to the common law; and all three to the statute law. So that from any one or
                    more of these, without all of them together, or from all of them together
                    without attending to their comparative obligation, it is not possible to exhibit
                    any distinct prospect of the English ecclesiastical constitution.’ Under the
                    head of <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit07newyrich/page/n649/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0907-0649-0628"/> statute law Burn includes ‘ the Thirty-nine
                    Articles of Religion, agreed upon in Convocation in the year 1562; and in like
                    manner the Rubric of the Book of Common Prayer, which, being both of them
                    established by Acts of Parliament, are to be esteemed as part of the statute
                    law.’”</p>
                <p>The first principle of the ecclesiastical law is the assertion of the supremacy
                    of the crown, -which in the present state of the constitution means the same
                    thing as the supremacy of Parliament. This principle has been maintained ever
                    since the Reformation. Before the Reformation the ecclesiastical supremacy of
                    the Pope was recognized, with certain limitations, in England, and the church
                    itself had some pretensions to ecclesiastical freedom. The freedom of the church
                    is, in fact, one of the standing provisions of those charters on which the
                    English constitution was based. The first provision of Magna Charta is <hi
                        rend="italic">quod</hi><hi rend="italic">ecclesia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Anglicana libera sit.</hi> By the various enactments of the period of the
                    Reformation the whole constitutional position of the church, not merely with
                    reference to the Pope but with reference to the state, was definitely fixed. The
                    legislative power of Convocation was held to extend to the clergy only, and even
                    to that extent required the sanction and assent of the Crown. The common law
                    courts controlled the jurisdiction of the ecclesiastical courts, claiming to
                    have “the exposition of such statutes or Acts of Parliament as concern either
                    the extent of the jurisdiction of these courts or the matters depending before
                    them. And therefore if these courts either refuse to allow these Acts of
                    Parliament, or expound them in any other sense than is truly and properly the
                    exposition of them, the king’s great courts of common law may prohibit and
                    control them.”</p>
                <p>The design of constructing a code of ecclesiastical laws was entertained during
                    the period of the Reformation, but never carried into effect. It is alluded to
                    in various statutes of the reign of Henry VIII., who obtained power to appoint a
                    commission to examine the old ecclesiastical laws, with a view of deciding which
                    ought to be kept and which ought to be abolished; and in the meantime it was
                    enacted that “such canons, institutions, ordinances, synodal or provincial or
                    other ecclesiastical laws or jurisdictions spiritual as be yet accustomed and
                    used here in the Church of England, which necessarily and conveniently are
                    requisite to be put in ure and execution for the time, not being repugnant,
                    contrarient, or derogatory to the laws or statutes of the realm, nor to the
                    prerogatives of the royal crown of the same, or any of them, shall be occupied,
                    exercised, and put in ure for the time within this realm” (35 Henry VIII. c. 16,
                    25 c. 19, 27 c. 8).</p>
                <p>The work was actually undertaken and finished iiι the reign of Edward VI. by a
                    sub-committee of eight persons, under the name of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Reformatio</hi><hi rend="italic">Legum Ecclesiasticarum,</hi> which,
                    however, never obtained the royal assent. Although the powers of the 25 Henry
                    VIII. c. 1, were revived by the 1 Elizabeth c. 1, the scheme was never executed,
                    and the ecclesiastical laws remained on the footing assigned to them in that
                    statute,—so much of the old ecclesiastical laws might be used as had been
                    actually in use and was not repugnant to the laws of the realm.</p>
                <p>The statement is, indeed, made by Sir R. Phillimore that the “Church of England
                    has at all times, before and since the Reformation, claimed the right of an
                    independent church in an independent kingdom, to be governed by the Jaws which
                    she has deemed it expedient to adopt.” This position can only be accepted if it
                    is confined, as the authorities cited for it are confined, to the resistance of
                    interference from abroad. If it mean that the church, as distinguished from the
                    kingdom, has claimed to be governed by laws of her own making, all that can be
                    said is that the claim has been singularly unsuccessful. From the time of the
                    Reformation no change has been made in the law of the church which has not been
                    made by the king and parliament, sometimes indirectly, as by confirming the
                    resolutions of Convocation, but for the most part by statute. The list of
                    statutes cited in Sir R. Phillimore’s <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Law</hi>
                    fills eleven pages. It is only by a kind of legal fiction that the church can be
                    said to have deemed it expedient to adopt these laws.</p>
                <p>The terms on which the Church Establishment of Ireland was abolished by 32 and 33
                    Vict. c. 42 may be mentioned. By sect. 20 the present ecclesiastical law is made
                    binding on the members for the time being of the church, “as if they had
                    mutually contracted and agreed to abide by and observe the same;” and by section
                    21 it is enacted that the ecclesiastical courts shall cease after 1st January
                    1871, and that the ecclesiastical laws of Ireland, except so far as relates to
                    matrimonial causes and matters, shall cease to exist as law. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(e. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
