<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-9739-0149-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ICHTHYOCOLLA, Isinglass (7th edition, volume 12, page
                    149)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1ds31">Isinglass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39097">Glue</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979763">Isinglass</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:943716">Glue</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192939739?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ICHTHYOCOLLA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Isinglass</hi></label>, a
                    preparation from the fish known by the name of <hi rend="italic">huso.</hi> The
                    word is Greek, formed of 7χSυj, <hi rend="italic">fish,</hi> and %oλλα, <hi
                    rend="italic">glue.</hi> The method of making isinglass was long a secret in the
                    hands of the Russians. The following account of it was published by Mr Humphrey
                    Jackson, in the 63d volume of the Philosophical Transactions.</p>
                <p>“All authors who have hitherto delivered processes for making ichthyocolla,
                    fish-glue, or isinglass, have greatly mistaken both its constituent matter and
                    preparation. To prove this assertion, it may not be improper to recite what
                    Pomet says upon the subject, as he appears to be the principal author, whom the
                    rest have copied. After describing the fish, and referring to a cut engraved
                    from an original in his custody, he says, ‘ As to the manner of making the
                    isinglass, the sinewy parts of the fish are boiled in water till all of them be
                    dissolved that will dissolve; then the gluey liquor is strained, and set to
                    cool. Being cold, the fat is carefully taken off, and the liquor itself boiled
                    to a just consistency, then cut to pieces and made into a twist, bent in form of
                    a crescent as commonly sold; then hung upon a string and carefully dried.’</p>
                <p>“From this account, it might be rationally concluded that every species of fish
                    which contained gelatinous principles would yield isinglass; and this parity of
                    reasoning seems to have given rise to the hasty conclusions of those who
                    strenuously vouch for the extraction of isinglass from sturgeon; but as that
                    fish is easily procurable, the negligence of ascertaining the fact by experiment
                    seems inexcusable.</p>
                <p>“In my first attempt to discover the constituent parts and manufacture of
                    isinglass, relying too much upon the authority of some chemical authors whose
                    veracity I had experienced in many other instances, I found myself constantly
                    disappointed. Glue, not isinglass, was the result of every process; and
                    although, in the same view, a journey to Russia proved fruitless, yet a steady
                    perseverance in the research proved not only successful as to this object, but
                    in the pursuit to discover a resinous matter plentifully procurable in the
                    British fisheries, which has been found by ample experience to answer similar
                    purposes. It is now no longer a secret that the lakes and rivers in North
                    America are stocked with immense quantities of fish, said to be the same species
                    with those in Muscovy, and yielding the finest isinglass; the fisheries whereof,
                    under due encouragement, would doubtless supply all Europe with this valuable
                    article.</p>
                <p>“No artificial heat is necessary to the production of isinglass, neither is the
                    matter dissolved for this purpose; for, as the continuity of its fibres would be
                    destroyed by solution, the mass would become brittle in drying, and snap short
                    asunder, which is always the case with glue, but never with isinglass. The
                    latter, indeed, may be resolved into glue with boiling water; but its fibrous
                    recomposition would be found impractlcable afterwards, and a fibrous texture is
                    one <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the most distinguishing characteristics of genuine
                    isinglass.</p>
                <p>“A due consideration that an imperfect solution of isinglass, called <hi
                    rend="italic">fining</hi> by the brewers, possessed a peculiar property of
                    clarifying malt liquors, induced me to attempt its analysis in cold subacid
                    menstruums. One ounce and a half of good isinglass, steeped a few days in a
                    gallon of stale beer, was converted into good fining, of a remarkable thick
                    consistence; the same quantity of glue, under similar treatment, yielded only a
                    mucilaginous liquor, resembling diluted gum-water, which, instead of clarifying
                    beer, increased both its tenacity and turbidness, and communicated other
                    properties in no respect corresponding with those of genuine fining. On
                    commixing three spoonfuls of the solution of isinglass with a gallon of malt
                    liquor, in a tall cylindrical glass, a vast number of curdly masses became
                    presently formed, by the reciprocal attraction of the particles of isinglass and
                    the feculen-cieş of the beer, which increasing in magnitude and specific
                    gravity, arranged themselves accordingly, and fell in a combined state to the
                    bottom, through the well-known laws of gravitation; for in this case there is no
                    elective attraction, as some have imagined, which bears the least affinity with
                    what frequently occurs in chemical decompositions.</p>
                <p>“If what is commercially termed <hi rend="italic">long</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >short stapled isinglass</hi> be steeped a few hours in fair cold water, the
                    untwisted membranes will expand, and re-assume their original beautiful
                    hue,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>If the transparent
                    isinglass be held in certain positions to the light, it frequently exhibits
                    beautiful prismatic colours.</p></note> and, by a dexterous address, may be
                    perfectly unfolded. By this simple operation we find that isinglass is nothing
                    more than certain membranous parts of fishes, divested of their native mucosity,
                    rolled and twisted into the forms above mentioned, and dried in open air.</p>
                <p>“The sounds or air-bladders of fresh-water fish in general are preferred for this
                    purpose, as being the most transparent, flexible, delicate substances. These
                    constitute the finest sorts of isinglass; those called <hi rend="italic"
                    >booh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ordinary staple</hi> are made of the
                    intestines, and probably of the peritoneum of the fish. The belluga yields the
                    greatest quantity, as being the largest and most plentiful fish in the Muscovy
                    rivers; but the sounds of all fresh-water fish yield, more or less, fine
                    isinglass, particularly the smaller sorts, found in prodigious quantities in the
                    Caspian Sea, and several hundred miles beyond Astracan, in the Wolga, Yaik, Don,
                    and even as far as Siberia, where it is called <hi rend="italic">hle</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">kla</hi> by the natives, which implies a glutinous matter; it is
                    the basis of the Russian glue, which is preferred to all other kinds for its
                    strength.</p>
                <p>“The sounds, which yield the finer isinglass, consist of parallel fibres, and are
                    easily rent longitudinally; but the ordinary sorts are found composed of double
                    membranes, whose fibres cross each other obliquely, resembling the coats of a
                    bladder; hence the former are more readily pervaded and divided with subacid
                    liquors; but the latter, through a peculiar kind of interwoven texture, are with
                    great difficulty torn asunder, and long resist the power of the same menstruum;
                    yet, when duly resolved, are found to act with equal energy in clarifying
                    liquors.</p>
                <p>“Isinglass receives its different shapes in the following manner: The parts of
                    which it is composed, particularly the sound, are taken from the fish while
                    sweet and fresh, slit open, washed from their slimy <hi rend="italic"
                    >sordes,</hi> divested of every thin membrane which envelopes the sound, and
                    then exposed to stiffen a little in the air. In this state they are formed into
                    rolls about the thickness of a finger, and in length according to the intended
                    size of the staple. A thin membrane is generally selected for the centre of the
                    roll, round which the rest are folded alternately; and about half an inch of
                    each extremity of the roll is turned inwards. The due dimensions being thus
                    obtained, the two ends of what is called <hi rend="italic">short staple</hi> are
                    pinned together with a small wooden peg; the middle of the roll is then pressed
                    a little downwards, which gives it the resemblance of a heart-shape; and thus it
                    is laid on boards, or hung up in the air to dry. The sounds which compose the
                    long <pb break="no" facs="nls:192939752?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-9752-0150"/> staple are longer than the former; but the
                    operator lengthens this sort at pleasure, by interfolđing the ends of one or
                    more pieces of the sound with each other. The extremities are fastened with a
                    peg, like the former; but the middle part of the roll is bent more considerably
                    downwards, and, in order to preserve the shape of the three obtuse angles thus
                    formed, a piece of round stick, about a quarter of an inch diameter, is fastened
                    in each angle with small wooden pegs, in the same manner as the ends. In this
                    state it is permitted to dry long enough to retain its form, when the pegs and
                    sticks are taken out, and the drying completed; lastly, the pieces of isinglass
                    are colligated in rows, by running pack-thread through the peg-holes, for
                    convenience of package and exportation.</p>
                <p>“The membranes of the <hi rend="italic">book</hi> sort, being thick and
                    refractory, will not admit a similar formation with the preceding; the pieces,
                    therefore, after their sides are folded inwardly, are bent in the centre, in
                    such manner that the opposite sides resemble the cover of a book, from whence
                    its name; a peg being run across the middle, fastens the sides together, and
                    thus it is dried like the former. This sort is interleaved, and the pegs run
                    across the ends, the better to prevent its unfolding.</p>
                <p>“That called <hi rend="italic">cake∙isinglass</hi> is formed of the bits and
                    fragments of the staple sorts, put into a flat metalline pan, with a very little
                    water, and heated just enough to make the parts cohere like a pancake when it is
                    dried; but frequently it is overheated, and such pieces, as before observed, are
                    useless in the business of fining. Experience has taught the consumers to reject
                    them.</p>
                <p>“Isinglass is best made in the summer, as frost gives it a disagreeable colour,
                    deprives it of weight, and impairs its gelatinous principles; its fashionable
                    forms are unnecessary, and frequently injurious to its native qualities. It is
                    common to find oily putrid matter, and <hi rend="italic">exuvicε</hi> of
                    insects, between the implicated membranes, which, through the inattention of the
                    cellarman, often contaminate wines and malt liquors in the act of clarification.
                    These peculiar shapes might probably be introduced originally with a view to
                    conceal and disguise the real substance of isinglass and preserve the monopoly;
                    but, as the mask is now taken off, it cannot be doubted to answer every purpose
                    more effectually in its native state, without any subsequent manufacture
                    whatever, especially to the principal consumers, who hence will be enabled to
                    procure sufficient supply from the British colonies. Until this laudable end can
                    be fully accomplished, and as a species of isinglass more easily produceable
                    from the marine fisheries may probably be more immediately encouraged, it maybe
                    manufactured as follows:</p>
                <p>“The sounds of cod and ling bear great analogy with those of the <hi
                    rend="italic">accipenser</hi> genus ot Linnaeus and Artedi, and are in general
                    so well known as to require no particular description. The Newfoundland and
                    Iceland fishermen split open the fish as soon as taken, and throw the backbones
                    with the sounds annexed in a heap; but previous to incipient putrefaction, the
                    sounds are cut out, washed from their slimes, and salted for use. In cutting out
                    the sounds, the intercostal parts are left behind, which are much the best; the
                    Iceland fishermen are so sensible of this, that they beat the bone upon a block
                    with a thick stick, till the pockets, as they term them, come out easily, and
                    thus preserve the sound entire. If the sounds have been cured with salt, that
                    must be dissolved by steeping them in water before they are prepared for
                    isinglass; the fresh sound must then be laid upon a block of wood, whose surface
                    is a little elliptical, to the end of which a small hair-brush is nailed, and
                    with a saw-knife the membranes on each side of the sound must be scraped off.
                    The knife is rubbed upon the brush occasionally, to clear its teeth; the pockets
                    are cut open with scissars, and perfectly cleansed of the mucous matter with a
                    coarse cloth; the sounds are afterwards washed a few minutes in lime-water, in
                    order to absorb their oily principle, and lastly in clear water. They are then
                    laid upon nets to dry in the air; but if intended to resemble the foreign
                    isinglass, the sounds of cod will only admit of that called <hi rend="italic"
                    >book,</hi> but those of ling both shapes. The thicker the sounds are, the
                    better the isinglass, colour excepted; but this is immaterial to the brewer, who
                    is its chief consumer.</p>
                <p>“This isinglass resolves into fining, like the other sorts, in subacid liquors,
                    as stale beer, cider, old hock, and the like, and in equal quantities produces
                    similar effects upon turbid liquors, except that it falls speedier and closer to
                    the bottom of the vessel, as may be demonstrated in tall cylindrical glasses;
                    but foreign isinglass retains the consistency of fining preferably in warm
                    weather, owing to the greater tenacity of its native mucilage. “Vegetable acids
                    are in every respect best adapted to fining; the mineral acids are too
                    corrosive, and even insalubrious, in common beverage.</p>
                <p>“It is remarkable, that during the conversion of isinglass into fining, the
                    acidity of the menstruum seems greatly diminished, at least to taste, not on
                    account of any alkaline property in the isinglass, probably, but by its
                    enveloping the acid particles. It is likewise reduced into jelly with alkaline
                    liquors, which indeed are solvents of all animal matters; even cold lime-water
                    dissolves it into a pulpous <hi rend="italic">magma.</hi> Notwithstanding this
                    is inadmissible as fining, on account of the menstruum, it produces admirable
                    effects in other respects; for, on commixture with compositions of plaster,
                    lime, &amp;c. for ornamenting walls exposed to vicissitudes of weather, it adds
                    firmness and permanency to the cement; and if common brick-mortar be worked up
                    with this jelly, it soon becomes almost as hard as the brick itself; but for
                    this purpose it is more commodiously prepared by dissolving it in cold water
                    acidulated with vitriolic acid, in which case the acid quits the jelly, and
                    forms with the lime a <hi rend="italic">selenitic</hi> mass, while, at the same
                    time, the jelly being deprived in some measure of its moisture, through the
                    formation <hi rend="italic">of</hi> an indissoluble concrete amongst its parts,
                    soon dries, and hardens into a firm body; whence its superior strength and
                    durability are easily comprehended.</p>
                <p>“It has long been a prevalent opinion, that sturgeon, on account of its
                    cartilaginous nature, would yield great quantities of isinglass; but, on
                    examination, no part of this fish, except tlιe inner coat of the sound, promised
                    the least success. This being full of <hi rend="italic">rugae,</hi> adheres so
                    firmly to the external membrane, which is useless, that the labour of separating
                    them supersedes the advantage. The intestines, however, which in the larger fish
                    extend several yards in length, being cleansed from their mucus and dried, were
                    found surprisingly strong and elastic, resembling cords made with the intestines
                    of other animals, commonly called <hi rend="italic">catgut,</hi> and, from some
                    trials, promised superior advantages whcruapplied to mechanic operations.’’</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:192939765?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-9765-0151"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
