<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-1377-0275-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INGRATITUDE (7th edition, volume 12, page 275)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192941377?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INGRATITUDE</label>, the opposite of gratitude. Ingratitude
                    is a crime so shameful, that there never was a man found who would own himself
                    guilty of it; and, though too frequently practised, it is so abhorred by the
                    general voice, that to be ungratefuΓis to be liable to the imputation of the
                    guilt or the capability of committing all other crimes.</p>
                <p>In a little work entitled <hi rend="italic">Friendly Cautions to Officers,</hi>
                    the following atrocious instance of ingratitude is related. An opulent city in
                    the west of England, little used to have troops with them, had a regiment sent
                    to be quartered there; and the principal inhabitants and wealthiest merchants,
                    glad to shew their hospitality and attachment to their sovereign, took the first
                    opportunity to get acquainted with the officers, inviting them to their houses,
                    and shewing them every civility in their power. This was truly a desirable
                    situation. A merchant, extremely easy in his circumstances, took so prodigious a
                    liking to one officer in particular, that he gave him an apartment in his own
                    house, and made him in a manner absolute master of it, the officer’s friends
                    being always welcome to his table. The merchant was a widower, and had only two
                    favourite daughters; the officer, in so comfortable à station, cast his wanton
                    eyes upon them; and too fatally succeeding, ruined both. The consequence of this
                    ungenerous action was, that all officers were ever afterwards shunned as a
                    public nuisance, and a pest to society; nor have the inhabitants perhaps yet
                    conquered their aversion to a red-coat.</p>
                <p>We are informed by Rapin, that during Monmouth’s rebellion, in the reign of James
                    II. a certain person knowing the humane disposition of one Mrs Gaunt, whose life
                    had been one continued exercise of beneficence, fled to her house, where he was
                    concealed and maintained for some time. Hearing, however, of the proclamation,
                    which promised an indemnity and reward to those who discovered such as harboured
                    the rebels, he betrayed his benefactress; and such was the spirit of justice and
                    equity which prevailed amongst the ministers, that he was pardoned and
                    recompensed for his treachery, whilst she was burned alive for her charity.</p>
                <p>The following instance is also mentioned by the same author. Humphry Bannister
                    and his father were both servants to and raised by the Duke of Buckingham, who
                    being driven to abscond, by an unfortunate accident befalling the army he had
                    raised against the usurper Richard HL, retired, without footman or page, to
                    Bannister’s house near Shrewsbury, as to a place where he had all the reason in
                    the world to expect security. Bannister, however, upon the king’s proclamation,
                    promising L. 1000 reward to him who shoιfld apprehend the duke, betrayed his
                    master to John Merton, high sheriff of Shropshire, who sent him under a strong
                    guard to Salisbury, where the king then was, and there in the market-place the
                    duke was beheaded. But divine vengeance pursued the traitor Bannister; for
                    demanding the L. 1000 which was the price of his master’s blood, King Richard
                    refused to pay it, saying, that “he who would be false to so good a master,
                    ought not to be encouraged.” He was afterwards hanged for manslaughter, his
                    eldest son run mad and died in a hog-sty, his second became deformed and lame,
                    and his third son was drowned in a small puddle of water. His eldest daugh <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:192941390?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-1390-0276"/> ter
                    was seduced by one of his own carters, and his second was seized with a leprosy
                    of which she died.</p>
                <p>The following barbarous instances are from ancient History. Wlιen Xerxes king of
                    Persia was at Celcne, a city of Phrygia, Pythius, a Lydian, who had his
                    residence in that city, and next to Xerxes was the most opulent prince of those
                    times, entertained him and his whole army with an incredible magnificence, and
                    made him an offer of all his wealth towards defraying the expenses of his
                    expedition. Xerxes, surprised ancĩ charmed at so generous an offer, had the
                    curiosity to inquire to what sum his riches amounted. Pythius made answer, that
                    having the design of offering them to his service, he had taken an exact account
                    of them, and that the silver he had by him amounted to two thousand talents
                    (about L. 255,000 Sterling), and the gold to four millions of darics (about L.
                    1,700,000 Sterling). All this money he offered him, telling him that his revenue
                    was sufficient for the support of his household. Xerxes made him very hearty
                    acknowledgments, and formed a particular friendship for him, but declined
                    accepting his present. The same prince who had made such obliging offers to
                    Xerxes, having desired a favour of him some time afterwards, that out of his
                    five sons who served in his army, he would be pleased to leave him the eldest,
                    in order to be a comfort to him in his old age, the king was so enraged at the
                    proposal, though so reasonable in itself, that he caused the eldest son to be
                    killed before the eyes of his father, giving the latter to understand, that it
                    was a favour he spared him and the rest of his children. Yet this is the same
                    Xerxes who is so much admired for his humane reflection at the head of his
                    numerous army, “that of so many thousand men, in a hundred years time there
                    would not be one remaining; on which account he could not forbear weeping at the
                    uncertainty and instability of human things.” He might have found another
                    subject of reflection, which would have more justly merited his tears and
                    affliction, had he turned his thoughts upon himself, and considered the
                    reproaches he deserved for being the instrument of hastening the fatal term to
                    millions of people, whom his cruel ambition was going to sacrifice in an unjust
                    and unnecessary war.</p>
                <p>Basilius Macedo the Emperor, exercising himself in hunting, a sport he took great
                    delight in, a great stag running furiously against him, fastened one of the
                    branches of his horns in the emperor’s girdle, and pulling him from his horse,
                    dragged him a good distance, to the imminent danger of his life; which a
                    gentleman of his retinue perceiving, drew his sword and cut the emperor’s girdle
                    asunder, which disengaged him from the beast, with little or no hurt to his
                    person. But observe what reward he had for his pains. “He was sentenced to lose
                    his head for putting his sword so near the body of the emperor and suffered
                    death accordingly.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
