<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0993-0953-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=993" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XATIVA</label>, a government of Spain, in the kingdom of
                    Valencia, extending from the river Alcia to the shores of the Mediterranean Sea.
                    It is now more commonly called St Felipe, its ancient name having been changed
                    by law since the expulsion of the Moors. The capital of the partido of the same
                    name was founded by the Romans, and called by them Setabis. It is situated on
                    the declivity of a calcareous mountain, overlooking a plain not very fruitful,
                    though watered by the river Albayda, one of the tributary streams of the Xucar.
                    The city is surrounded with ancient walls, partly of Roman and partly of Moorish
                    construction, on which are thirty towers. It has also double ditches, and a
                    strong citadel; but all have alike fallen into decay. It is supplied with water
                    by two ancient aqueducts. Before the recent changes, this city contained four
                    parish churches, thirteen monasteries, nine chapels, and eight poor-houses or
                    hospitals. The inhabitants are estimated at 14,000 souls, some of whom are
                    employed in making linen and silk goods, and some writing paper. Near to it are
                    twenty-two warm medicinal springs of various curative power. This place gave
                    birth to a celebrated painter named Ribero, but better known by the assumed name
                    of Spannoletto.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
