<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0994-0954-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jj0k">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n873131">Carthusians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017057">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=994" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XERES <hi rend="smallcaps">de la Frontera</hi></label>, so
                    called to distinguish it from a small town of the same name near Antequera. It
                    is the capital of a district of the province of Andalusia, in Spain, about ten
                    miles from the sea-shore at Puerto Santa Maria. The early history of this place
                    is obscure, and the origin of its name a very disputable matter with Spanish
                    antiquaries. It was known to the Romans as Acta Regia in the time of Pliny, but
                    only the name is given. It is chiefly remarkable in history as the place where
                    the great battle between the Moors and the Goths was fought in 714, by which,
                    after a contest of eight days, the former were <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=995" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0995-0955"
                    />conquerors of the whole of the peninsula. The river Guadalette, on whose banks
                    the decisive action took place, is a small stream, about a mile and a half from
                    the city, which at some seasons of the year is nearly dry. It has a stone
                    bridge, about four miles below which are a wharf and storehouses, from which
                    wine and other goods are shipped for Port St Mary’s.</p>
                <p>Xeres is situated in the lap of two rounded hillocks, which shelter it to the
                    east and the west; and it covers a considerable extent of ground. The city,
                    properly so called, is embraced by an old crenated Moorish wall, which, though
                    enclosing a labyrinth of narrow, ill-built, and worse drained streets, is of no
                    great circuit, and is so intermixed with the suburbs as to be visible only here
                    and there. The limits of the old town are however well defined by the numerous
                    antique gateways. Some of the buildings are of a unique kind of architecture. It
                    once had ten churches, eleven chapels, four hospitals, twenty-one monasteries
                    and convents. It is doubtful how many of these institutions yet survive the
                    convulsions to which Spain has been subjected for the last quarter of a century.
                    The population is dense, being estimated at 50,000 souls; but the amount is
                    subject to great variations, dependent on the recent or remote occurrence of the
                    last endemic fever generated in its pestiferous gutters and its uncleanly
                    streets and lanes.</p>
                <p>The environs of this city afford abundant supplies of corn, especially wheat, of
                    oil, and of cattle. It was long celebrated for its breed of horses, reared by a
                    well-endowed convent of Carthusian monks, now robbed and nearly deserted; but
                    the chief produce is the white wine so generally known by the name of Sherry.
                    This wine is collected by the merchants of the city from the neighbouring
                    vineyards; but some of them are also wine-growers. The quantity annually
                    produced is about 30,000 butts, of 120 gallons each. Of these, rather more than
                    two thirds are sent to England. The remainder is consumed at home, or sent to
                    the United States of America, to the Havannah, to Mexico, or Buenos Ayres. There
                    are not less than twenty-five great mercantile houses, chiefly engaged in the
                    trade with England. There is always on hand a large stock of old wines, which
                    are mixed with the new in such a proportion as is suitable for the various
                    markets. The storehouses are above ground, are vast piles of building, having
                    lofty roofs supported on arches, and their walls are pierced with numerous
                    windows, and thus admit a free circulation of air. Some of these storehouses are
                    so large as to be capable of containing 4000 butts. The oldest wines are kept in
                    huge casks, little inferior to the celebrated tun of Heidelberg, and some of
                    them have wine nominally 120 years old; but the quantity withdrawn is every year
                    supplied from casks of a later growth; and when wine is mixed for shipping, a
                    small portion of the oldest is mingled with the new. Much brandy is mixed with
                    all the wine for exportation, and the merchants are commonly the distillers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
