<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0069-0059-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAIN (7th edition, volume 19, page 59)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864856">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935308">Frogs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173186">Weathering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173087">Weather</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d278">Weather</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tb0xv96">Frogs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zg64">Dust</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=69" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAIN</label> the descent of water from the atmosphere in the
                    form of drops of considerable size. By this circumstance it is distinguished
                    from dew and from fog. In the former the drops are so small that they are quite
                    invisible; in the latter, although their size be larger, they seem to have very
                    little more specific gravity than the atmosphere itself, and may therefore be
                    reckoned hollow spherules rather than drops. This subject will be found fully
                    discussed in the articles on Meteobology, Physical Geography, and Weather.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Preternatural Rains.</hi> We have numerous accounts, in the
                    historians of our own as well as other countries, of preternatural rains; such
                    as the raining of stones, of dust, of blood, nay, even of living animals, as
                    young frogs, and the like. We cannot doubt the truth of what authors of veracity
                    and credit relate to us of this sort, nor can we suppose that the falling of
                    stones and dust never happened; the whole mistake consists in supposing them to
                    have fallen from the clouds. But as to the blood and frogs, it is very certain
                    that they never fell at all, and the opinion to the contrary has been produced
                    by a mere deception of sight. Men are extremely fond of the marvellous in their
                    relations; but the judicious reader must examine strictly whatever is reported
                    of this kind, and not sufi <hi rend="superscript">-</hi> er himself to be
                    deceived.</p>
                <p>There are two natural methods by which quantities of stones and of dust may fall
                    in certain places, without their having been generated in the clouds or
                    descended as rain. The one is by means of hurricanes; the wind which we
                    frequently see tearing off the tiles of houses, and carrying them to
                    considerable distances, being equally capable of raising a quantity of stones,
                    and dropping them again at some distant place. But the other, which is much the
                    most powerful, and probably the most usual way, is by the eruptions of volcanoes
                    and burning mountains tossing up, as they frequently do, a vast quantity of
                    stones, ashes, and cinders, to an immense height in the air; and these, being
                    hurried away by the hurricanes and impetuous winds which usually accompany such
                    eruptions, and being in themselves much lighter than common stones, from being
                    half calcined, may thus be easily carried to vast distances, and there falling
                    in places where the inhabitants know nothing of the occasion, cannot but be
                    supposed by the vulgar to fall on them from the clouds. It is well known, that,
                    in the great eruptions of AEtna and Vesuvius, showers of ashes, dust, and small
                    cinders, have been seen to obscure the air, overspread the surface of the sea
                    for a great way, and cover the decks of ships; and this at such a distance, that
                    it might appear scarcely conceivable they should have been carried so far: and
                    probably, if the accounts of all the showers of these substances mentioned by
                    authors were collected, they w ould all be ascertained to have fallen within
                    such distances of volcanoes, whilst, if compared as to the time of their
                    falling, they would be found to correspond in that also with the eruptions of
                    those mountains. We have knowm instances of the ashes from Vesuvius having been
                    carried thirty, nay, forty leagues; and peculiar accidents may have carried them
                    still farther. It is not to be supposed that these showers of stones and dust
                    fall continuously in the manner of showers of rain, or that the fragments or
                    pieces are as frequent as drops of water. It is sufficient that a number of
                    stones, or a quantity of dust, fall at once on a place, where the inhabitants
                    can have no knowledge of the point whence they came, and the vulgar will not
                    doubt their dropping from the clouds. Nay, in the canton of Berne, in
                    Switzerland, the inhabitants accounted it a miracle that it rained earth and
                    sulphur upon them at a time when a small volcano terrified them; and even whilst
                    the wind was so boisterous, and hurricanes so frequent, that they saw almost
                    every moment the dust, sand, and little stones torn up from the surface of the
                    earth in whirlwinds, and carried to a considerable height in the air, they never
                    considered that both the sulphur thrown up by the volcano, and the dust, sand,
                    and stones carried from their feet, must soon afterwards fall somewhere. It is
                    very certain that in some of the terrible storms of hail, where , the hailstones
                    have been several inches in circumference, there have been found, on breaking
                    them, what people called <hi rend="italic">stones in their middle;</hi> but
                    these observers need only to wait the dissolving of one of these hailstones, to
                    see the stone in its centre also disunite, it being formed merely of the
                    particles of loose earthy matter, which the water, exhaled by the sun’s heat,
                    had taken up with it in extremely small molecules, and this serving to give an
                    opaque hue to the inner part of the congelation, to which the freezing of the
                    water alone gave the apparent hardness of stone.</p>
                <p>The raining of <hi rend="italic">blood</hi> has ever been accounted a more
                    terrible sight and a more fatal omen than the other preternatural rains already
                    mentioned. It is very certain that nature forms blood nowhere but in the vessels
                    of animals, and therefore showers of it from the clouds are by no means to be
                    credited. Those who suppose that what people took for blood has actually been
                    seen falling through the air, have had recourse for its origin to flying
                    insects, and suppose it to be the eggs or dung of certain butterflies discharged
                    as they were high up in the air. But this seems to be a very wild conjecture, as
                    we know of no butterfly the excrements or eggs of which are of such a colour, or
                    its abode so high in the air, or its flocks so numerous, as to be tile occasion
                    of such a phenomenon.</p>
                <p>It is most probable that these bloody waters were never seen falling; but that
                    people, seeing the standing waters blood-coloured, were assured, from their not
                    knowing how it should else happen, that it had rained blood into them. A very’
                    memorable instance of this took place at the Hague in the year 1670. Swammerdam,
                    who relates it, tells us, that one morning the whole town was in an uproar on
                    finding, as they thought, their lakes and ditches full of blood; for these
                    having certainly been full of water the night before, they agreed that it must
                    have rained blood during the night. But a certain physician went down to one of
                    the canals, and taking home a quantity of this blood-coloured water, he examined
                    it by the microscope, and found that the water was water still, and had not at
                    all changed its colour; but that it was full of prodigious swarms of small red
                    animals, all alive, and very nimble in their motions, the colour and prodigious
                    number of which gave a reddish tinge to the whole body of the water in which
                    they lived. The certainty that this was the case, did not however persuade the
                    Hollanders to part with the miracle. They prudently concluded, that the sudden
                    appearance of such a number of animals was as great a prodigy as the raining of
                    blood would have been; and remain assured to this day, that this portent
                    foretold the scene of war and destruction that Louis XIV. afterwards brought
                    into that country, which had previously enjoyed forty years of uninterrupted
                    peace.</p>
                <p>The animals which thus colour the water of lakes and ponds are the <hi
                    rend="italic">pulices arborescentes</hi> of Swammerdam, or the water-fleas with
                    branched horns. These creatures are of a reddish-yellow or flame colour. They
                    live about the sides of ditches, under weeds, and amongst the mud; and are
                    therefore the less visible, except at a certain time, which is in the beginning
                    or end of June. It is at this time that these little animals leave their
                    recesses to float loose about the water, and meet for the propagation of their
                    species; and by this means they become visible in the colour which they give the
                    water. The colour in question is visible, more or less, in one part or other of
                    almost all standing waters at this season; and it is always at the same season
                    that the bloody waters have alarmed the ignorant.</p>
                <p>The raining of <hi rend="italic">frogs</hi> is a thing not less wonderful in the
                    accounts of authors who love the marvellous than those of blood or stones; and
                    this is supposed to happen so frequently, that there are multitudes who pretend
                    to have been eye<pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=70"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0070-0060"/>witnesses of it. These rains of frogs always
                    happen after very dry seasons, and are much more frequent in the hotter than in
                    the cold countries. In Italy they are very frequent; and it is not uncommon to
                    see the streets of Rome swarming with young frogs and toads in an instant after
                    a shower of rain. Nay, they have been seen to fall through the air down upon the
                    pavements. This seems to be a strong circumstance in favour of their being
                    rained down from the clouds; but, when strictly examined, i t comes to nothing.
                    For these frogs which are seen to fell are always found dead, lamed, or bruised
                    by the fall, and never hop about like the rest; and they are never seen to fall,
                    except close under the walls of houses, from the roofs and gutters of which they
                    have accidentally slipped down. Some people who love to add to things strange
                    others yet stranger, affirm that young frogs have fallen into their hats in the
                    midst of an open field; but this is equally idl e and false.</p>
                <p>Others, who cannot agree with the opinion of their felling from the clouds, have
                    tried to solve the difficulty of their sudden appearance, by supposing them
                    hatched out of the egg, or spawn, by these rains. Nay, some have supposed them
                    to be made immediately out of the dust. But there are unanswerable arguments
                    against all these suppositions. Equivocal generation, or the spontaneous
                    production of animals out of dust, is now wholly exploded. The fall from the
                    clouds would destroy and kill these tender and soft-bodied animals. And they
                    cannot be at this time hatched immediately out of eggs, because the young frog
                    does not make its appearance from the egg in form, but has its hinder legs
                    enveloped in a skin, and is what we call a <hi rend="italic">tadpole;</hi> and
                    the young frogs are at least a hundred times larger at the time of their
                    appearance than the egg from which they should be hatched.</p>
                <p>It is beyond a doubt that the frogs which make their appearance at this time were
                    hatched and in being long before. But the dry seasons had injured them, and kept
                    them sluggishly in holes or coverts; and all the rain does is enlivening them,
                    giving them new spirits, and calling them forth to seek new habitations, and
                    enjoy the element they were destined in a great measure to live in.
                    Theophrastus, the greatest of all the naturalists of antiquity, has affirmed the
                    same thing. We find that the error of supposing these creatures to fell from the
                    clouds was as old as the time of that author; and also that the truth in regard
                    to their appearance was as early known; though, in the ages that followed,
                    authors have taken care to conceal the truth, and to hand down to us the error.
                    We find this vencrable sage, in a fragment of his on the generation of animals
                    which appear on a sudden, ridiculing the opinion, and asserting that they were
                    hatched and living long before. The world, however, owes to the accurate Signor
                    Redi the great proof of this truth, which Theophrastus has only affirmed. This
                    gentleman, dissecting some of these frogs, found in their stomachs herbs and
                    other half-digested food; and, openly showing this to his credulous countrymen,
                    asked them whether they thought that nature, which engendered, according to
                    their opinion, these animals in the clouds, had also been so provident as to
                    provide grass there for their food and nourishment?</p>
                <p>To the raining of frogs we ought to add the raining of <hi rend="italic"
                    >grasshoppers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">locusts,</hi> which have sometimes
                    appeared in prodigious numbers, and devoured the fruits of the earth. There has
                    not been the least pretence for supposing that these animals descended from the
                    clouds, though they appeared on a sudden in prodigious numbers. The naturalist,
                    who knows the many accidents attending the eggs of these and other like animals,
                    cannot but know that some seasons will prove particularly favourable to the
                    hatching them; and the prodigious number of eggs that many insects lay could not
                    but every year bring us such abundance of the young, were they not liable to
                    many accidents, and had not provident nature taken care, as in many plants, to
                    continue the species by a very numerous stock of seeds, of which perhaps not one
                    in five hundred need take root in order to continue an equal number of plants.
                    It is thus also in regard to insects; and hence it cannot but happen, that if a
                    favourable season encourage the hatching of all those eggs, a very small number
                    of which alone is necessary to continue the species, we must in such seasons
                    have a proportional abundance of them. More than half a century ago, there
                    appeared in London such a prodigious swarm of the little beetle called the <hi
                    rend="italic">lady-cow,</hi> that the very posts in the streets were everywhere
                    covered with them. But, thanks to the progress of philosophy amongst us, we had
                    nobody to assert that it rained cow-ladies, but we contented ourselves with
                    saying that it had been a favourable season for their eggs. The prodigious
                    number of a sort of grub, which, about the same period, did vast mischief to the
                    corn and grass, by eating off the roots, might also have been supposed to
                    proceed from its having rained grubs, by people fond of making everything a
                    prodigy; but our knowledge in natural history assured us, that these were only
                    the hexapod worms of the common hedge-beetle called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >cockchafer.</hi></p>
                <p>The raining of <hi rend="italic">fishes</hi> has also been a prodigy much talked
                    of in France, where the streets of a town at some distance from Paris, after a
                    terrible hurricane in the night, which tore up trees, blew down houses, and did
                    other damage, were found in a manner covered with fishes of various sizes.
                    Nobody here made any doubt of these having fallen from the clouds; nor did the
                    absurdity of fish, of five or six inches in length, being generated in the air,
                    at all startle the people, or shake their belief in the miracle, until they
                    found, upon inquiry, that a very well-stocked fish-pond, which stood on an
                    eminence in the neighbourhood, had been blown dry by the hurricane, and only the
                    great fish left at the bottom of it, the smaller fry having been tossed into
                    their streets.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, all the supposed marvellous rains have been owing to substances
                    naturally produced on the earth either never having been in the air at all, or
                    only carried thither by accident.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
