<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0501-0489-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROTA (7th edition, volume 19, page 489)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1174522">Wheels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p84454w">Wheels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39307">Equality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cc21">Coaches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659g8k">Coaching</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=501" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROTA</label> a city of Spain, in the province of Seville, and
                    the district of St Lucar. It stands on the bay of Cadiz, and being strongly
                    fortified, forms one of the means of defence to that important estuary. It is
                    situated on an elevation, and, like most Spanish towns, has a beautiful
                    appearance when viewed at a distance. It contains some very fine buildings, and
                    about 6500 inhabitants, who partly follow the occupation of fishing, whilst
                    others deal in wine, as this place supplies the kind of red wine known in
                    England by the name of Tent, which is produced on the banks of the river
                    Tinto.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rota, the name of an ecclesiastical court of Rome, composed
                    of twelve prelates, of whom one must be a German, another a Frenchman, and two
                    Spaniards; the other eight are Italians, three of whom must be Romans, and the
                    other five a Bolognese, a Ferraran, a Milanese, a Venetian, and a Tuscan. This
                    is one of the most august tribunals in Rome, which takes cognizance, by appeal,
                    of all suits in the territory of the church, and also of all matters,
                    beneficiary and patrimonial.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Rota Aristotelica,
                    or</hi><hi rend="italic">Aristotle's Wheel,</hi> denotes a celebrated problem in
                    mechanics, concerning the motion or rotation of a wheel about its axis, so
                    called because Aristotle was the first who took notice of it. The difficulty of
                    it may be represented in the following manner. While the circle makes one
                    revolution on its centre, advancing at the same time in a right line along a
                    plane, it describes on that plane a right line which is equal to its
                    circumference. Now, if this circle carry with it another smaller circle,
                    concentric with it, like the nave of a coach-wheel, then this smaller circle or
                    nave will describe a line in the time of the revolution which shall be equal to
                    that of the large wheel or circumference itself, because its centre advances in
                    a right line as fast as that of the wheel does, being in reality the same with
                    it-Aristotle attempted to solve this problem; but his solution can only be
                    regarded as a good account of the difficulty. It was next attempted by Galileo,
                    who had recourse to an infinite number of infinitely small vacuities in the
                    right line described by the two circles, and imagined that the little circle
                    never applies its circumference to those vacuities, but in reality only applies
                    it to a line equal to its own circumference, though it appears to have applied
                    it to a much larger. This, however, is nothing to the purpose. According to
                    Tacquet, the little circle making its rotation more slowly than the great one,
                    does, on that account, describe a line longer than its own circumference, yet
                    without applying any point of its circumference to more than one point of its
                    base. This is not more satisfactory than the former. After the fruitless
                    endeavours of many great men, M. Dortous de Mey-ran, a French gentleman, had the
                    good fortune to hit upon a solution which, after being fully examined by a
                    committee of the Academy of Sciences, was declared to be satisfactory. The
                    following is his solution. The wheel of a coach is only acted on or drawn in a
                    right line; its rotation or circular motion arises purely from the resistance of
                    the ground. Now this resistance is equal to the force which draws the wheel in a
                    right line, as it defeats that direction, and therefore the causes of the two
                    motions are equal. The wheel therefore describes a right line on the ground
                    equal to its circumference. On the contrary, the nave is drawn in a right line
                    by the same force as the wheel, but it only turns round because the wheel does
                    so, and can only turn in the same time with it. Hence its circular velocity is
                    less than that of the wheel, in the ratio of the two circumferences, and
                    therefore its circular motion is less than the rectilinear one. Since it must
                    describe a right line equal to that of the wheel, it can only do it by partly
                    sliding and partly revolving, the sliding part being more or less as the nave
                    itself is smaller or greater.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
