<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0076-0066-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAMSAY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 66</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4251ft9s">Tea</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1120522">Slaves</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=76" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAMSAY</label> Allan, a Scottish poet, was born at Lead-hills
                    in Lanarkshire, in October 1686. His father was employed in the management of
                    Lord Hopetoun’s mines at that place; but died whilst the poet was yet in his
                    infancy, in consequence of which, and the marriage of his mother soon after his
                    father’s death, it seems probable that, during the earlier part of his life, he
                    continued in rather a destitute situation. He remained at Leadhills till he
                    reached his fifteenth year, and was employed in washing, preparing the lead ore
                    for smelting, and other operations about the works in which the children of
                    miners and young persons are usually employed.</p>
                <p>In 1701, when in his fifteenth year, he was bound apprentice to a wigmaker in
                    Edinburgh; and it appears from the record of his children’s birth in the parish
                    register that he continued in the same humble profession until the year 1716.
                    One of the earliest of Ramsay’s productions now known, an address to the members
                    of the Easy Club, appeared in 1712, when he was twenty-six years of age; and
                    three years afterwards he was humorously appointed their poet laureat. Many of
                    his poems written about this time were published in the form of separate
                    pamphlets. When he had followed the occupation of wigmaker for a considerable
                    time, he at last abandoned it for that of bookseller, as being more congenial to
                    the literary turn of his mind. His detached pamphlets were afterwards published
                    by him in the year 1721, in one volume 4to, which was encouraged by a very
                    liberal subscription. The first volume of his well-known collection, the
                    Tea-table Miscellany, was published in 1724·, after which a second volume soon
                    made its appearance, a third came forth in 1727, and a fourth after another
                    interval of time. He soon afterwards published what is called the Evergreen,
                    being a collection of Scotch poems written by ingenious poets prior to the year
                    1600. In 1725 appeared his Gentle Shepherd, part of which, called Patic and
                    Roger, was printed in 1721, and Jenny and Meggy in 1723, the great success of
                    which induced him to form them afterwards into a regular drama.</p>
                <p>In the year 1728, he published a second volume of his poems, which was afterwards
                    reprinted in 8vo. These performances so rapidly enlarged the circle of his fame
                    and reputation, that in 1731 an edition of his poetical works was published by
                    the booksellers of London, and two years afterwards they appeared at Dublin.
                    From his shop opposite to Niddry Street, he removed to one at the east end of
                    the Luckenbooths. In this shop he continued to sell and lend out books until he
                    was far advanced in years; and we have reason to believe that he was the first
                    person who established a circulating library in Scotland. His collection of
                    Fables appeared in 1730, after which period he may be said to have almost
                    discontinued the occupation of author.</p>
                <p>Such, however, was his enterprising spirit, that he built, at his own expense,
                    the first theatre for dramatical performances ever known in Edinburgh, which
                    took place in what is called Carrubber’s Close, in the year 1736; but he did not
                    long enjoy his character of manager, for the magistrates of</p>
                <p>Edinburgh required him to shut it up, as an act of parliament prohibited all such
                    amusements without a special license and his majesty’s letters patent. It is
                    generally understood that he relinquished the trade of bookseller about the year
                    1755, being then sixty-nine years of age, and lived the remainder of his days in
                    a small house erected by himself on the north side of the Castle-hill. A
                    scorbutic complaint, attended with excruciating pain, deprived him of his teeth,
                    and, after corroding one of his jaw-bones, put a period to his existence on the
                    7th of June 1758, in the seventy-first year of his age.</p>
                <p>Ramsay possessed a very considerable share of poetical genius. Of this his Gentle
                    Shepherd, which will continue to be admired as long as the language in which it
                    is written shall be understood, and especially by the natives of North Britain,
                    to whom only the peculiarities of dialect by which it is distinguished can be
                    familiar, affords the best proof. Some of his songs may contain far-fetched
                    allusions and childish conceits; but many of them are equal, if not superior, in
                    their pastoral simplicity, to productions of a similar nature in any other
                    language. Some of the imitations of the ancients by this poet are extremely
                    happy; and several of his tales have all the excellencies that belong to that
                    species of composition. But of a great proportion of his other productions it
                    may be pronounced with truth that they are mere prosaic compositions, filled
                    with the most commonplace observations, and destitute even of the ornament of
                    smooth versification and correct rhymes. A complete edition of his works, with a
                    Life, written by the late Mr George Chalmers, was published in two volumes
                    8vo.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsay,</hi><hi rend="italic">Andrew Michael,</hi> generally
                    known by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Chevalier Ramsoy,</hi> a polite
                    Scotch writer, was descended of a good family, and born at Ayr in 1686. His
                    parts and learning recommended him as tutor to the son of the Earl of Wemyss;
                    after which, conceiving a disgust for the religion in which he had been
                    educated, he in the same humour reviewed other Christian churches, and, finding
                    none to his liking, rested for a time in Deism. Whilst he was in this uncertain
                    state of mind, he went to Leyden, where, falling into the company of one Poiret,
                    a mystical divine, he received the infection of mysticism, which prompted him to
                    consult Fénelon, the celebrated archbishop of Cambray, who had imbibed
                    principles of the same nature, and who in 1709 gained him over to the Catholic
                    religion. The subsequent course of his life received its direction from his
                    friendship and connection with this illustrious prelate; and being appointed
                    governor to the Duke de Chateau-Thierry and the Prince de Turenne, he was made a
                    knight of the order of St Lazarus. Ramsay was sent for to Rome by the Chevalier
                    de St George, to undertake the education of his children; but on his arrival
                    there in 1724, he found so many intrigues and dissensions, that he obtained the
                    chevalier’s leave to return to Paris. He died in 1743, in the office of
                    intendant to the Duke of Bouillon, prince de Turenne. The principal work of his
                    composition is the Travels of Cyrus, which has been several times printed in
                    English.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsay,</hi><hi rend="italic">James,</hi> was born on the
                    25th of July 1733, at Frasersburgh, a small town in the county of Aberdeen. His
                    parents were of most respectable character, but in circumstances by no means
                    affluent From his earliest years he discovered a serious disposition, and a
                    strong thirst for knowledge; and after passing through the usual course of a
                    Scotch grammar-school education, he inclined to pursue the studies necessary to
                    qualify him for the profession of clergyman. Several circumstances, however,
                    conspired to divert him for a time from his favourite pursuit.</p>
                <p>He was educated in the episcopal persuasion; and having been unhappy enough to
                    lose his father whilst yet very young, he found, upon his advancing towards the
                    state of manhood, that the joint fortunes of himself and his mother could not
                    bear the expense of a regular education in either <pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=77" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0077-0067"
                    />of the universities of Oxford or of Cambridge. Yielding, ’ therefore, to
                    necessity, he resolved to study surgery and pharmacy; and was with this view
                    bound apprentice to Dr Findlay, a physician in Frasersburgh. But though obliged
                    to relinquish for a time his favourite studies, he did not think ignorance
                    excusable in a surgeon any more than in a clergyman; nor did he conceive that he
                    would ever become eminent in the profession in which circumstances had placed
                    him, merely by skill in setting a bone or compounding a medicine. He determined,
                    therefore, to make himself acquainted with at least the outlines of the liberal
                    arts and sciences; and with this view he repaired in 1750 to King’s College,
                    Aberdeen, where he obtained one of the bursaries or exhibitions which are there
                    annually bestowed upon such candidates as display the most accurate knowledge of
                    the Latin language. The small sum of five pounds, however, which none of these
                    bursaries exceeds, was still inadequate to the expense of residence in college;
                    but our young student was soon destined to obtain a more valuable exhibition,
                    also by his own merit.</p>
                <p>During the long vacation he returned to his master Dr</p>
                <p>Findlay, and was by him intrusted with a very desperate case in surgery, of which
                    his management may be said to have laid the foundation of his future fortunes.
                    His skill and excellent character recommended him so effectually to Sir
                    Alexander Ramsay of Balmain, that he presented him with a bursary of fifteen
                    pounds a year, which commenced at the next session or term in the same
                    college.</p>
                <p>Sir Alexander, whom he visited during some of the vacations, was so well pleased
                    with his conversation, that he promised him another bursary, in his gift, of
                    L.25 a year, to commence immediately on the expiration of that which he enjoyed.
                    This promise he performed in the beginning of the year 1755; and, at the
                    solicitation of Dr Findlay, even paid the money in advance, to enable the
                    exhibitioner to travel for the purpose of improving himself in his
                    profession.</p>
                <p>Thus provided, Mr Ramsay went to London, and studied surgery and pharmacy under
                    the auspices of Dr Macaulay, in whose family he lived for two years, esteemed
                    alike by him and by his lady. Afterwards, having passed the usual examination at
                    Surgeons’ Hall, he served in his medical capacity for several years in the royal
                    navy.</p>
                <p>Having met with an accident, by which his thigh-bone was fractured, he once more
                    turned his thoughts towards the church; and on coming home with Sir Charles
                    Middleton he was admitted into orders; after which he immediately returned to St
                    Christopher’s, where he was presented by the governor to two rectories, valued
                    at L.700 a year.</p>
                <p>As soon as he took possession of his livings, in 1763, he married Miss Rebecca
                    Akers, the daughter of a planter of the best family connections in the island,
                    and began to regulate his household on the pious plan inculcated in his Essay on
                    the Treatment and Conversion of the African Slaves in the British Sugar
                    Colonies. He summoned all his own slaves daily to the prayers of the family,
                    when he took an opportunity of pointing out to them their duty in the plainest
                    terms, reproving those who had done amiss, and commending such as had shown
                    anything like virtue. Although his serious studies were now theological, he
                    considered himself as answerable to God, his country, and his own family, for a
                    proper use of every branch of knowledge which he possessed. He therefore took
                    the charge of several plantations around him in the capacity of a medical
                    practitioner, and attended them with unremitting diligence and with great
                    success. Thus he lived till the year 1777, when, relinquishing the practice of
                    physic entirely, he paid a visit to the place of his nativity, which he had not
                    seen since 1755. His mother, whose latter days he had made comfortable by a
                    handsome annuity, had been dead for some years; but he rewarded all who had been
                    attentive to her, or in early life serviceable to himself; and he continued the
                    pension to his sister, who had a numerous family, for which her husband was
                    unable to provide.</p>
                <p>After remaining three weeks in Scotland, and nearly a year in England, during
                    which time he was admitted into the confidence of Lord George Germaine, then
                    secretary of state for the American department, Mr Ramsay was appointed chaplain
                    to Admiral Barrington, at that time going out to take a command in the West
                    Indies. Under this gallant officer, and afterwards under Lord Rodney, he was
                    present at several engagements, where he displayed a fortitude and zeal for the
                    honour of his country which would not have disgraced the oldest admiral. To the
                    navy, indeed, he seems to have been strongly attached; and, at an early period
                    of his life, he wrote an Essay on the Duty and Qualifications of a Sea-officer,
                    with such a knowledge of the service as would have done honour to the pen of the
                    most experienced commander. Although caressed by the admirals under whom he
                    served, Mr Ramsay once more quitted the naval service, and retired to his
                    pastoral charge in the island of St Christopher’s. There, however, though the
                    former animosities against him had entirely subsided, and though his friendship
                    was now solicited by every person of consequence in the island, he remained but
                    a little time. Sick of the life of a planter and of the prospect of slavery
                    around him, he resigned his livings, and bidding adieu to the island, returned
                    to England with his wife and family in the end of the year 1781. Immediately on
                    his arrival, he was, through the interest of his steady friend Sir Charles
                    Middleton, presented to the livings of Teston and Nettle-stead, in the county of
                    Kent. Here he was soon determined, by the advice of those whom he most
                    respected, to publish an Essay, which had been written many years before, on the
                    Treatment and Conversion of African Slaves in the British Sugar Colonies. This
                    publication involved him in controversies which embittered his life. The
                    agitation given to his mind, and the fatigues he underwent in his endeavours to
                    rescue from misery the most helpless portion of the human race, contributed to
                    shorten a life which had been in no common degree useful. He had for some time
                    been afflicted with a pain in his stomach, for which he was prevailed upon,
                    though with great reluctance, to try the effects of air and exercise, by
                    attempting a journey of a hundred miles. But in London, being seized with a
                    violent vomiting of blood, he was unable to proceed and unfit to be removed
                    hence; and, in the house of Sir Charles Middleton, he ended his days, on the
                    20th of July 1789. His works, besides those to which we have already alluded,
                    consist of a volume of Sea-Sermons, and a Treatise on Signals.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
