<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0883-0737-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STONEHENGE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 20, page 737</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39364">Monuments</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jq0sv10">Altars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1025892">Monuments</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:806095">Altars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=883" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STONEHENGE</label>, a celebrated monument of antiquity,
                    stands in the middle of a flat area near the summit of a hill six miles distant
                    from Salisbury. It is enclosed by a circular double bank and ditch near thirty
                    feet broad, after crossing which we ascend thirty yards before we reach the
                    work. The whole fabric consisted of two circles and two ovals. The outer circle
                    is about 108 feet in diameter, consisting, when entire, of sixty stones, thirty
                    uprights and thirty imposts, of which remain only twenty-four uprights,
                    seventeen standing and seven down, three and a half feet asunder, and eight
                    imposts. Eleven uprights have their five imposts on them by the grand entrance.
                    These stones are from thirteen to twenty feet high. The smaller circle is
                    somewhat more than eight feet from the inside of the outer one, and consisted of
                    forty smaller stones (the highest six feet), of which only nineteen remain, and
                    only eleven standing: the walk between these two circles is 300 feet in
                    circumference. The adytum or cell is an oval formed of ten stones (from sixteen
                    to twenty-two feet high), in pairs, with imposts, which Dr Stukeley calls <hi
                    rend="italic">trilithons,</hi> and above thirty feet high, rising in height as
                    they go round, and each pair separate, and not connected as the outer pair; the
                    highest eight feet. Within these are nineteen smaller single stones, of which
                    only six are standing. At the upper end of the adytum is the altar, a large slab
                    of blue coarse marble, twenty inches thick, sixteen feet long, and four broad;
                    pressed down by the weight of the vast stones that have fallen upon it. The
                    whole number of stones, uprights, imposts, and altar, is exactly 140. The stones
                    are far from being artificial, but were most probably brought from those called
                    the <hi rend="italic">Gray Weathers,</hi> on Marlborough Downs, fifteen or
                    sixteen miles off; and if tried with a tool, they appear of the same hardness,
                    grain, and colour, generally reddish. The heads of oxen, deer, and other beasts,
                    have been found on digging in and about Stonehenge; and human bones in the
                    circumjacent barrows. There are three entrances from the plain to this
                    structure, the most considerable of which is from the north-east, and at each of
                    them were raised on the outside of the trench two huge stones, with two smaller
                    within, parallel to them.</p>
                <p>It has been long a dispute among the learned, by what nation and for what purpose
                    these enormous stones were collected and arranged. The first account of this
                    structure we meet with is in Geoffrey of Monmouth, who, in the reign of King
                    Stephen, wrote the history of the Britons in Latin. He tells us that it was
                    erected by the counsel of Merlin the British enchanter, at the command of
                    Aurelius Ambrosius, the last British king, in memory of 460 Britons who were
                    murdered by Hengist the Saxon. The next account is that of Polydore Virgil, who
                    says that the Britons erected this as a sepulchral monument of Aurelius
                    Ambrosius. Others suppose it to have been a sepulchral monument of Boadicea, the
                    famous British queen. Inigo Jones is of opinion that it was a Roman temple; from
                    a stone sixteen feet long and four broad, placed in an exact position to the
                    eastward, altar-fashion. Dr Charlton attributed it to the Danes, who were two
                    years masters of Wiltshire. A tin tablet, on which were some unknown characters,
                    supposed to be Punic, was digged up near it in the reign of Henry VIII., but is
                    lost; probably that might have given some information respecting its founders.
                    Its common name, <hi rend="italic">Stonehenge,</hi> is Saxon, and signifies a
                    “stone gallows,” to which these stones, having transverse imposts, bear some
                    resemblance. It is also called in Welch <hi rend="italic">choir gour,</hi> or
                    “the giants’ dance.”</p>
                <p>Mr Grose thinks that Dr Stukeley has completely proved this structure to have
                    been a British temple, in which the Druids officiated. He supposes it to have
                    been the metropolitan temple of Great Britain, and translates the words <hi
                    rend="italic">choir gour “</hi> the great choir or temple.” The learned Mr
                    Bryant is of opinion that it was erected by a colony of Cuthites, probably
                    before the time of the Druids; because it was usual with them to place one vast
                    stone upon another for a religious memorial; and these they often placed so
                    equably, that even a breath of wind would sometimes make them vibrate. Of such
                    stones one remains at this day in the pile of Stonehenge. The ancients
                    distinguished stones erected with a religious view by the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">amber;</hi> by which was signified any thing solar and divine. The
                    Grecians called them <hi rend="italic">πετϑαι αμϐϑοσιαι</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >petroe ambrosia.</hi> Stonehenge, according to Mr Bryant, is composed of these
                    amber Stones: hence the next town is denominated <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ambresbury;</hi> not from a Roman Ambrosius, for no such person ever existed,
                    but from the <hi rend="italic">Ambrosia petroe,</hi> in whose vicinity it stood.
                    Some of them were rocking stones; and there was a wonderful monument of this
                    kind near Penzance in Cornwall, which still retains the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">main-amber,</hi> or the sacred stones. Such a one is mentioned by
                    Apollonius Rhodius, supposed to have been raised in the time of the Argonautae,
                    in the island Tenos, as the monument of the<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=884" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0884-0738"/>
                    two winged sons of Boreas, slain by Hercules; and there are others in China and
                    other countries.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
