<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0640-0560-13" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STANHOPE, Phillip Dormer (7th edition, volume 20, page
                    560)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p83w">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09w92">Addresses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852224">Chaplains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1744459">Dormers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1076230">Pricing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1076207">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=640" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STANHOPE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Phillip Dormer</hi></label>,
                    the fourth <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl. of Chesterfield,</hi> was born at London,
                    on the 22d of September 1694. He was the son of Philip, the third earl, by his
                    wife, Lady Elizabeth Savile, daughter of George, marquis of Halifax. At the age
                    of eighteen he was sent to Trinity Hall, Cambridge, where he studied
                    assiduously, and, according to his own account, became an absolute pedant. In
                    1714 he quitted the university, and travelled on the con tinent, where a
                    familiarity with good company soon convinced him he was totally mistaken in
                    almost all his notions; and an attentive study of the air, manner, and address
                    of people of fashion, soon polished a man whose prominent de sire was to please,
                    and who, as it afterwards appeared, valued exterior accomplishments beyond any
                    other human acquirement. While Lord Stanhope, he obtained an early seat in
                    parliament; and in 1722, succeeded to his father’s estate and titles. In 1728,
                    and in 1745, he was appointed ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary to
                    Holland. This high character he supported with the greatest dig nity, serving
                    his own country, and gaining the esteem of the States-General. Upon his return
                    from Holland, he was sent as lord-lieutenant of Ireland; and during his
                    administration there, gave general satisfaction to all parties. He left Dublin
                    in 1746, and in October succeeded the earl of Harrington as secretary of state,
                    in which post he officiated un til February 6, 1748. In 1752, being seized with
                    a deafness which incapacitated him for the pleasures of society, he from that
                    time led a private and retired life, amusing himself with books and his pen; in
                    particular, he engaged largely as a volunteer in a periodical miscellaneous
                    paper called <hi rend="italic">The World,</hi> in which his contributions have a
                    distinguished degree of excellence. He died on the 24th of March 1773, leaving a
                    character for wit and abilities that had few equals. He distinguished himself by
                    his eloquence in parliament on many important occasions, of which we have a
                    characteristic instance of his own relating. He was an active promoter of the
                    bill for altering the style; and on this occasion, as he himself writes in one
                    of his letters to his son, he made so eloquent a speech in the house, that every
                    one was pleased, and said he had made the whole very clear to them, “when,”<pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=641"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0720-0641-0561"/> says he, “God knows, I had not even attempted it.
                    I could just as soon have talked Celtic or Sclavonian to them, as astronomy; and
                    they would have understood me full as well.” Lord Macclesfield, who was
                    considered as a great mathematician, and who had a principal hand in framing the
                    bill, spoke afterwards, with all the clearness that a thorough knowledge of the
                    subject could dictate; but not having a flow of words equal to Lord
                    Chesterfield, the latter gained the applause which was more justly due to the
                    former. The high character which Lord Chesterfield supported during life,
                    received no small injury soon after his death, from a fuller display of it by
                    his own hand. He left no issue by his lady, Melosina de Schulenburg, countess of
                    Walsingham; but he had a natural son, Philip Stanhope, Esq., whose edu cation
                    was for many years a close object of his attention, and who was afterward envoy
                    extraordinary at the court of Dres den, but died before him. After Lord
                    Chesterfield’s death, Mr. Stanhope’s widow published a scries of letters,
                    written by the father to the son, filled with instructions suitable to the
                    different gradations of the young man’s life to whom they were addressed. These
                    letters contain many fine ob servations on mankind, and rules of conduct; but it
                    is observable that he lays a greater stress on exterior accomplishments and
                    address than on intellectual qualifications and sincerity; and allows a much
                    greater latitude to fashion able pleasures than good morals will justify. These
                    Letters to his Son, so discreditable to the memory of the writer, appeared in
                    1774, in 2 vols. 4to. This publication was followed by a collection of his
                    Miscellaneous Works, 1777, 2 vols. 4to. A third volume was added in 1778; but
                    his lord ship’s works do not appear to have attracted much attention.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stanhope, Charles</hi>, Earl Stanhope, born in 1753, was the
                    eldest son of Philip, the second earl, a man equally remarkable for his
                    mathematical talents, and his liberal political opinions. The subject of this
                    notice succeeded to the peerage in 1786, and died in 1816. By his first marriage
                    he became the brother-in-law of Pitt; and on the mother’s side he was closely
                    allied to the Scotish earls of Haddington. This eccentric but public-spirited
                    and most inventive man, while he divided his attention among a variety of
                    inquiries, sufficient to have prevented excellence in any, had the rare merit of
                    excelling in several most important pursuits, while in more than one he has
                    bequeathed to the world discoveries that have proved most extensively useful. In
                    politics he was a decided Whig, an assertor of religious toleration, and of
                    nonintervention in the internal affairs of foreign states. Sometimes, however,
                    he carried out the principles of his party with a boldness which other minds
                    scrupled to follow; and in the latter years of his parliamentary life, Earl
                    Stanhope used to be called “the minority of one.” His political works were a
                    refutation of Price’s scheme of the sinking fund, an answer to one of Burke’s
                    invectives on the French Revolution, and an essay on juries. But his inventions
                    in mechanical science are those by which he has secured the gratitude of
                    posterity. They are too many to be here so much as completely enumerated. The
                    principal of them, the Stanhope press, has been described in our article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Ρrinting,</hi> where notice has also been taken of his
                    exertions for improving the process of stereotype. He was an early student of
                    Franklin’s theory of electricity, to which he contributed several valuable
                    observations. Another of his most useful inventions was one for improving the
                    locks of canals; and more cu rious ones were his two calculating machines, one
                    of which performed addition and subtraction, the other multiplication and
                    division.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stanhope</hi>, <hi rend="italic">George,</hi> an eminent
                    divine, was born at Hertishorn in Derbyshire, in the year 1660. His father was
                    rector of that parish, vicar of St. Margaret’s at Leices ter, and chaplain to
                    the earls of Chesterfield and Clare. His grandfather, Dr. George Stanhope, was
                    chaplain to James I. and Charles I.; had the chancellorship of York, where he
                    was also a canon residentiary, held a prebend, and was rector of Weldrake in
                    that county. For his loyalty he was driven from his home with eleven children,
                    and died in 1664. The son was sent to school, first at Uppingham in Rutland,
                    then at Leicester; he was afterwards removed to Eton, and thence chosen to
                    King’s College in Cambridge, in the place of W. Cleaver. He took the degree of
                    A. B. in 1681, and of A. M. in 1685; was elected one of the syndics for the
                    university of Cambridge, in the business of Alban Francis, 1687; minister of
                    Quoi near Cambridge, and vice-proctor, 1688. He was that year preferred to the
                    rectory of Tringin Hertfordshire, which after some time he quitted. In 1689 he
                    was presented to the vicarage of Lewisham in Kent by Lord Dartmouth, to whom he
                    had been chaplain, as well as tutor to his son. He was also appointed chaplain
                    to King William and Queen Mary, and continued to enjoy that honour under Queen
                    Anne. He commenced D. D. July 5, 1697, performing all the exercises required to
                    that degree publicly and with great applause. He was made vicar of Deptford in
                    1703; succeeded Dr. Hooper as dean of Canterbury the same year; and was thrice
                    chosen prolocutor of the lower house of convocation. His uncommon diligence and
                    industry, assisted by his excellent parts, enriched him with a large stock of
                    polite, solid, and useful Iearning. His discourses from the pulpit were equally
                    pleasing and profitable; a beautiful intermixture of the clearest reasoning with
                    the purest diction, attended with all the graces of a just elocution. In him
                    were happily united the good Christian, the solid divine, and the fine
                    gentleman. His conversation was polite and delicate, grave without precise ness,
                    facetious without levity. His piety was real and rational, his charity great and
                    universal, fruitful in acts of mercy and in all good works He died March 18,
                    1728, aged sixty-eight years; and was buried in the chancel of the church at
                    Lewisham. The dean was twice married; first to Olivia Cotton, by whom he had one
                    son and four daughters. His second lady, who was sister to Sir Charles Wager,
                    survived him, dying October 1, 1738, aged about fifty-four. One of the dean’s
                    daughters was married to a son of Bishop Burnet. Dr. Moore, bishop of Ely, died
                    the day before Queen Anne; who, it has been said, designed the dean for that see
                    when it should become vacant. “The late Dean of Canterbury,” says Dr. Felton,
                    “is excellent in the whole. His thoughts and reasoning arc bright and solid. His
                    style is just, both for the purity of the language and for the strength and
                    beauty of expression; but the periods are formed in so peculiar an order of the
                    words, that it was an observation, nobody could pronounce them with the same
                    grace and advantage as himself." His writings, which are considered as a
                    treasure of piety and devotion, are, A Paraphrase and Comment upon the Epistles
                    and Gospels. 1705, 4 vols. 8vo. Sermons at Boyle’s Lectures. 1706, 4to. Fifteen
                    Sermons. 1700, 8vo. Twelve Sermons on Several Occasions. 1727, 8vo. A
                    Translation of Thomas à Kempis. 1696, 8vo. Epictetus’s Morals, with Simplicius’s
                    Comment, and the Life of Epictetus. 1700, 8vo. Parson’s Christian Directory.
                    1716, 8vo. Rochefoucault’s Maxims. 1706, 8vo. A Funeral Sermon on Mr. Richard
                    Sare, book seller, 1724; two editions 4to. Twenty Sermons, publish ed singly
                    between the years 1692 and 1724. Private Prayers for every Day in the Week, and
                    for the several Parts of each Day; translated from the Greek Devotions of Bishop
                    Andrews, with Additions, 1730. In his translations, it is well known, Dr.
                    Stanhope did not confine himself to a strict and literal version; he took the
                    liberty of paraphrasing, explaining, and improving upon his author, as will
                    evidently appear (not to mention any other work) by the slightest perusal of St.
                    Augustin’s Meditations, and the Devotions of Bishop Andrews.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
