<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0607-0533-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPENSER, Edmund (7th edition, volume 20, page
                    533)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fb3h">Calendar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0330j">Calendars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881352">Countesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=607" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPENSER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edmund</hi></label>, one of the
                    greatest of English poets, was born in East Smithfield, about the year 1533.
                    There is no record in which the admirers of his genius may trace the incidents
                    of his early years; but there is reason to suppose that they were clouded by
                    poverty and depen dence. On the 20th of May 1519, he entered Pembroke Hall,
                    Cambridge, in the humble character of a sizer; a circumstance which is alone
                    sufficient to rescue those luckless scholars from abject despondency, and to
                    render them respectable in the eyes of their more fortunate companions. Some
                    poems, in a collection of fugitive pieces entitled “The Theatre for Worldlings,”
                    which appeared during this year, are ascribed to Spenser, upon internal
                    evidence. On the 10th of January 1752—3 he took the degree of A.B., and on the
                    26th of June 1576 that of A.M. From a letter of his friend Gabriel Harvey,
                    himself a poet of some reputation in his time, it appears that, in consequence
                    of having made enemies, who had both the will and power to injure him, he
                    quitted Cambridge in despair of academical preferment. He had luckily some
                    friends in the north of England, among whom he now found a temporary asy lum.
                    Whether he was received as an honoured guest, or compelled to turn his learning
                    to account in the way of tuition, is unknown; but the latter supposition is the
                    more probable of the two.</p>
                <p>During his retirement in the north, Spenser wrote “The Shepherd’s Calendar.”
                    Nothing is more common than for poets to deprecate the barbarity of a phantom,
                    and to be reduced to despair, because some angelic nonenity turns a deaf ear to
                    their entreaties; but it is said that Rosalind was a real mistress, at whose
                    feet Spenser sighed in vain. The successful rival of the needy sonnetteer was,
                    in all likelihood, some substantial yeoman. At this period of his history,
                    Harvey advised him to try his fortune in London; and it is probable that he
                    abandoned without reluctance, the scene of his unrequited passion. Upon his
                    arrival in the metro polis, he was fortunate enough to obtain an introduction to
                    Sir Philip Sidney, who invited him to become his guest at Penshurst, the seat of
                    the family in Kent. As a token of gratitude for this hospitality the “Shepherd’s
                    Calendar,” published in 1579, was “entituled to the noble and vertuous
                    gentleman, most worthy of all titles, Maister Philip Sidney.”</p>
                <p>Till long after the time of Spenser, the poet depended upon the casual gratuities
                    of distinguished persons, who sometimes exerted their influence in procuring for
                    a favourite bard some less precarious means of subsistence. Re commended, as it
                    is conjectured, by the Earl of Leicester, the poet went to Ireland with Arthur
                    Lord Grey of Wil ton, who was appointed deputy of that kingdom in 1580. Spenser
                    was the secretary of the viceroy, and discharged the duties of his office with
                    greater promptitude and exactness than poets usually display in the ordinary
                    business of life. His “View of the State of Ireland,” a treatise written in the
                    form of a dialogue, displays no inconsiderable portion of political sagacity. By
                    the interest of Lord Grey, Leicester, and Sidney, Spenser obtained, in 1586, a
                    grant of three thousand and twenty-eight acres of the forfeited estates of the
                    Earl of Desmond. This piece of good fortune was embittered by the death of his
                    patron, the gallant Sidney, who fell in the same year at the battle of Zutphen.
                    The pastoral elegy of Astrophel, sacred to the memory of the departed hero,
                    although not published until 1591, was probably written when the grief of the
                    poet was at the height. It was provided by the royal patent, that those who
                    profited by the forfeiture should reside upon the lands that were allotted to
                    them. According to this arrangement, Spenser proceeded to a place named
                    Kilcolman, in the county of Cork. This exile, to what was then little better
                    than a region of barbarians, was cheered by a visit from the renowned Sir Walter
                    Raleigh. At the suggestion, it may be presumed, of his distinguished guest, whom
                    perhaps he accompanied to England, the poet soon exchanged his Hibernian
                    solitude for the splendours of a court. In 1590 were published the first three
                    books of the Fairy Queen; and the poet was afterwards presented by Raleigh to
                    Queen Elizabeth, who conferred upon him a pension of fifty pounds a-year, then
                    no despicable sum. The grant of this pension was discovered in the chapel of the
                    Rolls by Mr. Malone, who has thus been enabled to clear the repu<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=608" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0608-0534"/>
                    tation of Lord Burleigh from the stigma of having intercepted the bounty of his
                    sovereign to the author of the Fairy Queen. Mr. Malone has also made it appear,
                    that Queen Elizabeth had no poet-laureate; an appointment which was supposed to
                    have been held by Spenser. In the sonnets annexed to the poem, is one to his new
                    patron, “the right noble and valorous knight, Sir Walter Raleigh ;” but Spenser
                    does not forget to shed a grateful tear to the memory of Sidney. There is a
                    sonnet addressed to the Countess of Pembroke, the darling sister of that
                    accomplished person, for whose amusement he wrote his Arcadia. With mournful
                    dignity, the poet acknowledges to the coun tess his many obligations to that
                    most heroicke spirit,</p>
                <p>The heauens pride, the glory of our daies.</p>
                <p>During his absence in Ireland, to which kingdom he returned after the publication
                    of the Fairy Queen, was printed a collection of Spenser's minor pieces,
                    entitled, “Corn plaints: containing sundrie small Poemes of the Worlds Va nitie.
                    Whereof the next page maketh mention. By Ed.Sp.” Lond. 1591, 4to. This
                    production was followed by Daph noida, an elegy on the death of Douglas Howard,
                    daughter of Henry Lord Howard. It is dated January 1, 1591—2. About this period,
                    he is supposed to have paid a visit to his native country; after which a
                    considerable space intervenes unmarked by incidents.</p>
                <p>Being no longer a pennyless rhymster, Spenser now wooed a kinder mistress than
                    Rosalind. The lady, whose name is unknown, became his wife in 1594. The progress
                    of this successful courtship is traced in his Amoretti, or Sonnets. In 1595
                    appeared the pastoral of “Colin Clout’s come home again.” The dedication of this
                    production is erroneously dated 1591, as Mr. Todd satisfactorily proves. It is
                    dedicated to Sir Walter Raleigh, who is introduced as the Shepherd of the Ocean.
                    In 1596, he published four Hymns. He informs the Countess of Cumberland and the
                    Countess of Warwick, to whom they are inscribed, that the two latter, composed
                    in his riper years, and treating of heavenly love and beauty, were designed to
                    atone for the two for mer, which were written in the heyday of his blood, and of
                    which the subjects are sensual desire and earthly grace. In the same year were
                    produced the fourth, fifth, and sixth books of the Fairy Queen. Of that
                    magnificent poem, two additional imperfect cantos are all that can be found. Our
                    limits prohibit the discussion of the question, whether the remaining six books,
                    which would have completed the design, were destroyed by fire during the Irish
                    rebellion, or left unfinished. Nor is there much utility in transcribing a long
                    list of poems no longer extant, which are sup posed to have shared their fate.
                    In the course of this year, Spenser presented his <hi rend="italic">View of the
                    State of Ireland</hi> to the queen; but, for reasons not very clearly explained,
                    that performance was not printed until thirty-five years after the author’s
                    death.</p>
                <p>In a letter from Queen Elizabeth to the Irish govern ment, dated September 30,
                    1598, which was discovered by Mr. Malone, Spenser is recommended to be sheriff
                    of Cork. A royal recommendation is generally equivalent to a command; but the
                    rebellion of Tyrone put a period to all the poet’s hopes of dignity and
                    emolument. To escape the fury of the insurgents, he abandoned his house in
                    Kilcolman, leaving behind him one of his children, who had been forgotten in the
                    terror of the moment. Having removed every thing else that it contained, the
                    miscreants set fire to the building, and left the infant to perish in the
                    flames. Spen ser did not long survive these multiplied calamities. On the 16th
                    of January 1598—9, soon after his arrival in Eng land, he died at an inn in King
                    Street, Westminster. The expenses of his funeral were defrayed by the
                    unfortunate Earl of Essex, who buried him in Westminster Abbey, near the remains
                    of Chaucer; a spot on which he had always de sired to take his last repose.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ben Jonson, in his
                    Conversations with Drummond, stated, " that the Irish having rob’d Spenser’s
                    goods and burnt his house and a little child new born, be and his wyf escaped;
                    and after, be died for lake of bread in King Street, and refused twenty pieces
                    sent to him by my Lord of Essex, and said, 'He was sorrie be bad no time to
                    spend them.’”</p></note></p>
                <p>Spenser left two sons, Sylvanus and Peregrine. Hugo lin, the son of the latter,
                    was restored to his grandfather’s estate by Charles II.; but, adhering to the
                    infatuated successor of that monarch, he was outlawed, after the revolution, for
                    high treason. The lands of the outlaw, however, were bestowed upon his cousin
                    William, the son of Sylva nus, through the interest of Mr. Montague, afterwards
                    Earl of Halifax. William Spenser was presented to the notice of Montague by
                    Congreve. “The family of the Spensers,” says Gibbon, “has been illustrated and
                    enriched by the trophies of Marlborough, but I exhort them to consider the Fairy
                    Queen as the most precious jewel in their coronet.”</p>
                <p>Of Spenser’s personal character, we are in a great measure left to form our
                    opinion from his works. Both the tendency and details of these are highly
                    favourable to virtue; and the many chaplets he threw upon the hearse of Sidney
                    prove that he cherished the memory of his benefactor with pious care. It is easy
                    to imagine gratitude allied to every other noble quality, and it is mere
                    misanthropy to question the sincerity of tears that fall to those who can give
                    no more; for it is vain to seek pensions from the tomb,</p>
                <p>Or laurels from the dust.</p>
                <p>There is, however, a dark spot on the fame of Spenser. From some original
                    documents preserved in the Rolls Office at Dublin, it appears that the murder of
                    his infant, his own ruin, despair, and death, are to be traced to his cupidity;
                    for the outrage that was the immediate cause of these disasters, was perpetrated
                    less from the hopes of plunder than the desire of vengeance for some unjust and
                    oppressive at tempts to add to his possessions.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Hardiman’s Irish Minstrelsy, or Bardic
                    Remains of lreland, vol. i. p. 320. Loπd. 1881, 2 vols. 8vo.</p></note>
                    Injustice and oppression were so habitual with the English settlers in Ireland,
                    that it was not easy for Spenser to escape the general contamination.</p>
                <p>This great poet is far from being a favourite of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >general</hi> readers of modern times, who demand something of a more
                    stimulating nature than the lives and adventures of the cardinal virtues.
                    Indeed, to have made an interminable allegory interesting to thousands, must be
                    allowed to be one of the greatest efforts of genius. This Spenser has
                    accomplished; and his pages, if not devoured with trembling eagerness, are
                    always perused with wonder, and often with delight, by the great majority of
                    those whose suffrage is of any value. It has been urged that Arthur, the hero of
                    the poem, instead of achieving the principal adventures, acts only as an
                    auxiliary to others, and that either his character, or those of the twelve
                    worthies, might with great propriety have been expunged; that the allegory often
                    de generates into mere description, without any occult meaning; and that the <hi
                    rend="italic">ottava rima</hi> of Tasso and Ariosto, with the addition of an
                    Alexandrine, is a measure which is little adapted to the genius of the English
                    language. There is however little rashness in predicting that the Fairy Queen
                    will last as long as the English language itself.</p>
                <p>An edition of Spenser’s Works, with a glossary and a life of the author, and an
                    essay on allegorical poetry, was published by John Hughes. Lond. 1715, 6 vols.
                    12mo. The Fairy Queen, with an exact collation of the two original<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=609" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0609-0535"/>
                    editions, a life of the author by Dr. Birch, and a glossary, together with 32
                    plates from designs by Kent, must likewise be mentioned. Lond. 1751, 3 vols.
                    4to. Another edition of this poem, with notes critical and explanatory, was soon
                    afterwards published by Ralph Church, A.M. Lond. 1758,</p>
                <p>4 vols. 8vo. And about the same time appeared a new edi tion, with a glossary and
                    notes explanatory and critical, by John Upton, A.M. Lond. 1758, 2 vols. 4to. An
                    elaborate and complete edition of Spenser’s Works was at length published by Mr.
                    Todd. Lond. 1805, 8 vols. 8vo. Nor must we fail to direct the reader’s more
                    particular attention to Mr. Warton’s “Observations on the Faerie Queen of Spen
                    ser,” in 2 vols. 8vo. As a proof of the poet’s continental reputation, we may
                    here refer to <hi rend="italic">Spenser’s Sonnetten, übersetzt durch Joseph von
                    Hammer.</hi> Wien, 1814, 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
