<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0566-0543-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JAINS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 543</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:981259">Jains</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:840025">Buddhas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1037910">Nirvana</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:981236">Jainism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110714">Sects</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gt9w">Jains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sn0189m">Jainism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mv15">Sects</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n566/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JAINS</label>, the most numerous and influential sect of
                    heretics, or noncomformists to the Brahmanical system of Hinduism, in India, are
                    found in every province of Upper Hindustan, in the cities along the Ganges, and
                    in Calcutta. But they are more numerous to the west—in Mewar, Guzerat, and in
                    the upper part of the Malabar coast—and are also scattered throughout the whole
                    of the southern peninsula. They are mostly traders, and live in the towns; and
                    the wealth of many of their community gives them a social importance greater
                    than would result from their mere numbers. Of what their actual number may be it
                    is unfortunately impossible to form any exact estimate, as in the census returns
                    they are confounded with the Buddhists. Their magnificent series of temples and
                    shrines on Mount Abu, one of the seven wonders of India, is perhaps the most
                    striking outward sign of their wealth and importance.</p>
                <p>The Jains are the last direct representatives on the continent of India of those
                    schools of thought which grew out of the active philosophical speculation and
                    earnest spirit of religious inquiry so rife in the valley of the Ganges during
                    the 5th and 6th centuries before the Christian era. Fof many centuries Jainism
                    was so overshadowed by that stupendous movement, born at the same time and in
                    the same place, which we call Buddhism, that it remained almost unnoticed by the
                    side of its powerful rival. But when Buddhism, whose widely open doors had
                    absorbed the mass of the community, became thereby corrupted from its pristine
                    purity and gradually died away, the smaller school of the Jains, less
                    diametrically opposed to the victorious orthodox creed of the Brahmans,
                    survived, and in some degree took its place.</p>
                <p>Jainism purports to be the system of belief promulgated by Vardhamäna, better
                    known by his epithet of Mahâ-vïra, who was a contemporary of Gautama, the
                    Buddha. But the Jains, like the Buddhists, believe that the same system had
                    previously been proclaimed through countless ages by each one of a succession of
                    earlier teachers. The Jains count twenty-four such prophets, whom they call
                    Jinas, or Tirthankaras, that is, conquerors or leaders of schools of thought. It
                    is from this word Jina that the modern name Jainas, meaning followers of the
                    Jina, or of the Jinas, is derived. This legend of the twenty-four Jinas contains
                    a germ of truth. Mahâ-vïra was not an originator; he merely carried on, with but
                    slight changes, a system which existed before his time, and which probably owes
                    its most distinguishing features to a teacher named Pärswa, who ranks in the
                    succession of Jinas as the predecessor of Mahâ-vïra. Pärswa is said, in the Jain
                    chronology, to have lived two hundred years before Mahâ-vïra (that is, about 700
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.);</hi> but the only conclusion that it is safe to draw
                    from this statement is that Pärswa was considerably earlier in point of time
                    than Mahâ-vïra. Very little reliance can be placed upon the details reported in
                    the Jain books concerning the previous Jinas in the list of the twenty-four
                    Tirthankaras. The curious will find in them many reminiscences of Hindu and
                    Buddhist legend; and the antiquarian must notice the distinctive symbols
                    assigned to each, in order to recognize <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n567/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0567-0544"/> the statues of the different Jinas, otherwise
                    identical, in the different Jain temples.</p>
                <p>Very little is at present known of the details of the Jain system of belief. But
                    fresh light is being thrown upon this question year by year, and some of their
                    principal tenets are already beyond dispute. The Jains are divided into two
                    great parties,—the <hi rend="italic">Digambaras,</hi> or Sky-clad Ones, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Sιvetambaras,</hi> or the White-robed Ones. The latter have
                    only as yet been traced, and that doubtfully, as far back as the 6th century
                    after Christ; the former are almost certainly the same as the Niganthas, who are
                    referred to in numerous passages of the Buddhist Pali Pitakas, and must
                    therefore be at least as old as the 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    In many of these passages the Niganthas are mentioned as contemporaneous with
                    the Buddha; and details enough are given concerning their leader Nigantha
                    Näta-putta (that is, the Nigantha of the Jnâtrika clan) to enable us to identify
                    him, without any doubt, as the same person as the Vardhamâna Mathâ-vïra of the
                    Jain books. This remarkable confirmation, from the scriptures of a rival
                    religion, of the Jain tradition seems conclusive as to the date of Mathâ-vïra;
                    and, should any one still doubt the antiquity of the sect, it may be mentioned
                    here that the Niganthas are referred to in one of Asoka’s edicts <hi
                    rend="italic">(Corpus</hi><hi rend="italic">Inscriptionum,</hi> Plate xx.).
                    Unfortunately the account of the teachings of Nigantha Näta-putta given in the
                    Buddhist scriptures are, like those of the Buddha’s teachings given in the
                    Brahmanical literature, not only very meagre, but also very little to be
                    depended upon. And the Jain scriptures themselves, though based on earlier
                    traditions, are not older in their present form than the 6th century of our era.
                    The most distinctively sacred books are called the forty-five Ägamas, consisting
                    of eleven Angas, twelve Upangas, ten Pakinnakas, six Chedas, four Müla-sütras,
                    and two other books. Several of these are in process of translation into English
                    for the series of translations from the sacred books of the East now being
                    published under the auspices of the university of Oxford. It was Devaddhi-ganin,
                    who occupies among the Jains a position very similar to that occupied among the
                    Buddhists by Buddho-ghosa, who at the date just mentioned collected the then
                    existing traditions and teachings of the sect into these forty-five Ägamas. It
                    is most probable that, previous to his time, the sacred lore of the Jains was
                    handed down by memory, and not by writing. This mode of transmitting a
                    literature seems very unsafe according to modern European ideas. But when we
                    call to mind the very great value of the historical results drawn from the Vedas
                    and the Buddhist scriptures, both of which were for many centuries preserved for
                    posterity by memory alone, we may confidently look forward to important
                    additions to our knowledge when the Jain Agamas shall have been made accessible
                    to European scholars. Like the Buddhist scriptures, the earlier Jain books are
                    written in a dialect of their own, the so-called Jaina Prakrit; and it was not
                    till between 1000 and 1100 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> that the Jains adopted
                    Sanskrit as their literary language.</p>
                <p>The most distinguishing outward peculiarity of Mahâ-vira and of his earliest
                    followers was their practice of going quite naked, whence the term <hi
                    rend="italic">Digαmbαrα.</hi> Against this custom Gautama, the Buddha,
                    especially warned his followers; and it is referred to in the well-known Greek
                    phrase <hi rend="italic">Gymnosophist,</hi> used already by Megasthenes, which
                    applies very aptly to the Niganthas. Even the earliest name Nigantha, which
                    means “free from bonds,” may not be without allusions to this curious belief in
                    the sanctity of nakedness, though it also alluded to freedom from the bonds of
                    sin and of transmigration. The statues of the Jinas in the Jain temples, some of
                    which are of enormous size, are still always quite naked; but the Jains
                    themselves have abandoned the practice, the Digambaras being sky-clad at meal
                    time only, and the Swetâmbaras being always completely clothed. And even among
                    the Digambaras it is only the recluses or <hi rend="italic">Yatis,</hi> men
                    devoted to a religious life, who carry out this practice. The Jain laity—the <hi
                    rend="italic">Srävakas,</hi> or disciples —do not adopt it.</p>
                <p>The supreme aim of the Jains as of the Buddhists is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nirvana</hi>; but the word conveys different ideas in the two religions. The
                    Jains appear to believe in the existence of a soul inside the human body, and in
                    the transmigration of souls; and their Nirvana seems to consist in the delivery
                    of the soul from this transmigration. It differs from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >moksha</hi> of the Hindus in that the Jains, not teaching the existence of a
                    supreme being, do not hope for an absorption of the soul into the deity. This
                    Nirvana will follow on the belief in certain metaphysical theories, the nature
                    of which still remains unknown to scholars. But it is to be accompanied by the
                    practice of the four virtues—liberality, gentleness, piety, and remorse for
                    failings—by goodness in thought, word, and deed, and by kindness to the mute
                    creation and even to the forms of vegetable life. This last item in their
                    belief, though common to the Jains and the Buddhists, has been carried out by
                    the Jains to a more extreme result, and seems to be based on the wide extension
                    of the doctrine of the soul. They regard all animals and plants as endowed with
                    souls, and they consider it an act of piety to put up and to maintain hospitals
                    for sick animals. They believe also in the existence of numerous angels or
                    demons, good and bad, among whom they include most of the deities of the Hindu
                    pantheon; and the later Jains do not scruple to render a kind of worship to
                    these spirits. This practice is, however, not in accordance with the earlier and
                    stricter Jainism; and it is the negative side of their creed, their denial of
                    the power of the gods, of the authority of the Vedas, and of the sacredness of
                    caste, which has been the most important part of their teaching. Practically, no
                    doubt, many of their laity adhere to some of the social caste distinctions of
                    the Hindus; and their authors quote the Vedas with respect when passages from
                    the Vedas can be used in support of their own views; but no distinction of caste
                    excludes from their religious orders, or prevents the attainment of their
                    Nirvana; and the Vedas, even when quoted, are not regarded as conclusively
                    authoritative. Professor Jacobi, who is the best authority on the history of
                    this sect, thus sums up the distinction between the Mahâ-vïra and the Buddha: ’
                    ‘ Mahâ-vira was rather of the ordinary class of religious men in India. He may
                    be allowed a talent for religious matters, but he possessed not the genius which
                    Buddha undoubtedly had The Buddha’s philosophy forms a system based on a few
                    fundamental ideas, whilst that of Mahâ-vira scarcely forms a system, but is
                    merely a sum of opinions <hi rend="italic">{pannattis)</hi> on various subjects,
                    no fundamental ideas being there to uphold the mass of metaphysical matter.
                    Besides this . . . . it is the ethical element that gives to the Buddhist
                    writings their superiority over those of the Jains. Mahâ-vïra treated ethics as
                    corollary and subordinate to his metaphysics, with which he was chiefly
                    concerned.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Bhadrabähn's <hi rend="italic">Kalρa
                    Siitra,</hi> the recognized and popular manual of the Swetâmbara Jains, edited
                    with English introduction by Professor Jacobi, Leipsic, 1879; Hemacandra <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s “Yoga Sδstram," edited by Windisch, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Zeitschrift der deutschen</hi><hi rend="italic">rn.org</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">. Ges.</hi> for 1874; “Zwei Jaina Stotra,” edited in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Indische Studien,</hi> vol. xv.; <hi rend="italic">Ein</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Fragment</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bhagavatï,</hi> by Professor weber; <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">Académie</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Berlin,</hi> 1866; <hi rend="italic">Nirayävaliya</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sutta,</hi> edited by Dr warren, with Dutch introduction, Amsterdam, 1879; <hi
                    rend="italic">Over de godsdienstige</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">wijsgeerige Begrippen</hi><hi rend="italic">der</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Jainas,</hi> by Dr warren (his doctor-dissertation, Zwolle, 1875);
                    <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Grammatik</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Jaina-prâkrit,</hi> by Dr Edward Müller, Berlin, 1876; Colebrooke’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Essays,</hi> vol. ii. Mr Burgess has an exhaustive account of the
                    Jain Cave Temples (none older than the 7th centuιy) in Fergusson and Burgess's
                    <hi rend="italic">Cave Temples in India,</hi> London, 1880. (T. W. R. D.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
