<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0784-0751-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JOSEPHUS, Flavius (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    751)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61d88">Judaism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:811364">Apion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n784/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JOSEPHUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Flavius</hi></label>, the
                    well-known historian of the Jews, was born at Jerusalem in the first year of the
                    reign of Caligula; the precise date is uncertain, but it lies somewhere between
                    September 13, 37, and March 16, 38 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> His early
                    advantages were very considerable. His father Matthias belonged to one of the
                    best priestly families in the city, while on his mother’s side he was descended
                    from Jonathan, the first Hasmonean high priest. The position of his parents
                    procured for him a careful education, and such was his progress (at least if his
                    own account of himself is to be believed) that at the age of fourteen he was
                    often consulted by the high priests and prominent citizens on difficult points
                    of Jewish law. At sixteen he resolved upon an experimental study of the
                    doctrines of the three leading sects, or schools of philosophy, as he prefers to
                    consider them; and, hearing that Banus, a celebrated Essene, was living in the
                    wilderness with the rigorous asceticism of a hermit, he joined him and remained
                    under his teaching for three years. Returning to Jerusalem at the age of
                    nineteen, he definitively joined the Pharisees, to whom he continued ever after
                    to adhere. In 64 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> (aet. 26) he undertook a journey
                    to Rome to intercede for some priests of his acquaintance whom Felix the
                    procurator had sent thither as prisoners to be tried on some trifling charges.
                    Landing safely at Puteoli after a narrow escape from death by shipwreck in the
                    Adriatic, he gained the friendship of Alityrus, a famous Jewish mime of the day,
                    and a favourite of Nero; by this means he not only obtained the pardon of his
                    friends, but was also loaded with many valuable gifts by the empress Poppaea. On
                    reaching Judaea again he found his countrymen bent at all hazards on throwing
                    off the Roman yoke; knowing well the resources of Rome, and the hopelessness of
                    successfully <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n785/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0785-0752"/> resisting her power, he (according to his own
                    account, which is not in itself very improbable) did his best to dissuade them
                    from any such attempt. Ultimately, however, after the victory over Cestius
                    Gallus, he yielded to the force of the current, and joined the revolutionary
                    movement in 66, being entrusted with the task of governing and defending the
                    province of Galilee, an appointment for which he was indebted to family
                    influence rather than to any known military skill. Proceeding at once to his
                    province, he set about the execution of plans of political reorganization, at
                    the same time fortifying various military positions, and getting together and
                    drilling an army of 100,000 men. Very soon, however, he had to encounter the
                    opposition of a strong party, headed by John of Giscala, and it was with
                    difficulty that he averted an insurrection at Taricheae, and afterwards saved
                    himself by flight from Tiberias. His enemies actually at one time had succeeded
                    in obtaining his recall; but the act was afterwards cancelled, through the
                    powerful influence he still possessed in Jerusalem. Meanwhile Vespasian had
                    assembled a large force at Antioch, and in the spring of 67 threw a garrison
                    into Sepphoris, whence (the troops of Josephus not waiting his attack) he made
                    himself master of all Lower Galilee. Josephus himself falling back on Tiberias
                    sent for large reinforcements from Jerusalem; these not being forthcoming, he in
                    May shut himself up in Jotopata, the defence of which he maintained against all
                    the efforts of the Romans for forty-seven days. At the end of that period the
                    place was taken by storm, and such of the garrison as had not perished in the
                    siege were put to death by the conquerors. The governor himself demanded to be
                    led into the presence of the general, and, with great adroitness assuming the
                    rôle of a prophet, told his captor that he was no chance prisoner, but had been
                    commissioned by heaven to predict that he was shortly to become the sole head of
                    the Roman empire. The plan was so far successful that the prisoner’s life was
                    spared; Vespasian, however, kept him in close confinement for two years, but on
                    attaining the purple liberatedhim. Thenceforward Josephus assumed the family
                    name of his patron (Flavius). After having accompanied Vespasian to Alexandria,
                    he attended Titus to Palestine, and remained in his train until the close of the
                    war. At the risk of his life he was more than once sent to urge his countrymen
                    to yield, but without success. After the fall of the city he accompanied Titus
                    to Rome, where Vespasian assigned him a residence in what had once been his own
                    house, conferred on him the citizenship*-and gave him a yearly pension, to which
                    was afterwards added an estate in Judaea. Under Titus and Domitian he was
                    confirmed in all his privileges, devoting the peaceful remainder of his days to
                    those literary labours with which his name is now so exclusively associated. The
                    precise date of his death is unknown; he must have survived the first century,
                    for his autobiography mentions the death of Agrippa II., which occurred in 100
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi></p>
                <p>His extant works are the following. (1) <hi rend="italic">History of the Jewish
                        War</hi> (∏epl του ’Ιουδαϊκού <hi rend="italic">πoλiμoυ),</hi> in seven
                    books. It was originally written in Aramaic for the benefit of the Jews dwelling
                    beyond the Euphrates, but was afterwards translated by its author into the
                    Greek, which alone we now possess. Books i.-ii. 14 sketch the whole course of
                    Jewish history from the period of the Maccabees to the beginning of the war. The
                    remainder of the work gives a minute account of the entire struggle from 6δ to
                    its complete suppression in 73 A.n. On its completion the whole work was
                    submitted to Vespasian, Titus, and Agrippa II., who, the author tells us, bore
                    witness to its accuracy. Of its general trustworthiness there can be no
                    reasonable doubt: Josephus had a considerable personal share in much of what he
                    records; and on other points he seems to have had access to direct documentary
                    evidence. The speeches which he reports are not of course to be construed by
                    stricter rules than those which occur in the works of Livy or Thucydides; and
                    apart from this some allowance also must be made for a tendency to exaggeration
                    or false accentuation wherever his vanity judged such a thing to be desirable.
                    (2) <hi rend="italic">Antiquities of the Jews</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >(’Ιουδαϊκή</hi><hi rend="italic">iρχaιoKoyia),</hi> in twenty books, a
                    comprehensive Jewish history from the earliest times down to the outbreak of the
                    war in ,66. It was completed in the thirteenth year of Domitian (93-94 A.D. ),
                    long after the author's own interest in it had exhausted itself. For the first
                    eleven books, covered by the Scripture narrative, his exclusive authority seems
                    to have been the Bible itself, especially the LXX. translation. He frequently,
                    however, omits or modifies points which seemed to him likely to give offence;
                    sometimes he supplements with current traditions or uses the woιks of his
                    predecessors in the same field, Demetrius and Artapanus; and occasionally he
                    gives excerpts from profane writers. The remaining nine books are very unequal
                    in merit. The period between Alexander the Great and the Maccabees is almost an
                    entire blank. For the Maccabean wars (xii. 5-xiii. 7) he had 1 Macc. to draw
                    upon; for the reigns of the later Hasmoneans (xiii. 8-xiv.) he is dependent upon
                    the historians Strabo and Nicolaus of Damascus. The last-named writer is also
                    his chief authority for the portion of his narrative which relates to the times
                    of Herod (xiv.- xvii.), but he appears to have had access to some original
                    memoirs. The last three books (xviii∙-xx.), relating to the times immediately
                    subsequent to the death of Herod, are more meagre than might have been expected,
                    and by the carelessness of their manner bear witness to the author’s confessed
                    fatigue. Book xviii. (chap. iii. sec. 3) contains a remarkable passage relating
                    to Jesus Christ, which is twice cited by Eusebius as genuine <hi rend="italic"
                        >(H. B.,</hi> i. 11; <hi rend="italic">Dem. Bv.,</hi> iii. 3, 105-6), and
                    which is met with in all the extant MSS. It is, however, unanimously believed to
                    be, in its present form at least, spurious, and those who contend even for its
                    partial genuineness are decidedly in the minority. (3) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Autobiography,</hi> in seventy-six chapters, all of which, however, except
                    the first six and the last two relate to the occurrences in Galilee in which he
                    had so large a share during 66-67 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> written in
                    defence of himself against the representations of a certain Justus of Tiberias.
                    His narrative of these events cannot be regarded as an impartial one, and that
                    in some points at least he was led to sacrifice truth to self-interest can be
                    conclusively shown by comparison even with his own earlier work, the <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the Jewish War.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vita,</hi> which èontains the allusion to the death of Agrippa II., must
                    have been written at a date subsequent to 100 A.m (4) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Against</hi><hi rend="italic">Apion,</hi> in two books. This is the .usual
                    but somewhat misleading title of a general apology for Judaism in which the
                    polemic against Apion occupies only a subordinate place. Porphyry cites it by
                    the title Πp0s τoυj "Eλληυαs, while Origen and Eusebius call it ∏∈pl τηs <hi
                        rend="italic">των</hi><hi rend="italic">'Ιουδαίων αρχαιότητας.</hi> The date
                    of its composition is later than that of the <hi rend="italic">Antiquities.</hi>
                    Other works referred to by Josephus, but no longer extant, are (1) ∏eρl <hi
                        rend="italic">των νόμων</hi><hi rend="italic">(Ant.,</hi> iii. 5, 6), which
                    is most probably to be identified with the composition elsewhere cited by the
                    title ∏∈pl <hi rend="italic">tθωv κal</hi><hi rend="italic">αίτιων</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">(Ank</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> iv. 8, 4); and (2) ∏∈pi <hi
                        rend="italic">θeoυ κal τηs ol&gt;σlas abτoυ,</hi> in four books <hi
                        rend="italic">(Ant.,</hi> xx. 11, 2). The so-called fourth book of Maccabees
                    has sometimes, but erroneously, been assigned to Josephus. One or two
                    philosophical treatises are also attributed to him by Photius; they are,
                    however, obviously of Christian origin, and most probably are from the pen of
                    Hippolytus of Ostia.</p>
                <p>The Greek text of the works of Josephus was first printed at Basel in 1544. The
                    earliest critical editions were those of Hudson (Oxford, 1720) and Havercamp
                    (Utrecht, 1726); the text of the latter is that given by Oberthür (3 vols. 8vo.,
                    Leipsic, 1782-85) and by hichter (Leipsic, 1826-27). Further emendations occur
                    in the edition of Dindorf (Paris, 1845-47), which is the basis of Bekker <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s edition (Leipsic, 1855-56). A new edition based
                    upon fresh collation of MSS. is promised by Niese. The treatise <hi
                        rend="italic">Against</hi><hi rend="italic">Apion</hi> was separately
                    edited, with notes, by J. G. Müller, 1877. The translations of Josephus have
                    been very numerous, and his writings are also the basis of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bellum Judaicum</hi> which bears the name of Egesippus (corrupted from
                    Josippus), and of the mediaeval Hebrew history ascribed to Josippon ben Gorion.
                    For the whole subject, biographical and literary, see Schürer’s <hi
                        rend="italic">B'Tliche</hi><hi rend="italic">Zeitgeschichte</hi> (1874) and
                    his exhaustive article “Josephus” in Herzog-Plitt’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Real∙Encycl.,</hi> vol. vii. (1880).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
