<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0571-0548-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JÁLPÁIGURÍ, or Julpigoree</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 548</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1207216">Bhutan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1432109">Tobacco</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1939163">Jute</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:985280">Jutes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916580">Eurasians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jn74">Eurasians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qr4p">Jute</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vb7j">Frontiers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JÁLPÁIGURÍ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Julpigoree</hi></label>,
                    a British district of India, forming the north-eastern part of the RAjshAhi Kucħ
                    Behar division, under the lieutenant-governor of Bengal, and lying between 26°
                    0' 35" and 26° 59' 30" N. lat., and between 88° 22' 40" and 89° 55' 20" E. long.
                    It consists of an irregularly shaped tract south of BhutAn and north of the
                    state of Kuch Behar and Rangpur district, with an area (1875) of 290,464 square
                    miles. The district divides into a “regulation” tract, lying towards the
                    southwest, and a strip of country, about 22 miles in width, running along the
                    foot of the Himalayas, and known as the Western DwArs. The former is a
                    continuous expanse of level paddy fields, only broken by groves of bamboos,
                    palms, and fruit-trees. The Western DwArs are, for the most part, overgrown with
                    grassy jungle, the secure home of large game, and are everywhere traversed by
                    hill torrents, which, on the higher slopes, lose themselves beneath the sandy
                    soil. The frontier towards BhutAn is formed by the SinchulA mountain range, some
                    peaks of which attain an elevation of 6000 feet. It is thickly wooded from base
                    to summit. The principal rivers, proceeding from west to east, are the
                    MahAnandA, KarAtoyA, Tistâ, Jâldhakâ, DuduyA, Mujnai, TorshA, KAljAni, RAidhak,
                    and Sankos. The most important is the Tistâ, which forms a valuable means of
                    water communication. The Government forest reserves in the Western DwArs cover a
                    total area of 342 ’ 54 square miles. Lime is quarried in the lower BhutAn hills.
                    During the last few years tea-planting has been introduced, with every prospect
                    of success.</p>
                <p>The parliamentary abstract of 1878 gives a population of 418,665. The returns
                    from the Dwars were not drawn up in the form adopted for Bengal generally. The
                    remaining part has a population of 327,985 (169,288 males and 158,697 females),
                    comprising 25 Europeans, 7 Eurasians, 8 Chinese, 144 Nepâlis, 553 aborigines,
                    148,043 semi-Hinduized aborigines, 32,155 Hindus according to caste, 2070 Hindus
                    not recognizing caste, and 144,980 Mahometans. The great bulk of the population
                    belongs to the semi-Hinduized tribe known as Koch or Rajbansi, which numbers
                    137,135, and is ascertained to form as much as two-thirds of the total
                    inhabitants in the Western Dwars. Rice is the staple crop in all parts of the
                    district. Mustard seed is extensively grown; cotton is the staple of the DwArs,
                    jute and tobacco of the regulation tract. Irrigation is common in the Western
                    DwArs. There is still some spare land uncultivated in the regulation tract; and
                    in the Western DwArs it has been estimated that about three-fourths of the land
                    now waste is capable of cultivation. Of late years trade has been stimulated by
                    the demand for agricultural produce from the south, and by the institutions of
                    fairs on the BhutAn frontier. The chief exports are jute, tobacco, timber, and
                    rice; the chief imports are piece-goods, salt, and betel-nuts.</p>
                <p>Education encounters great difficulties in Jalpaiguri, because the people are not
                    gathered into villages, each family living in its own sequestered homestead. In
                    1875 the number of schools was 153, with 3263 pupils. The climate in the
                    vicinity of JAlpAiguri town does not materially differ from that common to
                    northern Bengal, except that the rainfall is heavier, and during the cold months
                    fogs and mists are of daily occurrence. The average annual rainfall is over 100
                    inches; the average temperature is 76 <hi rend="superscript"> α</hi> Fahr. The
                    climate of the Western DwArs is markedly different; the hot weather disappears
                    altogether, and the rains last continuously from April to October. The average
                    annual rainfall at BaxA is 280 inches; the temperature averages 74° Fahr. The
                    principal diseases are malarious fevers, splenitis, enlargement of the liver,
                    diarrhcea, dysentery, and goitre. Of late years some very fatal outbreaks of
                    cholera have occurred.</p>
                <p>The district of Jalpaiguri first came into existence in 1869, when the TitAlyA
                    subdivision of Rangpur was incorporated with the Western DwArs, and erected into
                    an independent revenue unit. The permanently settled portion of Jalpaiguri has
                    no history of its own, apart from the parent district of Rangpur. The Western
                    DwArs became British territory as the result of the war with Bhutan in 1864-65.
                    The newly acquired territory was immediately formed into the two districts of
                    the Eastern and Western DwArs, the former of which has since been incorporated
                    with the Assam district of GoAlparA. The remainder, with the exception of a
                    subdivision, was formed into the new district of Jalpaiguri with the addition of
                    a portion taken from the unwieldy jurisdiction of Rangpur. Cultivation is now
                    rapidly extending throughout the Dwars; and it is believed that the population
                    has been doubled during the ten years that have elapsed since British
                    annexation. From motives of precaution, a regiment of native infantry is
                    stationed in permanent cantonments at the hill pass of BaxA.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jalpaiguri,</hi> the administrative head-quarters of the
                    above district, is situated on the west bank of the TistA, in 26° 32' 20" N.
                    Iat,, 88° 45' 38" E. long. This town has only risen into importance since the
                    creation of the district in 1869, since which date its population has doubled.
                    The population is estimated at between 4000 and 5000, including the regiment of
                    native infantry in the cantonments, which lie south of the civil station.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
