<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0590-0565-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JANSEN [Jansenius], Cornelius (9th edition, volume 13,
                    page 565)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845721">Canis</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n590/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JANSEN <hi rend="smallcaps">[Jansenius],
                        Cornelius</hi></label> (1585- 1638), bishop of Ypres, and the author of the
                    celebrated <hi rend="italic">Augustinus,</hi> was born, of humble Catholic
                    parentage, at Acquoy or Ackooi, a small village near Leerdam, and 7 miles to the
                    north-east of Gorcum, Holland, on 28th October 1585. After completing his
                    preliminary studies at Leerdam and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n591/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0591-0566"/> Utrecht, he in 1602 proceeded to Louvain,
                    where he studied for a short time at the Jesuit college; but afterwards,
                    becoming dissatisfied with the doctrines there taught on the hotly discussed
                    questions of free will and grace, he transferred himself to the college of
                    Adrian VI., where he came under the influence of a pious and learned teacher,
                    Jacobus Jansonius by name, who is described as having been an ardent disciple of
                    Augustine and a follower of Michael Bajus (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Ba
                        jus),</hi> whose doctrinal views had been condemned by Pius V. and Gregory
                    XIII. At the same time he formed an acquaintance, which grew into intimate
                    friendship, with the likeminded Vergerius (see Du <hi rend="smallcaps">Vergier
                        de Hauranne),</hi> who afterwards became abbé of St Cyran. Having graduated
                    in philosophy at Louvain in 1604, Jansen went to Paris for the benefit of his
                    health, which had suffered from the ardour with which he had pursued his studies
                    in theology with a view to a doctor’s degree. Here he remained for some time,
                    supporting himself by teaching; afterwards he accompained Vergerius to Bayonne,
                    the native place of the latter, where they spent several years together, Du
                    Vergier ultimately becoming canon of the cathedral, and Jansen head of the
                    episcopal college. Every available moment of their time was devoted to the study
                    of the fathers and especially of Augustine. In 1617 Jansen returned to Louvain,
                    whither he had been urgently summoned by Jansonius, who greatly desired to have
                    there a man of real learning and energy who should be able to counteract the
                    growing influence of the Jesuits. On his arrival he undertook the principal
                    charge of the newly founded college of St Pulcheria, but this appointment he did
                    not long retain, feeling, it is said, a growing aversion to philosophical
                    pursuits, and desiring to possess the utmost possible leisure that he might
                    devote himself wholly to theology. In 1619 he became doctor in that faculty. The
                    reputation which he even then enjoyed as a theologian is well indicated by the
                    fact that he was formally requested by the papal nuncio to undertake a reply to
                    the recently published <hi rend="italic">De Republica</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Ecclesiastica</hi> of Marco Antonio de Dominis, archbishop of Spalatro,
                    while the direction in which his sympathies so strongly ran was at the same time
                    not obscurely indicated by the fact that he excused himself from complying with
                    the invitation. In 1624, and again in 1626, he undertook a journey to Spain, on
                    behalf of the university, with reference to certain encroachments of the Jesuits
                    on its exclusive privileges; in the second of these missions he was successful,
                    the members of the Society of Jesus in the Low Countries being ordered to
                    continue to observe the restrictions which had been laid upon them in 1612. In
                    1630 Jansen was made regius professor of Biblical exegesis; and in the same
                    year, in connexion with the recent introduction of the Reformed religion into
                    Bois-le-Duc, he entered upon a controversy about Protestantism with the learned
                    Voetius, the issue of which conclusively showed that he had grievously
                    underestimated his adversary’s strength. In 1635 he published a pseudonymous
                    work entitled <hi rend="italic">Alexandri Patricii</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Arma-cani,</hi><hi rend="italic">Theologi,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Mars</hi><hi rend="italic">Gallicus, seu</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">justitia armorum et foederum Regis Gallise libri</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">duo,</hi> embodying an argument and remonstrance against the
                    policy of France in its recent alliance with the Protestant Gustavus Adolphus.
                    For this supposed service to Spain he was rewarded in 1636 with the bishopric of
                    Ypres. He was preparing for the press his great work upon St Augustine, which
                    had occupied him for twenty-two years, when he was cut off by sudden illness on
                    May 6, 1638. By his last will the MSS. of this work were bequeathed to his
                    chaplain Lamaeus, and his friends Fromondus and Calenus, to be published “quam
                    fidelissime”; at the same time he declared his obedience to the Roman See should
                    any alterations be desired.</p>
                <p>The title of the first work of Jansen against Voetius was <hi rend="italic"
                        >Alexi-phαrmαcon</hi>; it called forth <hi rend="italic">Notae</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">in Alexipharmaeon,</hi> to which he replied in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Spongia,</hi> 1630. On the publication of Voet’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Desperata</hi><hi rend="italic">Causa Ρapatus</hi> in 1635,
                    Jansen handed over the further management of the controversy to Fromond, whose
                        <hi rend="italic">Crisis</hi> (1636) was met with Schook’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Desperatissima</hi><hi rend="italic">Causa Papatus.</hi> Among other works
                    of Jansen are mentioned <hi rend="italic">Τetrateuchus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >sive Commentarius</hi><hi rend="italic">in IV.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Evangelia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pentateuchus siυe</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Commentarius</hi><hi rend="italic">in V.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >libros Moysis.</hi> See Leydecker, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Jansenismi</hi> (Utrecht, 1695).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
