<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0722-0689-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JHANG (9th edition, volume 13, page 689)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1118436">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1057086">Pensions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1101348">Running</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:840028">Buddhism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z5k">Pensions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n722/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JHANG</label>, a British district in the
                    lieutenant-governorship of the Punjab, India, between 30° 35' and 32° 4' N.
                    lat., and between 71° 39' and 73° 38' E. long., with an area of 5712 square
                    miles. It forms the northern district of the Mùltân division, and is bounded on
                    the N. by Shâhpur and Gujrânwâla, on the W. by Derâ Ismâil Khân, and on the S.E.
                    by Montgomery. It comprises an irregular triangle, artificially constituted for
                    administrative purposes from portions of three separate tracts. Its eastern half
                    embraces a large part of the high dorsal bridge in the Rechna Doâb; thence it
                    stretches across the Chenab into the wedge of land between that stream and the
                    Jhélum, whose waters unite a few miles below the town of Jhang; while westward
                    again the boundary runs beyond the joint river, far into the heart of the Sind
                    Sâgar Doâb. The Ravi also bounds the district for a few miles along its southern
                    edge. So artificial a tract can hardly be said to possess any common natural
                    features of its own. Along the banks of the river strips of comparatively
                    fertile lowland support a dense population.</p>
                <p>At the census of 1868 the population was 348,027 (193,624 males and 154,403
                    females). The Mahometans numbered 270,819; Hindus, 57,297; Sikhs, 2994; and
                    “others,” 16,917. Only three towns contain a population exceeding 5000—Jhang,
                    9124; Maghiâna, 10,525; and Chiniot, 11,477. The area under cultivation in 1873
                    amounted to 241,325 acres, out of an assessed total of 3,650,867 acres. No crops
                    can anywhere be grown without irrigation. Wheat, barley, gram, <hi rend="italic"
                        >sarsοη, china,</hi><hi rend="italic">joâr,</hi> maize, and cotton form the
                    staples of the district. Grain is imported. Country cloth is manufactured at
                    Jhang and Maghiâna, and bought up by the Po-winda merchants of Afghanistan.
                    Manufactures of gold and silver lace also exist. The principal road from Mùltân
                    to Wazirâbâd passes through the chief towns in the district. A bridge of boats
                    is in course of construction (1875) across the united stream of the Jhelum and
                    the Chenâb. Both rivers are navigable. The total revenue for 1873 was £49,302.
                    The police force in 1872 numbered 503 mem In 1872 there were 32 Government and
                    123 native schools, with a joint roll of 3696 pupils. The district bears a good
                    reputation for healthiness. Small-pox and fever form the most prevalent
                    diseases. The average rainfall for the seven years ending 1872-73 was 10 inches.
                    There are seven charitable dispensaries.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n723/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0723-0690"/>
                <p>The district of Jhang possesses unusual historical interest from the presence
                    within its borders of the rains which crown the rocky eminence of Sanglawala
                    Tiba. This site has been identified with the Sakala of the Brahmans, the Sagal
                    of Buddhism, and the Sangala of Alexander’s historians. In modern times the
                    history of Jhang centres in the famous family of Sials, who exercised an
                    extensive sway over a large tract between Shahpur and Mιiltan, with little
                    dependence on the imperial court at Delhi, until they finally fell before the
                    all-absorbing power of Ranjit. Sinh. The Sials of Jhang are Mahometans of Rajput
                    descent, whose ancestor, Rai Shankar of Dâranagar, emigrated early in the 13th
                    century from the Gangetic Doâb to Jaunpur. In the beginning of the present
                    century "the maharaja Ranjιt Sinh invaded Jhang, and captured the Sial
                    chieftain’s territories. He recovered a small portion afterwards, which he λvas
                    allowed to retain on payment of a yearly tribute. In 1847, after the
                    establishment of the British agency at Lahore, the district came under the
                    charge of the British Government; and in 1848 Ismail Khan, the Sial leader,
                    rendered important services against the rebel chiefs, for which he received a
                    pension. During the mutiny of 1857 the Sial leader again proved his loyalty by
                    serving in person on the British side. His pension was afterwards increased, and
                    he obtained the title of Khan Bahadur, with a small <hi rend="italic"
                        >jdgir</hi><hi rend="italic">îoi</hi> life.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jhang,</hi> a municipal town in the above district. The
                    sister town of Maghiâna, containing the civil station for the district, lies 3
                    miles south of Jhang, and has a population of 10,525 persons. They form together
                    a single municipality, and may be regarded as practically one town, situated in
                    31° 16' 16" N. lat., and 72° 21' 45" E. long., about 3⅛ miles to the west of the
                    present bed of the Chenab. Jhang itself lies on the lowland, a little apart from
                    the regular lines of trade, and since the removal of the Government offices to
                    Maghiâna, has yielded its commerce and importance to its younger rival. Founded
                    by Mal Khân, a Siâl chieftain, in 1462, it long formed the capital of a native
                    Mahometan state. The population of Jhang proper in 1868 was 9124, comprising
                    4568 Hindus, 4244 Mahometans, 129 Sikhs, 12 Christians, and 171 “others.”
                    Population of the united towns, 19,649.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
