<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0570-0547-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JALÁUN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 547</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:898449">Droughts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1029821">Murderers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1029781">Murder</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1103711">Sal</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:837525">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:837522">Brahman</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w26p">Murder</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j569">Droughts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JALÁUN</label>, a British district in the
                    lieutenant-governorship of the North-Western Provinces of India, lies between
                    25° 46' and 26° 26' N. lat., and between 78° 59' and 79° 55' E. long., with an
                    area of 1553 square miles, and forms the northern district of the Jhânsi
                    division. It is bounded on the N.E. and N. by the river Jumna, on the W. by the
                    Gwalior and Datia states, on the S. by the Samthar state and the river Betwa,
                    and on the E. by Baoni state. The district lies entirely within the level plain
                    of Bundelkhand, north of the hill country, and is almost surrounded by the Jumna
                    and its tributaries the Betwa and Pahùj. The central region thus enclosed is a
                    dead level of cultivated land, almost destitute of trees, and sparsely dotted
                    with villages. The southern portion especially presents one unbroken sheet of
                    cultivation. The boundary rivers form the only interesting feature in Jaläun.
                    The little river Noh flows through the centre of the district, which it drains
                    by innumerable small ravines instead of watering. Jaläun has little
                    picturesqueness or beauty, but possesses great fertility and abundant
                    agricultural resources.</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 gives a population of 404,384, of whom 216,607 were males and
                    187,777 females. The principal tribes are the Brahmans, the Kurmis, the Gùjars,
                    the Kachhwâhas, the Lengars, the Kayaths, and the Musalmâns. There were four
                    towns in 1872 with a population exceeding 5000 :—Kâlpi, 15,570; Kùnch, 14,448;
                    Jaläun, 10,197; and Urai, 6398. The staple crops arc the cereals, gram, and
                    cotton. Oil-seeds, dye-stuffs, and sugar-cane are also raised, but in no large
                    quantities. Irrigation was employed in 1872 over 19,157 acres. Jaläun has
                    suffered much from the noxious <hi rend="italic">kdns</hi> grass, owing to the
                    spread of which many villages have been abandoned and their lands thrown out of
                    cultivation. Drought is the great danger in Jaläun. The last important drought
                    was that of 1868-69; no actual famine resulted, but great distress prevailed.
                    Jaläun is almost entirely an agricultural district, and its trade accordingly
                    depends mainly upon its raw materials and food-stuffs. Kâlpi is the great mart
                    of the district; Kùnch is also a considerable trading town. The river traffic by
                    Kalpi is chiefly for through goods; and the Jumna is little used as a highway. A
                    good commercial road connects Urâi and Jaläun with Phaphund, the railway station
                    on the East Indian line. There is also a great military road from Kalpi to
                    Jhânsi. The administration is on the non-regulation system, which unites civil,
                    criminal, and fiscal functions in the same officer. In 1860 there were 1434
                    children under instruction; in 1871, 2703. The climate, though hot and dry, is
                    not considered unhealthy. The mean temperature is 81 <hi rend="superscript">
                    o-</hi> 9 Fahr. The prevailing diseases are fevers, ana dysenteιγ and other
                    bowel complaints.</p>
                <p>Jaläun seems to have been subject to the Naga dynasty, which <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0571-0548"/> lasted from the 1st to the 3d century of our era.
                    In course of time the eastern portion fell under the power of the Chandels,
                    while the western districts, including that of JalAun, were ruled by the
                    KachhwAhas, a Rajput clan. These seem to have held most of the district until
                    the invasion of the Bundelas in the 14th century. But the town of KAlpi on the
                    Jumna was conquered for the princes of Ghor as early as 1196. Early in the 14th
                    century the Bundelas occupied the greater part of JalAun, and even succeeded in
                    holding the fortified post of KAlpi. That important possession was soon
                    recovered by the Musalmans, and passed under the sway of the Mughal emperors.
                    Akbar’s governors at KAlpi maintained a nominal authority over the surrounding
                    district; and the native princes were in a state of chronic revolt, which
                    culminated in the war of independence under Chhatar Sal. On the outbreak of his
                    rebellion in 1671 he occupied a large province to the south of the Jumna.
                    Setting out from this basis, and assisted by the MarhattAs, he reduced the whole
                    of Bundelkhand. On his death he bequeathed one-third of his dominions to his
                    Marhatta allies, who displayed their usual alacrity in occupying their new
                    territory, and before long succeeded in quietly annexing the whole of
                    Bundelkhand. Under Marhatta rule the country was a prey to constant anarchy and
                    intestine strife. To this period must be traced the origin of all the poverty
                    and desolation which are still conspicuous throughout the district. In 1806
                    KAlpi was made over to the British, and in 1840, on the death of Nana Gobind
                    RAs, his possessions lapsed to them also. Various interchanges of territory took
                    place, and in 1856 the present boundaries were substantially settled. During the
                    whole period of British rule before the mutiny, JalAun only recovered its
                    prosperity by very slow degrees. When the news of the rising at Cawnpur reached
                    KAlpi, the men of the 53d native infantry deserted their officers, and in June
                    the JhAιιsi mutineers reached the district, and began their murder of Europeans.
                    The natives everywhere revelled in the licence of plunder and murder which the
                    mutiny had spread through all Bundelkhand, and it was not till September 1858
                    that the rebels were finally defeated. Since the mutiny the condition of Jalaun
                    seems to have been steadily but slowly improving.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">JalAun,</hi> a decayed town in the above district, and the
                    former capital of a native state, is situated in 26° 8' 32" N. lat,, 79° 22' 24"
                    E. long. It occupies a large area, and contains a considerable number of good
                    houses, and a ruined fort. The position is low, and swamps surrounding the town
                    engender cholera and malarious fever, for which reason the headquarters of the
                    district have been fixed at Urâi. The population in 1872 was 10,197,—8824 Hindus
                    and 1373 Mahometans.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
