<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0626-0599-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JAUNPUR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 599</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1103674">Sais</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1095872">Rest</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1103481">Sai</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1118436">Sikhs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4610w100">Rulers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JAUNPUR</label>, a British district in the
                    lieutenantgovernorship of the North-Western Provinces, India, lying between 25°
                    23' 15" and 26° 12' N. lat., and between 82° 10' and 83° 7' 45" E. long. It
                    forms the north-eastern district of the Allahâbâd division, and is bounded on
                    the N. and N.W. by the Oudh districts of Faizâbâd, Partabgarh, and Sultânpur, on
                    the E. and N.E. by Ghâzipur and Azamgarh, on the S. by Benares and Mfrzâpur, and
                    on the W. by Allahâbâd.</p>
                <p>The district of Jaunpur forms part of the wide Gangetic plain, and its surface is
                    accordingly composed of a thick alluvial deposit. The whole country is closely
                    tilled, and no waste lands break the continuous prospect of cultivated fields.
                    The northern and central positions are richly wooded. The district is divided
                    into two unequal parts by the sinuous channel of the Gumti, a tributary of the
                    Ganges, which flows past the city of Jaunpur. Its total course within the
                    district is about 90 miles, and it is nowhere fordable. It is crossed by two
                    famous bridges, one at Jaunpur and the other 2 miles lower down. The other
                    rivers are the Sai, Barna, Pilli, and Basohi. Lakes are numerous in the north
                    and south; the largest has a length of 8 miles.</p>
                <p>The census of 1872 was taken upon an area of 1556 square miles, and. it disclosed
                    a total population of 1,025,961, of whom 545,752 were males and 480,209 fémales.
                    Jaunpur is essentially a Hindu district, in spite of its long subjection to
                    Mahometan rulers. The returns show 929,525 Hindus to 96,319 Mahometans; the
                    Christian population (European and native) numbers 117. There are only two towns
                    with more than 5000 inhabitants,—Jaunpur, 23,327, and Machhlishahr, 8715.</p>
                <p>The ordinary soil of Jaunpur is a mixture of mould, clay, and. sand; but in old
                    river beds and the basins of temporary lakes a rich black alluvial deposit may
                    occasionally be found. The harvests are those common to the rest of Upper India.
                    The crops yielded are cotton, rice, <hi rend="italic">bdjrα,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">joàr,</hi><hi rend="italic">moth,</hi> wheat, barley, oats, pease,
                    and other pulses. Sugar yields the greatest profit, but it requires great care.
                    Indigo, poppy, tobacco, and vegetables are also cultivated. The Gumti is liable
                    to sudden inundations during the rainy season, owing to the high banks it has
                    piled up at its entrance into the Ganges, which act as dams to prevent the
                    prompt outflow of its flooded waters. These inundations extend to its tributary
                    the Sai. Much damage was thus effected in 1774; but the greatest recorded flood
                    took place in September 1871, when 4000 houses in the city were swept away,
                    besides 9000 more in villages along its banks. On the other hand, Jaunpur has
                    been comparatively free from drought, the great plague of the north-west
                    generally, as of the rest of India. The district is almost entirely devoted to
                    agriculture, and its trade is confined to raw materials and food-stuffs. The
                    principal fairs are held at Mariahu in September, and at Karchuli in March; they
                    are attended by from 20,000 to 25,000 pilgrims and traders. The Oudh and
                    Rohilkhand railway passes through the district. There are 145 miles of metalled
                    and 364 of unmetalled roads. The Gumti and Sai are navigable for boats of
                    moderate burden. The climate is moist, and the temperature is more equable, and
                    the rain more evenly distributed throughout the year, than in most districts of
                    the North-Western Provinces. The average rainfall for 1861-70 was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n627/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0627-0600"/> 43 inches; during that period the maximum was 51
                    ’ 6 inches, the minimum 22 inches. There are two charitable dispensaries.</p>
                <p>In prehistoric times Jaunpur seems to have formed a portion of the Ajodhya
                    principality, and when it first makes an appearance in authentic history it was
                    subject to the rulers of Benares. With the rest of their dominions it fell under
                    the yoke of the Musalman invaders in 1194. From that time the district appears
                    to have been ruled by a prince of the Kanauj dynasty, as a tributary of the
                    Mahometan suzerain. In 1388 Malik Sarwar Khwaja was sent by Muhammad Tughlak to
                    govern the eastern province, lie fixed his residence at Jaunpur, made himself
                    independent of the Delhi court, and assumed the title of Sultan-us-Shark, or
                    eastern emperor. For nearly a century the Sharki dynasty ruled at Jaunpur, and
                    proved formidable rivals to the sovereigns of Delhi. The last of the dynasty was
                    Sultan Hussen, who passed his life in a fierce and chequered struggle for
                    supremacy with Bahlol Lodi, then actual emperor at Delhi. At length, in 1478,
                    Bahlol succeeded in defeating his rival in a series of decisive engagements. He
                    took the city of Jaunpur, but permitted the conquered Hussen to reside there,
                    and to complete the building of his great mosque, the Jama Masjid, which now
                    forms the chief ornament of the town. Many other architectural works in the
                    district still bear witness to its greatness under its independent Musalman
                    rulers. Under the Lodi dynasty the history of Jaunpur contains nothing more than
                    the stereotyped narrative of provincial intrigue, constant revolt, and bloody
                    repression. When the last of that line was killed, a local kingdom was once more
                    established for a short time in the district, but after the fall of Agra and
                    Delhi Jaunpur was recovered, and the district thenceforward formed a portion of
                    the Mughal empire. Nothing worthy of note occurred in connexion with this
                    district until 1722, when it was transferred, with Benares, Ghazipur, and
                    Chunar, to the naw&lt;ib wazir of Oudh, who appointed a commander to the
                    districts with the title of raja of Benares. The first connexion of the British
                    with the district arose in 1765, when it passed for a short time into their
                    hands after the battle of Baxar. In 1775 it was finally made over to them by the
                    treaty of Lucknow. From that time nothing occurred which calls for notice till
                    the date of the mutiny. On tjιe 5th June 1857, when the news of the Benares
                    revolt reached Jaunpur, the Sikhs mutinied. The district continued in a state of
                    complete anarchy till the arrival of the Gurkha force from Azamgarh in
                    September. In November the surrounding country was lost again, and it was not
                    till May 1858 that the last smouldering embers of disaffection were stifled by
                    the repulse of the insurgent leader at the hands of the people themselves.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jaunpur,</hi> a municipal town and the administrative
                    headquarters of the above district, situated in 25° 41' 31" N. lat. and 82° 43'
                    38" E. long., on the northern bank of the river Gumti. Jaunpur is a very ancient
                    city, the former capital of a considerable Mahometan kingdom, which once
                    extended from Budâun and Etâwah to Behar. It abounds in splendid architectural
                    monuments, most of which belong to the Pathân period, when the rulers of Jaunpur
                    made themselves independent of Delhi. Among the remains are the fort of Firoz,
                    the <hi rend="italic">hammams</hi> or baths, the Atâla Masjid and the Jinjiri
                    Masjid, mosques built by Ibrâhîm, the Dariba mosque constructed by two of
                    Ibrâhîm’s governors, the Lâl Darwâza erected by the queen of Mahmud, the Jamâ
                    Masjid or great mosque of Hussen, and the splendid bridge over the Gumti,
                    erected by Mumzin Khân, governor under the Mughals, in 1569-73. During the
                    mutiny of 1857 Jaunpur formed a centre of great disaffection. The town still
                    possesses a considerable trade. There are two railway stations there. The
                    population in 1872 was 23,327, comprising 12,369 Hindus and 10,949 Mahometans
                    and 9 “others.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
