<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0723-0690-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JHELUM, or Jhilam (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    690)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1118436">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104337">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dq72">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n723/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JHELUM, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Jhilam</hi></label>, a
                    district iu the lieutenantgovernorship of the Punjab, India, between 32° 26' and
                    33° 15' N. lat., and between 71° 51'and 73° 50' E. long., bounded on the N. by
                    Râwal Pindi district, E. by the Jhelum river, S. by Shâhpur district, and W. by
                    Bannu district. It forms the south-eastern portion of a rugged, Himâlayan spur,
                    extending between the Indus and Jhelum to the borders of the Sind Sâgar Doâb.
                    Its scenery is very picturesque, although not of so wild a character as the
                    mountain region of Râwal Pindi to the north, and is lighted up in places by
                    smiling patches of cultivated valley. The backbone of the district is formed by
                    the Salt Range, a treble line of parallel hills running in three long forks from
                    east to west throughout its whole breadth. The range rises in bold and striking
                    precipices, broken by gorges, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n724/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0724-0691"/> clothed with green brushwood and traversed by
                    trickling streams, at first pure and fresh, but soon impregnated with the saline
                    matter over which they pass. Between the line of hills lies a picturesque
                    table-land, in which the beautiful little lake of Kallar Kahâr nestles amongst
                    the minor ridges. North of the Salt Range, the country extends upwards in an
                    elevated plateau, diversified by countless ravines and fissures, until it loses
                    itself in the tangled masses of the Râwal Pindi mountains. In this rugged tract
                    cultivation is rare and difficult, the soil being choked with saline matter. At
                    the foot of the Salt Hills, however, lies a small strip of level soil, lying
                    along the banks of the Jhelum, and thickly dotted with prosperous villages. The
                    drainage of the district is determined by a low central watershed running north
                    and south at right angles to the Salt Range. The waters of the western portion
                    find their way into the Sohân, and finally into the Indus; those of the opposite
                    slope collect themselves into small torrents, and empty themselves into the
                    Jhelum.</p>
                <p>The census of 1868 returned the population of Jhelum district at 500,988,
                    inhabiting 113,010 houses, and spread over an area of 3910 square miles. The
                    Mahometans numbered 434,157; Hindus, 49, 111; Sikhs, 13,865; and “others,” 3855.
                    Five towns contained in 1868 a population exceeding 5000 :—Find Dädan Khan,
                    15,740; Chakwal, 5767; Talâgang, 5767; Lawa, 5256; and Jhelum, 5148. Of a total
                    area of 2,502,290 acres, but 763,845 acres are under cultivation, and only
                    258,825 acres more are returned as capable of tillage. The staple crops are
                    wheat and <hi rend="italic">bâjra.</hi> Trade is chiefly concentrated in the
                    town of Find Dadau Kham The exports are salt, silk and cotton goods, brass and
                    copper wares; the imports, English piece goods and metals, and woollen fabrics
                    from Kashmir and from Central Asia <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Peshawar. Salt is
                    procured in immense quantities from the central hills of the Salt Range; the net
                    revenue from this source in 1871-72 amounted to £362,193. The total revenue in
                    .1872-73, excluding salt, was £70,299, of which £59,766 was derived from the
                    land tax. The police force consisted in 1873 of 527 men. For fiscal and
                    administrative purposes the district is subdivided into 4 <hi rend="italic"
                        >tahsils</hi> and <hi rend="italic">V par</hi><hi rend="italic">garnis,</hi>
                    containing 939 estates, and owned by 49,866 proprietors.</p>
                <p>The history of the district dates back from the semi-mythical period of the <hi
                        rend="italic">MahΛbhcιrata.</hi> Hindu tradition represents the Salt Range
                    as the refuge of the five Pandava brethren during the period of their exile, and
                    every salient point in its scenery is connected with some legend of the national
                    heroes. Modern research has fixed the site of the conflict between Alexander and
                    Porus as within Jhelum district, although the exact point at which the
                    Macedonian king effected the passage of the Jhelum (or Hydaspes) is disputed.
                    After this event, we have little information with regard to the condition of the
                    district until the Mahometan conquest brought back literature and history to
                    Upper India. The Janjιiahs and Jâts, who now hold the Salt Range and its
                    northern plateau respectively, appear to have been the earliest inhabitants. The
                    Ghakkars seem to represent an early wave of conquest from the east, and they
                    still inhabit the whole eastern slope of the district; while the Awans, who now
                    cluster in the western plain, are apparently later invaders from the opposite
                    quarter. The Ghakkars were the dominant race at the period of the first
                    Mahometan incursions, and long continued to retain their independence. During
                    the flourishing period of the Mughal dynasty, the Ghakkar chieftains were among
                    the most prosperous and loyal vassals of the house of Babar; but after the
                    collapse of the Delhi empire Jhelum fell, like its neighbours, under the sway of
                    the Sikhs. In 1765 Gujar Sinh defeated the last independent Ghakkar prince, and
                    reduced the wild mountaineers to subjection. His son succeeded to his dominions,
                    until 1810, when he fell before the irresistible power of Ranjit Sinh. In 1849
                    the district passed, with the rest of the Sikh territories, into the hands of
                    the British. Ranjit Sinh, however, had so thoroughly subjugated the wild
                    mountain tribes that little difficulty was experienced in reducing it to working
                    order, and the subsequent history of Jhelum has been purely fiscal and
                    administrative.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jhelum,</hi> the headquarters of the above district,
                    situated on the north bank of the Jhelum river, in <hi rend="italic">32°
                        55'</hi> 26* N. lat. and 73° 46' 36" E. long. The town is quite of modern
                    origin, and in 1868 contained a population of 5148, viz., Mahometans, 2831;
                    Hindus, 1858; Sikhs, 442; Christians, 3; and “others,” 14. The civil lines and
                    cantonments for a regiment of native infantry lie about a mile north of the
                    town, which is noted for boat building.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
