<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0562-0539-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JADE (9th edition, volume 13, page 539)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn07">Jade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q506">Aluminium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fj5w">Calcium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp1x">Gnosticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:981065">Jade</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947579">Green</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n562/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JADE</label>, a name popularly applied to several distinct
                    ornamental stones, but restricted scientifically to a definite mineral species
                    known as <hi rend="italic">nephrite.</hi> The term nephrite, from vf≠pos, the
                    kidney, refers to the reputed value of the mineral in renal diseases, whence it
                    was formerly known as <hi rend="italic">Lapis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >nephriticus.</hi> Probably the word <hi rend="italic">jade</hi> is a
                    corruption of the Spanish <hi rend="italic">hijada,</hi> since this mineral is
                    one of the stones which were known to the Spanish conquerors of Mexico and Peru
                    under the name of <hi rend="italic">ρiedra de hijada,</hi> or “stone of the
                    loins ”—a name which first appears in the writings of Monardes, in 1565, as <hi
                        rend="italic">piedra de la yjada.</hi> So numerous have been the names
                    applied to this mineral in <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n563/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0563-0540"/> various parts of the world, and at different
                    times, that Professor Fischer has collected nearly one hundred and fifty
                    synonyms of jade.</p>
                <p>True jade, or nephrite, is a native silicate of calcium and magnesium, which may
                    be regarded as a compact or crypto-crystalline variety of hornblende, and may be
                    referred either to actinolite or to tremolite, according as its colour tends to
                    green or to white. It never exhibits crystalline form or distinct cleavage; but,
                    according to recent observers who have visited the old quarries in Turkestan,
                    and have seen the mineral <hi rend="italic">in situ,</hi> traces of cleavage may
                    occasionally be observed; usually, however, the substance breaks with a
                    splintery fracture. The specific gravity of jade varies from 2 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 91 to 3Ό6, and offers one of the readiest means
                    of distinguishing between this mineral and others with which it is likely to be
                    confounded. Most specimens of jade are scratched by flint or quartz, their
                    hardness being about 6 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5; but, while the hardness
                    is not excessive, the mineral is remarkable for its toughness. It is notable
                    that Hermann von Schlagintweit, who inspected the quarries in the Kara-kash
                    valley, found that the hardness of the stone when freshly broken was
                    considerably less than that assumed by it after a short exposure. The colour of
                    jade is subject to great diversity, —some varieties presenting almost every
                    shade of green, while others are yellowish, grey, or even white.</p>
                <p>So far as is at present known, no true jade has ever been detected <hi
                        rend="italic">in situ</hi> in Europe. A loose block has been found at
                    Schwemsal near Leipsic, and the mineral is said to occur in the drift at Potsdam
                    near Berlin. Corsica and Turkey have also been recorded as jade localities, but
                    probably on insufficient grounds.</p>
                <p>It is by the Chinese that jade has always been most highly prized, and,
                    notwithstanding its intractability, most elaborately carved. To the Chinese it
                    is known under the name of <hi rend="italic">yu</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >yu-chi</hi> (yu-stone). Much of the Chinese jade was formerly obtained from
                    quarries in the Kuen-lun mountains, on the sides of the Kara-kash valley, in
                    Turkestan. These ancient workings were visited and described a few years ago by
                    H. v. Schlagintweit, by Dr Stolicka, and by Dr Cayley. The mineral is found in
                    nests and veins running through schistose and gneissose rocks. It is probable
                    that jade occurs throughout the Kuen-lun range, and that a rich site exists to
                    the south of Khotan. The Khotan jade has been known to the Chinese for upwards
                    of two thousand years. In Turkestan the jade is known as <hi rend="italic"
                        >yashm</hi> or <hi rend="italic">yeshm,</hi> a word which appears in Arabic
                    as <hi rend="italic">yeshb,</hi> and is said to be cognate with *αcms or jasper.
                    Indeed, by early mineralogists the jade was often described as <hi rend="italic"
                        >jaspis</hi><hi rend="italic">viridis.</hi> Fine boulders of dark green jade
                    have been found by M. Alibert in the neighbourhood of his graphite mine near
                    Batougol in Siberia. New Zealand is one of the most famous localities for jade,
                    and the stone is highly prized by the natives, who work it, with great labour,
                    into amulets, axe-heads, and various other objects. Among these objects may be
                    mentioned the peculiar club-like implement known as the <hi rend="italic"
                        >mere</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pattoo- 2&gt;attoo,</hi> and the hideous
                    breast ornament termed <hi rend="italic">hei tiki.</hi> By the Maories jade is
                    known <hi rend="italic">ΛS,punamu</hi> or “green-stone,” and the occurrence of
                    this mineral along the western coast of the south island has led to the name <hi
                        rend="italic">Te wahi punamu,</hi> or “the place of the green-stone,” being
                    applied to this district. Jade also occurs in New Caledonia and in some of the
                    smaller Pacific islands. In consequence of its use by the South Sea islanders as
                    a material for making axeheads, it is often known to German mineralogists as <hi
                        rend="italic">Beilstein</hi> or “axe-stone.”</p>
                <p>Under the name of “oceanic jade,’’ M. Damour has described a fibrous variety
                    found in New Caledonia and in the Marquesas Islands, having a specific gravity
                    of 3 ’ 18, and differing from ordinary nephrite in the proportion of lime and
                    magnesia which it contains. If this oceanic jade be recognized as a distinct
                    variety, the ordinary nephrite may be distinguished as “oriental jade.”</p>
                <p>Although it was from America that the original jade, or “spleen-stone,” was
                    introduced into Europe, it is curious that few, if any, American localities for
                    this mineral are recorded in modern works on mineralogy. Dr Dawson has, however,
                    noted its occurrence in British Columbia. At the time of the Spanish conquest of
                    America, amulets in jade or in some jade-like mineral were highly venerated
                    throughout Mexico, Central America, and Peru. It has been supposed by Mr E. G.
                    Squier that jade was one of the green stones so greatly prized by the ancient
                    Mexicans under the name of <hi rend="italic">chalchihuitl.</hi> The “Amazon
                    stone,” which has sometimes been regarded as jade, is a green variety of
                    microcline-felspar; while the “Bowenite” from Smithfield in Rhode Island, which
                    was at one time supposed to be nephrite, is found to be a variety of serpentine
                    of unusual hardness. Serpentine is also used as a substitute for jade in some of
                    the common objects imported from China.</p>
                <p>While true jade has not hitherto been found <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> in
                    Europe, it is a very suggestive fact that neolithic celts and scrapers have been
                    found among the relics of several of the ancient pile-dwellings in the lakes of
                    Switzerland. The principal localities have been the stations of Lüscherz and
                    Schaffis on the Lake of Bienne (Biel), Meilen on the Lake of Zurich, and
                    Robenhausen on the Lake of Pfäffikon. Yet no jade has been discovered among the
                    rocks of the Swiss Alps; neither have any chippings been found which might lead
                    us to suspect that the stone was worked in Switzerland. As it seems beyond doubt
                    that the jade must be a foreign material, it becomes an interesting question to
                    determine whether such objects were obtained by barter, or had been brought by
                    the ancestors of the old lakedwellers from their primitive abode in the East,
                    and preserved generation after generation during their migration westwards. It
                    should be mentioned that jade celts have been found by Dr Schliemann among the
                    relics of the oldest of the cities at Hissarlik. A jade celt engraved with a
                    Gnostic formula in Greek characters is preserved in the Christy collection; and
                    among the Assyrian and Babylonian seal-cylinders in the British museum there is
                    said to be one specimen of jade.</p>
                <p>It was shown by M. Damour, in 1863, that much of the so-called jade is altogether
                    different from nephrite, and must be separated as a distinct species, for which
                    he suggested the name of “jadeite.” Jadeite is a silicate of aluminium and
                    sodium, and therefore differs widely from nephrite in chemical composition.
                    Mineralogically its relations lie rather with epidote than with hornblende. Its
                    colour is generally brighter than that of nephrite, and the paler-tinted kinds
                    often contain veins of a bright-green colour. It is slightly harder than
                    nephrite, but its most distinctive characteristic is its high specific gravity;
                    this ranges from 3 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 28 to 3 <hi rend="superscript"
                        > ,</hi> 35, while the density of nephrite, even in oceanic jade, never
                    exceeds 3 ’ 18.</p>
                <p>Much of the Chinese “jade” is really jadeite. According to Pumpelly the jadeite
                    of Yu-nan in south-west China is known as <hi rend="italic">fei-tsui..</hi>
                    Jadeite also occurs to the north-west of Bhamo in Burmah. Axes of jadeite are
                    not unfrequently found in the remains of the Swiss lake-dwellings, but the
                    mineral is not known to occur in the rocks of Europe. Jadeite forms the
                    substance of many ancient Mexican ornaments, while implements wrought in the
                    same material have been found in Costa Rica. Fischer records an Egyptian
                    scarabaeus in jadeite.</p>
                <p>The green jade-like stones which are known to the Maories as <hi rend="italic"
                        >kawa-kawα</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tangiwai</hi> do not appear to be <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n564/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0564-0541"/> either jade or jadeite. From analyses
                    published by Von Hochstetter, the former is a hydrated silicate of aluminium and
                    magnesium, while the latter is a silicate of aluminium, calcium, magnesium, and
                    iron.</p>
                <p>It was pointed out by Damour, in 186-5, that certain stone celts found in the
                    dolmens of France and in the lakes of Switzerland, as well as some from Mexico,
                    are wrought in a material which resembles jadeite, but contains a larger
                    proportion of iron, and is marked by having a specific gravity as high as 3 4 or
                    even 3‘65. This substance he distinguished as <hi rend="italic"
                        >chloromelanite,</hi> a word which has an unfortunate resemblance to the
                    name <hi rend="italic">chloromelaη</hi> which Breithaupt bestowed, as far back
                    as 1823, upon a mineral resembling cronstedite. Damour’s chloromelanite is a
                    substance of spinach-green or blackish green colour, frequently flecked with
                    paler patches, and enclosing garnets and iron-pyrites. When H. B. de Saussure
                    examined the geology of the Swiss Alps, he found a greenish mineral, of singular
                    toughness, which he described as jade. By Haüy it was afterwards called <hi
                        rend="italic">jade tenace.</hi> Its chemical composition, however, is quite
                    unlike that of jade, and Beudant separated it as a distinct mineral under the
                    name of “saussurite.” Placed by the older mineralogists among the felspars, it
                    seems to take its right position with the species called zoisite. Saussurite is
                    a silicate of aluminium and calcium, having a specific gravity of about 3 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 2. It forms a constituent of the Alpine rock
                    known as “euphotide,” boulders of which are scattered around the Lake of Geneva,
                    and were used by the lake-dwellers in the manufacture of implements.</p>
                <p>Another mineral occasionally mistaken for some of the paler kinds of jade, and
                    used as a material for implements by the Neolithic occupants of western Europe,
                    is the species termed “fibrolite.” This is a silicate of aluminium with a
                    specific gravity of about 3 ’ 2,—a density serving to distinguish it from
                    quartz, while it may be separated from other jade-like minerals by its
                    infusibility.</p>
                <p>The following table, containing a few selected analyses of jade and the other
                    minerals mentioned in this article, may be useful for reference.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> X</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>II.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>III.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                                l</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>V.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>VI.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>VII.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>VIII.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>IX.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Silica 1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>58'46</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59-50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>57-75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56-50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52-25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59-17</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56-40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>43 59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>37-10</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Magnesia</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27-09</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24-24</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19-86</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1 20-09</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18-07</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>115</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>V82</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2-98</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Lime</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12-06</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11-60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14-89</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13-27</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19-27</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2-68</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5'49</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19-71</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ferrous oxide. J</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>115</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1-35</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4-79</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6-75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6-80</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1-56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6-06</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Manganous „ ..</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-79</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0-46</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0-42</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Alumina</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>.0-90</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0'∙58</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">22-58</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14-76</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27-72</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>61'03</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Feιτic oxide ...</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-38</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>3-27</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2-61</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0-71</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Manganic,, ....</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-66</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Nickelic</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-22</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Chromic ,, ....</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-26</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Soda</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-68</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12-93</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>ii∙20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3 <hi rend="superscript">;</hi> 08</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Potash</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>'1-57</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>ï <hi rend="superscript">:</hi> 20</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Water</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0 85</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'0'68</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8⅛0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Γδ</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0'∙35</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>98-76</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100-65</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>99-93</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100-53</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>99-41</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100-07</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>99-66</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100-04</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100-04</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>I.</p><p>II.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>White jade, China; Damour, . . . s.g. 2‘97</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>„ ,, Turkestan; L. R. von Fellenberg ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2∙96</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>III.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Green jade, New Zealand; ,, ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3Ό2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>IV.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>,, ,, Swiss Lake-dwelling; ., ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙02</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>V.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Oceanic jade; Damour, . . ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙18</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>VI.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Jadeite, China; ,, . . . · ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙34</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>VII.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Chloromelanite, stone celt; Damour, . ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙41</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>VIII.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Saussurite, L. Geneva; T. Sterry Hunt, . ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙30</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>IX.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Fibrolite, celt from Morbihan; Damour, . ,,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3∙18</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The literature of jade is very extensive, but it will be sufficient to refer to
                    the work of Heinrich Fischer, which is almost exhaustive of the subject: <hi
                        rend="italic">Nephrit und Jadeit, nach ihren mineralogischen Eigenschaften
                        sowie nach ihrer zirgeschichtlichen und ethnographischen Bedeutung,</hi> 2d
                    ed., Stuttgart, 1880. (F. W. R.*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
