<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0728-0695-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JOAN of Arc, or more properly Joanneta Darc (9th
                    edition, volume 13, page 695)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj8h">Berries</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx74153">Documents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830788">Berries</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n728/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JOAN <hi rend="smallcaps">of Arc</hi>, or more properly
                        Joanneta Darc</label>, afterwards known in France as Jeanne d’Arc,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In the Act of ennoblement
                            the name is spelt Day, due probably to the peculiar current
                            pronunciation. It has been disputed whether the name was written
                            originally d’Arc or Darc. It is beyond doubt that the father of Joan was
                            not of noble origin, but Bouteiller suggests that at that period the
                            apostrophe did not indicate nobility.</p></note> the Maid of Orleans,
                    was born about 1411, the daughter of Jacques Darc, peasant proprietor of
                    Domremy, a small village partly in Champagne and partly in Lorraine, and of his
                    wife Isabeau de Vouthon, who from having made a pilgrimage to Rome had received
                    the usual surname of Romée. Joan never learned to read or write, and received
                    her sole religious instruction from her mother, who taught her to recite the
                    Pater Noster, Ave Maria, and Credo. In her childhood she was noted for her
                    abounding physical energy; but her vivacity, so far from being tainted by any
                    coarse or unfeminine trait, was the direct outcome of intense mental activity
                    and an abnormally sensitive nervous temperament. Towards her parents her conduct
                    was uniformly exemplary, and the charm of her unselfish kindness made her the
                    special favourite of many in the village. In all household work she was
                    specially proficient, her skill in the use of the needle not being excelled by
                    that of any matron even of Rouen. As she grew to womanhood she became inclined
                    to silence, and spent much of her time in solitude and prayer. All advances made
                    by the young men of her acquaintance with the view of winning her attention or
                    favour she decisively repelled; and, while active in the performance of her
                    usual round of duties, and apparently finding her mode of life quite pleasant
                    and congenial, inwardly she was engrossed with thoughts reaching far beyond the
                    circle uf her daily concerns.</p>
                <p>At this time, through the alliance and support of Philip of Burgundy, the English
                    had extended their conquest over the whole of France north of the Loire as well
                    as Guienne; and, while the infant Henry VI. of England had in 1422 been
                    proclaimed king of France at his father’s grave at St Denis, Charles the
                    dauphin, devoted only to present ease and pleasure, was almost passively
                    contemplating the slow dismemberment of his kingdom by internal confusion and
                    misery, and by the progressive encroachments of the English rule. The fact that
                    the hard straits to which the kingdom was reduced were greatly owing to the
                    conduct of Isabella, the dauphin’s mother, who disinherited her son <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n729/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0729-0696"/> iu favour of Henry V. of England, the husband
                    of her daughter Catherine, supplied an opportunity for the fulfilment of the
                    ancient prophecy of the enchanter Merlin, that the calamities which should fall
                    upon France through the depravity of a woman would be removed by the
                    instrumentality of a chaste virgin. To the imagination of the time there was,
                    moreover, nothing strange in such a mode of deliverance, for it was no uncommon
                    occurrence for damsels to accompany their lovers to the wars, and, disguised as
                    pages, to share to some extent in their dangers and adventures. In the country
                    of Joan the tradition was current that this virgin should come out of the forest
                    of Domremy, where Joan was accustomed in her childhood to tend her father’s
                    sheep. How it therefore became fixed in her mind that she was the destined
                    deliverer of her country there is little difficulty in understanding. She
                    possessed a nature strongly sympathetic, and it was kindled to ardent patriotism
                    by the sad condition of her country; her imagination was so overpower-ingly
                    vivid that it frequently deceived her reason; and her consciousness of
                    endowments which could find no proper scope for their activity within her narrow
                    sphere must have confirmed if they did not originate her prognostications that
                    she was appointed to some high destiny. Gradually her whole attention became so
                    engrossed with her country’s wrongs that all her waking hours were one continued
                    and prolonged prayer for its deliverance. The result was that, owing to a
                    peculiarity in her nervous constitution, her own thoughts and hopes seemed to
                    take audible voice, and returned to her as assurances and commands spoken to her
                    by the saints. At last, when in 1428 Orleans, the key to the south of France,
                    was invested by the English under the earl of Salisbury, the voices became so
                    peremptory and urgent as to overcome all pretexts for delay on account of
                    previous discouragements and rebuffs. Notwithstanding the strong remonstrances
                    of her parents, who viewed her resolve with poignant grief and dismay, she now
                    renewed with increased determination her efforts to win from Robert de
                    Baudricourt, governor of Vaucou-Ieurs, an introduction to the dauphin Charles.
                    In all her subsequent acts she professed to be guided by the voices of the
                    saints, who had set before her the twofold task of relieving Orleans and
                    crowning the young dauphin at Rheims. By persistent importunity, the effect of
                    which was increased by the simplicity of her demeanour and her calm assurance of
                    success, she at last prevailed on the governor to grant her request; and in
                    February 1429, accompanied by two knights, she set out on her perilous journey
                    to the court of the dauphin at Chinon. At first Charles refused to see her, but
                    the rising tide of popular feeling in her favour induced his advisers to
                    persuade him after three days to grant her an interview. Of the divinity of her
                    commission she is said to have persuaded him by discovering him though disguised
                    in the crowd of his courtiers, and by assuring him regarding his secret doubts
                    as to his legitimacy. Accordingly, after a commission of doctors had reported
                    that they had found in her nothing of evil or contrary to the Catholic faith,
                    and a council of matrons had reported on her chastity and virginity, she was
                    permitted to set forth with an army of 4000 or 5000 men designed for the relief
                    of Orleans. At the head of the army she rode clothed in a coat of mail, armed
                    with an ancient sword which she had divined to be hidden near the altar of St
                    Catherine de Fierbois, and carrying a white standard of her own design
                    embroidered with lilies and having on the one side the image of God seated on
                    the clouds and holding the world in his hand, and on the other a representation
                    of the annunciation. Joan was of medium height, stoutly built, but finely
                    proportioned; and her frame was capable of enduring great fatigue.
                    Notwithstanding subsequent traditions, she does not appear to have been
                    strikingly handsome. Conventional beauty of the highest type could not be
                    expected in one accustomed to her mode of life, but the most authentic
                    testimonies represent her as less comely than many in her own station. Her
                    features were, moreover, expressive rather of rustic honesty and innocence than
                    of mental power, although she is said to have possessed grand melancholy eyes
                    which, probably on account of the high and noble purpose which animated them,
                    exercised an indescribable charm.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>On the personal appearance of the Maid, sée especially
                            E. de Bouteiller, <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >Iconographiques sur</hi><hi rend="italic">Jeanne d’Arc,</hi> 1879,
                            containing engravings of the most authentic statues.</p></note> Her
                    voice was powerful, but at the same time of great sweetness, and her manner
                    possessed a fine natural dignity and grace, which, while it repelled
                    familiarity, softened and subdued even the rudest of the soldiers. Nominally she
                    had been entrusted with the command of the army, but in reality it was under the
                    direction of experienced generals; and it cannot be pretended that the victories
                    accomplished in consequence of her co-operation were the result of brilliant
                    military genius. Indeed, the blind obstinacy with which in the face of
                    overwhelming odds she refused to acknowledge defeat place it beyond doubt that
                    she was unable to estimate the elements of success in battle, and was actuated
                    throughout by a fatalistic persuasion that victory was inevitable if she
                    persevered unflinchingly in her efforts to obtain it. At the same time she
                    possessed a shrewd and penetrating judgment both as to men and things, and the
                    manner in which she conducted herself amid the varied difficulties of her career
                    indicated extraordinary force of character and high and noble prudence. What,
                    however, she chiefly supplied to the French cause was concentrated energy and
                    resolution. Above all, she inspired the soldiery with a fanatic enthusiasm armed
                    with the sanctions and ennobled by the influences of religion; and she overawed
                    the enemy by the superstitious fear that she was in league with supernatural
                    powers.</p>
                <p>By a remarkable stroke of good luck Joan succeeded in entering Orleans on the
                    29th April 1429, and through the vigorous and unremitting attacks of the French
                    the English gradually became so discouraged that on the 8th of May they raised
                    the siege. By the capture of Jargeau and Beaugency, followed by the great
                    victory of Patay, where Talbot was taken prisoner, the English were driven
                    beyond the Loire. With some difficulty the king was then persuaded to set out
                    towards Rheims, which he entered with an army of 12,000 men on July 16th, Troyes
                    having on the way been taken by assault at the sole instigation of the Maid. On
                    the following day, holding the sacred banner, she stood next to Charles at his
                    coronation in the cathedral. After an endeavour to detach Burgundy from the
                    English cause, the king at last agreed to attempt the capture of Paris, but on
                    account of the disastrous result of an attack made on the 8th September, in
                    which Joan was wounded, he resolved, notwithstanding her passionate
                    remonstrance, to withdraw from the city, and disbanded his troops. Joan went
                    into Normandy to assist the duke of Alençon, but in December returned to the
                    court, and on the 29th she and her family were ennobled with the surname of du
                    Lis. Unconsoled by such honours, she rode away from the court in March, to
                    assist in the defence of Compiègne against the duke of Burgundy; and on the 24th
                    May she led an unsuccessful sortie against the besiegers, when on account of her
                    determination to fight to the last she was surrounded and taken prisoner.
                    Charles, partly perhaps on account of his natural indolence, partly on account
                    of the intrigues at the court, made no effort to effect her ransom, and never
                    showed any sign of interest in her fate. Probably he had found her so difficult
                    to <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n730/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0730-0697"/> manage and control that he as well as his
                    generals regarded her presence with the army as more embarrassing than helpful;
                    and doubtless her capture dissipated the halo of supernatural power that had
                    surrounded her. By means of negotiations instigated and prosecuted with great
                    perseverance by the university of Paris and the Inquisition, and through the
                    persistent scheming of Pierre Cauchon, the ejected bishop of Beauvais, she was
                    sold in November by Luxembourg and Burgundy to the English, who on January 3,
                    1431, at the instance of the university of Paris, delivered her over to the
                    Inquisition for trial. After a public examination, begun on the 9th January and
                    lasting six days, and another conducted in the prison, she was, on the 20th
                    March, publicly accused as a heretic and sorcerer, and, being in the end found
                    guilty, she made her submission at the scaffold on the 24th May, and received
                    pardon. She was still, however, the prisoner of the English, and, having been
                    induced by those who had her in charge to resume her male clothes, she was on
                    this account judged to have relapsed, was sentenced to death, and burned at the
                    stake on the streets of Rouen, May 30,1431. The sentence was revoked by the pope
                    on the 7th July 1456, and since then it has been the custom of Catholic writers
                    to uphold the reality of her divine inspiration. In 1436 an impostor appeared,
                    professing to be Joan of Arc escaped from the flames, who succeeding in inducing
                    many people to believe in her statement, but afterwards confessed her
                    imposture.</p>
                <p>There is no doubt that Joan herself believed in her supernatural guidance, and
                    her judges, notwithstanding all their efforts, were unable to bring to light the
                    smallest semblance of a sign of conscious dishonesty on her part. At the same
                    time the nobility of her purpose was unstained by the faintest symptom of
                    selfish regard to her own fame and glorification. Indeed the greatness of her
                    career did not consist in her military achievements, but in her pure, true, and
                    ardent character, which made her a pathetic victim to the mean and grovelling
                    aims of those in whose cause she fought with such simple sincerity of faith, and
                    to the cruelties of a superstitious age.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> All previous works on Joan of Arc were
                    deprived of a great part of their critical value by the publication, in 5 vols.,
                    1841-49, of the <hi rend="italic">Procès de condamnation et de réhabilitation de
                        Jeanne</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Arc,</hi> edited by J. Quicherat. The record
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Procès de condamnation</hi> consisted originally of the
                    official notes of the trial, afterwards edited in Latin by P. Cauchon, and bears
                    internal marks of general truthfulness. The original French minute does not
                    exist except in a fragment which has been reproduced by Μ. Vallet de Viriville
                    in his French translation of the Latin version, published in 1867. A French
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Procès de condamnation</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Procès de réhabilitation</hi> by E. O’Reilly appeared in 1868.
                    The 4th vol. of Quicherat is occupied with old chronicles and histories, the
                    principal of which are those of <hi rend="italic">Percival de Cagny,</hi> a
                    retainer of the duke of Alençon, never before published; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jacques</hi><hi rend="italic">le</hi><hi rend="italic">Bouvier</hi>
                    (Berri), that from 1402-1411 first published in 1653 as part of a history of
                    Charles VI., and the remainder, 1411-1444, in the collection of Denis Godefroy,
                    1661; <hi rend="italic">Jean Chartier,</hi> only contemporaneous from 1437,
                    before which it borrows chiefly from the <hi rend="italic">Chroniqτce de la
                        Pvxelle</hi> and Le Bouvier, what it does not borrow being utterly
                    untrustworthy, published 1476-77, 1493, 1514, 1517-18, by Denis Godefroy, 1661,
                    and Vallet de Viriville, with notes, 1858; <hi rend="italic">Journal du
                        Siege</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Orléans,</hi> founded on the chronicles of
                    Berri and Jean Chartier, with a few other documents, published 1576, 1606, 1611,
                    1619, 1621, and reprinted with notes by Jacob in 1855; <hi rend="italic">la
                        Geste</hi><hi rend="italic">des nobles</hi><hi rend="italic">François,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">Chronique</hi><hi rend="italic">de Cousinot,</hi> which
                    closes with 1429, but some years afterwards was completed by a nephew of
                    Cousinot to the siege of Paris so as to form the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chronique</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Pucelle,</hi> published by Denis
                    Godefroy, 1661, by Μ. Petitot, 1825, in vol. viii. of <hi rend="italic">Mémoires
                        relatifs</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="italic">l'histoire</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de France,</hi> and with notes by Vallet de Viriville, 1859;
                        <hi rend="italic">Chronique</hi><hi rend="italic">d:Enguerran de
                        Monstrelet,</hi> first published about 1500 and very frequently afterwards,
                    English translation by Thomas Johnes, 1840, the last and best French edition,
                    that of L. Douët d’Arcq, 6 vols., 1857-62. The principal other contemporary
                    authorities are Basin’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Règnes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Charles VII. ct de Louis XI.,</hi> first published in a
                    complete form by Quicherat, with notes and life, 4 vols., 1855-1859; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Chronique Normande</hi> of Pierre Cochon, the part referring
                    to Joan published along with <hi rend="italic">Chronique</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >de la Pucelle</hi> by Vallet de Viriville, 1859, the whole by De Robillard
                    de Beaurepaire, 1870; <hi rend="italic">Chronique</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Robert</hi><hi rend="italic">Blondel,</hi> first published by Vallet de
                    Viriville, 1859; <hi rend="italic">Chronique</hi><hi rend="italic">de Jean
                        Raoult,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Chronique anonyme</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Charles VII.,</hi> first published by Vallet de Viriville, 1858; <hi
                        rend="italic">Abrégé</hi><hi rend="italic">d'</hi><hi rend="italic">Histoire
                        chronologique,</hi> by Denis Godefroy, 1661; <hi rend="italic">Le mystère du
                        Siégé d'Orléans,</hi> in verse, published from a manuscript in the Vatican
                    in <hi rend="italic">Collection de Documents</hi><hi rend="italic">inédits
                        sur</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi rend="italic">Histoire de France,</hi>
                    1862; a Latin poem by Valesan Vasanius, 1501; an anonymous Latin poem,
                    manuscript 5970 of the Imperial Library of Paris; a poem by Christine de Pisan,
                    1429, printed in 1865; Martial Auvergne, <hi rend="italic">Les Vigilles du roy
                        Charle,</hi> in verse, 1505—one hundred copies of the portion relating to
                    Joan of Arc -printed at Orleans, 1866, of which one copy is in the British
                    Museum.</p>
                <p>The earliest life by other than contemporaries is that in Latin by Jean Hordal,
                    1612. Edmond Richer, who had procured the original documents of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Procès,</hi> finished a life of Joan in 1628 which was never
                    published, but of which Lenglet-Dufresnoy made use to correct his own work,
                    published in 1754 in two volumes. Charles du Lys, a descendant of her kin,
                    published <hi rend="italic">D’</hi><hi rend="italic">l'extraction et parenté de
                        la Pucelle d'Orléans,</hi> 1611, enlarged edition 1612, 3d in 1628, all of
                    which were republished by Vallet de Viriville in <hi rend="italic">Trésor des
                        pièces rares et anciennes,</hi> 1856. In 1790 L’Averdy published an analysis
                    of the manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Procès</hi> in the 3d vol. of <hi
                        rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of the Academy or Inscriptions. The principal
                    other works previous to the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Procès</hi> are
                    those of Lebrun des Charmettes, 1817, 4 vols.; Saint-Prix, 1817; Lemaire, 1818;
                    Jollois, 1821; Dumas, 1843; De Beauregard, 1847; and the accounts by De Barante,
                    Michelet, and Sismondi in their several histories. Since the publication of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Procès</hi> the works of original critical value are <hi
                        rend="italic">Aperçus Nouveaux</hi><hi rend="italic">by</hi> J. Quicherat,
                    1850; the lives by B. Henri Martin, last ed., 1875; Wallon, I860; and Villiaumé,
                    1863. Other lives have been written by Lamartine, 1852; Lafontaine, 1854;
                    Desjardins, 1854; Michaud, 1861; Sepet, 1869. See also Vallet de Viriville, <hi
                        rend="italic">Recherches sur la famille de Jeanne</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d'Arc,</hi> 1854; <hi rend="italic">Histoire de Charles VIL,</hi> by the
                    same, 3 vols., 1862—65; De Robillard de Beaurepaire, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Recherches sur le procès de condamnation de Jeanne</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d'Arc,</hi> 1869; Boucher de Molandon, <hi rend="italic">Première
                        Expédition de Jeanne d'Arc,</hi> 1874; E. de Bouteiller, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jeanne</hi><hi rend="italic">d’Arc</hi><hi rend="italic">dans les
                        chroniques</hi><hi rend="italic">Missives</hi><hi rend="italic">de P.
                        Vigneullcs,</hi> 1878; and E. de Bouteiller and G. de Braux, <hi
                        rend="italic">Lafamille de Jeanne</hi><hi rend="italic">d’Arc,</hi> 1878,
                        <hi rend="italic">Nouvelles Recherches sur la famille de Jean</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">d'Arc,</hi> 1879, and <hi rend="italic">Notes
                        Iconographiques,</hi> 1879. The principal German works are those of Görres,
                    2d ed., 1835 (French transi., 1843); Hase, 1861; Eysell, 1861; andHirzell, 1877.
                    In English, in addition to the essays of De Quincey and Lord Mahon, there are
                    lives by Harriet Parr, 1866; Mrs Bray, 1874; and Janet Tuckey, 1880. Of the
                    numerous dramas and poems of which Joan of Arc has been the subject, mention can
                    only be made of <hi rend="italic">Die Jungfrau von Orleans</hi> of Schiller, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Joan of Arc</hi> of Southey, and the scandalous
                    burlesque-epic of Voltaire. A drama in verse by Jules Barbier has been set to
                    music by C. Gounod, 1873.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
