<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0721-0688-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JEYPORE, or Jaipur</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 688</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996964">Leveling</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n721/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JEYPORE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Jaipur</hi></label>, a
                    native state in Râjputâna, under the political superintendence of the Râjputâna
                    agency and the Government of India, lies between 25° 41' and'28° 27' N. lat. and
                    between 74° <hi rend="italic">55'</hi> and 77° 15' E. long. It is bounded on the
                    N. by Bikaner, Lohâru Jhajjar, and Patiâla; on the E. by Al war, Bhartpur, and
                    Karâuli; on the S. by Gwalior, Bundi, Tonk, and Udâipur; on the W. by
                    Kishangarh, Jodhpur, and Bikaner. Its area is 14,465 square miles. The country
                    is tolerably level and open, although its surface is diversified by groups and
                    ranges of hills and by isolated peaks. The centre of the state is an elevated
                    triangular table-land from 1400 to 1600 feet above sea-level, whose eastern
                    limitis formed by ranges running north and south. On the north and west it is
                    bounded by a broken chain of hills, an offshoot from the Aravalli mountains,
                    which forms the apex of the triangle. To the east, beyond the hills, the country
                    becomes gradually more open as it spreads out towards the alluvial flats of the
                    Jumna. On the north-west stretches the sandy and desert tract of Shaikhawati (or
                    the country of the Shaikhawat clan). The general drainage of Jeypore from the
                    central table-land is to the east and south-east, though a few streams follow
                    the slope to the north-west. Those flowing south are the Banâs and the Bangangâ,
                    the tributary of the Jumna, and their tributaries, the Aman-i-shâh, Bândi,
                    Moril, Dùnd, and Khari. The Sabi and Kâotli flow north. In the south of the
                    state, water is everywhere found at a depth varying from a few feet to 30 or 40
                    feet; but in Shaikhawati water is always at a great depth, averaging from 80 to
                    100 feet. The soil is generally sandy. The hills are more or less covered with
                    jungle trees, of no value except for fuel. The hill ranges are said to consist
                    in the north chiefly of granite, and in the south and east of sandstones, mixed
                    sometimes with white and black marble, and occasionally with mica. Copper ore
                    and cobalt are found. Salt is largely manufactured and exported from the Sambhar
                    Lake, the average yearly turn-out amounting to nearly 40,000 tons.</p>
                <p>In Shaikhawati there is generally but one crop in the year, consisting chiefly of
                    <hi rend="italic">bfjra, mung,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">moth.</hi> In the
                    north, besides these, a little wheat and barley are grown. Towards the south and
                    east, as the soil becomes richer and firmer, <hi rend="italic">jodr,</hi> Indian
                    corn, cotton, <hi rend="italic">til,</hi> wheat, barley, gram, sugar-cane,
                    opium, tobacco, <hi rend="italic">ddl,</hi> and linseed are extensively grown.
                    Since 1868 the state has spent £5000 annually on irrigation.</p>
                <p>In the absence of a census the population has been roughly estimated at about If
                    millions for the whole territory, with the following proportions of the various
                    classes :—Rajputs, ⅛; Hindus, ⅞; Mahometans, <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅞;
                    Jains <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅛. The most notable feature in the commerce
                    of the state is the large banking and exchange business carried on at the
                    capital and in the large towns. The chief manufactures are marble sculpture,
                    enamel work done on gold, woollen cloths and fabrics. Education has made great
                    progress in the state. Jeypore city is the site of a college, with a daily
                    attendance (1876) of 800 students; also of a school for the sons of thakιirs and
                    higher officials, and a Sanskrit college and industrial school. In the district
                    there are 33 elementary schools, wholly supported by the state, and 379
                    indigenous schools, with an aggregate attendance of nearly 8000. The coins
                    minted at Jeypore are distinguished from those of other independent states by
                    the <hi rend="italic">jhαr</hi> or sprig on the reverse. The Râjputâna State
                    Railway on the metre gauge runs from Agra to Jeypore city, and thence to Ajrnir
                    and Nusseerâbâd. The military force of the state consists of 824 artillerymen,
                    4450 cavalry, and 15,858 infantry. The number of forts is 38, with an aggregate
                    of 220 guns of all calibres. Some £700,000 from the revenues of the state are
                    alienated in <hi rend="italic">jâgirs</hi> and religion grants, but the
                    available receipts are about £475,000. The climate is dry and healthy. The
                    average temperature, taken from a record of five years, is 81° Fahr. The average
                    rainfall is 25⅜ inches.</p>
                <p>The maharaja of Jeypore belongs to the Kachhwaha tribe of Rajputs, and claims
                    descent from Rama, king of Ajodhya in Oudh. Jeypore state was founded in 967 by
                    Dhola Rao, who, along with his Kachhwahas, is said to have absorbed or driven
                    out the petty chiefs. On the irruption of the Mahometans, Jeypore state had very
                    soon to succumb to them, and the Jeypore house furnished some of their most
                    distinguished generals. Among them were Man Sinh, who fought in Orissa and
                    Assam, Jâi Sinh, commonly known by his imperial title of Mirza Râjâ, whose name
                    appears in all the wars of Aurangzeb in the Deccan, and Jâi Sinh II., the famous
                    mathematician and astronomer, and the founder of Jeypore city. Towards the end
                    of the 18th century the Jâts of Bhartpur annexed a portion of the state. The
                    chief of Al war reduced the territory of Jeypore. By the end of the century the
                    state was in great confusion, distracted by internal broils, and impoverished by
                    the exactions of the Marhattâs. The disputes between the chiefs of Jeypore and
                    Jodhpur had brought both states to the verge of ruin, and Amir Khan, with the
                    Pindhâris, was exhausting the country. By a treaty in 1818 the protection of the
                    British was extended to Jeypore, and an annual tribute fixed. In 1835, on the
                    accession of the maharaja, then two years old, there was a serious disturbance
                    in the city, after which the British Government took measures to insist upon
                    order, and to reform administration as well as to support its effective action;
                    and the state has become gradually well governed and. prosperous. When the
                    mutiny broke out in 1857, the maharaja assisted the British in every way that
                    lay in his power.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jeypore,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Jàipur,</hi> capital
                    of the state of the same name, is situated in 26° 55' N. lat. and 75° 52' E.
                    long., on the Râjputâna State Railway and the Agra and Ajmere trunk road. It is
                    the largest town and the chief commercial centre of Râjputâna, and in many
                    respects the finest of modern Hindu cities. The city, which takes its name
                    (Jâinagar or Jâipur) from the famous Mahârâjâ Siwâi Jâi Sinh II., by whom it was
                    founded in 1728, stands on a small plain surrounded on all sides except the
                    south by rugged hills, the summits of which are at all important points crowned
                    with forts. At the end of the ridge, overhanging the city on the north-west, is
                    the chief defensive work, the <hi rend="italic">Nahaτgarh,</hi> or “Tiger Fort,”
                    the rock face of which is so scarped as to be inaccessible on the south or city
                    side. Jeypore is remarkable for the regularity and wideness of its streets, and
                    the architectural beauty of the mosques, temples, and private residences which
                    adorn them. From east to west the town is a little over 2 miles in length, with
                    a breadth of about 1∣ miles. The main streets are paved, and the city is lighted
                    by gas. The houses of the nobility and the citizens are in the suburbs, while
                    the mahârâjâ’s palace with its pleasure-grounds occupies the centre of the town.
                    In Jeypore there are as many as seven banking firms, w hose aggregate annual
                    business amounts to about £2,500,000, and which possess a capital of upwards of
                    £6,000,000 sterling. Besides these, there are several minor houses, whose
                    collective business may be estimated at £500,000 a year. Exchange and banking
                    form the greater portion of the business of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n722/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0722-0689"/> the place. The city is well provided with
                    hospitals, dispensaries, alms-houses, and schools. One of the most interesting
                    antiquities of the state is the Hindu observatory in the capital, erected by the
                    founder of the city.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>On
                    the summit of a range of hills, about a mile and a half east of Jeypore town, is
                    a sacred shrine called the “Gulta,” where there is a temple dedicated to
                    “Surya,” or the Sun-god. Below the platform a spring issues, which pours over
                    the rock by a fall of 70 feet into the valley below. The water of this spring is
                    considered peculiarly sacred by the Brâhmans.</p></note> The population in 1870
                    was 137,847.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
