<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0657-0630-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JEROME, St (9th edition, volume 13, page 630)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106878">Scholars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn1111w">Scholars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n657/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JEROME, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(Hieronymus,</hi> in full <hi rend="smallcaps">Eusebius
                        Sophronius Hieronymus),</hi> was born at Strido (modern Strigaul), a town on
                    the border of Dalmatia fronting Pannonia, destroyed by the Goths in 377 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Some authorities, following Prosper’s chronicle,
                    give 330 or 331 as the date of his birth, but from certain passages in his
                    writings it is more probable that he was not born till 340. or 342. He says, for
                    example, that he was a boy learning grammar when Julian died; but Julian died in
                    363, and Jerome would scarcely call himself a boy if he had been thirty-three
                    years old. What is known of Jerome has mostly been recovered from his own
                    writings, for he was a gossiping sort of man, and biographers have only to
                    string together extracts from his epistles and prologues to get a very good
                    account of his life. His parents were Christians, orthodox though living among
                    people mostly Arians, and wealthy. He was at first educated at home, Bonosus, a
                    life-long friend, sharing his boyish studies, and was afterwards sent to Rome to
                    perfect his education. Donatus, whose Latin grammar was to be the plague of
                    generations of mediaeval school-boys from St Andrews to Prague till Corderius
                    and the Reformation drove it out, taught him grammar and explained the Latin
                    poets. Victorinus taught him rhetoric. He attended the law-courts, and listened
                    to the Roman advocates pleading in the Forum. He went to the schools of
                    philosophy, and heard lectures on Plato, Diogenes, Clitomachus, and Carneades;
                    the conjunction of names shows how philosophy had become a dead tradition. His
                    Sundays were spent in the catacombs in discovering graves of the martyrs and
                    deciphering inscriptions. Pope Liberius baptized him in 360; three years later
                    the news of the death of the emperor Julian the Apostate came to Rome, and
                    Christians felt relieved from a great dread.</p>
                <p>When his student days were over Jerome returned to Strido, but did not stay there
                    long. His character was formed. He was a scholar, with a scholar’s tastes and
                    cravings for knowledge, easily excited, bent on scholarly discoveries. From
                    Strido he went to Aquileia, where he formed some friendships among the monks of
                    the large monastery there, the most notable being his acquaintance with Rutinus,
                    with whom he was destined to quarrel bitterly over the question of Origen’s
                    orthodoxy and worth as a commentator; for Jerome was a man who always sacrificed
                    a friend to an opinion, and when he changed sides in a controversy expected his
                    acquaintances to follow him. From Aquileia he went to Gaul, visiting in turn the
                    principal places in that country, from Narbonne and Toulouse in the south to
                    Treves on the north-east frontier. He stayed some time at Treves studying and
                    observing, and it was there that he first began to think seriously upon divine
                    things. From Treves he returned to Strido, and from Strido to Aquileia. He
                    settled down to literary work in Aquileia, and composed there his first original
                    tract, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Muliere septies percussa,</hi>
                    in the form of a letter to his friend Innocentius. Some quarrel, no one knows
                    what, caused him to leave Aquileia suddenly; and with some companions,
                    Innocentius, Evagrius, and Heliodorus being among them, he started for a long
                    tour in the East. The epistle to Rufinus (3d in Vallarsi’s enumeration) tells us
                    the route. They went through Thrace, visiting Athens, Bithynia, Galatia, Pontus,
                    Cappadocia, and Cilicia, to Antioch, Jerome observing and making notes as they
                    went. He was interested in the theological disputes and schisms in Galatia, in
                    the two languages spoken in Cilicia, &amp;c. At Antioch the party remained some
                    time. Innocentius died of a fever, and Jerome was dangerously ill. This illness
                    brought him face to face with death; he experienced conversion, and resolved to
                    renounce whatever kept him back from God. His greatest temptation was the study
                    of the literature of pagan Rome. In his dreams God reproached him with caring
                    more to be a Ciceronian than a Christian. He disliked the uncouth style of the
                    Scriptures. “O Lord,” he prayed, “Thou knowest that whenever I have and study
                    secular MSS. I deny Thee,” and he made a resolve henceforth to devote his
                    scholarship to the Holy Scripture. “David was to be henceforth his Simonides,
                    Pindar, and Alcaeus, his Flaccus, Catullus, and Severus.” Fortified by these
                    resolves he betook himself to a hermit life in the wastes of Chalcis. Chalcis
                    was the Thebaid or the Marseilles of Syria. Great numbers of monks, each in
                    solitary cell, spent lonely lives, scorched by the sun, ill-clad and scantily
                    fed, pondering on portions of Scripture or copying MSS. to serve as objects of
                    meditation. Jerome at once set himself to such scholarly work as the place
                    afforded. He discovered and copied MSS., and began to study Hebrew. There also
                    he wrote the life of St Paul of Thebes, probably an imaginary tale embodying the
                    facts of the monkish life around him. Just then the Meletian schism, which had
                    to do with the relation of the orthodox to Arian bishops and to those baptized
                    by Arians, distressed the church at Antioch, and Jerome as usual eagerly joined
                    the fray. Here as elsewhere he had but one rule to guide him in matters of
                    doctrine and discipline,—the practice of Rome and the West; for it is singular
                    to see how Jerome, who is daringly original in points of scholarly criticism,
                    was simply a ruthless partisan in all other matters; and, having discovered what
                    was the Western practice, he set tongue and pen to work with his usual
                    bitterness <hi rend="italic">(^Altercatio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Luciferiani</hi><hi rend="italic">et Orthodoxi).</hi> From Antioch he went
                    to Constantinople, where he met with the great eastern scholar and theologian
                    Gregory of Nazianzus, and with his aid tried to perfect himself in Greek. The
                    result of his studies there was the translation of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Clιronicon</hi> of Eusebius, with a continuation,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Comp. Schoene’s critical edition (Berlin,
                            1866, 1875).</p></note> of twenty-eight homilies of Origen on Jeremiah
                    and Ezekiel, and of nine homilies of Origen on the Visions of Isaiah.</p>
                <p>In 381 Meletius died, and Pope Damasus interfered in the dispute at Antioch,
                    hoping to end it. Jerome was called to Rome in 382 to give help in the matter,
                    and was made secretary during the investigation. His work brought him into
                    intercourse with this great pontiff, who soon saw what he could best do, and how
                    his vast scholarship might be made of use to the church. Damasus suggested to
                    him to revise the existing Latin translation of the Bible; and to this task he
                    henceforth devoted his great abilities (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bible).</hi> At
                    Rome were published the Gospels (with a dedication to Pope Damasus, an
                    explanatory introduction, and the canons of Eusebius), the rest of the New
                    Testament, and the version of the Psalms from the LXX. text, known as the <hi
                        rend="italic">Psalterium Pomanum,</hi> which was followed in 385 by the <hi
                        rend="italic">Psalt.</hi><hi rend="italic">Gallicanum,</hi> based on the
                    Hexaplar Greek text. These scholarly labours, however, did not take up his whole
                    time, and it was almost impossible for Jerome to be long anywhere without
                    getting into a dispute. He was a zealous defender of that monastic life which
                    was beginning to take such a large place in the church of the 4th century, and
                    he found enthusiastic disciples among the Roman ladies. A number of widows and
                    maidens met together in the house of Marcella to study the Scriptures with him;
                    he taught them Hebrew, and preached the virtues of the celibate life. His
                    arguments and exhortations may be gathered from many of his epistles and from
                    his tract <hi rend="italic">Adversus Helvidium,</hi> in which he defends the
                    perpetual virginity of the Virgin Mary <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n658/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0658-0631"/> against Helvidius, who maintained that Mary
                    bore children to Joseph. His influence over these ladies alarmed their
                    relations, and excited the suspicions of the regular priesthood and of the
                    populace, but while Pope Damasus lived Jerome remained secure. Damasus died,
                    however, in 384, and was succeeded by Siricius, who did not show much friendship
                    for Jerome. He found it expedient to leave Rome and set out for the East in 385.
                    His letters (especially Ep. 45) are full of outcries against his enemies and of
                    indignant protestations that he had done nothing unbecoming a Christian, that he
                    had taken no money, nor gifts great nor small, that he had no delight in silken
                    attire, sparkling gems, or gold ornaments, that no matron moved him unless by
                    penitence and fasting, &amp;c. His route is given in the third book <hi
                        rend="italic">In Pufηum∙,</hi> he went by Rhegium and Cyprus, where he was
                    entertained by Bishop Epiphanius, to Antioch. There he was joined by two wealthy
                    Roman ladies, Paula, a widow, and Eustochium her daughter, one of Jerome’s
                    Hebrew students. They came accompanied by a band of Roman maidens vowed to live
                    a celibate life in a nunnery in Palestine. Accompanied by these ladies Jerome
                    made the tour of Palestine, carefully noting with a scholar’s keenness the
                    various places mentioned in Holy Scripture. The results of this journey may be
                    traced in his translation with emendations of the book of Eusebius on the
                    situation and names of Hebrew places, written probably three years afterwards,
                    when he had settled down at Bethlehem. From Palestine Jerome and his companions
                    went to Egypt, remaining some time in Alexandria; and they visited the convents
                    in the Nitrian desert. Jerome’s mind was evidently full of anxiety about his
                    translation of the Old Testament, for we find him in his letters recording the
                    conversations he had with learned men about disputed readings and doubtful
                    renderings; Didymus of Alexandria appears to have been most useful. When they
                    returned to Palestine they all settled at Bethlehem, where Paula built four
                    monasteries, three for nuns and one for monks. She was at the head of the
                    nunneries until her death in 404, when Eustochium succeeded her; Jerome presided
                    over the fourth monastery. In this monastery at Bethlehem Jerome did most of his
                    literary work and, throwing aside his unfinished plan of a translation from
                    Origen’s Hexaplar text, translated the Old Testament directly from the Hebrew,
                    with the aid of Jewish scholars. He mentions a rabbi from Lydda, a rabbi from
                    Tiberias, and above all Rabbi Ben Anina, who came to him by night secretly for
                    fear of the Jews. Jerome was not familiar enough with Hebrew to be able to
                    dispense with such assistance, and he makes the synagogue responsible for the
                    accuracy of his version: “Let him who would challenge aught in this
                    translation,” he says, “ask the Jews.” The result of all this labour was the
                    Latin translation of the Scriptures which, in spite of much opposition from the
                    more conservative party in the church, afterwards became the Vulgate or
                    authorized version; but the Vulgate as we have it now is not exactly Jerome’s
                    Vulgate, for it suffered a good deal from changes made under the influence of
                    the older translations; the text became very corrupt during the Middle Ages, and
                    in particular all the Apocrypha, except Tobit and Judith, which Jerome
                    translated from the Chaldee, were added from the older versions.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Vercellone, <hi
                                rend="italic">Variae</hi><hi rend="italic">Lectiones</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Vulgatae,</hi> Rome, 1860, 1864
                        (unfinished).</p></note></p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the labour involved in translating the Scriptures, Jerome found
                    time to do a great deal of literary work, and also to indulge in violent
                    controversy. Earlier in life he had a great admiration for Origen, and
                    translated many of his works, and this lasted after he had settled at</p>
                <p>Bethlehem, for he translated in 389 Origen’s homilies on Luke; but he came to
                    change his opinion and wrote violently against the admirers of the great
                    Alexandrian scholar, <hi rend="italic">Contra Joannem</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Hierosolymitanum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Adversus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Kufiηum Lib. III.,</hi> for both John, bishop of Jerusalem, and Rufinus,
                    Jerome’s old friend, were followers of Origen. At Bethlehem also he found time
                    to finish <hi rend="italic">Didymi de</hi><hi rend="italic">Spiritu
                        Sancto</hi><hi rend="italic">Liber,</hi> a translation begun at Rome at the
                    request of Pope Damasus, to denounce the revival of Gnostic heresies by
                    Jovinianus and Vigilantius <hi rend="italic">(Adv. ^Tovinianum Lib. II.</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Contra</hi><hi rend="italic">Vigilantium</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Liber),</hi> and to repeat his admiration of the hermit life
                    in his <hi rend="italic">Vita S. Hilarioηis</hi><hi rend="italic">Eremitae,</hi>
                    in his <hi rend="italic">Vita Malchi</hi><hi rend="italic">Monachi Captivi,</hi>
                    in his translation of the Rule of St Pachomius (the Benedict of Egypt), and in
                    his <hi rend="italic">S.</hi><hi rend="italic">Pachomii</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        S. Theodorici Epistolae</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Verba</hi><hi rend="italic">Mystica.</hi> He also wrote at Bethlehem <hi
                        rend="italic">De Vims</hi><hi rend="italic">illustribus sive</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Scriptonbus</hi><hi rend="italic">Ecclesiasticis,</hi> a
                    church history in biographies, ending with the life of the author; <hi
                        rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Nominibus Hebraicis,</hi> compiled
                    from Philo and Origen; and <hi rend="italic">De Situ</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        Nominibus Locorum Hebraicorum.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Compare the critical edition of these two works in
                            Lagarde’s <hi rend="italic">Onornastica Sacra,</hi> Gotting., 1870.
                            .</p></note> At the same place, too, he wrote <hi rend="italic"
                        >Quaes-</hi><hi rend="italic">tiones</hi><hi rend="italic">Hebraicae</hi> on
                        Genesis,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                            Lagarde’s edition appended to his <hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">Graece,</hi> Leipsic, 1868.</p></note> and a series of
                    commentaries on Isaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Daniel, the Twelve Minor Prophets,
                    Matthew, and the Epistles of St Paul. Jerome engaged in the Pelagian controversy
                    with more than even his usual bitterness <hi rend="italic">(Dialogi</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">contra Pelagianos)</hi>; and it is said that the violence of
                    his invective so provoked his opponents that an armed mob attacked the
                    monastery, and that Jerome was forced to flee and to remain in concealment for
                    nearly two years. He returned to Bethlehem in 418, and after a lingering illness
                    died on September 30, 420.</p>
                <p>By far the best edition of Jerome’s works is that of Vallarsi (Verona, 1734-42),
                    which contains in prefaces and appendices almost all that is known of the great
                    Western scholar. The student will find the article on “Hieronymus” by Colin in
                    Erseh and Gruber’s <hi rend="italic">Encyclopädie</hi> very useful, and the
                    English reader will find a succinct account of his writings taken from Vallarsi
                    in Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Diet, of Greek and Roman Biography and
                        Mythology,</hi> art. ‘ ‘ Hieronymus.” (T. Μ. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
