<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0821-0788-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JUSTICE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 788</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:830288">Benches</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:936106">Functions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n821/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JUSTICE</label>, in law, has long been the official title of
                    the judges of two of the English superior courts of common law, and it is now
                    extended to all the judges in the Supreme Court of Judicature—a judge in the
                    High Court of Justice being styled Mr Justice, and in the Court of Appeal Lord
                    Justice. Before the Judicature Act the Queen’s Bench and the Common Pleas were
                    each presided over by a lord chief <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n822/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0822-0789"/> justice, and the lord chief justice of the
                    Queen’s Bench was nominal head of all the three courts, and held the title of
                    Lord Chief Justice of England. The titles of Lord Chief Justice of the Common
                    Pleas and Lord Chief Baron have recently been abolished, and all the common law
                    divisions of the High Court are united into the Queen’s Bench division, the
                    president of which is the lord chief justice of England.</p>
                <p>The lord chief justice of England or of the Queen’s Bench .traces his descent
                    from the justiciar of the Norman kings. This officer appears first as the
                    lieutenant or deputy of the king, exercising all the functions of the regal
                    office in the .absence of the sovereign. “In this capacity William Fitz-Osbern,
                    the steward of Normandy, and Odo of Bayeux, acted during the Conqueror’s visit
                    to the Continent in 1067; they were left, according to William of Poitiers, the
                    former to govern the north of England, the latter to hold rule in Kent, <hi
                    rend="italic">vice sua ∙,</hi> Florence of Worcester describes them as “custodes
                    Angliae,” and Ordericus Vitalis gives to their office the name of “praefectura.”
                    It would seem most probable that William Fitz-Osbern at least was left in his
                    character of steward, and that the Norman seneschalship was thus the origin of
                    the English justiciarship,” Stubbs’s <hi rend="italic">Constitutional
                    History,</hi> vol. i. p. 346. The same authority observes that William of
                    Warenne and Richard of Bien-faite, who were left in charge of England in 1074,
                    are named by a writer in the next generation “praecipui Angliae justitiarii”;
                    but he considers the name to have not yet been definitely attached to any
                    particular office, and that there is no evidence to show that officers appointed
                    to this trust exercised any functions at all when the king was at home, or in
                    his absence exercised supreme judicial authority to the exclusion of other high
                    officers of the court. The office became permanent in the reign of William
                    Rufus, .and in the hands of Ranulf Flambard it became coextensive with the
                    supreme powers of government. For some time, however, the title of justiciar
                    seems not to have been •definitely appropriated to this high minister. Judges of
                    the curia regis were occasionally so named, and it was not till the reign of
                    Henry II. that the chief officer of the crown acquired the exclusive right to
                    the title of <hi rend="italic">capitalis</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >totins</hi><hi rend="italic">Angliae, justitiarûis.</hi> Canon Stubbs considers
                    that the English form of the office is to be accounted for by the king’s desire
                    to prevent the administration falling into the hands of an hereditary noble. The
                    early justiciars were •clerics, in whom the possession of power could not become
                    hereditary. The justiciar continued to be the chief officer of state, next to
                    the king, until the fall of Hubert de Burgh (in the reign of King John),
                    described by Mr Stubbs as the last of the great justiciars. Henceforward,
                    according to Mr Stubbs, the office may be regarded as virtually extinct, or it
                    may be said to have survived only in the judicial functions, which were merely
                    part of the official character I of the chief justiciar. He was at the head of
                    the curia i regis, which was separating itself into the three historical ∣courts
                    of common law about the time when the justiciarship I was falling from the
                    supreme place. The chancellor took I the place of the justiciar in council, the
                    treasurer in the ιexchequer, while the two offshots from the curia regis, the
                    [Common Pleas and the Exchequer, received chiefs of their I own. The Queen’s
                    Bench represented the original stock of [the curia regis, and its chief justice
                    the great justiciar. The justiciar may, therefore, be said to have become from a
                    political a purely judicial officer. A similar development ,awaited his
                    successful rival the chancellor.</p>
                <p>I The lord chief justice is, next to the lord chancellor, the highest judicial
                    dignitary in the kingdom. The office is .generally the prize of the chief law
                    officer of the Government, and political considerations, therefore, enter
                    largely into the appointment. But the chief justices have been generally worthy
                    of their great position. The list of them contains the names of some of the
                    greatest masters of the common law, among whom pre-eminent rank must be assigned
                    to Hale, Coke, Holt, Mansfield, and Cockburn. Lord Campbell has written the <hi
                    rend="italic">Lives of the Chief Justices,</hi> in 3 vols. A list of the lords
                    chief justices will be found in Haydn’s <hi rend="italic">Book of
                    Dignities,</hi> 1851. Robert de Brus, said by Fox to be the first judge who took
                    the distinctive title of lord chief justice of the King’s Bench (1268), was the
                    grandfather of Robert the Bruce, king of Scotland.</p>
                <p>In the United States the supreme court consists of a chief justice and eight
                    associate justices, any five of whom make a quorum. The salary of the chief
                    justice is $10,500, and that of the associates $10,000.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
