<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0591-0566-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JANSENISM (9th edition, volume 13, page 566)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:981348">Jansenists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056638">Pelagianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2s98r">Augustinians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n591/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JANSENISM</label>. The <hi rend="italic">Augustinus,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">seu doctrina</hi><hi rend="italic">S.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Augustini</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">humanae</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">naturae sanitate,</hi><hi rend="italic">aegritudine,
                        et</hi><hi rend="italic">medicina, adversus Pelagianos et Massilienses</hi>
                    of Jansen, published in 1640, is a work in three folio volumes. The first of
                    these is devoted to an historical exposition of the Pelagian and Massilian
                    (semi-Pelagian) heresies; the second sets forth the Augustinian doctrine as to
                    the state of innocence and the fallen state; while the third treats, in ten
                    books, of the grace of Christ the Saviour. The sting of the work is to be found
                    mainly in the epilogue, which draws a parallel, in various particulars, between
                    the errors of the Massilians and those “recentiorum quorundam,” the Jesuits
                    being referred to. Its bearing upon previous controversy had become well known
                    long before its publication; and while it was still in the press at Louvain
                    strenuous efforts were made by the Jesuit party there, through the papal
                    internuncio, to induce the university to prohibit its appearance, on the ground
                    that various popes had forbidden that anything should be written on the delicate
                    subject of the grace of God without express papal permission. These efforts not
                    only failed to attain their immediate object, but had the effect of greatly
                    stimulating public interest in the <hi rend="italic">Augustinus</hi> when it
                    appeared; and as soon as it arrived in Paris it was forthwith reprinted with the
                    written approval of six of the most eminent doctors of the faculty of theology
                    there. In 1641 the reading of the book, thus flung into the arena of theological
                    controversy and ecclesiastical intrigue, was prohibited by the Inquisition; no
                    opinion, however, was pronounced as to its doctrine, and the counter-agitation
                    of the Jesuits in relation to it was condemned as inconsistent with the spirit
                    of the papal injunctions already referred to. But the dispute did not admit of
                    being thus quietly repressed, and accordingly, in 1643, the bull <hi
                        rend="italic">In emiηeιιti</hi> of Urban VIII. was published, renewing and
                    confirming the constitutions of Pius V. and Gregory XIII., as well as the
                    decrees of Paul V. and of himself, and forbidding the reading of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Augustinus,</hi> not only on the ground that its appearance
                    had not been sanctioned, but also because it contained various errors. This bull
                    encountered a very general resistance in the Netherlands, on the part both of
                    the university of Louvain and of the clergy at large; but ultimately, through
                    the intervention of the Spanish Government, it was accepted (1651), subscription
                    to it, however, not being insisted on. At the Sorbonne also it was badly
                    received, and the dissatisfaction it had caused in France found expression in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Apology for Jansen</hi> by Arnauld in 1644, which was
                    followed by a second in 1645. The strength of these <hi rend="italic"
                        >Apologies</hi> lying largely in the fact that no particular doctrines of
                    Jansenius had been condemned as heretical in the papal bull, the Jesuits,
                    inflexible in their determination to secure the effectual condemnation of a book
                    which told so powerfully against their distinctive theology, immediately set
                    about obviating this weakness in their attack, and various attempts were
                    accordingly made to formulate, in the shape of definite propositions, the heresy
                    which they believed to exist. In 1646 eight such propositions were stated by
                    Habert, “théologal” of Notre Dame, to be submitted to the judgment of the pope;
                    subsequent successive adjustments reduced them in 1650 to five, which in the
                    name of eighty-five French prelates were forwarded for condemnation to Rome.
                    They were as follows :—(1) There are some commandments<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n592/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0592-0567"/> of God which just men, although willing and
                    anxious to obey them, are unable with the strength they have to fulfil, and the
                    grace by which they might fulfil them is also wanting to them; (2) in the state
                    of fallen nature inward grace is never resisted; (3) in the fallen state merit
                    and demerit do not depend on a liberty which excludes necessity, but on a
                    liberty which excludes constraint; (4) the semi-Pelagians admitted the necessity
                    of an inward prevenient grace for the performance of each particular act, and
                    also for the first act of faith, and yet were heretical inasmuch as they
                    maintained that this grace was of such a nature that the will of man was able
                    either to resist or obey it; (5) it is semi-Pelagian to say that Christ died or
                    shed His blood for all men without exception. The pope long resisted the
                    pressure with which he was urged to pronounce upon these theses in an adverse
                    sense; it is easy to understand why he should steadily have inclined to the old
                    and simple expedient of enjoining silence upon disputants on either side of the
                    controversy; for, if the Jansenist propositions had a Calvinistic ring about
                    them, there was no denying that they also admitted of au Augustinian and
                    therefore presumably of au orthodox interpretation. At length, however (May
                    1653), Innocent X. in the bull entitled <hi rend="italic">Cum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">occasione impressionis libri</hi> pronounced the first four
                    points heretical, while the fifth was declared to be false, with the addition
                    that, if it was intended to convey the meaning that Christ died only for the
                    elect, it was impious and blasphemous as well as heretical. This bull was
                    accepted and promulgated in France and the Netherlands with the royal consent,
                    and the victory of the Jesuits was quite decisive. The Jansenists still seemed
                    indeed to have one line of defence left to them; they expressed themselves
                    willing to condemn the five propositions in their heretical sense, but not as
                    propositions of Jansen. This position, however, ceased to be tenable when, in
                    September 1654, the pope declared that the propositions were found in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Augustinus</hi> of Jansen, and that their condemnation, as
                    doctrines of Jansen, was imperative. Arnauld nevertheless, with whom were the
                    other Port Royalists (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Port Royal),</hi> refused to
                    yield. In the second of his “Letters” to a person of quality (the Due de
                    Luines), he argued that, while the Holy See had authority to decide with respect
                    to doctrine, and every good Catholic owed submission not only “de respect” but
                    also “de croyance” to such determinations, yet it might be mistaken on the
                    question of “fact” whether a given book contained certain statements or not. The
                    commotion which ensued called forth in January 1656 the first and second of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Provincial Letters</hi> of Pascal, but these brilliant
                    controversial efforts did not suffice to avert the expulsion of Arnauld from the
                    Sorbonne (31st January 1656). In the following year the theological faculty of
                    Paris drew up a formula avowing full acceptance of the bull of Alexander VIL, in
                    which it had been specifically declared that the five propositions contained <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> Jansenist error. This document, sanctioned by
                    the king in 1661, the clergy and all inmates of conventual establishments were
                    called upon to sign, all who refused being treated as heretics. The leading
                    Jansenists were compelled to go into hiding, and the nuns of Port Royal were
                    subjected to imprisonment and other harsh treatment. Many of the clergy, with
                    whom were four bishops, persisted in their refusal to sign, until at last, in
                    September 1668, the compromise called the “peace of Clement IX.” was arranged,
                    in virtue of which, by the omission of a single word (“purement”), assent was no
                    longer required to the proposition that Jansen had actually taught the five
                    propositions in a “purely” heretical sense. The respite from controversy and
                    persecution thus secured was not of long duration. The Jesuits were quite unable
                    to make a moderate use of the power of which they were now so fully ascertained.
                    Arnauld was driven into Holland, where he found congenial society and apt
                    disciples in Catholic circles, and particularly at Delft. In 1705 a bull was
                    obtained from Clement XL in which the heretical character of Jansen’s teaching,
                    in Jansen’s sense, was authoritatively asserted, and thus the peace of Clement
                    IX. was destroyed. This measure ultimately led, in 1710, not only to the
                    breaking up of the establishment at Port Royal, but also to the destruction of
                    the very buildings. Louis XIV. was further induced to approach the pope for a
                    decision upon the doctrine contained in Quesnel’s <hi rend="italic">Deflexions
                        morales</hi><hi rend="italic">sur le</hi><hi rend="italic">Nouveau
                        Testament,</hi> a work of practical edification, which, published in
                    1693—94, had attained great popularity in France, and been recommended by many
                    bishops, including the cardinal-archbishop of Paris, De Noailles, but was
                    suspected of latent Jansenism. In this way the bull <hi rend="italic"
                        >Unigenitus</hi> (1713) was obtained, in which no fewer than one hundred and
                    one propositions taken from Quesnel were condemned as erroneous and heretical.
                    The result was to divide the French Church into two parties, the acceptants or
                    constitutionists, and the appellants or anti-constitutionists; but again the
                    Jesuit influence was able to secure the ultimate defeat (1728) of Nôailles and
                    his party, and in 1730 the bull was formally registered as the law of the
                    kingdom. Oppressed Jansenism now changed its method of defence. Reports of
                    miracles wrought in the cemetery of St Medard, Paris, at the grave of François
                    de Paris, a young Jansenist deacon who had died in 1727, began to be circulated;
                    and the spot became a pilgrimage centre daily visited by thousands of fanatics.
                    It was in vain that the place was walled up (giving occasion to the witty
                    epigram “De par le Roi, défense à Dieu De faire miracle en ce lieu ”); portions
                    of earth which had been taken from the grave were equally efficacious, and the
                    number of convulsionary prophets of coming ruin to the state and church
                    continued to increase. Repression by imprisonment and other violent means was
                    vainly attempted; but as the novelty of the movement wore off the excitement
                    gradually died down; and after the middle of the 18th century, the appellants or
                    Jansenists of France ceased to make any figure in the public view. Their cause
                    may be said to have been buried in the grave of François de Paris. In Holland
                    the history of the disciples of Jansen followed a different course. The
                    Catholics there, though steadfastly refusing to be called Jansenists, became
                    deeply imbued with his views; at their head was the archbishop of Utrecht, who
                    on this account was deprived by the pope in 1704. In 1723 the chapter there
                    secured the consecration of a successor (which the pope had steadily refused) by
                    an appellant bishop; in similar circumstances bishops were consecrated at
                    Haarlem and Deventer also, and the separatist church thus constituted still
                    subsists, though its members in 1869 were under 6000. Its adherents claim to be
                    disciples of St Augustine and members of the Catholic Church, of which they
                    recognize the pope as the visible head, although they deny his
                    infallibility.</p>
                <p>For the earlier stages of the history of Jansenism, see Leydecker, <hi
                        rend="italic">Histοriα Jansenismi,</hi> 1695, and the anonymous work of
                    Gerberon <hi rend="subscript"> v</hi><hi rend="italic">Histoire Générale du
                        Jansénisme,</hi> 1700. Modéra authorities are Sainte-Beuve, <hi
                        rend="italic">Port-Royal,</hi> 1840-48, 3d ed. 1867; Reuchlin, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">v. Port-Royal,</hi> 1839-44;
                    and Bouvier, <hi rend="italic">Étude</hi><hi rend="italic">critique</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sur le Jansénisme,</hi> 1864.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
