<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0587-0562-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JAMESON, Anna (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    562)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202945">Dominica</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1114160">Sex</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9781s">Sex</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n587/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JAMESON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anna</hi></label> (1794-1860),
                    was born in Dublin in 1794. Her father, Mr Brownell Murphy, who was a miniature
                    and enamel painter of some celebrity, took part in his early days in the
                    political commotions which then agitated Ireland. His removal to England in 1798
                    confined his attention fortunately to his more peaceful calling, in which he
                    attained considerable skill, but his daughter’s mind seems to have been
                    influenced in the highest sense by the circumstances that surrounded her birth;
                    she was distinguished from her tenderest years by that ardour and courage and
                    keenness to supply the needs and redress the injuries of others which marked her
                    career through life.</p>
                <p>At sixteen years of age she undertook the office of governess in the family of
                    the marquis of Winchester, and later in that of Mr Littleton, afterwards Lord
                    Hatherton. Between these two engagements she accompanied a young pupil, one of a
                    party of travellers, to Italy, a tour which gave rise to a narrative of what she
                    saw and did, written in an imaginary character. This, her first literary
                    production, the merits of which she little appreciated, did not make its
                    appearance until after her marriage with Mr Robert Jameson, a barrister, in
                    1825, when it was advertised by a friend under the title of a <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ladfs Diary,</hi> and ultimately published by Mr Colburn as <hi
                        rend="italic">The Diary of an</hi><hi rend="italic">Ennuyée.</hi> Mrs
                    Jameson’s marriage was not a happy one; but, if not more unfortunate than many
                    of her sex in this form of trial, she set the example of a rare discretion under
                    it. Her marriage troubles were made no excuse for appealing against the laws of
                    the land or the usages of society. The <hi rend="italic">Diary of an</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Ennuyée</hi> attracted much attention. Italy was no such
                    beaten ground then, nor ∙a traveller with ardent feelings for art and nature so
                    common, as both have become since. The authoress has been blamed for assuming
                    the disguise of an invalid, who dies on her way back; but such a tinge of
                    romance made no difference in the truth of her descriptions, while it procured
                    them more readers.</p>
                <p>In 1829 Mr Jameson was appointed puisne judge in the island of Dominica. It was
                    decided to be impracticable for her to accompany him, and meanwhile Mrs Jameson
                    visited the Continent again with her father. Traces of this journey appear in
                        <hi rend="italic">Visits and Sketches at Home and Abl·oad.</hi> Hitherto the
                    subjects she had treated had been limited to impressions of outer scenes and
                    passing things, or to abridgments of history, as in her good schoolbook <hi
                        rend="italic">Female Sovereigns.</hi> The first work in which her powers of
                    original thought became embodied were her <hi rend="italic">Characteristics of
                        Shakespeare's Women,</hi> which appeared in 1832. These analyses of the
                    great poet’s heroines are unsurpassed for delicacy of critical insight and
                    fineness of literary touch. They are the result of a penetrating but essentially
                    feminine mind, applied to the study of individuals of its own sex, detecting
                    characteristics and defining differences not perceived by the ordinary critic,
                    and entirely overlooked by the general reader.</p>
                <p>In 1833 Mrs Jameson paid her first visit to Germany, the literature and art of
                    which country may be said to have then first roused the curiosity of English
                    minds. Dresden and Tieck and Retsch, Frankfort and Dannecker, Weimar and, if not
                    Goethe, who had died the year before, yet the homage which more than restored
                    him to life, successively occupied her. Nor was she proof to the spell of the
                    modem German art which the late King Louis of Bavaria had evoked in his capital.
                    Those conglomerations of hard lines, cold colours, and pedantic subjects which
                    decorated Munich were new to the world, and Mrs Jameson’s enthusiasm first gave
                    them the reputation which has long since faded away.</p>
                <p>It was in 1836 that Mrs Jameson was summoned by her husband to join him in
                    Canada. She started with many a regret for the life she was leaving, and was not
                    long left in doubt as to the fruitlessness of the step. He failed to meet her,
                    even by a letter, at New York, and she was left to make her way alone at the
                    worst of seasons to Toronto. After six months’ experiment she felt it useless to
                    prolong a life far from all ties of family happiness and Opportunities of
                    usefulness. Before leaving, she undertook a journey to the depths of the Indian
                    settlements in Canada; she explored Lake Huron, and saw much of emigrant and
                    aborigines life unknown to travellers, which she afterwards embodied in her <hi
                        rend="italic">Winter Studies and Summer Rambles.</hi> She returned to
                    England in 1838. It was at this period that Mrs Jameson first devoted her
                    attention to the subject of art. She began by making careful notes of the chief
                    private collections in and near London which had hitherto received no systematic
                    description. This <hi rend="italic">Companion to the Private Galleries</hi> was
                    soon followed by the <hi rend="italic">Handbook to the Public Galleries.</hi>
                    These works were useful compilations, and had a certain circulation; but the
                    authoress laid claim to no powers of real discrimination, and many of her
                    verdicts, in which she only followed those that went before her, have been since
                    superseded by exacter knowledge. These works, however, led on to those by which
                    her literary career has been specially distinguished,—her series of <hi
                        rend="italic">Sacred and Legendary Art.</hi> The time was ripe for such
                    contributions to the traveller’s library. The <hi rend="italic">Acta
                        Sanctorum</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Rook of the Golden Legend</hi> had
                    had their readers, but no one had ever pointed out the connexion between these
                    tales and the works of Christian art. The painters employed by convent or church
                    had introduced the local or family saints according to contract, and the
                    faithful had retained the tradition of their names; but foi' the modern
                    Protestant traveller the whole was a <hi rend="italic">terra incognita.</hi> The
                    way to these studies had been pointed out in the preface to Kugler’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Handbook of Italian Painting</hi> by Sir Charles Eastlake, who
                    had intended pursuing the subject himself. Eventually he made over to Mrs
                    Jameson the materials and references he had collected. They could not have been
                    placed in better hands. She recognized the extent of the ground before her as a
                    mingled sphere of poetry, history, devotion, and art. She directed the taste of
                    her readers with judgment and even enthusiasm; and, with the same penetration
                    that had guided her in her literary tasks, she threw many a light on a master’s
                    intentions which had escaped both artists and critics.</p>
                <p>Another service Mrs Jameson rendered to the English public, and that the most
                    valuable of all, has still to be noticed. She began her literary career by
                    analysing books, she proceeded to analyse works of art, and she ended by
                    analysing society. It was a natural supplement to a course of varied personal
                    experience and no little struggle that her attention should be directed to the
                    great moral questions of the day, and especially to those affecting the
                    education, occupations, and maintenance of her own sex. Her early essay on <hi
                        rend="italic">The Relative Social Position of Mothers and Governesses</hi>
                    is a masterpiece. She knew both sides; and in no respect does she more clearly
                    prove the falseness of the position she describes than in the certainty with
                    which she predicts its eventual reform.</p>
                <p>To Mrs Jameson we owe the first popular enunciation of the principle of male and
                    female cooperation in works of mercy and education. Her mind was peculiarly to
                    be trusted with the advocacy of such tenets—it had become as clear and judicious
                    by experience as it was ardent and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n588/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0588-0563"/> vigorous by nature. In her later years she
                    took up a succession of subjects all bearing on the same principles of active
                    benevolence, and the best ways of carrying them into practice. Sisters of
                    charity, hospitals, penitentiaries, prisons, and workhouses all claimed her
                    interest—all more or less included under those definitions of “the communion of
                    love and communion of labour” which are inseparably connected with her memory.
                    To the clear and temperate forms in which she brought the results of her
                    convictions before her friends in the shape of private lectures, subsequently
                    printed, may be traced the source whence living reformers and philanthropists
                    took counsel and courage.</p>
                <p>Mrs Jameson died in March 1860. She left the last of her <hi rend="italic">Sacred
                        and Legendary Art</hi> series in preparation. It was completed, under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">The History of our Lord in Art,</hi> by Lady
                    Eastlake. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. e.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
