<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0799-0766-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">JUGURTHA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 766</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:844959">Camps</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n799/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JUGURTHA</label>. After the final conquest of Carthage by the
                    Romans in 146 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> the larger part of the north of
                    Africa was practically under Roman control. The so-called province, indeed, of
                    Africa, as then constituted, was but a small strip of territory, comprising the
                    possessions retained by Carthage during the few years previous to her downfall.
                    It coincided with the north-eastern portion of Tunis. Around it, to the west,
                    south, and east, was the region to which the Romans gave the name of Numidia,
                    the country of the “Nomads,” which stretched westwards to Mauretania, the river
                    Malucha (Malûwi), which flows into the gulf of Melillah, being here roughly its
                    boundary, and eastwards to the Great Syrtis, thus bordering on Cyrene and Egypt.
                    We may say that Numidia corresponds with what is now Algiers, the south of
                    Tunis, and Tripoli, including in addition a region of indefinite extent to the
                    south. Over this extensive territory, parts of which were rich and populous,
                    Masinissa had ruled for many years, and had rendered Rome substantial aid in her
                    war with Carthage. On his death in 149 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> his
                    sovereign power was divided under the direction of Scipio Africanus the younger,
                    the conqueror of Carthage, between his three sons Micipsa, Gulussa, and
                    Mastanabal. The actual government, however, was chiefly in the hands of an
                    illegitimate son of Mastanabal, Jugurtha. The Numidian princes were by no means
                    mere barbarous chiefs. Micipsa, though too weak to be a king, is said to have
                    been imbued with a considerable tincture of Greek philosophy, and Jugurtha’s
                    father too was a man of some literary culture. Jugurtha himself had many of the
                    qualities which command success. He was strong and active; he had a handsome
                    face and keen intelligence; he was a skilful rider, and was a thorough adept in
                    all warlike exercises. In fact, he was in many respects a very worthy grandson
                    of Masinissa, and he inherited much of his political ability and adroitness.
                    Micipsa was naturally rather afraid of him, and knowing his military tastes he
                    sent him to Spain in command of a Numidian force, to serve under Scipio, who was
                    then engaged in the war with Numantia. Jugurtha soon won Scipio’s good opinion,
                    and he became a favourite with the Roman nobles serving in the camp, some of
                    whom put into his head the idea of making himself the sole king of Numidia,
                    hinting that at Rome anything could be done for money. There was truth in the
                    hint, as subsequent events proved.</p>
                <p>In 118 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> Micipsa died. He had thought it politic to
                    adopt Jugurtha, and to provide by his will that he should be associated with his
                    own two sons, Adherbal and Hiempsal, in the government of Numidia. Scipio had
                    written to Micipsa a strong letter of recommendation in favour of Jugurtha; and
                    to Scipio, accordingly, Micipsa entrusted the execution of his will. His
                    testamentary arrangements thus had the Roman guarantee, but they utterly failed.
                    The princes soon quarrelled; and Jugurtha, who was thoroughly unscrupulous,
                    claimed the-entire kingdom. His cousin Hiempsal he contrived to have
                    assassinated; and Adherbal he quickly drove out of Numidia by force of arms,
                    compelling him to take refuge in the Roman province of Africa. He had next the
                    audacity to send envoys to Rome to defend his usurpation. Hiempsal, they were to
                    say, had been murdered by his subjects for his cruelty, and Adherbal, who was
                    now at Rome to get redress, had been himself the aggressor. The senate decided
                    that Numidia was tobe divided between the two princes, and the division, which
                    was arranged under the superintendence of Roman commissioners, gave the western,
                    the richest and most populous half of the country, to Jugurtha, while the sands
                    and deserts of the eastern half were left to Adherbal. Jugurtha’s envoys appear
                    to have found several of the Roman nobles and senators accessible to judicious
                    bribery. So far, however, was he from being satisfied with having secured the
                    best of the bargain that he at once began to molest Adherbal’s dominions and to
                    provoke him to a war of self-defence. He so completely defeated him, somewhere
                    near, it would seem, the modern Philippeville, that Adherbal sought safety in
                    Cirta (Constantina), the chief town of Numidia, and a very strong fortress. Here
                    he was besieged by J ugurtha, who, notwithstanding the interposition of a Roman
                    embassy headed by Marcus Scaurus, a leading Roman senator, ultimately forced the
                    place to capitulate, and then treacherously massacred all the inhabitants, his
                    cousin Adherbal among them, and a number of Italian merchants who had settled in
                    the town. There was great wrath at Rome and throughout all Italy; and the
                    senate, a majority of which still clung to Jugurtha in spite of the proof they
                    had just had of his atrocious treachery and cruelty, were persuaded in the same
                    year, 111 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> on the motion of the tribune Caius
                    Memmius, to allow a declaration of war against the Numidians. An army was
                    despatched to Africa under the command of the newly elected consul, Calpurnius
                    Bestia, and several of the Numidian towns voluntarily surrendered, while
                    Bocchus, the king of Mauretania, and Jugurtha’s father-in-law, offered the
                    Romans his alliance.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n800/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0800-0767"/>
                <p>Jugurtha was alarmed, but, having plenty of money at his command out of the
                    accumulated treasures of his grandfather Masinissa, he again acted on his
                    experience of Roman venality, and he was successful in arranging for himself
                    with the Roman general a peace which left him in undisturbed possession of the
                    whole of Numidia. When the facts were known at Rome, the tribune Memmius
                    insisted that Jugurtha should appear in person and be questioned as to the
                    precise nature of the negotiations. Jugurtha indeed appeared under a safe
                    conduct, but he had partisans who took care that his mouth should be closed. The
                    treaty, however, was set aside, and war was again declared, Spurius Albinus, the
                    new consul, having the command. The Roman army in Africa was thoroughly
                    demoralized, and quite unfit to take the field. An unsuccessful attempt was made
                    on a fortified town, Suthul, in which the royal treasures were deposited. Worse
                    followed: the army was surprised by the enemy in a night attack, and the camp
                    was taken and plundered. Jugurtha was master of the situation, and every Roman
                    was driven out of Numidia.</p>
                <p>By this time the feeling at Rome and in Italy against the corruption and
                    incapacity of the nobles had become so strong that prosecutions on a wholesale
                    scale struck down a number of the senators, and Bestia and Albinus were
                    sentenced to exile. The Numidian war was now entrusted to Quintus Metellus, an
                    aristocrat indeed in sentiment, but at the same time an able soldier and a stern
                    disciplinarian. With him was associated the famous Caius Marius, who had risen
                    from the rank of a centurion. The army was soon in a condition to face the
                    enemy, and from the year 109 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> to the close of the
                    war in 106 the contest was carried on with credit to the Roman arms. Jugurtha
                    was defeated in an action on the river Muthal, after an obstinate resistance and
                    a display of much military skill. Once again he even succeeded in surprising the
                    Roman camp and forcing Metellus into winter quarters. There were fresh
                    negotiations, but Metellus insisted on the surrender of the king’s person, and
                    this Jugurtha refused. Numidia on the whole seemed disposed to assert its
                    independence, and Rome had before her an indefinite prospect of a long and
                    troublesome guerilla war. The country was a particularly trying one for a
                    regular army, and a victory seemed to lead to no substantial result. Nothing
                    could be really accomplished unless Jugurtha himself could be secured; and to
                    this end negotiations, reflecting little credit on the Romans, were set on foot
                    with Bocchus, who for a time, as his interest seemed to dictate, played fast and
                    loose with both parties. The war dragged on till in 106 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> Marius was called on by the vote of the Roman people to supersede
                    Metellus. Marius found that he had a difficult work, and his army was once
                    seriously imperilled on the borders of Mauretania, whither he had led them to
                    overawe Bocchus, who had just made a.friendly treaty with Jugurtha. Shortly
                    afterwards this cunning and treacherous prince again offered his friendship to
                    the Romans, and it was through his perfidy and not by Roman skill or valour that
                    the war with Jugurtha was ended. In the final negotiations Lucius Sulla, who was
                    Marius’s quaestor and commanded the cavalry, had the honour, such as it was, of
                    winning over to the Roman side the king of Mauretania, and prevailing on him to
                    sacrifice Jugurtha. The Numidian fell into an ambush through his father-in-law’s
                    treachery, and was conveyed a prisoner to Rome. Two years afterwards, in 104 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> he figured with his two sons in Marius’s triumph,
                    and in the subterranean prisonbeneaththe Capitol, “the bath of ice,” as he
                    called it, he was either strangled or starved to death. The war had been an
                    inglorious one for Rome, and its end with all its attendant circumstances was
                    deplorably disgraceful.</p>
                <p>Jugurtha, though doubtless for a time regarded by his African and Numidian
                    countrymen as their deliverer from the yoke of Rome, mainly owes his historical
                    importance to the very full and minute account of him which we have from the
                    hand of Sallust, himself afterwards governor of Numidia. The Jugurthine war too
                    happened to coincide with a period of considerable political interest at Rome.
                    The symptoms of revolution were beginning to make themselves visible. The
                    weakness and corruption of the government of the senate was forcing itself on
                    the notice of all men, and popular opinion was becoming too strong to be
                    disregarded. One general after another had been superseded and disgraced, and
                    Marius, a man of the humblest origin, had been summoned by the public voice to
                    put an end to a war in which the incapacity and disloyalty of consuls and
                    senators had been grievously exposed. . The names of both Marius and Sulla
                    became famous for the first time in a struggle with a Numidian chief. The time
                    was clearly at hand when the old system of Rome’s govern- <hi rend="subscript">
                    ι</hi> ment could sustain itself no longer.</p>
                <p>The best modern account of Jugurtha and the Jugurthine war is to be found in
                    Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of Rome,</hi> book iv. chap. v. (W. J. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
