<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0638-0611-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JAY, John (9th edition, volume 13, page 611)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q760">Jays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:982161">Jays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015496">Meetings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n638/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1745-1829),
                    American statesman, was the descendant of a refugee Huguenot family, and was
                    born at New York, December 12, 1745. After three years spent in the house of the
                    pastor of the French church at New Rochelle, followed by four under a private
                    tutor at home, he entered King’s (now Columbia) College in 1760. On graduating
                    there, May 15, 1764, he entered the office of Mr Kissam, an eminent New York
                    lawyer; and in 1768 he was called to the bar. He rapidly rose into a lucrative
                    practice, and in 1774 was married to Sarah, youngest daughter of William
                    Livingston, afterwards governor of New Jersey. The great crisis in the fate of
                    the American colonies was fast approaching; and, like many other clever young
                    lawyers, Jay took an eager, active part in the proceedings that resulted in the
                    independence of the United States. He was one of the committee of fifty selected
                    by the citizens of New York in 1774 to correspond with other colonial committees
                    on the subject of the Boston Port Bill. He was returned as a delegate from New
                    York city to the continental Congress held at Philadelphia in September 1774,
                    and, though almost the youngest member, was entrusted with drawing up the <hi
                        rend="italic">Address to the People oj Great Britain.</hi> The numerous
                    committees and associations which were from time to time appointed to meet the
                    exigencies of that troubled period almost always included Jay’s name. Of the
                    second Congress also, which met at Philadelphia on May 10, 1775, Jay was a
                    member; and his able and eloquent pen was again useful in writing addresses to
                    the peoples of Canada and Ireland. He was a member of the secret committee of
                    Congress for corresponding with the friends of America in Europe. In April 1776,
                    while still retaining his seat in Congress, Jay was returned to the provincial
                    convention of New York by New York city and county; and his consequent absence
                    from Philadelphia deprived him of the honour of affixing his signature to the
                    declaration of independence issued on July 4, 1776. It was Jay who drafted the
                    constitution that was finally adopted by the New York convention; and that
                    statesman, after acting as one of the council of safety for some time, accepted
                    a provisional appointment as chief justice of New York State, which was
                    afterwards confirmed under the organized constitution, with the proviso that he
                    could hold with his judicial post no other save that of delegate to Congress “on
                    special occasion.” Such occasion was found in the secession of what is now the
                    State of Vermont from the jurisdiction of New Hampshire and New York. Jay was
                    sent to Congress (December 7, 1778), of which he was immediately elected
                    president. The following<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n639/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0639-0612"/> September his letter, written in the name of
                    Congress, was addressed to the people of the States on the subject of currency
                    and finance; and before the end of the year, having previously resigned his
                    chief-justiceship and his presidency, he was despatched as plenipotentiary to
                    Spain, where he landed January 22, 1780. The results of the mission were
                    unsatisfactory. In addition to the fact that he was not received by the Spanish
                    court in a formally diplomatic character, he was seriously embarrassed by the
                    action of Congress in drawing bills upon him for more than half a million
                    dollars, in the hope apparently that he would have received a subsidy from Spain
                    before the bills fell due. Although by stooping to the humiliation of
                    importuning the Spanish minister, and by accepting a number on his own personal
                    responsibility, Jay was able to meet some of the bills, he was at length forced
                    to protest others; and the credit of the new country was only saved by a timely
                    subsidy from France, out of which Franklin was enabled to remit from Paris the
                    sum required to meet the bills then due. In 1781 Jay was commissioned to act
                    with Franklin, Adams, Jefferson, and Laurens in negotiating a peace with Great
                    Britain. He arrived in Paris from Spain, June 23, 1782; and after a variety of
                    negotiations, in the course of which Jay evinced a jealous suspicion of the
                    disinterestedness of France and a punctilious attention to the dignity of his
                    country, the provisional articles were signed on November 30, 1782, and the
                    formal treaty on September 3, 1783. Jay resigned his commissions, and on July
                    24, 1784, landed as a private citizen in New York, where he was presented with
                    the freedom of the city, and elected a delegate to Congress. On May 7th the
                    last-named body had already chosen him to be foreign secretary; and in that post
                    he remained till the beginning of the Federal Government in 1789. In the
                    question of the institution of such a government he had taken a keen interest:
                    he joined Hamilton and Madison in issuing the <hi rend="italic">Federalist;</hi>
                    he published anonymously (though without succeeding in concealing the
                    authorship) <hi rend="italic">An Address to the People of Hew York,</hi> in
                    vindication of the constitution; and he ably seconded Hamilton in inducing his
                    native State to adopt it. On September 26, 1789, he became the first
                    chiefjustice of the supreme court of the United States. During one of his
                    circuits Harvard University conferred on him the degree of LL.D. In 1792 he
                    consented to stand for the governorship of New York State; but the “canvassers”
                    who scrutinized the votes disqualified the returns of three counties; and,
                    though Jay had received an actual majority of votes, his opponent General
                    Clinton was declared elected.</p>
                <p>During the war between Great Britain and France, the relations between the former
                    and the American States became critical; a definite commercial treaty seemed the
                    only means of averting war. Chief-Justice Jay was chosen envoy to England,
                    though not without strong opposition. He landed at Falmouth in June 1794, signed
                    a treaty with Lord Grenville on November 19, and disembarked again at New York,
                    May 28, 1795. Several of the articles of “Jay’s Treaty,” especially that which
                    declared that a free ship did not make free cargo, were hailed at home with
                    furious denunciation. Jay was accused of having betrayed his country; his effigy
                    was burnt along with copies of the treaty, and even after Washington signed the
                    ratification in August, the States were in a ferment that prevented for a time
                    the really beneficial action of the treaty. Two days before he landed, and
                    before the particulars of the treaty had been published, Jay had been
                    triumphantly returned as governor of his native State, and, notwithstanding his
                    temporary unpopularity, he was reelected in April 1798. With the close of this
                    second term of office in 1801, he closed his public career. Although not yet
                    fifty-six years old, he refused all offers of office, and, retiring to his
                    estate near Bedford in Westchester county, New York, spent the rest of his life
                    in rarely interrupted seclusion. His public utterances from 1821 till 1828 were
                    mostly as president of the American Bible Society. On May 17, 1829, John Jay, in
                    his eighty-fourth year, ended a life whose purity and integrity are commemorated
                    in a sentence by Daniel Webster: “When the spotless ermine of the judicial robe
                    fell on John Jay, it touched nothing less spotless than itself.”</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Life of John Jay, with Selections from his Correspondence
                        and Miscellaneous Papers,</hi> was published in 2 vols, by his son William
                    Jay in 1833.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
