<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0882-0847-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FAIR (9th edition, volume 8, page 847)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1226682">Albania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919892">Fairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919882">Fairings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919888">Fairness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010316">Markets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6bb1s">Tolls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n882/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FAIR</label>. A fair is defined as a “greater species of
                    market recurring at more distant intervalsboth have been distinguished by Lord
                    Coke from “mart,” which he considers as a greater species of fair; and all three
                    may comprehensively be described as customary or legalized public places for the
                    sale of commodities (including labour). Thus, in England, no fair can be held
                    without a grant from the sovereign, or prescription which presupposes such
                    grant. In France, the establishment and abolition of fairs— with the exception
                    of cattle markets and the markets of the metropolis—are generally left to the
                    discretion of the departmental prefects. The most commonly accepted derivation
                    of the word fair is from <hi rend="italic">ferice,</hi> a name which the church
                    borrowed from Roman custom and applied to her own festivals. A fair was
                    generally held during the period of a saint’s feast, and in the precincts of his
                    church or abbey —the time and the place of the chief popular assemblages; but in
                    England this desecration of church and churchyard was first forbidden by the
                    statutes of Henry III. and Edward II. Most of the famous fairs of mediaeval
                    England and Europe, with their tolls or other revenues, and, within certain
                    limits of time and place, their monopoly of trade, were grants from the
                    sovereign to abbots, bishops, and other ecclesiastical dignitaries. Their “holy
                    day” associations are preserved in the German word for fairs, <hi rend="italic"
                    >messen;</hi> as also in the <hi rend="italic">kirmiss,</hi> “church mass,” of
                    the people of Brittany. So very intimate was the connexion between the fair and
                    the feast of the saint that the former has very commonly been regarded as an
                    off-shoot or development of the latter. Nevertheless, there are grounds for the
                    supposition that fairs were already existing national institutions, long before
                    the church turned or was privileged to turn them to her own profit. The first
                    charter of the great fair of Stourbridge, near Cambridge, was granted by King
                    John, for the maintenance of a leper hospital; but the origin of the fair itself
                    is ascribed to Carausius, the rebel emperor of Britain, 207 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >\.d.</hi> At all events, it may be seen from the <hi rend="italic">data</hi>
                    given in Mr Herbert Spencer’s <hi rend="italic">Descriptive Sociology</hi> that
                    the country had then arrived at the stage of development where fairs might have
                    been recognized as a necessity, The Romans also appear to have elaborated a
                    market law similar to that in force throughout mediaeval Europe— though it must
                    be observed that the Roman <hi rend="italic">nundince,</hi> which some have
                    regarded as fairs, were weekly markets. It has also been supposed that the
                    ancient fairs of Lyons were a special privilege granted by the Roman conquerors;
                    and Sidonius Apollinaris, 427 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> alludes to the
                    fairs of the district afterwards known as the county of Champagne, as if they
                    were then familiarly known institutions. Fairs, in a word, would not only have
                    arisen naturally, wherever the means of communication between individual centres
                    of production and consumption were felt to be inadequate to the demand for an
                    interchange of commodities; but, from their very nature, they might be expected
                    to show somo essential resemblances, even in points of legislation, and where no
                    international transmission of custom could have been possible. Thus, the fair
                    courts of pre-Spanish Mexico corresponded very closely to those under whose
                    supervision the Beaucaire fair is conducted in the present day. They resembled
                    our own courts of piepowder. The Spaniards, when first they saw the Mexican
                    fairs, were reminded of the like institutions in Salamanca and Granada. The
                    great fair or market at the city of Mexico is said to have been attended by
                    about 40,000 or 50,000 persons, and is thus described by Prescott:—</p>
                <p>“Officers patrolled the square, whose business it was to keep the peace, to
                    collect the dues imposed on the various kinds of merchandise, to see that no
                    false measures or fraud of any kind were used, and to bring offenders at once to
                    justice. A court of twelve judges sat in one part of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >tianguez</hi> clothed with those ample and summary powers which, in despotic
                    countries, are often delegated even to petty tribunals. The extreme severity
                    with which they exercised those powers, in more than one instance, proves that
                    they were not a dead letter.”</p>
                <p>But notwithstanding the great antiquity of fairs, their charters are
                    comparatively modern—the oldest known being that of St Denys, Paris, which
                    Dagobert, king of the Franks, granted (642 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> to
                    the monks of the place “for the glory of God, and the honour of St Denys at his
                    festival.” The first recorded grant in England appears to be that of William the
                    Conqueror to the bishop of Winchester, for leave to hold an annual “free fair”
                    at St Giles’s hill. The monk who had been the king’s jester received his charter
                    of Bartholomew fair, Smithfield, in the year 1133. And in 1248 Henry III.
                    granted a like privilege to the abbot of Westminster, in honour of the
                    “translation” of Edward the Confessor. Sometimes fairs were granted to towns as
                    a means for enabling them to recover from the effects of war and other
                    disasters. Thus, Edward III. granted a “free fair” to the town of Burnley in
                    Rutland, just as, in subsequent times, Charles VII. favoured Bordeaux, after the
                    English wars, and Louis XIV. gave fair charters to the towns of Dieppe and
                    Toulon. The importance attached to these old fairs may be understood from the
                    inducements which, in the 14th century, Charles IV. held out to traders visiting
                    the great fair of Frankfort-on-the-Maine. The charter declared that both during
                    the continuance of the fair, and for eighteen days before and after it,
                    merchants would be exempt from imperial taxation, from arrest for debt, or civil
                    process of any sort, except such as might arise from the transactions of the
                    market itself and within its precincts. Philip of Valois’s regulations for the
                    fairs of Troyes in Champagne might not only be accepted as a fair type of all
                    subsequent fair-legislation of the kingdom, but even of the English and German
                    laws on the subject. The fair had its staff of notaries for the attestation of
                    bargains, its court of justice, its police officers, its sergeants for the
                    execution of the market judges’ decrees, and its visitors— of whom we may
                    mention the <hi rend="italic">prud' hommes,—</hi> whose duty it was to examine
                    the quality of goods exposed for sale, and to confiscate those found unfit for
                    consumption. The confiscation<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n883/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0883-0848"/> required the consent of five or six
                    representatives of the merchant community at the fair. The effect of these great
                    “free fairs” of England and the Continent on the development of society was
                    indeed great. They helped to familiarize the western and northern countries with
                    the banking and financial systems of the Lombards and Florentines, who resorted
                    to them under the protection of the sovereign’s “firm peace,” and the ghostly
                    terrors of the pope. They usually became the seat of foreign agencies. In the
                    names of her streets Provins preserved the memory of her 12th century
                    intercourse with the agents and merchants of Germany and the Low Countries, and
                    long before that time the Syrian traders at St Denys had established their
                    powerful association in Paris. Like the church on the religious side, the free
                    fairs on the commercial side evoked and cherished the international spirit. And
                    during long ages, when commercial “protection” was regarded as indispensable to
                    a nation’s wealth, and the merchant was compelled to “fight his way through a
                    wilderness of taxes,” they were the sole and, so far as they went, the complete
                    substitute for our modern free trade.</p>
                <p>Their privileges, however, were, from their very nature, destined to grow more
                    oppressive and intolerable the more the towns were multiplied and the means of
                    communication increased. The people of London were compelled to close their
                    shops during the days when the abbot of Westminster’s fair was open. But a more
                    curious and complete instance of such an ecclesiastical monopoly was that of the
                    St Giles’s fair, at first granted for the customary three days, which were
                    increased by Henry III. to sixteen. The-bishop of Winchester was, as we have
                    seen, the lord of this fair. On the eve of St Giles’s feast the magistrates of
                    Winchester surrendered the keys of the city gates to the bishop, who then
                    appointed his own mayor, bailiff, and coroner, to hold office until the close of
                    the fair. During the same period, Winchester and Southampton also—though it was
                    then a thriving trading town—were forbidden to transact their ordinary
                    commercial business, except within the bishop’s fair, or with his special
                    permission. The bishop’s officers were posted along the highways, with power to
                    forfeit to his lordship all goods bought and sold within seven miles of the
                    fair—in whose centre stood “the pavilion,” or bishop’s court. It is clear, from
                    the curious record of the <hi rend="italic">Establishment and Expenses of the
                    Household</hi> of Percy, fifth earl of Northumberland, that fairs were the chief
                    centres of country traffic even as late as the 16th century. They began to
                    decline rapidly after 1759, when good roads had been constructed and canal
                    communication established between Liverpool and the towns of Yorkshire,
                    Cheshire, and Lancashire. In the great towns their extinction was hastened in
                    consequence of their evil effects on public morals. All the London fairs were
                    abolished as public nuisances before 1855,—the last year of the ever famous fair
                    of St Bartholomew; and the fairs of Paris were swept away in the storm of the
                    Revolution.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">English Fairs and Markets.—</hi> For the general reasons
                    apparent from the preceding sketch, fairs in England, as in France and Germany,
                    have very largely given way to markets for specialities. Even the live-stock
                    market of the metropolis is being superseded by the dead-meat market, a change
                    which has been encouraged by recent legislation on cattle disease, the movements
                    of home stock, and the importation of foreign animals. Agricultural markets are
                    also disappearing before the “agencies” and the corn exchanges in the principal
                    towns. Still there are some considerable fairs yet remaining. Of the English
                    fairs for live stock, those of Weyhill in Hampshire (October 10), St Faith’s,
                    near Norwich (October 17), as also several held at Devizes, Wiltshire, are among
                    the largest in the kingdom. The first named stands next to none for its display
                    of sheep; whilst the second is the principal resort of the Scotch drovers and
                    cattle-dealeis, and supplies a large proportion of the fat stock required for
                    the London market. Horncastle, Lincolnshire, is the largest horse fair in the
                    kingdom, and is regularly visited by American and Continental dealers. The other
                    leading horse fairs in England areHowden in Yorkshire (well known for its
                    hunters), and Woolbridge (on Lady Day) for Suffolk horses. Exeter December fair
                    has a large display of cattle, horses, and most kinds of commodities. Large
                    numbers of Scotch cattle are also brought to the fairs of Market Harborough,
                    Carlisle, and Ormskirk. Ipswich has a fair for lambs on 1st of August, and for
                    butter and cheese on 1st of September. Gloucester fair is also famous for the
                    last-named commodity. The guild or jubilee held at Preston, Lancashire, every
                    twentieth year, occurred last in 1862. Falkirk fair, or tryst, for cattle and
                    sheep, is one of the largest in Scotland; and Ballinasloe, Galway, holds a like
                    position among Irish fairs. The Ballinasloe cattle are usually fed for a year in
                    Leinster before they are considered fit for the Dublin or Liverpool markets. In
                    1790 there were 61,931 sheep and 8632 horned cattle exhibited at the fair, and
                    for 1867 the returns, in the foregoing order, were 73,364 and 23,734.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">French Fairs.—</hi> The most important is that of Beaucaire,
                    once among the first in Europe. Its position on the Rhone (14 miles east of
                    Nismes), and its connexion with the canals, still enable it to maintain a high
                    rank among the Continental markets. It lasts from the 22d to the 28th July, and
                    is visited by about 60,000 persons, from all parts of the Continent between
                    Spain and the Levant; articles of all descriptions are sold at it. It is a rule
                    that all bills due at this fair must be presented on the 27th and protested, if
                    necessary, on the 28th.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">German Fairs.—</hi> First, though no longer of world-wide
                    importance, are those of Frankfort-on-the-Maine, Frankfort-on-the-Oder, and
                    Leipsic. Those of Frankfort-on-the-Maine begin on Easter Tuesday and on the
                    nearest Monday to September 8 respectively, and their legal duration is three
                    weeks, though the limit is regularly extended. The fairs of the second-named
                    city are <hi rend="italic">Reminiscere,</hi> February or March; <hi
                    rend="italic">St Margaret,</hi> July; <hi rend="italic">St Martin,</hi>
                    November. Ordinarily they last fifteen days, which is double the legal term. The
                    greatest of the German fairs are those of Leipsic, whose display of books is
                    famous all over the world. Its three fairs are dated January 1, Easter,
                    Michaelmas. The Easter one is the book fair, which is attended by all the
                    principal booksellers of Germany, and by many more from the adjoiuing countries.
                    Most German publishers have agents at Leipsic. As many as 5000 new publications
                    have been entered in a single Leipsic catalogue. As in the other instances
                    given, the Leipsic fairs last for three weeks, or nearly thrice their allotted
                    duration. Here no days of grace are allowed, and the holder of a bill must
                    demand payment when due, and protest, if necessary, on the same day, otherwise
                    he cannot proceed against either drawer or endorser. <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi><hi rend="italic">Russian Fairs.—</hi> These are very numerous, the chief
                    being those of Nijni Novgorod, of Irbit in Perm, Kharkoff (January and August),
                    Poltava (August and February), Koreunais in Koursk, Ourloupinsknia in the Don
                    Cossack country, Krolevetz in Tchernigoff, and a third fair held at Poltava on
                    the feast of the Ascension. It is calculated that in 1851 the aggregate value of
                    goods sold at the above named fairs amounted to nearly 120,000,000 silver
                    roubles. The chief fair of Novgorod is attended by 100,000 to 130,000 persons
                    from all parts of Asia and of eastern Europe. Thirty years ago the fair of
                    Kiatcha, on the Russo-Chinese frontier, yielded one million sterling in revenue;
                    but in 1867, according to Mr Lumley, secretary to the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n884/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0884-0849"/> English embassy at St Petersburg, the sum had
                    fallen by one half This was in consequence of the opening of new communications,
                    and the abolition of the Kiatcha monopoly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Turkish Fairs.—</hi> Of these there are a very considerable
                    number, and the vast bulk of the internal commerce of the country is transacted
                    at them. Among the most noteworthy are the fairs of Usundji, in Roumelia, on a
                    tributary of the Maritza, 40 miles from Adrianople; Janina in Albania; Strouga,
                    on the lake of Orida; Novi-Bazaar in Upper Moesia; Islioni in Thrace; Nicopoli
                    and Pielip in Macedonia; Eski-djouma in Bulgaria; and Zeitoun and Pharsalia in
                    Thessaly. There is a large show of western manufactures at the Usundji fair.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Indian Fairs.—</hi> The largest of these, and perhaps the
                    largest in Asia, is that of Hurd war, on the upper course of the Ganges. The
                    visitors to this holy fair number from 200,000 to 300,000; but every twelfth
                    year there occurs a special pilgrimage to the sacred river, when the numbers may
                    amount to a million -or upwards. Those who go solely for purposes of trade are
                    Nepaulese, Mongolians, Thibetans, Central Asi itics, and Mahometan pedlars from
                    the Punjab, Scinde, and the border states. Persian shawls and carpets, Indian
                    silks, Cashmere shawls, cottons (Indiau and English), preserved fruits, spices,
                    drugs, Arc., together with immense numbers of cattle, horses, sheep, and camels,
                    are brought to this famous fair.</p>
                <p>Awierzeim <hi rend="italic">Fairs.—</hi> The word fair, as now used in the United
                    States, appears to have completely lost its Old World meaning It seems to be
                    exclusively applied to industrial exhibitions, and to what we in England would
                    call fancy bazaars. Thus, during the civil war, large sums were collected at the
                    “sanitary fairs,” for the benefit of the sick and wounded. To the first-named
                    class belong the State and county fairs, as they are called. Among the first and
                    best known of these was the “New York World’s Fair,” opened in 1853 by a company
                    formed in 1851. Since 1829 the “American Institute” held annual “fairs’’for the
                    encouragement of the agricultural and manufacturing arts. The chief centres of
                    these “fairs,” or exhibitions, appear to be Cincinnati, Baltimore, Boston, San
                    Francisco, and Buffalo.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lav: of Fairs.—</hi> As no market or fair can he held in
                    England without a royal charter, or right of prescription, so any person
                    establishing a fair without such sanction is liable to be sued, under a writ of
                    <hi rend="italic">Quo warranto,</hi> by any one to whose property the said
                    market maybe injurious. Nor can a fair or market lm legally held beyond the time
                    specified in the grant; and by 5 Edward HI. c. 5 a merchant selling goods after
                    the legal expiry of the fair forfeited double their value. To be valid, a sale
                    must take place in “market-overt” (open market); “it will not be binding if it
                    carries with it a presumption of fraudulence.’’ These regulations satisfied, the
                    sale “transfers a complete property in the thing sold to the vendee; so that
                    however injurious or illegal the title of the vendor may be, yet the vendee's is
                    good against all men except the king.” (In Scotch law, the claims of the real
                    owner would still lemain valid.) However, by 21 Henry VIII. c. 2 it was enacted
                    that, “if any felon rob or take away money, goods, or chattels, and be indicted
                    and found guilty, or otherwise attainted upon evidence given by the owner or
                    party robbed, or by any other by their procurement, the owner or party lobbed
                    shall be restored to his money, goods, or chattels," but only those goods were
                    restored which were specified in the indictment, nor could the owner recover
                    from a <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> purchaser in market-overt, who had sold
                    the goods before conviction. For obvious leasons the rules of market overt were
                    made particularly stringent in the case of horses. Thus, by 2 Philip and Mary c.
                    7 and 31 Eliz. c. 12, no sale of a horse was legal which had not satisfied the
                    following conditions Public exposure of the animal for at least an hour between
                    sunrise and sunset; identification of the vendor by the market officer, or
                    guarantee for his honesty by “one sufficient and credible person;” entry of
                    these particulars, together with a description of the animal, and a statement of
                    the price paid for it, in the market officer’s book. Even if his rights should
                    have been violated in spite of all these precautions, the lawftd owner could
                    recover, if he claimed within six months, produced witnesses, and tendered the
                    price paid to the vendor. Tolls were not a “necessary incident” of a fair— <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> they were illegal unless specially granted in the
                    patent. or lecognized by custom. As a rule, they were paid only by the vendee,
                    and to the market clerk, whose record of the payment was an attestation to the
                    genuineness of the purchase. By 2 and 3 Philip and Mary c. 7 every lord of a
                    fair entitled to exact tolls was bound to appoint a clerk to collect and enter
                    them. It was also this functionary’s business to test measures and weights.
                    Tolls, again, are sometimes held to include “stallage” and “picage, which mean
                    respectively the price for permission to erect stalls and to dig holes for posts
                    in the market grounds. But toll proper belongs to the lord of the market,
                    whereas the other two are usually regarded as the property of the lord of the
                    soil. The law also provided that stallage might l&gt;e levied on any house
                    situated in the vicinity of a market, and kept open for business during the
                    legal term of the said market. Among recent statutes, one of the chief is the
                    Markets and Fairs Clauses Act (10 Vict. c. 14), the chief purpose of whieh is to
                    consolidate previous measures. By the Act no proprietors of a new market are
                    permitted to let stallages, take tolls, or in any way open their grounds for
                    business, until two justices of the peace have certified to the completion of
                    the fair or market. After the opening of the place for public use, no person
                    other than a licensed hawker shall sell anywhere within the borough, his own
                    house or shop excepted, any articles in respect of which tolls are legally
                    exigible in the, market. A breach of this provision entails a penalty of forty
                    shillings. Vendors of unwholesome meat are liable to a penalty of £5 for each
                    offence; and the “inspectors of provisions” have full liberty to seize the goods
                    and institute proceedings against the owners. They may also enter “at all t imes
                    of the day, with or without assistance,” the slaughter-house whieh the
                    undertaker of the market may, by the special Act, have been empowered to
                    construct. For general sanitary reasons, persons are prohibited from killing
                    animals anywhere except in these slaughter-houses. Again, by 36 and 37 Vict. c.
                    37, times of holding fairs are determined by the secretary of state; while 34
                    Viet, c. 12 empowers him to abolish any fair on the representation of the
                    magistrate and with the consent of the owner. The preamble of the Act states
                    that many fairs held in England and Wales are both unnecessary and productive of
                    “grievous immorality.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Fair Courts.—</hi> The Piepowder Courts, the lowest but
                    most expeditious courts of justice in the kingdom, as Chitty calls them, were
                    very ancient. The Conqueror’s law <hi rend="italic">De Emporiis</hi> shows their
                    pre-existence in Normandy. Their name was derived from <hi rend="italic">pied
                    puldreux,</hi> Norman for pedlar.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Skene has shown the identity in Scotch borough law between
                    “marchand travelland” and “pied puldreux,” or “dusty fute.</p></note> The lord
                    of the fair or his representative was the presiding judge, and usually he was
                    assisted by a jury of traders chosen on the spot. Their jurisdiction was limited
                    by the legal time and precincts of the fair, and to disputes about contracts,
                    “slander of wares,” attestations, the preservation of order, &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">.Authorities.—See</hi> Herbert Spencer’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Descriptive Sociology,</hi> 1873, especially the columns and paragraphs on
                    “Distribution ;’’ Prescott’s <hi rend="italic">History of Mexico,</hi> for
                    descriptions of fairs under the Aztecs; Giles Jacob’s <hi rend="italic">Law
                    Dictionary,</hi> London, 1809; Joseph Chitty’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the
                    Law of Commerce and Manufactures</hi> (vol. ii. chap. 9), London, 1824;
                    Holinshed’s and Grafton’s <hi rend="italic">Chronicles,</hi> for lists, &amp;c.,
                    of English fairs; Meyer's <hi rend="italic">Dos Grosse Conversations
                    Lexicon,</hi> 1852, under “Messen;” article “Foire” in Larousse’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Dictionnaire Universelle du XIXc. SiWe,</hi> Paris, 1866-1874, and
                    itsreferences to past authorities; and especially, the second volume, commercial
                    series, of the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopedic Methodiquc,</hi> Paris, 1783;
                    M'Cullocli’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Commerce,</hi> 1869-1871; Wharton’s
                    <hi rend="italic">History of English Poetry,</hi> pp. 185, 186, of edition of
                    1870, London, Murray &amp; Son, for a description of the Winchester Fair,
                    &amp;c.; a note by Professor Henry Morley in p. 498, vol. vii. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notes and Queries,</hi> second series; the same author’s unique’ <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Fair of St Bartholomew,</hi> London, 1859;
                    Wharton's <hi rend="italic">Law Lexicon,</hi> Will’s edition, London, 1876; and
                    also, for some effects of recent legislation, as regards meat ami fat stock
                    markets, the debates in the House of Lords Feb. 12 and March 5, 1878.
                    (J-MA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
