<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0879-0844-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FACTORY ACTS (9th edition, volume 8, page 844)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1013130">Meal</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tj5p">Pauperism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FACTORY ACTS</label>. The long series of Factory Acts,
                    culminating in the home secretary’s bill of the present session (1878),
                    constitutes one of the most important chapters in the history of modem English
                    legislation. The Acts assert the right of the state to control the industrial
                    organizations which depend upon the labour of women and children. As yet the
                    freedom of the adult male labourer has been held sacred from the interference of
                    the legislature, but it is necessarily involved, to some extent, in the
                    protection exercised over persons whose co-operation is necessary to his work.
                    The gradual rise of the important principle that, in the interests of the moral
                    and physical well-being of the community, the labour of women and children
                    should be restricted by law within reasonable limits may be seen by a glance at
                    the Factory Bills introduced in parliament since the beginning of the
                    century.</p>
                <p>In 1802 an Act was passed “for the Preservation of the Health and Morals of
                    Apprentices and others employed in Cotton and other Mills, and Cotton and other
                    Factories.” The immediate cause of passing this bill was the fearful spread
                    throughout the factory district of Manchester of epidemic disease, which made
                    dreadful havoc among the youthful labouring population on account of their
                    scanty mode of living and peculiar way of working.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Von Plener, <hi rend="italic">Factory
                    Legislation,</hi> p. 1.</p></note> Pauper children from the agricultural
                    districts of the south were sent to the northern counties to work in the
                    factories which sprang up there in consequence of their superior supply of
                    water-power. Their long hours of labour, the wretched accommodation provided for
                    them, and the over-crowding of workmen in mills and factories, caused the
                    alarming epidemic fevers of those times and districts. The Act of 1802 subjected
                    all mills employing three or more apprentices, or twenty other persons, to the
                    rules and regulations of the Act. The walls were to be washed with quicklime and
                    water; a sufficient number of windows was to be provided; the apprentices were
                    always to have two suits of clothing, one to be new every year. The most
                    important regulation, however, was that which fixed the hours of work at twelve
                    per day, and prohibited work altogether from 9 o’clock at night to 6 in the
                    morning. This Act, being intended to meet the evils of the apprentice system,
                    did not extend to factories where children residing in the neighbourhood were
                    employed. The use of steam-power had meanwhile caused the growth of factories in
                    populous town districts. In 1819 an Act was passed for the regulation of cotton
                    mills: children were not to be admitted before the age of nine, and between that
                    age and sixteen were restricted to twelve hours a day, exclusive of an hour and
                    a half for meal-time.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n880/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0880-0845"/>
                <p>In 1825 Sir John Cam Hobhouse’s Bill was passed, which established a partial
                    holiday on Saturday, and provided penalties for offences against the Act. An
                    amending Act was passed (10 Geo. IV. c. 51), and in 1831 (by the 1 and 2 WilL
                    IV. c. 39) night work in the cotton factories was prohibited for persons between
                    nine and twenty-one years of age; the working day for persons under eighteen was
                    to be twelve hours, and on Saturdays nine. This was the time of the great
                    political movement which brought about the Reform Act of 1832, and the factory
                    question entered into and to some extent complicated the purely political
                    issues. In the wool districts the unions of the working men clamoured for a
                    restriction of non-adult labour in factories to ten hours a day, and their
                    demand was supported by the Conservative and country party, out of opposition to
                    the manufacturers, who were.for the most part keen supporters of the Reform
                    Bill. The wool factories had not been touched by the recent legislation, and the
                    sufferings of the over-worked children appealed powerfully to the imagination of
                    the public. After much discussion in committees and commissions, the Act of 1833
                    (3 and 4 Will. IV. c. 103) was passed. Night work (between 8.30 p.m. and 5.30
                    a.m.) was prohibited to persons under eighteen in cotton, wool, worsted, hemp,
                    flax, tow, and linen spinneries and weaving mills; children from nine to
                    thirteen were not allowed to work more than 48 hours a week; and young persons
                    from thirteen to eighteen were restricted to 68 hours a week. In silk factories
                    children might be admitted under nine, and children under thirteen were to be
                    allowed ten hours a day. Provision was also made for school attendance and for
                    the appointment of factory inspectors to watch over the working of the law. The
                    manufacturers, dreading the economical results of thelossof children’s labour,
                    subsequently induced the Government to propose that children over eleven should
                    be allowed to work the full time of 69 hours a week, but in the face of the
                    agitation for greater restrictions this amendment was not persisted in.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>One of the consequences of
                    the restrictions imposed on the employment of children was the increased use of
                    machinery as a substitute. In 1835 (before the Factory Act), there were 56,455
                    children employed in 3164 factories; in 1838 (under the Factory Act), 29,283
                    children were employed in 4217 factories.—Von Plener’s <hi rend="italic">English
                    Factory Legislation,</hi> p. 22.</p></note></p>
                <p>The extension of the Factory Acts to unprotected industries now engaged the
                    attention of philanthropists. A Mining Act (5 and 6 Vict. c. 99) was passed,
                    which prohibited under-ground work to children under ten and women. In 1844 the
                    Factory Act, 7 Vict. c. 15, was passed. Children from eight to thirteen might be
                    employed in textile industries for not more than six hours and a half per day,
                    but in factories where “young persons” restricted to ten hours a day were
                    employed, children might also be employed for ten hours a day on alternate days.
                    Children so employed had to attend school during the “half time.” Adult women
                    were brought under the same rules as “young persons.” Lord Ashley’s<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Afterwards earl of
                    Shaftesbury, whose name, more than any other, is entitled to be associated for
                    ever with the English factory legislation.</p></note> Printworks Act followed in
                    1845. A Ten Hours Bill was at last carried in 1847 (10 Vict. c. 29). Women and
                    young persons were restricted to ten hours a day, and the legal working day was
                    fixed from 5.30 a.m. to 8.30 p.m. By employing protected persons in relays,
                    manufacturers were enabled to keep their works going during the whole of the
                    legal day; and to meet this evasion, as it was deemed to be, of the factory
                    legislation a uniform working day was fixed, 13 and 14 Vict. c. 54. Young
                    persons and women were allowed to work only between 6 a.m. and 6 p.m.—an hour
                    and a half being allowed for meal-time. No protected person was to work on
                    Saturday after 2 p.m. By the 16 and 17 Vict. c. 104, children were limited to a
                    legal day beginning at 6 a.m. and ending at 6 p.m. Bleaching and dyeing works
                    were subjected to similar restrictions by Acts passed in 1860 and 1862,
                    calendering and finishing works in 1863 and 1864. Lace factories were placed
                    under the regulations of the Factories Acts by 24 and 25 Viet c. 117. Night work
                    in bakehouses was prohibited to young persons under eighteen, by 26 and 27 Vict.
                    c. 40. After the report of a commission, a new Factory Acts Extension Act was
                    passed (27 and 28 Viet, c. 48), which brought manufactories of earthenware,
                    percussion caps, lucifer matches, and cartridges, paper-staining, and
                    fustian-cutting within the scope of the factory legislation. In 1867 a
                    distinction was drawn in legislation between factories and workshops. The
                    Factory Acts Extension Act of that year applied to all furnaces, iron and copper
                    works, machine manufactories, metal and guttapercha factories, paper-mills,
                    glass-works, printing offices, and bookbinders’ shops, and to all establishments
                    in which over 50 persons are employed for a period of a hundred days. Special
                    modifications, however, were introduced to suit the requirements of the
                    different trades. In the same year the Workshop Regulation Act was passed, for
                    small trades and handicrafts, fixing the working day for children at 6 a.m. to 8
                    p.m., and for young persons and women from 5 a.m. to 9 p.m. Printing, bleaching,
                    and dyeing works were brought under the general law by the Factory and Workshop
                    Act 1870. In 1871 another Act with the same title was passed, which, <hi
                    rend="italic">inter alia,</hi> subjected Government factories to the general
                    law. The Factory Act of 1874, the last of the series, raised the minimum of age
                    in children to ten.</p>
                <p>By these various enactments the state has emphatically taken under its protection
                    the whole class of children and young persons employed in manufacturing
                    industries. It has done this in the name of the moral and physical health of the
                    community. The slow but steady advance of the principle of interference may be
                    traced in the titles of the successive statutes. It is needless here to discuss
                    the wisdom of the policy, which has now received <hi rend="italic">en bloc</hi>
                    the stamp of legislative approval. The substantive law of the Factories Acts has
                    been re-enacted in a measure laid before parliament in the present session,
                    which has already (May 1878) passed both Houses. In the debates in the Commons
                    the only question of principle seriously raised was whether the freedom of adult
                    women ought to be curtailed by legislative interference. Mr Fawcett’s motion in
                    the negative was rejected by a large majority.</p>
                <p>The following outline will give some idea of the scope of the law relating to
                    factories and workshops consolidated by the new measure :—</p>
                <p>Part I. contains the general law relating to factories and workshops, under the
                    following heads—(1) Sanitary Provisions; (2) Safety; (3) Employment and meal
                    hours; (4) Holidays; (5) Education; (6) Certificates of fitness for employment;
                    (7) Accidents.</p>
                <p>(1.) Under the first head, the buildings must be kept in a clean state, and free
                    from effluvia arising from any drain, privy, or other nuisance.</p>
                <p>(2.) The second contains provisions for the fencing of dangerous machinery, and
                    restrictions on the employment of children and young persons in cleaning,
                    &amp;c., machinery in motion.</p>
                <p>(3.) A child, young person, or woman shall not be employed except during the
                    period of employment fixed as follows:—</p>
                <p>(a.) In textile factories.—Jbr <hi rend="italic">young persons and women,</hi>
                    the period shall be from 6 a.m. to 6 p.m. or 7 a.m. to 7 p.m.; on Saturday, from
                    6 a.m. till 1 p.m. for manufacturing processes, and 1.30 for all employment, if
                    one hour is allowed for meals; otherwise at 12.30 and 1. Or if the work begins
                    at 7 a.m., it shall end on Saturdays at 1.30 and 2 p.m. respectively. For meal
                    times two hours at least on week days, and on Saturdays half an hour, must be
                    allowed. Continuous employment without a meal time of at least half an hour not
                    to exceed four hours and a half.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">For children.</hi> Employment to be for half time only (in
                    morning or afternoon sets, or alternate days). The work-day is the same as <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n881/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0881-0846"/> above. A child must not be employed for cwo
                    successive periods of seven days in the same set, whether morning or afternoon,
                    nor on two successive Saturdays, nor on Saturday in any week if he has already
                    on one day been employed more than five hours and a half. Nor shall a child be
                    employed on two successive days, nor on the same day in two successive
                    weeks.</p>
                <p>(&amp;.) In non-textile factories.— <hi rend="italic">For young persons and
                    women.</hi> Period of employment same as before, ending at 2 p.m. on Saturdays;
                    meal times not less than an hour and a half, on Saturday half an hour;
                    continuous employment without a meal not to exceed 5 hours; these regulations
                    also apply to <hi rend="italic">young persons in workshops.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">For children.</hi> Half time arrangements generally the same as
                    before, continuous employment without a meal not to exceed 5 hours.</p>
                <p>Women in workshops are subject to the same regulations as young persons, if young
                    persons or children are employed; if not, the period of employment for a woman
                    in a workshop shall be from 6 a.m. to 9 p.m. (on Saturday 4 p.m.). Absent time
                    for meals, &amp;c., must be allowed to the extent of four hours and a half
                    (Saturdays two hours and a half).</p>
                <p>The employment of young persons or children at home, when the work is the same as
                    in a factory or workshop, but no machine power is used, is also regulated,—the
                    day being fixed at 6 a.m. to 9 p.m.; for children, 6 a.m. to 1 p.m., or 1 p.m.
                    to 8. Meal times in factories or workshops must be simultaneous, and employment
                    during such meal times is forbidden. The occupier of a factory or workshop must
                    issue a notice of the times of employment, &amp;c. No children under 10 shall be
                    employed.</p>
                <p>(4.) The following holidays shall be allowed to all protected persons :—Christmas
                    day, Good Friday (or the next public holiday), and eight half-holidays, two of
                    which may be commuted for one entire holiday.</p>
                <p>(5.) Occupiers must obtain a weekly certificate of school attendance for every
                    child in their employment.</p>
                <p>(6.) Medical certificates of fitness for employment are required in the case of
                    children and young persons under 16. When*a child becomes a young person a fresh
                    certificate is necessary.</p>
                <p>(7.) Notice of accidents, causing loss of life or bodily injury, must be sent to
                    the inspector and certifying surgeon of the district.</p>
                <p>Part 11. contains special provisions for particular classes of factories and
                    workshops, such as bake-houses, print-works, bleaching and dyeing works. The
                    third schedule to the Act contains a list of special exceptions too numerous to
                    be given in detail.</p>
                <p>Part III. provides for the administration of the law. Two classes of officers are
                    to be appointed by the secretary of state, viz., (1) inspectors, charged with
                    the duty of inspecting and examining factories and workshops at all reasonable
                    times, and of exercising such other powers as may be necessary to the carrying
                    out of the Act; and (2) certifying surgeons to grant certificates of fitness
                    under the Act. Numerous other sections relate to penalties and legal
                    proceedings.</p>
                <p>Part IV. defines the principal terms used in the Act Child means a person under
                    fourteen years of age; a “young person” is between fourteen and eighteen; “a
                    woman” means a woman over eighteen. Other sections apply the Act to Scotland and
                    Ireland, with a temporary saving for the employment of children under 10 and
                    children over thirteen (lawfully employed at the time of the passing of the
                    Act). Previous enactments are repealed. (E. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
