<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0838-0813-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INDIANA (9th edition, volume 12, page 813)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204604">Indiana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208387">Michigan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204595">Wisconsin</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n838/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INDIANA</label><hi rend="italic">Copyright,</hi> 1880, <hi
                        rend="italic">by Charles Scribner's Sons.</hi><hi> INDIANA</hi>, one of the
                    Central States of the American Union, lies between 37° 47' and 41° 50' N. lat.,
                    and 84° 49' and 88° 2' W. long. It is bounded on the E. by the State of Ohio,
                    from which it is separated by a line drawn due north from the mouth of the Great
                    Miami river; on the S. by the Ohio river, separating it from Kentucky, between
                    the mouths of the Great Miami and the Wabash; on the W. by Illinois, from which
                    it is separated by the Wabash river from its mouth to a point where a line drawn
                    due north from Vincennes last touches the western bank of that stream, thence
                    north on that line to a point 10 miles north of the southern extreme of Lake
                    Michigan; on the N. by a line drawn from that point due east until it intersects
                    the eastern boundary, separating the State from Michigan. A small portion of
                    Lake Michigan is included within the northern boundary. The coast-line is about
                    60 miles in length. Michigan City is the only lake harbour in the State. The
                    extreme length of the State is 276 miles, with an average breadth of 145 miles;
                    and the area is 33,809 square miles.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Topography.—</hi> Indiana occupies a broad table-land, for the
                    most part level or gently undulating, except along the Ohio, where the plain has
                    been deeply grooved by the affluent streams into hills and valleys. There are no
                    elevations that could properly be termed mountains or mountain ranges. With the
                    exception of a small portion which drains into the great lakes, the whole State
                    inclines gently towards the south-west. The highest point (except a knob in
                    Brown county) is found in the southern portion of Randolph county, and is 1253
                    feet above the sea; the lowest, at the mouth of the Wabash, is 370 feet. From
                    careful surveys the mean altitude of the State is estimated at 735 feet above
                    sea-level. It is well watered by numerous streams and rivers,, but, with the
                    exception of the Ohio and Wabash, few of them are navigable. The Wabash is the
                    largest river that has its course mainly within the State; and, together with
                    its branches, it drains three-fourths of the entire surface. It rises in the
                    west of Ohio, and flows first in a north-west direction, and then south-west
                    till it meets the boundary of Illinois, which it follows southward for more than
                    100 miles, till it falls into the Ohio, after a course of upwards of 500 miles.
                    The Ohio forms the entire southern boundary of the State. The other principal
                    rivers of Indiana are tributaries of the Wabash. The White River, the most
                    important of these, is formed by the W. and E. Forks,—two rivers respectively
                    about 300 and 200 miles long,—which unite about 100 miles above its confluence
                    with the Wabash. The Maumee is formed by the St Joseph and St Mary in the
                    north-east, and falls into Lake Erie. The Upper St Joseph, with its tributaries,
                    passes through the northern counties, and falls into Lake Michigan. That portion
                    south of the Wabash was originally covered with heavy forests of oak, beech,
                    maple, walnut, ash, and other hard woods; north of that river was principally
                    prairie, interspersed with small lakes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Geology and Minerals.—</hi> Lower Silurian strata are well
                    developed in the south-eastern part of the State, with a thickness of 800 feet.
                    Next, to the west and north, in succession occur rocks of the Upper Silurian,
                    with a thickness of 200 feet, and those of Devonian age, 180 feet thick. The
                    last two formations spread over all the northern third of the State, deeply
                    covered with glacial drift, and at points deeply eroded by ice and water flow of
                    that age. The Coal-measures occupy over 7000 square miles in the western and
                    south-western parts, furnishing seven workable seams, at a depth of 50 to 220
                    feet, and averaging 80 feet below the surface; the seams vary in thickness from
                    2⅛ to 11 feet, averaging 4 J feet; the quality is from fair to good , an area of
                    600 square miles in this field yields a superior “block” or splint coal. This,
                    being free from sulphur and phosphorus, is used in blast furnaces as it comes
                    from the mine, without coking, and is well adapted for the preparation of
                    Bessemer steel. The Sub-Carboniferous or Mountain Limestone borders the
                    Coal-measures on the south and east; it yields giant bands of choice limestone
                    for building purposes, 30 to 50 feet thick, unlimited in extent, homogeneous,
                    elastic to compensate for inequalities of temperature, and with endurance to
                    bear the climatic changes. Near Leavenworth, in the southern part of the State,
                    there is a remarkable calcareous cavern, the Wyandotte Cave. One of its chambers
                    is 350 feet long and 245 in height. It abounds with stalactites and stalagmites
                    of great variety and size.</p>
                <p>Inexhaustible beds of fire clay, potter’s clay, kaolin, and lime, as well as
                    paving and building stone, are found in the southern parts of the State.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Agriculture</hi> is the chief branch of industry, the climate
                    and soil being suited to the growth of cereals, fruits, and grasses. The
                    following table, compiled from the report of the Bureau of Statistics, shows the
                    production of the chief grain crops for 1880 :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Acres.</p><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Bushels.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Wheat</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,109,845</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>47,130,684</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Indian corn</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,130,327</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>87,335,014</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Oats</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>686,901</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,563,430</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Rye</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15,028</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>217,192</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">J</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                                yj</hi></p><p>Barley</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31,019</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>687,911</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The meadow land amounted to 778,691 acres, and the hay produced was 1,221,164
                    tons. The same year the domestic animals numbered — horses 494,809, cattle
                    1,150,559, sheep 1,508,242, and hogs 4,253,586. There were 145,826 stands of
                    bees, yielding 1,114,883 fl) of honey.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate.—</hi> The climate is equable and healthy. In 1865 a
                    United States signal station was established at Indianapolis, and the following
                    meteorological tables have been compiled from the daily reports of this office.
                    They indicate the temperature (in degrees Fahrenheit) and rainfall in inches
                    during a period of fourteen years. The mean height of the barometer for the same
                    period was 30Ό10 inches. The prevailing winds are from the south and west in
                    summer, veering round to the north in winter.</p>
                <p>Mean Monthly Temperature and Rainfall for Fourteen Years.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>January.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>February.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>March.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>April.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>May.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>June.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>July.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>August.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>September.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>October.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>November.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>December</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Temperature</p><p>Rainfall (inches)..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31∙3° 3∙75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>36∙7° 3∙00</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>41-8’ 4∙50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54∙l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 3∙66</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>64∙4° 4∙47</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>74∙3° 4∙36</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>77∙7° 4∙57</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>75∙6°</p><p>317</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>67∙9° 3∙68</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54∙7°</p><p>2 37</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>41∙6°</p><p>2 94</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>33 5’ 3 51</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Annual Mean Temperature and Rainfall.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>1865.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1866.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1867.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1868.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1869.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1870.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1871.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1872.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1873.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>I874.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1 1875.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1876.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1877.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1878.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Temperature</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56-32’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56-46’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56-33’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55-56’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52-52’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55-25’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55-89’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52-75’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52-15’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55-04’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50-46’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>53-20’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54-60’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55∙40°</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Rainfall (inches)..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50∙69</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52’44</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>48∙54</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45Ό5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>42∙98 .</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3513</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>36 05</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>37 95</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52 32</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>43∙60</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>54∙58</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56'56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>39 08</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>38∙62</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n839/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0912-0839-0814"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures, Communication, &lt;kc.—</hi> The manufacturing
                    interests have increased rapidly during the last decade. The Bureau of
                    Statistics reported the value of manufactured products for 1878 at $185,050,220,
                    and the mercantile trade sales at $300,323,256. The increase of wealth is shown
                    as follows by the appraisement for taxation</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1860</p><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>411,042,424</p><p>663,455,044</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1880</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>767,387,172</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>On April 1, 1880, there were sixty-three railway corporations, working 4963 miles
                    of railway in the State, traversing eighty-five counties, and appraised for
                    taxation at $38,442,941. So completely does the railway system cover the State
                    that one can go from the capital to almost any county and return the same day.
                    The geographical position of the State is such that all the main railroad
                    through-lines between the east and west have to cross Indiana.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration.—</hi> The State is divided into ninety-two
                    counties, containing about 400 square miles each. The governor is elected for
                    four years. The legislature, which meets biennally, consists of a senate of
                    fifty, elected for four years, and a house of representatives of one hundred,
                    elected for two years. The judges (five) of the supreme court are elected for
                    six years. The State has thirteen representatives and two senators in Congress.
                    All popular elections are by ballot. All elections by the legislature are <hi
                        rend="italic">viva voce.</hi> The State has no permanent debt. The
                    constitution declares that no debts shall be incurred by the State except to
                    meet casual deficits in the revenue, or to provide for the public defence, repel
                    invasion, and suppress insurrection. On the organization of Indiana as a
                    territory in 1800, Vincennes was made the capital; when the State Government was
                    formed in 1816, the capital was fixed temporarily at Corydon, until provision
                    could be made for the permanent seat at Indianapolis, to which it was removed in
                    1824.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Education.—</hi> The foundation of the free school system was
                    laid by Congress when, in admitting the State into the Union, the Government
                    presented a section of land in each township to the inhabitants for free
                    schools. A great advance was made in 1851, when in framing the new constitution
                    it was provided that certain funds then belonging to the State, with all penal
                    fines and forfeitures accruing, should constitute a common school fund, the
                    principal to remain a perpetual fund, to be increased, but never diminished, and
                    the annual income used for tuition only. This fund in 1880 amounted to
                    $9,220,708, and is increasing. In the same year there were 9647 schoolhouses in
                    the State, valued at $11,817,954. Of the children of school age (six to
                    twenty-one) there were—males, white 351,761, coloured 7162; females, white
                    334,249, coloured 7386. Of these 511,283 attended the schools. The tuition
                    revenue expended for the year ending June 30,1880, was</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Amount derived from State tax</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>. $1,519,791-69</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Interest on common school fund held by counties..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>204,145 ∙30</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>State’s interest on non-negotiable bonds</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>234,187'00</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Amount derived from unclaimed fees .</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>895 ∙22</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Congressional township revenue</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>198,247’66</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Amount of local tuition tax</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>589,093∙21</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Proceeds of liquor licences</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>193,51215</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Total ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>...$2,939,872-23</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The State university is at Bloomington, and the State normal school at Terre
                    Haute. The function of the latter is to fit its pupils to become teachers in the
                    common schools. Perdue University, at Lafayette, is the State agricultural
                    college. There are also a number of colleges, mainly under the control of
                    religious societies, chief among which are Asbury University (Methodist) at
                    Greencastle, Wabash College (Presbyterian) at Crawfordsville, Butler University
                    (Christian) at Irvington (near Indianapolis), Notre Dame (Catholic) at South
                    Bend, and Earlham College (Friend) at Richmond.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population.—</hi> In point of population Indiana ranks as fifth
                    State in the Union. The white inhabitants in 1765 are stated to have consisted
                    of a few French families along the Wabash. The following table shows the
                    population at decennial periods during this century :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>White.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Coloured.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1800</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,577</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>298</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,875</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1810</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>23,890</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>630</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24,520</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1820</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>145,758</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,420</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>147,178</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1830</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>339,399</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,632</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>343,031</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1840</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>678,698</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,168</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>685,866</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1850</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>977,154</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11,262</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>988,416</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1860</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,338,710</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>11,428</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,350,428</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1870</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,655,837</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24,560</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,680,637</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1880</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>1,976,261</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The return for 1880 shows a density of population of 57 ’ 8 persons per square
                    mile.</p>
                <p>The following are the chief towns, with population in 1880:—Indianapolis, 75,074;
                    Evansville, 29,280; Fort Wayne, 26,880; Terre Haute, 26,040; New Albany, 16,422;
                    Lafayette, 14,860; South Bend, 13,279; Richmond, 12,473; Logansport, 11,198;
                    Jeffersonville, 10,422.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Indiana originally constituted a part of New
                    France. It was visited by the Jesuits as early as 1672. At the beginning of the
                    18th century the French opened a line of communication between the lakes and the
                    Mississippi by way of the Maumee, Wabash, and Ohio rivers. Trading posts for
                    barter with the natives were established at the head of the Maumee, where is now
                    the city of Fort Wayne; at Ouantenon, on the Wea Prairie, near the city of
                    Lafayette; and at Vincennes on the Wabash. Missionary stations were also
                    established by the Jesuit fathers, in their endeavour to convert the Indians. At
                    the close of the French war in 1763-4, the territory east of the Mississippi and
                    north of the Ohio passed under British dominion. Pending the war between Great
                    Britain and the American colonies, Colonel George Rogers Clark of Virginia, with
                    an armed force, took possession of the territory, raising the American flag at
                    Vincennes in 1778. By the treaty of 1783 between England and the United States
                    this territory was recognized as belonging to the latter; inasmuch as Virginia
                    had fitted out Clark’s expedition, she was entitled by the law of conquest to
                    claim this vast dominion. During the colonial war Congress recommended the
                    several States to cede their claims to unappropriated lands in the western
                    country to the general government for the common benefit of the Union. Virginia,
                    in pursuance of this request, yielded up her claims to the territory north-west
                    of the Ohio. The deed of cession, executed on March 1, 1784, was signed by
                    Thomas Jefferson, James Monroe, Arthur Lee, and Samuel Hardy. In 1787 Congress
                    passed an ordinance for the government of the north-west territory, which
                    provided, among other things, that not more than five States should ever be
                    formed thereof, prohibiting slavery, and declaring that “religion, morality, and
                    knowledge being necessary to good government and the happiness of mankind,
                    schools and the means of education shall for ever be encouraged.” This territory
                    was subsequently divided into the States of Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, Michigan,
                    and Wisconsin. Indiana was admitted into the Union as a State by Congress on
                    April 19,1816, being the sixth State received after the formation of the
                    government by the thirteen original States and the adoption in 1787 of the
                    present constitution. (A. C. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
