<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0912-0868-0843-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INDIGO (9th edition, volume 12, page 843)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205154">Guatemala</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k440">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p29x">Process</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1744329">Isatin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970275">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1164604">Vats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834915">Blue</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n868/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INDIGO</label> is a well known and exceedingly valuable blue
                    dyeing material. The substance has been known among Western communities from an
                    early period, being mentioned by Dioscorides as ’Ινδικόν, and by Pliny as <hi
                        rend="italic">Indicum</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when it made its
                    appearance in England it was called indico. As all these names show, the
                    material in its origin and production is closely related to India, among the
                    commercial commodities of which it has always occupied a distinctive and
                    important place. It was not, however, till after the establishment of the Cape
                    route to India that indigo came to be largely used in the dyeing establishments
                    of Western Europe, woad having in earlier times been utilized for purposes to
                    which indigo was subsequently applied.</p>
                <p>As a commercial substance indigo is entirely obtained from the vegetable kingdom,
                    although it may be produced, in minute quantity, from a principle contained in
                    urine, and its synthetical formation has also been accomplished. The number of
                    plants from which indigo may be procured is known to be large, but only from a
                    very few is it prepared in practice. These are various species of the leguminous
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Indigofera,</hi> especially the four species <hi
                        rend="italic">I.</hi><hi rend="italic">tinctona,</hi><hi rend="italic">I.
                        Anil, I. disperma,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">I.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >argentea</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and it is said that in China <hi
                        rend="italic">Polygonum</hi><hi rend="italic">tinctonum</hi> and other
                    non-leguminous plants are used as the source of <hi rend="italic">lan</hi> or
                    Chinese indigo. The woad plant, <hi rend="italic">Isatis tinctona,</hi> owes its
                    value as a dye to the presence of indigo matter, although indigo is not actually
                    prepared from it. The most important source of indigo, and that most generally
                    cultivated, is <hi rend="italic">I.</hi><hi rend="italic">tinctona,</hi> which
                    is an herbaceous plant growing 3 to 5 feet high, and having bipinnate leaves. It
                    is in the leaves that the indigo-yielding principle chiefly resides, and these
                    are most gorged with it at the period when the flower-buds are about to open. It
                    is then that the plant is cut down; and in some regions the same stock yields in
                    one year a second and even a third crop of stems.</p>
                <p>Two principal methods of preparing indigo are pursued, —dried leaves being
                    operated on in the one, while the fresh green stalks and leaves are used in the
                    other. It will be sufficient to describe the latter, the more important process,
                    as it is conducted in Bengal, where the most highly esteemed varieties of indigo
                    are made. The cut leaves and stems are tied up into small bundles and conveyed
                    at once to the factory, in which there are two ranges of large tanks or vats,
                    one series being at a lower level than the other. In the upper or fermenting
                    vats the bundles are submerged; and cross-bars are fixed over the vats. A
                    fermentation more or less rapid ensues, its completion occupying, according to
                    the temperature, from nine to fourteen hours. The progress of the operation is
                    judged by the tint assumed by the water, which under favourable conditions
                    should at the end of this stage be of a fine clear yellow colour. In this
                    condition the liquid is run off into the lower vats, in which it is necessary to
                    maintain it in a state of violent agitation. For this purpose a number of men,
                    armed with long bamboos, enter the vats and lash the water incessantly for two
                    or three hours, thus constantly exposing new surfaces to the air. Gradually the
                    liquid assumes a green colour, and indigo appears in broadish flakes, which as
                    it forms begin to sink. After this transformation is complete, the liquid is
                    allowed to settle, and as the indigo sinks the clear liquid is drawn off in a
                    series of discharges by pipes at different heights in the vat. The deposit of
                    indigo is then placed in a boiler, and, to prevent any further fermentation, is
                    raised to the boiling point. After resting for about a day, it is boiled for
                    three or four hours, and then filtered over a thick filtering cloth, and the
                    paste is dried by pressure. The cakes formed during the pressing are then put
                    away to dry gently in the shade, and in a few days are ready for packing.</p>
                <p>Bengal indigo of good quality forms a porous earthy mass, light and easily
                    pulverized; and when newly fractured it has that brilliant purple-blue colour
                    distinctively known as indigo, with a kind of coppery lustre. Experts
                    distinguish upwards of forty qualities of Bengal indigo, principally
                    characterized by varying shades of colour.—the inferior qualities being dull in
                    hue, with greenish or greyish tones, hard, dense, and not readily broken. The
                    varieties of indigo which come into the European markets are classified
                    according to their sources: the classes most frequently met with are Bengal,
                    Oude, Madras, Manila, Java, Egypt, Guatemala, Caraccas, Mexico, and Brazil. The
                    best qualities are the Bengal, Java, and Guatemala.</p>
                <p>The condition in which the indigo-yielding principle exists in the fresh plants
                    has been a subject of some speculation and controversy. Dr Schunck has
                    investigated the leaves of the woad <hi rend="italic">(Isatis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">tinctona),</hi> the Chinese indigo-plant <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Polygonum</hi><hi rend="italic">tinctonum),</hi> and others, and from all
                    these has isolated a glucoside body indican, which, under the influence of
                    dilute mineral acids, is decomposed, forming indigotin or indigo-blue and a
                    variety of glucose which he calls indiglucin. It has been assumed that the same
                    principle resides in <hi rend="italic">Indigofera</hi> as in these other plants,
                    and is the efficient source of the dye-stuff from that genus. In the
                    decomposition of indican there are formed in addition to indigo-blue—indigo-red
                    (indigo-rubin or indigo-purpurin) isomeric with the blue, indigo-brown, and
                    indigo-gluten, all of which, forming part of the precipitate, modify the colour
                    of the product, and render commercial indigo a compound body. Indigo also
                    contains a certain amount of inorganic matter and other non-tinctorial
                    constituents, so that the proportion of indigo-blue may vary from about 72 down
                    to Γ2 or 14 per cent, of the mass. Pure indigo blue or indigotin, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> N.,O <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, is a neutral body of a deep blue colour, destitute
                    of taste and odour, and insoluble in water, dilute acids, and alkalies, and in
                    cold alcohol and ether. Boiling alcohol, ether, and aniline dissolve it, as do
                    also petroleum, benzene, chloroform, and phenol, melted spermaceti and stearic
                    acid, and several oils. It sublimes at <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit12newyrich/page/n869/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0912-0869-0844"/> 290°-300° C., giving off violet vapours which
                    condense into right rhomboidal prisms possessing a brilliant coppery lustre. By
                    destructive distillation, indigotin yields, among other products, aniline,—a
                    circumstance to which that now well-known body owes its name (from the Sanskrit
                        <hi rend="italic">nili</hi> through the Portuguese <hi rend="italic"
                        >anil,</hi> indigo). Treated with oxidizing agents, indigotin takes up
                    oxygen, and is converted into isatin, thus :—</p>
                <p>C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> a</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2O = C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>;</p>
                <p>Indigotin. Isatin.</p>
                <p>and by further oxidation nitro-salicylic acid and picric acid are evolved. The
                    most valuable character, however, of indigotin is found in its behaviour under
                    the influence of hydrogenizing or reducing agents. In the presence of nascent
                    hydrogen indigotin absorbs that element and is converted into white indigo, a
                    colourless body which is readily soluble in alkaline or earthy alkaline
                    solutions, and by simple exposure to the air re-oxidizes and reverts to its
                    original blue condition indigotin. The reduction to white indigo is thus
                    formulated :—</p>
                <p>C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2H = C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Advantage is taken of these properties in dyeing with indigo as detailed under
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dyeing,</hi> vol vii. pp. 576-7. See also <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Calico-printing,</hi> vol. iv. pp. 689-90.</p>
                <p>Indigo when dissolved in strong sulphuric acid, forms with it two acid compounds,
                    both of which have limited industrial applications. These are (1) sulphindigotic
                    acid, C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> (SO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 3</hi> H) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, known also as
                    sulphate of indigo or soluble blue indigo, and (2) sulphophoenicic acid,
                    sul-phopurpuric acid, or indigo purple, C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 9</hi> N <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (SO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> H). These bodies
                    are formed together in the sulphuric acid solution of indigo; but, as the second
                    is insoluble in weak acids, it precipitates when the solution in which it is
                    formed is largely diluted with water. Both these acids are soluble in water. The
                    first was formerly used in dyeing Saxon-blue on wool and silk, a style now
                    little known; and the sodium salt of the second is known as red indigo
                    carmine.</p>
                <p>The synthetical preparation of indigo is a subject which has long occupied the
                    attention of chemists, as obviously any means by which the substance might be
                    artificially obtained on a commercial scale could not fail to be of great
                    industrial value. The numerous efforts made in this direction appear at last
                    (1881) to be crowned with success; and there is now little doubt that artificial
                    indigo will soon become a commercial product. It is to Professor Adolf Baeyer of
                    Munich that the measure of success already attained in manufacturing indigo is
                    due. For many years he has patiently investigated the molecular constitution of
                    indigotin and its derivatives. From isatin, prepared by the oxidation of
                    indigotin, Baeyer and Knob produced successively di-oxindol, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 14</hi> N <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, oxindol, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">C</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 16</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> h</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">N</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">O</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> s</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">,</hi> and indol, C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 14</hi> N <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ∙ Baeyer at a later
                    period, with the assistance of Emmerling, succeeded in producing indol from
                    cinnamic acid, and as that body can be prepared from coal-tar a new connecting
                    chain was established between indigo at one extreme and coal-tar at the other,
                    meeting in indol just as at a much earlier date they had similarly met in
                    aniline. The task remained of reconverting these derivatives of indigotin into
                    that body, and towards that, in 1870, Baeyer and Emmerling, by heating isatin
                    with phosphorus trichloride, acetyl chloride, and phosphorus, succeeded in
                    obtaining a mixture of indigotin and indigorubin. In 1878 the further steps
                    necessary to complete the cycle were accomplished by Baeyer, when from
                    phenylacetic acid he prepared oxindol. Acting on oxindol by nitrous acid he
                    produced nitrosoxindol, which in its turn, by treatment with nascent hydrogen,
                    was transformed into amidoxindol, a body which on oxidation yielded isatin. Thus
                    the series of transformations was complete: but they were effected by a process
                    so roundabout and elaborate as to preclude all hope of any commercial issue from
                    the method. Quite recently Baeyer, coming back to the use of cinnamic acid, has
                    devised the much simpler and more direct process which now promises to become,
                    and indeed already is in operation as, a method for the commercial preparation
                    of indigo. By treating cinnamic acid with nitric acid, ortho-nitro-cinnamic acid
                    is prepared, which on exposure to bromine vapour readily combines with that
                    body, forming ortho-nitro-dibrom-hydro-cinnamic acid. This substance when
                    treated with caustic alkali is converted by the loss of the bromine into
                    ortho-nitro-phenyl-propiolic acid, which, lastly, when heated in an alkaline
                    solution of grape sugar develops into indigotin. The steps in the process are
                    therefore represented thus :—</p>
                <p>(1) C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> COOH + N0 <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H0 = C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi> (NO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>)C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> COOH + H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O .</p>
                <p>Cinnamic acid. Nitric acid. Nitro-cinnamic acid. Water.</p>
                <p>(2) C <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> (NO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>)C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> COOH + 2Br = C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi> (NO <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi>)C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Br <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> COOH. Nitro-cinnamic acid. Bromine.
                    Nitro-dibrom-cinnamic acid.</p>
                <p>(3) C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> (N0 <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>)C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Br <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> CO0H+2NaOH=C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> (NO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>)C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> C00H+2NaBr+2H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O.</p>
                <p>Caustic Nitro-propiollc soda. acid.</p>
                <p>(4) 2C <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> NO <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 2H, = C <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> N <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2CO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O.</p>
                <p>Nitro-propiolic Indigotin.</p>
                <p>acid.</p>
                <p>The nitro-propiolic acid is now being manufactured by the Badische Anilinfabrik
                    as a material for indigo printing. The acid has simply to be printed on the
                    cloth with a thickening containing grape sugar and alkali, and, by steaming,
                    indigo is developed in the fibre. This reaction is in itself a matter of no
                    small importance, seeing that the printing of indigo direct is an extremely
                    troublesome operation. Hitherto indigo in mass has not been produced, but there
                    can be little doubt that the remaining difficulties, among which is the present
                    expensiveness of cinnamic acid, will soon be overcome, and that artificial
                    indigo will take its place among ordinary chemical manufactures. (j. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">pa.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
