<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0497-0431-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SNOW</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1121907">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950345">Hail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966505">Ice</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rn70">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r44r">Hail</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=497" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SNOW</label>, a well-known meteor, formed by the
                    freezing of the vapour of water in the atmosphere. It differs from hail and
                    hoar-frost, in being as it were crystallized, which they are not. This appears
                    in examining a flake of snow by a magnifying glass; when the whole of it will
                    appear to be composed of fine shining spicula diverging like rays from a centre.
                    As the flakes fall down through the atmosphere, they are continually joined by
                    more of those radiated spi cula, and thus increase in bulk like the drops of
                    rain or hailstones. Dr. Grew, in a discourse of the nature of snow, observes,
                    that many parts thereof are of a regular figure, for the most part stars of six
                    points, and are as perfect and transparent ice as any we see on a pond. Upon
                    each of these points are other collateral points, set at the same angles as the
                    main points themselves; among which there are divers other irregular, which are
                    chiefly broken points, and fragments of the regular ones. Others also, by
                    various winds, seem to have been thawed and frozen again into irregular
                    clusters, so that it seems as if the whole body of snow were an infinite mass of
                    icicles irregularly figured; that is, a cloud of vapours being gathered into
                    drops, the said drops forthwith descend; upon which descent, meeting with a
                    freezing air as they pass through a colder region, each drop is immediately
                    frozen into an icicle, shooting itself forth into several (points; but these
                    still continuing their descent, and meeting with some intermitting gales of
                    warmer air, or in their continual waftage to and 1fo, touching upon each other,
                    some of them are a little thawed, blunted, and again frozen into clusters, or
                    entangled so as to fall down in what we call flakes.</p>
                <p part="N">The lightness of snow, although it is firm ice, is owing to the excess
                    of its surface, in comparison to the matter contained under it; as gold itself
                    may be extended in surface till it ride upon the least breath of air.</p>
                <p part="N">The whiteness of snow is owing to the small particles into which it is
                    divided; for ice, when pounded, will become equally white. An artificial snow
                    has been made by the following experiment. A tall phial of aquafortis being
                    placed by the fire till it is warm, and filings of pure silver, a few at a time,
                    being put into it, after a brisk ebullition, the silver will dissolve slowly.
                    The phial being then placed in a cold window, as it cools, the silver particles
                    will shoot into crystals, several of which running together, will form a flake
                    of snow, which will descend to the bottom of the phial. While they are
                    descending, they represent perfectly a shower of silver snow, and the flakes
                    will lie upon one another at the bottom, like real snow upon the ground.</p>
                <p part="N">According to Signor Beccaria, clouds of snow differ in nothing from
                    clouds of rain, but in the circumstance of cold that freezes them. Both the
                    regular diffiιsion of the snow, and the regularity of the structure of its
                    parts, particularly some figures of snow or hail which fall about Turin, show
                    that clouds of snow are acted upon by some uniform cause like electricity; and
                    he endeavours to show how electricity is capable of forming these figures. He
                    was confirmed in his conjectures by perceiving, that his apparatus for observing
                    the electricity of the atmosphere never failed to be electrified by snow as well
                    as rain. Professor Winthrop sometimes found his apparatus electrified by snow
                    when driven about by the wind, though it had not been affected by it when the
                    snow itself was falling. A more intense electricity, according to Beccaria,
                    unites the particles of hail more closely than the more moderate electricity
                    does those of snow, in the same manner as we see that the drops of rain which
                    fall from thunder-clouds are larger than those which fall from others, though
                    the former descend through a less space.</p>
                <p part="N">But we are not to consider snow merely as a curious and beautiful
                    phenomenon. The Great Dispenser of universal bounty has so ordered it, that it
                    is eminently subservient, as well as all the works of creation, to his
                    benevolent designs. Were we to judge from appearances only, we might imagine,
                    that so far from being useful to the earth, the cold humidity of snow would be
                    detrimental to vegetation. But the experience of all ages asserts the contrary.
                    Snow, particularly in those northern regions where the ground is covered with it
                    for several months, fructifies the earth, by guarding the corn or other
                    vegetables from the intenser cold of the air, and especially from the cold
                    piercing winds.<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=498"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0720-0498-0432"/> Snow or ice water is always deprived of its
                    fixed air, which escapes during the process of congelation. Accordingly, as some
                    of the inhabitants of the Alps who use it for their constant drink, have
                    enormous wens upon their throats, it has been ascribed to this circumstance. If
                    this were the cause of these wens, it would be easy to remove it by exposing the
                    snow-water to the air for some time. But several eminent physicians have
                    rejected the notion that snowwater is the cause of these wens; for in Greenland,
                    where snow-water is commonly used, the inhabitants are not affected with such
                    swellings; and on the other hand, they are common in Sumatra, where snow is
                    never seen.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
