<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0097-0083-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SELKIRK, A lexander</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xk84v4n">Swallows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41g0j38j">Swallowing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=97" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SELKIRK, A <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >lexander</hi></label>, whose adventures gave rise to Defoe’s well-known
                    historical romance of Robinson Crusoe, was born at Largo, in Fifeshire,
                    Scotland, about the year 1676. He was bred a seaman, and went from England in
                    1703, in the capacity of sailing-master of a small vessel called the
                    Cinque-Ports galley, Charles Pickering captain. In September the same year he
                    sailed from Cork, in company with another ship called the St George, commanded
                    by the celebrated navigator William Dampier, intended to cruise against the
                    Spaniards in the South Sea. On the coast of Brazil, Pickering died, and was
                    succeeded in the command by his lieutenant Thomas Stradling. They proceeded on
                    their voyage round Cape Horn to the island of Juan Fernandez, whence they were
                    driven by the appearance of two French ships of thirty-six guns each, and left
                    five of Stradling's men there on shore, who were taken off by the French. From
                    this they sailed to the coast of America, where Dampier and Stradling
                    quarrelled, and separated by agreement, on the 19th of May 1704. In September
                    following, Stradling came again to the island of Juan Fernandez, where Selkirk
                    and his captain had a difference, which, with the circumstance of the ship’s
                    being very leaky, and in bad condition, induced him to determine upon staying
                    there alone; but when his companions were about to depart, his resolution was
                    shaken, and he desired to be taken on board again. The captain, however, refused
                    to admit him, and he was obliged to remain, having nothing but his clothes,
                    bedding, a gun, and a small quantity of powder and ball; a hatchet, a knife, and
                    a kettle; with his books, and mathematical and nautical instruments. He kept up
                    his spirits tolerably till he saw the vessel put off, when, as he afterwards
                    related, his heart yearned within him, and melted at parting at once with his
                    comrades and all human society.</p>
                <p part="N">Thus left sole monarch of the island, with plenty of the necessaries of
                    life, he found himself in a situation which was hardly supportable. He had fish,
                    goats’ flesh, turnips and other vegetables; yet he grew dejected, languid, and
                    melancholy, to such a degree, as to be scarcely able to refrain from doing
                    violence to himself. Eighteen months passed before he could, by reasoning,
                    reading his Bible, and study, be thoroughly reconciled to his condition. At
                    length he grew happy, employing himself in decorating his huts, chasing the
                    goats, whom he equalled in speed, and scarcely ever failed in catching. He also
                    tamed young kids, laming them to prevent their becoming wild; and he kept a
                    guard of tame cats about him, to defend him when asleep from the rats, that were
                    very troublesome. When his clothes were worn out, he made others of goat-skins,
                    but could not succeed in making shoes, with the use of which, however, habit, in
                    time, enabled him to dispense. His only liquor was water. He computed that
                    during his abode in the island he had caught a thousand goats, of which he had
                    let go five hundred, after marking them by slitting their ears. Commodore
                    Anson’s people, who were there about thirty years afterwards, found the first
                    goat which they shot upon landing was thus marked, and, as it appeared to be
                    very old, concluded that it had been under the power of Selkirk. But it appears
                    by Captain Carteret’s account of his voyage in the Swallow sloop, that other
                    pcrsons practised this mode of marking, as he found a goat with his ears thus
                    slit on the neighbouring island of Mas-a-fuera, where Selkirk never was. He made
                    companions of his tame goats and cats, often dancing and singing with them.
                    Although he constantly performed his devotions at stated hours, and read aloud,
                    yet, when he was taken off the island, his language, from disuse of
                    conversation, had become scarcely intelligible. In this solitude he continued
                    four years and four months, during which time only two incidents happened which
                    he thought worth relating, the occurrences of every day being in his
                    circumstances nearly similar. The one was, that, pursuing a goat eagerly, he
                    caught it just on the edge of a precipice, which was covered with bushes, so
                    that he did not perceive it; and he fell to the bottom, where he lay, according
                    to Captain Rogers’s account, twenty-four hours senseless; but, as he related to
                    Sir Richard Steele, he computed, by the alteration of the moon, that he had lain
                    three days. When he came to himself, he found the goat lying under him dead. It
                    was with great difficulty that he could crawl to his habitation, whence he was
                    unable to stir for ten days, and did not recover of his bruises for a long time.
                    The other event was the arrival of a ship, which he at first supposed to be
                    French. And such is the natural love of society in the human mind, that he was
                    eager to abandon his solitary felicity, and surrender himself to them, although
                    enemies; but upon their landing he found them to be Spaniards, of whom he had
                    too great a dread to trust himself in their hands. They were by this time so
                    near that it required all his agility to escape, which he effected by climbing
                    into a thick tree, being shot at several times as he ran off. Fortunately the
                    Spaniards did not discover him, though they stayed some time under the tree
                    where he was hidden, and killed some goats just by. In this solitude Selkirk
                    remained until the 2d of February 1709, when he saw two ships come into the bay,
                    and knew them to be English. He immediately lighted a fire as a signal; and on
                    their coming on shore, found they were the Duke, Captain Rogers, and the
                    Duchess, Captain Courtney, being two privateers from Bristol. He gave them the
                    best entertainment he could afford; and as they had been a long time at sea
                    without fresh provisions, the goats which he caught were highly acceptable. His
                    habitation, consisting of two huts, one to sleep in, and the other for dressing
                    his food, was so obscurely situated, and so difficult of access, that only one
                    of the ship’s officers would accompany him to it. Dampier, who was pilot on
                    board the Duke, and knew Selkirk very well, told Captain Rogers that, when on
                    board the Cinque-Ports, he was the best seaman in the vessel, upon which Captain
                    Rogers appointed him master’s mate of the Duke-After a fortnight’s stay at Juan
                    Fernandez, the ships proceeded on their cruize against the Spaniards; plundered
                    a town on the coast of Peru; took a Manilla ship off Califor-<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=98" xml:id="kp-eb0720-0098-0084"
                    /> nia; and returned by way of the East Indies to England, where they arrived on
                    the 1st of October 1711; Selkirk having been absent, on the day of his arrival
                    in London, eight years one month and three days, more than half of which time he
                    had spent alone on the island. The public curiosity being excited respecting
                    him, he was induced to put his papers into the hands of Defoe, to arrange and
                    form them into a regular narrative. These papers must have been drawn up after
                    he left Juan Fernandez, as he had no means of recording his transactions there.
                    Captain Cooke remarks, as an extraordinary circumstance, that he had contrived
                    to keep an account of the days of the week and the month; but this might be
                    done, as Defoe makes Robinson Crusoe do, by cutting notches in a post, or many
                    other methods. From this account of Selkirk, Defoe adopted the notion of writing
                    a more extensive work, the romance of Robinson Crusoe, and very dishonestly
                    defrauded the original proprietor of his share of the profits. After his return
                    to England he waited in London till he got his effects realized, and then
                    proceeded, in the spring of 1712, to his native village Largo. For a few days he
                    enjoyed the society of his relatives and friends; but, from long habit, he soon
                    felt averse to society, and was most happy in being alone. In the upper part of
                    the garden attached to his father’s house, he formed a kind of cave or grotto,
                    which commanded an extensive and delightful view of the bay of Largo, and the
                    shores of the Forth. In musing here, or wandering through a secluded and
                    solitary valley called Keil’s Den, and fishing in the bay, he spent the greater
                    part of his time. How long he remained here cannot be ascertained, but he eloped
                    some time afterwards with a girl of the neighbourhood, named Sophia Bruce, and
                    proceeded with her to London. He never returned to Largo, and but little is
                    known of him during the latter part of his life. Sophia Bruce appears to have
                    died between 1717 and 1720; for in the latter year he again married Frances
                    Candis, who survived him. Selkirk died lieutenant on board his majesty’s ship
                    Weymouth, some time in the year 1723; and it is believed that he had no children
                    by either of his wives.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Life and Adventures of Alexander Selkirk, by John Howell,
                            Edinburgh.</p></note></p>
                <p part="N">S <hi rend="smallcaps">elkirk,</hi> an ancient royal burgh, and chief
                    town of the county of Selkirk, in Scotland. It is situated on an elevation
                    overlooking the valley of the river Ettrick, and commands an extensive view. It
                    consists chiefly of one street, which expands at the market-place into an open
                    space; and in it is the ancient tolbooth. In addition to this main street, there
                    are a few small streets that diverge from it. The town has not increased in size
                    or in importance for centuries; but it has been much improved of late years, and
                    now contains many good houses, with a town-hall, having an elegant spire 110
                    feet in height, and in which there are apartments for the burgh and sheriff
                    courts. There are two places of worship, one belonging to the established
                    church, and the other to the United Associate Synod. A new prison has been
                    erected at the north side of the town; and it also possesses several excellent
                    schools, in which the classics, French, Italian, and the more usual branches,
                    are taught.</p>
                <p part="N">Selkirk was formerly famed for the manufacture of shoes, in which it had
                    an extensive trade; but it has now no manufactures of any consequence, the
                    restrictions on trade, and the jealousy of the burghers or freemen, preventing
                    young men of small capital from pushing business, and forcing them to repair to
                    places more open to enterprise. The property of the burgh extends to 1784 acres,
                    and its yearly income amounts to nearly L.1100. In 1833, its debts amounted to
                    L. 16,088. It is governed by a provost, two bailies, a treasurer, and
                    twenty-nine councillors; and it votes with the county in returning a member to
                    parliament. The population of the burgh and parish in 1821 amounted to 2728, and
                    in 1831 to 2833. The population of the burgh alone in the latter year was
                    1880.</p>
                <p part="N">During the wars between England and Scotland the citizens of Selkirk
                    were famed for their courage. A party of them, amounting to between eighty and a
                    hundred, under the command of the town-clerk, William Brydone, proceeded to the
                    battle of Flodden, and fought with such gallantry that only a few returned.
                    Brydone was afterwards knighted for his conduct; and the town received from
                    James V. a grant of a thousand acres, as a recompense for the courage of the
                    burghers, and for the town being totally burned by the English, in revenge for
                    the bravery displayed by them at that battle. Brydone’s sword is still in the
                    possession of his lineal descendants; and a pennon, taken, it is believed, from
                    the Percys, by a person of the name of Fletcher, is still kept by the successive
                    deacons of the weavers, and displayed on all civic occasions by that
                    corporation. A mile north from the town is Philiphaugh, where the celebrated
                    Marquis of Montrose was defeated by the covenanters under General Leslie.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
