<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0720-0105-0091-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SENECA, L ucoius Annaeus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zx91">Anger</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v97zt6b">Poisoners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3821v">Poisons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068139">Poisoners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068184">Poisons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1096993">Rhetoricians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808763">Anger</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=105" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SENECA, L <hi rend="smallcaps">ucoius
                        Annaeus</hi></label>, a Stoical philosopher, was born at Cordoba, in Spain,
                    about the beginning of the Christian era, of an equestrian family, which had
                    probably been transplanted thither in a colony from Rome. He was the second son
                    of Marcus Annaeus Seneca, commonly called the Rhetorician, whose remains are
                    printed under the title of <hi rend="italic">Suasoria et controversia, cum
                        Declamation urn Excerptis;</hi> and his youngest brother Annaeus Mela, for
                    there were three of them, had the honour of being father to the poet Lucan. He
                    was removed to Rome, together with his father and the rest of his family, while
                    he was yet in his infancy. There he was educated in the most liberal manner, and
                    under the best masters. He learned eloquence from his father; but his genius
                    rather leading him to philosophy, he put himself under the stoics Attalus,
                    Sotion, and Papirius Fabianus, men famous in their way, and of whom he has made
                    honourable mention in his writings. It is probable, too, that he travelled when
                    he was young, since we find him, in several parts of his works, particularly in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Quastiones Naturales,</hi> making very exact and curious
                    observations upon Egypt and the Nile. But this, though entirely agreeable to his
                    own humour, did not at all correspond with that plan of life which his father
                    had drawn out for him; and therefore he forced him to the bar, and put him upon
                    soliciting for public employments, so that he afterwards became quaestor,
                    praetor, and, as Lipsius will have it, even consul.</p>
                <p part="N">In the first year of the reign of Claudius, when Julia the daughter of
                    Germanicus was accused of adultery by Mesgalina, and banished, Seneca was also
                    banished, being charged as one of the adulterers. Corsica was the seat of his
                    exile, where he lived eight years, “happy in the midst of those things which
                    usually make other people miserable” <hi rend="italic">(inter eas res beatus qua
                        solent miseros facere);</hi> and he wrote his books of consolation,
                    addressed to his mother Helvia, and to his friend Polybius, and perhaps some of
                    those tragedies which go under his name. Agrippina being married to Claudius
                    upon the death of Messalina, she prevailed with the emperor to recall Seneca
                    from banishment, and afterwards procured his appointment as tutor to her son
                    Nero, whom she designed for the empire. Africanus Bur rhus, a praetorian
                    praefect, was joined with him in tills important charge; and these two
                    preceptors, who were intrusted with equal authority, had each his respective
                    department. By the bounty and generosity of his royal pupil, Seneca acquired
                    that prodigious wealth which rendered him in a manner equal to kings. His houses
                    and walks were the most magnificent in Rome. His villas were innumerable; and he
                    had immense sums of money placed out at interest in almost every part of the
                    world. The historian Dio reports him to have had L.250,000 sterling at interest
                    in Britain alone, and reckons his calling it in all at once as one of the causes
                    of a war with that nation.</p>
                <p part="N">All this wealth, however, together with the luxury and effeminacy of the
                    court, does not appear to have had any ill effect upon the temper and
                    disposition of Seneca. He continued abstemious, exact in his manners, and, above
                    all, free from the vices so commonly prevalent in such places, flattery and
                    ambition. “I had rather,” said he to Nero, “offend you by speaking the truth,
                    than please you by lying and flattery” <hi rend="italic">(maluerim veris
                        offendere, quam placere adulando).</hi> How well he acquitted himself in
                    quality of preceptor to his prince, may be known from the first five years of
                    Nero’s reign, which have always been considered as a perfect pattern of good
                    government; and if that emperor had but been as observant of his master through
                    the whole course of it as he was at the beginning, he would have been the
                    delight, and not, as he afterwards proved, the curse and detestation, of
                    mankind. But when Poppaea and Tigellinus had got the command of his humour, and
                    hurried him into the most extravagant and abominable vices, he soon grew weary
                    of his master, whose life must indeed have been a constant rebuke to him.
                    Seneca, perceiving that his favour declined at court, and that he had many
                    accusers about the prince, who were perpetually whispering in his ear the great
                    riches of Seneca, his magnificent houses and fine gardens, and what a favourite,
                    through the means of these, he was grown with the people, made an offer of them
                    all to Nero. Nero refused to accept them. This, however, did not hinder Seneca
                    from changing his way of life; for, as Tacitus relates, he “kept no more levees,
                    declined the usual civilities which had been paid to him, and, under pretence of
                    indisposition, or some engagement or other, avoided as much as possible
                    appearing in public.”</p>
                <p part="N">In the mean time Nero, who, as it is supposed, had despatched Burrhus by
                    poison, could not be easy till he had also rid himself of Seneca; for Burrhus
                    was the manager of his military concerns, and Seneca conducted his civil
                    affairs. Accordingly, he attempted, by means of Cleonicus, a freedman of Seneca,
                    to take him off by poison; but as this did not succeed, he ordered him to be put
                    to death, upon an information that he was privy to Piso’s conspiracy against his
                    person. Not that he had any real proof of Seneca’s being concerned in this plot,
                    but only that he was glad to lay hold of any pretence for destroying him. He
                    left Seneca, however, at liberty to choose his manner of dying; and the latter
                    caused his veins to be opened immediately. His wife Paulina, who was very young
                    in comparison of himself, had yet the resolution and affection to bear him
                    company, and therefore ordered her veins to be at the same time opened; but as
                    Nero was not willing to make his cruelty more odious and insupportable than
                    there seemed occasion for, he gave orders to have her death prevented. Her
                    wounds were therefore bound up, and the blood stopped, just in time enough to
                    save her; though, as Tacitus says, she looked so miserably pale and wan all her
                    life afterwards, that it was easy to read the loss of her blood and spirits in
                    her countenance. In the mean time, Seneca, finding his death slow and lingering,
                    desired Statius Annaeus, his physician, to give him a dose of poison, which had
                    been prepared some time before in case it should be wanted; but this not having
                    had its usual effect, he was carried to a hot bath, where he was at length<pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490924&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=106"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0720-0106-0092"/> stifled with the steam. He died, as Lipsius
                    conjectures, in the sixty-third or sixty-fourth year of his age, and in about
                    the tenth or eleventh of Nero’s reign. Tacitus, on mentioning his death,
                    observes, that, as he entered the bath, he took of the water, and with it
                    sprinkled some of his nearest domestics, saying, “that he offered these
                    libations to Jupiter the Deliverer.” These words are an evident proof that
                    Seneca was not a Christian, as some have imagined him to have been; and that the
                    thirteen epistles from Seneca to St Paul, and from St Paul to Seneca, are
                    supposititious pieces. The writings of Seneca, excepting his books of Physical
                    Questions, are chiefly of a moral kind. They consist of a hundred and
                    twenty-four epistles, and distinct treatises on Anger, Consolation, Providence,
                    Tranquillity of Mind, Constancy, Clemency, The Shortness of Life, Happiness,
                    Retirement, and Benefits. A number of tragedies are extant under the name of
                    Seneca, and written in a vicious style; but it is uncertain whether the whole or
                    any part of them were his. The first good edition of his acknowledged works was
                    published by Justus Lipsius, which was succeeded by the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Variorum,</hi> 1672, three vols. 8vo, and others. Of the tragedies, the
                    best are that of Scriverius, 1621, the <hi rend="italic">Variorum,</hi> 1651,
                    and Schroeder's, 1728, 4to.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
