<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0898-0858-13" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WESLEY, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018703">Methodists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926972">Flame</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rj4928x">Potters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09w92">Addresses</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=898" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">WESLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>,
                    founder of the sect of Methodists, was the son of Samuel Wesley, rector of
                    Epworth, in the isle of Axholme in Lincolnshire, and was born in that village in
                    the year 1703. His very infancy was distinguished by an extraordinary incident;
                    for when he was only six years old, the parsonage-house at Epworth was burnt to
                    the ground, and the flames had spread with such rapidity that few things of
                    value could be saved. His mother, in a letter to her son, Samuel Wesley, then on
                    the foundation at Westminster school, thanks God that no lives were lost,
                    although for some time they gave up <hi rend="italic">Poor Jachy,</hi> as she
                    expresses herself; for his father had twice attempted to rescue the child, but
                    was beaten back by the flames. Finding all his efforts ineffectual, he resigned
                    him to divine providence. But parental tenderness prevailed over human fears,
                    and Mr Wesley once more attempted to save his child. By some means equally <pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=899"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0899-0859"/>unexpected and unaccountable, the boy got
                    round to a window in the front of the house, and was taken out by one man's
                    leaping on the shoulders of another, and thus getting within his reach.
                    Immediately on his rescue from this very perilous situation, the roof fell in.
                    This extraordinary escape explains a certain device, in a print of John Wesley,
                    engraved by Vertue in the year 1745, from a painting by Williams. It represents
                    a house in flames, with this motto from the prophet, “Is he not a brand plucked
                    out of the burning?” Many have supposed this device to be merely emblematical of
                    his spiritual deliverance; but from this circumstance it is apparent that it has
                    a primary as well as a secondary meaning; it is real as well as allusive.</p>
                <p part="N">In the year 1713 he was entered a scholar at the Charter-house in
                    London, where he continued seven years under the tuition of Dr Walker, and of
                    the Rev. Andrew Tooke, author of the Pantheon. In his seventeenth year he was
                    sent to Christ Church at Oxford. In 1726 he was elected a fellow of Lincoln
                    College, and took the degree of A. Μ. in 1727. He was afterwards appointed a
                    tutor of his college. He discovered very early an elegant turn for poetry. Some
                    of his gayer poetical effusions are proofs of a lively fancy and a fine
                    classical taste; and some translations from the Latin poets, while at college,
                    are allowed to have great merit. He had early a strong impression, like Count
                    Zinzendorf, of his designation to some extraordinary work. This impression
                    received additional force from some domestic incidents, all which his active
                    fancy turned to his own account. His wonderful preservation, already noticed,
                    naturally tended to cherish the idea of his being designed by Providence to
                    accomplish some purpose or other that was out of the ordinary course of human
                    events.</p>
                <p part="N">The reading of the writings of Mr William Law, the celebrated author of
                    Christian Perfection, and of a Serious Address to the Christian World,
                    contributed to lead John Wesley and his brother Charles, with a few of their
                    young fellow-students, into a more than common strictness of religious life.
                    They received the sacrament of the Lord’s Supper every week, observed all the
                    fasts of the church, visited the prisons, rose at four in the morning, and
                    refrained from all amusements. From the exact method in which they disposed of
                    every hour, they acquired the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Methodists;</hi>
                    by which their followers have been ever since distinguished.</p>
                <p part="N">From Dr Potter, bishop of Oxford, he received deacon’s orders in 1725,
                    and priest’s in 1728. For some time he officiated as his father’s curate. But
                    the boundaries of this island were soon deemed by Wesley too confined for a zeal
                    which displayed the piety of an apostle, and of an intrepidity to which few
                    missionaries had been superior. In 1735 he embarked for Georgia, one of our
                    colonies, which was at that time in a state of political infancy; and the great
                    object of this voyage was to preach the gospel to the Indian nations in the
                    vicinity of that province. He returned to England in 1737. Of his spiritual
                    labours, both in this country and in America, he himself has given a very
                    copious account, in a series of Journals printed at different periods. These
                    journals drew upon our laborious preacher and his coadjutors some severe
                    animadversions from two prelates, Dr Lavington, bishop of Exeter, and Dr
                    Warburton, bishop of Gloucester. The former published, in three parts, the
                    Enthusiasm of the Methodists and Papists compared; the third part of this
                    performance containing a personal charge of immoral conduct. Mr Wesley, in his
                    vindication, published a letter to his lordship, which produced a reply from the
                    latter. Bishop Warburton’s attack is contained in his celebrated treatise,
                    entitled “The Doctrine of Grace: or, the Office and Operations of the Holy
                    Spirit vindicated from the Insults of Infidelity, and the Abuses of Fanaticism:
                    concluding with some thoughts, humbly offered to the consideration of the
                    Established Clergy, with regard to the right Method of defending Religion
                    against the Attacks of either party.” Lond. 1762, 2 vols. 8vo. There is much
                    acute reasoning, and much poignant and sprightly wit, in his Doctrine of Grace;
                    but there is too much levity in it for a grave bishop, and too much abuse for a
                    candid Christian. On this occasion Wesley published a letter to the bishop, in
                    which, with great temper and moderation, as well as with great ingenuity and
                    address, he endeavoured to shelter himself from his lordship’s attacks, not only
                    under the authority of the holy Scriptures, but of the church itself as by law
                    established.</p>
                <p part="N">On his return from Georgia, Mr Wesley paid a visit to Count Zinzendorf,
                    the celebrated founder of the sect of Moravians or Hernhutters, at Hernhut in
                    Upper Lusatia. In the following year he appeared again in England, and with his
                    brother Charles, at the head of the Methodists. He preached his first field
                    sermon at Bristol, on the 2d of April 1738, from which time his disciples have
                    continued to increase. In 1741 a serious altercation took place between him and
                    Whitefield. In 1744, attempting to preach at an inn at Taunton, he was regularly
                    silenced by the magistrates. Although he chiefly resided for the remainder of
                    his life in the metropolis, he occasionally travelled through every part of
                    Great Britain and Ireland, establishing congregations in each kingdom. In 1750
                    he married a lady, from whom he was afterwards separated. By this lady, who died
                    in 1781, he had no children. He had been gradually declining for three years
                    before his death; yet he still rose at four in the morning, and preached, and
                    travelled, and wrote as usual. He preached at Leatherhead in Surrey, on the
                    Wednesday before that event. On the Friday following, appeared the first
                    symptoms of his approaching dissolution. The four succeeding days he spent in
                    praising God; and he left this scene, at a quarter before ten in the morning of
                    the 2d of March 1791, in the 88th year of his age. His remains, after lying in a
                    kind of state at his chapel in the City Road, dressed in the sacerdotal robes
                    which he usually wore, and on his head the old clerical cap, a Bible in one
                    hand, and a white handkerchief in the other, were, agreeably to his own
                    directions, and after the manner of the interment of Mr Whitefield, deposited in
                    the cemetery behind his chapel, on the morning of the 9th March, amid an
                    innumerable concourse of his friends and admirers, many of whom appeared in deep
                    mourning on the occasion.</p>
                <p part="N">Wesley was a very various and voluminous writer. Divinity, both
                    devotional and controversial, biography, history, philosophy, politics, and
                    poetry, were all, at different times, the subjects of his pen; and whatever
                    opinion may be entertained of his theological sentiments, it is impossible to
                    deny him the merit of having done very extensive good among the lower classes of
                    people. He certainly possessed great abilities, and a fluency which was well
                    accommodated to his hearers, and highly acceptable to them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
