<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0943-0903-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WINTON, Andrew</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c55w">Amazons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1113088">Serfs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806706">Amazons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=943" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">WINTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew</hi></label>,
                    prior of Lochleven, appears to have been born during the reign of David the
                    Second, which extended from 1329 to 1370. For the few scattered notices of him
                    that have been preserved, we are chiefly indebted to the valuable work which has
                    transmitted his name to posterity. Of his parentage and education no record has
                    hitherto been discovered; but we learn from his prologue that he was a canon
                    regular of St Andrews, and prior of the monastery of St Serf. The priory of St
                    Andrews was endowed with very ample revenues; and the prior, in consideration of
                    his connection with the metropolitan cathedral, was entitled to take precedence
                    of all priors, <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=944"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0944-0904"/>and even of all abbots. There were five
                    subordinate priories belonging to St Andrews; namely, those of St Serf in the
                        <hi rend="italic">inch</hi> or isle of Lochleven, Portmoak on the northern
                    bank of the same lake, both in the county of Kinross, Pittenweem in the
                    neighbouring county of Fife, the isle of May near the termination of the Firth
                    of Forth, and Monymusk in the county of Aberdeen. In the isle of Lochleven there
                    was a very ancient religious house belonging to the Culdees, for whom the canons
                    regular of St Augustin were afterwards substituted by the bishop of St Andrews.
                    The beautiful and romantic situation of this priory furnished a very suitable
                    abode for a poet; and here Winton must chiefly have resided during a
                    considerable part of his life. In the Chartulary of the Priory of St Andrews,
                    which is now printed, there are several documents bearing the name of Andrew
                    Winton as prior of Lochleven between the years 1395 and 1413; but his life must
                    have been prolonged several years after this last date, for he mentions the
                    death of Robert duke of Albany, an event which happened in 1420. In the prologue
                    to the last book of his chronicle, he expresses his anticipation of a speedy
                    dissolution.</p>
                <p part="N">His Orygynale Cronykil of Scotland was undertaken at the suggestion of
                    Sir John Wemyss, ancestor of the noble family of that name.</p>
                <p part="N">This tretys sympylly</p>
                <p part="N">I made at the instans of a larde That hade my serwys in his warde, Schyr
                    Jhone of the Wemya be rycht name, Ane honest knycht and of gude fame.</p>
                <p part="N">Winton’s chronicle, while it yet remained in manuscript, was not
                    entirely neglected by more curious enquirers: it was quoted by Selden, a writer
                    of prodigious research, who was not however acquainted with the author’s name;
                    it afforded some useful information to Ruddiman for his edition of Buchanan, and
                    to Innes for his Critical Essay on the Ancient Inhabitants of Scotland; nor was
                    it completely overlooked by Lord Hailes and Mr Pinkerton. Of that portion which
                    relates more immediately to Scotish affairs, a splendid edition was at length
                    published by the late David Macpherson, who has added a copious glossary, a
                    series of valuable annotations, and other useful appendages.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">The orygynale
                            Cronykil of Scotland, be Λndrow of Wyntown, Priowr of Sanct Serfis Yncbe
                            in Loch Levyn, &amp;c. Lond. 1795, 2 vols. 4to &amp; 8vo.</p></note> It
                    may safely be affirmed that none of our ancient writers has yet been edited in a
                    more faithful and judicious manner. The basis of his text is the Royal MS. in
                    the British Museum: this appears to have been transcribed for George Barclay of
                    Achrody, and its date is supposed to be at least as early as the year 1430; but
                    he likewise had recourse to several other manuscripts, belonging to the same
                    institution and to the Advocates Library.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">Of Winton's chronicle a considerable number of
                            MSS. is mentioned by Macpherson, but several others are known to be
                            preserved. There is one in the Lansdowne collection, lately added to the
                            British Museum, another in the library of the university of St Andrews,
                            and a third in that of Captain Wemyss of Wemyss.</p></note> ®</p>
                <p part="N">The chronicle of Winton is valuable as a specimen of the literary taste
                    and attainments of our ancestors at a very remote period, but it is still more
                    valuable as a repository of historical information, and as a delineation of
                    ancient manners. His simple pages present to our view many curious prospects of
                    society; and with a perseverance of industry which had numerous difficulties to
                    encounter, he has collected and preserved many anecdotes that tend to illustrate
                    the history of his native country. He divides his work into nine books, “in
                    honour of the orders nine of holy angels.” Although he merely professes to wτite
                    an original chronicle of Scotland, yet, like other Gothic chroniclers, he
                    presents his readers with an outline of the ancient history of the world.
                    Towards the beginning of his work, he treats of the nature of angels, the
                    creation of the world, the death of Abel, the generations of Cain and Seth, the
                    primeval race of giants, the situation of India, Egypt, Africa, Europe, Britain,
                    Ireland, and divers other countries, the confusion of tongues, and the origin of
                    poetry and idolatry. One chapter he devotes to the history of the Amazons, and
                    another to that of Samson. After commencing in so hopeful a manner, he continues
                    to amass an immense pile of lumber, till having completed five books in this
                    pantographical spirit, he at last confines himself more soberly to his proper
                    subject. The adoption of such a plan is not to be considered as peculiar to the
                    author: Winton follows the models which at that period were generally approved;
                    and the Latin chronicle of Fordun, who was nearly contemporary, is composed of
                    the same heterogeneous materials. (x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
