<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0954-0914-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WOLOGDA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gw7g">Flax</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:813025">Archangels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927119">Flax</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=954" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">WOLOGDA</label>, one of those large divisions into
                    which the European part of the Russian empire is formed, and commonly
                    denominated a government or stadtholdership. The extent is given differently by
                    several authors; but as Storch seems the preferable authority, it is here given
                    according to his representation, at 151,074 square miles. It extends in north
                    latitude from 58° 23’ to 64° 56', and in east longitude from 38° 47’ to 57° 10'.
                    It is bounded on the north by Archangel, on the north-east by Tobolsk, on the
                    south-east by Perm and by Wiatka, on the south by Kostroma, on the south-west by
                    Jaroslaw, on the west by Novogorod, and on the north-west by Olonetz.</p>
                <p part="N">The surface of this province is a most extensive plain, on the eastern
                    side touching the Ural Mountains, a few branches or spurs from which penetrate
                    into the north-east part. Besides these, no hills are to be seen, and but few
                    elevations, but immeasurable woods, broad heaths and morasses, small lakes, and
                    especially a most abundant supply of water in streams of all dimensions. The
                    soil is of various qualities, clayey, loamy, and sandy, and in some parts there
                    is good marl. There are however some tracts of good alluvial soil to be found
                    over the worst subsoils. In most parts it is capable of cultivation, but the
                    best portions are the south-west parts of the province. Cultivation in the whole
                    province requires watchfulness with respect both to the weather, the nature of
                    the soil, the rotation of crops, and the nature and quantity of manure; but,
                    with the greatest attention to them, it is not common to obtain more than five
                    times the quantity of the seed that is sown, even of rye, which is the most
                    extensive crop; whereas in barley and oats not three times the seed are commonly
                    obtained. Besides those kinds of grain, a little winter wheat is sown, and some
                    pease. It is only in very good years that sufficient corn for the consumption is
                    grown. According to Storch, the annual quantity of rye and wheat together does
                    not exceed four English bushels for each person. Flax and hemp succeed better
                    than either kind of grain. In some of the divisions beyond the Dwina, no other
                    corn but barley is attempted to be raised. In the northeast part no fruit is
                    grown; but in the south-west, in the gardens, apples and cherries come to a
                    tolerable degree of ripeness. The cultivation of potatoes has of late years been
                    introduced or extended, and affords a prospect of increasing the means of
                    subsistence.</p>
                <p part="N">The manufacturing industry is not considerable, and only extends to
                    common necessaries, such as woollen and linen goods, from their own sheep and
                    flax. A little paper, some glass and earthenware, and a few metal articles, form
                    the chief part of the products, exclusive of the leather, and of the brandy,
                    which is distilled from corn in prodigious quantities. During the long nights of
                    winter, spinning flax or wool is the constant occupation of the females, and
                    hence much yarn is produced and sold to other districts.</p>
                <p part="N">The trade is chiefly in domestic articles; and these are sent by the
                    rivers or canals in summer, or on sledges in winter, to St Petersburg or Moscow,
                    by merchants residing in the large towns. They are tallow candles, tar, peltry,
                    feathers, isinglass, marts, hogs’ bristles, turpentine, potash, and some wooden
                    furniture. There is a transit-trade, by which the productions of Siberia are
                    exchanged with those of Archangel. The number of persons employed in internal
                    navigation is very great; and besides these, others, living on the rivers that
                    are not navigable, are employed in summer in forming rafts of timber, which are
                    floated down by the stream till they reach the barges destined to convey them to
                    the places where the timber is wanted.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal rivers are, lst, The Dwina, which is composed of several
                    rivulets, which, when united, first receives that name within the province. It
                    then receives the waters of the Wytschegda, the Sysola, the Wym, the Keltma, and
                    the Ustjuga. After leaving the province, it is increased by the great stream of
                    the Vaga and its tributary brooks, and runs to the sea at Archangel. 2d, The
                    Petschora, a considerable river rising from the Ural Mountains, and forming a
                    means of intercourse between Tobolsk, Wologda, and Perm. It is navigable during
                    the whole summer, with a depth of from twelve to fourteen feet. There is also a
                    canal, constructed in 1786, which connects the waters of the rivers that run to
                    the Caspian with those that run to the Frozen Ocean. There arc many lakes, some
                    of them <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=955"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0955-0915"/>very extensive. The largest are the Kubenskoe,
                    the Piati-sorskoi, the Sandor, and the Rondas. This vast province, which in
                    extent is greater than Britain and Ireland, does not contain more than 940,000
                    inhabitants. These are divided into nobility, civil officers, clergy, colonists,
                    merchants, citizens, and peasants; the last being by far the most numerous. They
                    are in fact slaves, one third of whom belong to the nobility, and two thirds to
                    the crown. The whole of the inhabitants profess the Greek religion, and are
                    under the spiritual government of a bishop, whose see is in the city of Wologda.
                    'Γhe capital of the province, and also of a circle, is the city from which it
                    takes its name. It stands on both sides the river Wologda, which divides it into
                    two nearly equal parts, and is without fortifications. It contains fifty-one
                    churches, of which six only are of stone, and the others wooden structures. It
                    has a monastery, a nunnery, an ecclesiastical seminary, some charitable
                    institutions, and public schools for 600 sons of the clergy. The dwellings are
                    1664, of which all but forty-five are of wood. The inhabitants are 12,100, among
                    whom are many tanners, tallow-chandlers, and some makers of silk, linen, and
                    woollen goods. The commerce chiefly consists of the produce of the soil, or of
                    such manufactured goods as are of the simplest fabrication, which are sent to
                    the seaports in exchange for the few foreign commodities which the condition of
                    society may render desirable. The city is 870 miles from St Petersburg. Long.
                    40. 6. E. Lat. 59. 13. 30. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
