<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0908-0868-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WHARTON, Philip, Dure of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353235">Homes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=908" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">WHARTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip, Dure
                        of</hi></label>, a nobleman of the most brilliant parts, but of the most
                    whimsical, extravagant, and inconsistent turn of mind, was the son of Philip
                    marquis of Wharton. He was educated at home; and his father’s great aim was to
                    render him a complete orator. At a very early age he married a young lady, the
                    daughter of Major-general Holmes, which disappointed his father’s views of
                    disposing of him in such a marriage as would have been a considerable addition
                    to the fortune and grandeur of his illustrious family; yet that amiable lady
                    deserved infinitely more felicity than she met with by this alliance. This
                    precipitate marriage is thought to have hastened the death of his father; after
                    which the son, being free from paternal restraints, and possessing a fortune of
                    L.16,000 a year, plunged into those excesses which rendered him, as Pope
                    expresses it,</p>
                <p part="N">A tyrant to the wife his heart approv'd,</p>
                <p part="N">A rebel to the very king he lov’d.</p>
                <p part="N">In the beginning of the year 1716 he began his travels; and as he was
                    designed to be educated in the strictest Whig principles, Geneva was thought a
                    proper place for <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=909"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0909-0869"/>his residence. He first passed through
                    Holland, and visited several courts of Germany; and being arrived at Geneva,
                    conceived such a disgust against his governor, that he left him, and set out
                    post for Lyon, where he wrote a letter to the Chevalier de St George, who then
                    resided at Avignon, and presented him with a very fine stout horse; which the
                    chevalier no sooner received than he sent a man of quality to him, who took him
                    privately to his court, where he was entertained with the greatest marks of
                    esteem, and had the title of duke of Northumberland conferred upon him. He
                    however remained there but one day, and then returned to Lyon, whence he set out
                    for Paris. He likewise paid a visit to the dowager of James II. then residing at
                    St Germains. During his stay at Paris, his winning address and abilities gained
                    him the esteem and admiration of all the British subjects of rank of both
                    parties.</p>
                <p part="N">About the latter end of December 1716, he arrived in England, whence he
                    soon after set out for Ireland, where, though still under age, he was allowed
                    the honour to take his seat in the House of Peers, as earl of Rathfarnham and
                    marquis of Catherlough. Notwithstanding his former conduct, he immediately
                    distinguished himself as a violent partisan for the ministry; and in consequence
                    of his zeal the king created him a duke. He no sooner came of age than he was
                    introduced to the House of Lords in England with the same blaze of reputation.
                    In a little time he opposed the court, and appeared one of the most vigorous in
                    defence of the bishop of Rochester; and soon afterwards he printed his
                    lucubrations twice a week, in a paper called “The True Briton,” several thousand
                    copies of which were circulated.</p>
                <p part="N">The duke’s boundless profusion had by this time so burdened his estate,
                    that by a decree of Chancery it was vested in the hands of trustees for the
                    payment of his debts, allowing him a provision of L.1200 per annum for his
                    subsistence. This being insufficient to support his title with suitable dignity,
                    he went abroad, and appeared to great advantage at the imperial court. From
                    thence he made a tour to Spain. The English minister was alarmed at his arrival,
                    fearing that his grace was received in the character of an ambassador. The duke
                    received a summons under the privy seal to return home; but instead of obeying
                    it, he endeavoured to inflame the Spanish court against that of Great Britain,
                    for exercising an act of power, as he calls it, within the jurisdiction of his
                    Catholic majesty. He then acted openly in the service of the Pretender, and was
                    received at his court with the greatest marks of favour.</p>
                <p part="N">While his grace was thus employed, his neglected duchess died in England
                    on the l4th of April 1726, without issue. He soon afterwards fell violently in
                    love with Miss Obyrne, one of the maids of honour to the queen of Spain, the
                    daughter of an Irish colonel, whose fortune chiefly consisted in her personal
                    accomplishments. All his friends, and particularly the queen of Spain, opposed
                    the match; but he falling into a lingering fever, occasioned by his
                    disappointment, the queen gave her consent, and they were soon after married. He
                    then spent some time at Rome, where he accepted of a blue garter, assumed the
                    title of duke of Northumberland, and for a while enjoyed the confidence of the
                    exiled prince. But not always keeping within the bounds of Italian gravity, it
                    became necessary for him to remove from hence; when, going by sea to Barcelona,
                    he wrote a letter to the king of Spain, acquainting him that he would assist at
                    the siege of Gibraltar as a volunteer. Soon after he wrote to the Chevalier de
                    St George, expressing a desire to visit his court; but the chevalier advised him
                    to draw near to England.</p>
                <p part="N">The duke seemed resolved to follow his advice; and setting out with his
                    duchess, arrived in Paris in May 1728, whence he soon after proceeded to Rouen,
                    where he took up his residence; and was so far from making any conces sion to
                    the government of England, that he did not give himself the least trouble about
                    his estate, or any other concern there, though, on his arrival at Rouen, he had
                    only about L.600 in his possession, and a bill of indictment was preferred
                    against him in England for high treason. Soon after, the chevalier sent him
                    L.2000, which he squandered away in a course of extravagance, when, to save the
                    charges of travelling by land, he went from Orleans to Nantz by water, and staid
                    there till he got a remittance from Paris, which was squandered almost as soon
                    as received. At Nantz he was joined by his ragged servants, and from hence took
                    shipping with them for Bilboa, when the queen of Spain took the duchess to
                    attend her person. About the beginning of the year 1731, the duke, who commanded
                    a regiment, was at Lerida, but declined so fast that he could not move without
                    assistance, yet when free from pain did not lose his gaiety. He however received
                    benefit from some mineral waters in Catalonia; but soon after relapsed at a
                    small village, where he was utterly destitute of all the necessaries of life,
                    till some charitable fathers of a Bernardine convent removed him to their house,
                    and gave him all the relief in their power. Under their hospitable roof he
                    languished a week, and died on the 31st of May, without one friend or
                    acquaintance to close his eyes; and his funeral was performed in the same manner
                    in which the fathers inter the members of their own fraternity. He died without
                    issue, and his titles became extinct. The duchess survived till February
                    1777.</p>
                <p part="N">Two octavo volumes, published under the title of his Life and Writings,
                    include seventy-four papers of the True Briton, and his speech in defence of
                    Atterbury. Other two duodecimo volumes likewise bear his name; and the same life
                    occurs in a publication called “The Poetical Works of Philip late Duke of
                    Wharton, and others of the Wharton Family, and of the duke’s intimate
                    acquaintance,” &amp;c. Lond. 1731, 2 vols. 8vo. On such a collection as this no
                    reliance can be placed. Ritson intended to publish an edition of the duke’s
                    genuine poems, accompanied with an account of his life.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
