<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0710-7308-0257-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">FUNERAL Rites</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 10, page 257</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term><term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term><term n="18" ref="fasttopic:888385">Dead</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1058667">Personality</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1058664">Personalism</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193517308" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">FUNERAL <hi rend="smallcaps">Rites</hi></label>, ceremonies
                    accompanying the interment or burial of the dead. The word is formed of the
                    Latin <hi rend="italic">funus,</hi> and that of <hi rend="italic">funalia,</hi>
                    on account of the torches <hi rend="italic">(Junes</hi><hi rend="italic">cera
                    circumdati)</hi> used in the funerals of the Romans. Others, however, derive <hi rend="italic">funus</hi> from the Greek <hi rend="italic">φonς, death</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">slaughter.</hi></p><p>The first people who seem to have paid any particular respect to their dead were
                    the Egyptians, the posterity of Ham, the first cultivators of idolatrous worship
                    and superstition after the deluge. They were also the first who asserted the
                    immortality of the sou', its migration into all kinds of animals, and its return
                    to the human body, which they supposed to be within the term of three thousand
                    years. Hence the great care which they evinced in embalming their dead, and the
                    vast expense they incurred in building proper repositories for them. In fact,
                    they were more solicitous about graves for the dead than about houses for the
                    living. This is strikingly displayed in those stupendous remains of architecture
                    under ground which were appropriated to the reception of the dead, as well as
                    those above ground, such as the pyramids, where some of the Egyptian kings were
                    interred.</p><p>Amongst the Egyptians, when a person died, his parents and friends put on
                    mourning habits, and abstained from all banquets and entertainments. This
                    mourning lasted from forty to seventy days, during which period they embalmed
                    the body. After this ceremony was completed, it was restored to the friends, who
                    placed it in a kind of open chest, which was preserved either in their houses,
                    or in the sepulchres of their ancestors. But before the dead were allowed to be
                    deposited in the tomb, they underwent a solemn judgment, which extended even to
                    their kings. Of this remarkable custom we have a particular account in the first
                    book of Diodorus Siculus. “Those who prepare to bury a relative give notice of
                    the day intended for the ceremony to the judges, and to all the friends of the
                    deceased, informing them that the body will pass over the lake of that district
                    to which the dead belonged; when, on the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193517321" xml:id="kp-eb0710-7321-0258"/>judges
                    assembling, to the number of more than forty, and ranging themselves in a
                    semicircle on the further side of the lake, the vessel is set afloat, which
                    those who superintend the funeral have prepared for this purpose. This vessel is
                    managed by a pilot, called in the Egyptian language Charon; and hence they say,
                    that Orpheus, travelling in o&gt;d times into Egypt, and seeing this ceremony,
                    formed his fable of the infernal regions, partly from what he saw, ana partly
                    from invention. The vessel being launched on the lake, before the coffin which
                    contains the body is put on board, the law permits all who are so inclined to
                    produce an accusation against it. If any one steps forth and proves that the
                    deceased has led an evil life, the judges pronounce sentence, and the body is
                    precluded from burial; but if the accuser is convicted of injustice in his
                    charge he falls himself under a considerable penalty. When no accuser appears,
                    or when the accusation is proved to be an unfair one, the relations who are
                    assembled change their expressions of sorrow into encomiums on the dead; yet do
                    not, like the Greeks, speak in honour of his family, because they consider all
                    Egyptians as equally well born; but they set forth the education and manners of
                    his youth, his piety and justice in maturer life, his moderation, and every
                    virtue by which he was distinguished; and they supplicate the infernal deities
                    to receive him as an associate amongst the blessed. The multitude join their
                    acclamations of applause in this celebration of the dead, whom they consider as
                    going to pass an eternity amongst the just below.” Such is the description which
                    Diodorus gives of this funeral judicature, to which even the kings of Egypt were
                    subject. The same author asserts that many sovereigns had been thus judicially
                    deprived of the honours of burial by the indignation of their people; and that
                    the terrors of such a fate had the most salutary influence on the conduct of
                    their kings.</p><p>The funeral rites amongst the Hebrews were solemn and magnificent. Upon the
                    demise of any person, the relatives and friends of the deceased rent their
                    clothes. This custom is still imitated, but with a due regard to economy, by the
                    modern Jews, who only cut off a piece of their garment in token of affliction.
                    It was usual to bend the dead person’s thumb into the hand, and fasten it in
                    that posture with a string, because the thumb having then the figure of the name
                    of God, they thought the evil spirit would not dare to approach it. When they
                    came to the burying-place, they made a speech to the dead in the following
                    terms: “thessed be God, who has formed thee, fed thee, maintained thee, and
                    taken away thy life. O dead, he knows your numbers, and shall one day restore
                    your life and so on. After this they delivered the eulogium, or funeral oration,
                    upon the deceased; then said a prayer, called the “righteousness of judgment and
                    finally, turning the face of tire dead body towards heaven, they called out, “Go
                    in peace.”</p><p>Amongst the ancient Greeks it was usual sometimes, before the interment, to place
                    a piece of money in the mouth of the deceased, as Charon’s fare for wafting the
                    departed soul over the river Styx. This ceremony was considered as unnecessary
                    in those countries which were supposed to be situated in the neighbourhood of
                    the infernal regions, and to lead thither by a ready and direct road. The corpse
                    was likewise furnished with a cake, composed of flour, honey, and other
                    ingredients, which was designed to appease the fury of Cerberus, and to procure
                    the ghost a safe and quiet entrance. Whilst the corpse continued in the house, a
                    vessel of water was placed before the door, the design of which was, that those
                    concerned about the body might purify themselves by washing; it being the
                    opinion of the Greeks, as well as of the Jews, that pollution was contracted by
                    touching a dead body.</p><p>The ceremonies by which they expressed their sorrow for the death of their
                    friends were various; but it seems to have been a constant rule to recede as
                    much as possible in ' habit and behaviour from their ordinary customs. For this
                    reason they abstained from banquets and entertainments; they divested themselves
                    of all ornaments; and they tore, cut off, or shaved their hair, which they cast
                    into the funeral pile, to be consumed with the remains of their deceased friend.
                    Sometimes they threw themselves on the ground and rolled in the dust, or covered
                    their heads with ashes. They beat their breasts, and even tore their flesh with
                    their nails, upon the loss of a person whom they much lamented. When people of
                    rank, such as public magistrates or great generals, died, the whole city mourned
                    their loss. All public meetings were intermitted; the schools, baths, shops,
                    temples, and all places of concourse were shut up.</p><p>After interment followed the <hi rend="italic">epulιe</hi> or feasts, at which
                    the company used to appear crowned; and upon this occasion they spoke in praise
                    of the dead, as far as they could go with truth, it being esteemed a notorious
                    wickedness to disregard truth in their eulogiums. And not only at these feasts,
                    but even before the company quitted the sepulchre, they were sometimes
                    entertained with a panegyric upon the deceased.</p><p>The Grecian soldiers who died in battle had not only their tombs adorned with
                    inscriptions showing their names, parentage, and exploits, but were also
                    honoured with an oration in their praise. The custom amongst the Athenians in
                    the interment of their soldiers was as follows: “They used to place the bodies
                    of their dead in tents three days before the funeral, that all persons might
                    have an opportunity of finding out their relatives, and paying their last
                    respects to them. Upon the fourth day a coffin of cypress was sent from every
                    tribe to convey the bones of their own relatives; after which went a covered
                    hearse, in memory of those whose bodies could not be found. All these,
                    accompanied by a concourse of people, were carried to the public burying-place,
                    called Ceramicus, and there interred. One oration was spoken in commendation of
                    them all, and their monuments were adorned with pillars, inscriptions, and other
                    ornaments usual about the tombs of the most honourable persons. The oration was
                    pronounced by the fathers of the deceased persons who had behaved themselves
                    most valiantly. Thus, after the battle of Marathon, the fathers of Callimachus
                    and Cynaegyrus were appointed to pronounce the funeral oration. And on the
                    return of the day upon which the solemnity was first held, the same oration was
                    annually repeated.”</p><p>Interring or laying the dead in the ground seems to have been the most ancient
                    practice amongst the Greeks; though burning came afterwards to be generally had
                    recourse to. It was customary to throw into the funeral pile those garments
                    which the deceased had usually worn. The pile was lighted by one of his nearest
                    relatives or friends, who made prayers and vows to the wind to assist the
                    flames, that the body might quickly be reduced to ashes; and whilst the pile was
                    burning, the friends of the deceased stood by it, called upon him, and poured
                    out libations of wine.</p><p>The funeral rites amongst the ancient Romans were very numerous. The deceased was
                    kept seven days, and every day washed with hot water, and sometimes with oil,
                    that, in case he was only in a slumber, he might be thus awakened; and at
                    intervals his friends collected and raised a shout with the same intent. This
                    last act they called <hi rend="italic">conclamatio.</hi> The third conclamation
                    was on the seventh day; when, if no signs of life appeared, the defunct was
                    dressed and embalmed by the <hi rend="italic">pollinctores,</hi> placed in a bed
                    near the door, with his face and heels towards the street; and the outside of
                    the gate, if the deceased were of condition, was hung with cypress boughs. In
                    the course of these seven days an altar was raised near his bed side, called <hi rend="italic">accrra,</hi> on which his friends every day offered incense; and
                    the <hi rend="italic">libitinarii</hi> provided articles necessary for tire
                    interment.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193517334" xml:id="kp-eb0710-7334-0259"/><p>On the seventh day a public crier was sent about the city, inviting the people to
                    the solemnization of the funeral in these words: <hi rend="italic">Exequias L.
                    Tit.</hi><hi rend="italic">filii, quibus est commodum ire, jam tempus est.
                    Olus</hi> (i. e. <hi rend="italic">ille) ex a:dibus effertur.</hi> The company
                    being assembled, the last conclamativn ended, and the bed was covered with
                    purple. A trumpeter then marched forward, followed by old women called <hi rend="italic">preeficae,</hi> singing songs in praise of the deceased. Lastly,
                    the bed followed, borne by the next relations; and if the person were of quality
                    and office, the waxen images of all his predecessors were carried before him on
                    poles. The bed was followed by his children, kindred, and others, <hi rend="italic">atrati,</hi> or in mourning. From this act of following the
                    corpse, these funeral rites were called <hi rend="italic">exequiae.</hi> The
                    body being thus brought to the rostra, the next of kin <hi rend="italic">laudabat defunctum</hi><hi rend="italic">pro</hi><hi rend="italic">rostris,</hi> made a funeral oration in his praise and that of his ancestors.
                    This being completed, the body was carried to the <hi rend="italic">pyra,</hi>
                    or funeral pile, and there burnt, his friends first cutting off a finger, which
                    was buried with a second solemnity. When the body was consumed, the ashes were
                    gathered; and the priest, sprinkling the company thrice with clean water, the
                    eldest of the <hi rend="italic">praficae</hi> crying aloud, <hi rend="italic">Ilicet,</hi> dismissed the people, who took their leave of the deceased in this
                    form, <hi rend="italic">Vale, vale, vale</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">nos</hi><hi rend="italic">te ordine</hi><hi rend="italic">quo</hi><hi rend="italic">natura permiserit sequemur.</hi> The ashes, enclosed
                    in an um, were laid in the sepulchre or tomb.</p><p>The ancient Christians testified their abhorrence of the Pagan custom of burning
                    their dead, and always deposited the body entire in the ground; and it was usual
                    to bestow the honour of embalming upon the martyrs at least, if not upon others.
                    They prepared the body for burial by washing it with water, and dressing it in a
                    funeral attire. The exportation or carrying forth of the body was performed by
                    near relations, or persons of such dignity as the circumstances of the deceased
                    required. Psalmody, or singing of psalms, was the great ceremony used in all
                    funeral processions amongst the early Christians.</p><p>In the Roman Catholic church, the body of the deceased person is washed, and a
                    crucifix is put in its hand. At its feet stands a vessel full of holy water, and
                    a sprinkler is placed, that those who come in may sprinkle both themselves and
                    the body. A priest also stands by the con&gt;sc, and prays for the deceased till
                    it is interred. In the funeral procession, the exorcist walks first, carrying
                    the holy water, next the cross-bearer, afterwards the rest of the clergy, and
                    lastly the officiating priest. They all sing the <hi rend="italic">miserere,</hi> and some other psalms; and at the end of each psalm a <hi rend="italic">requiem.</hi> We learn from AIet ’ β ritual that the faces of
                    deceased laymen must be turned towards the altar when they are placed in the
                    church, and those of the clergy towards the people. The corpse is placed in the
                    church, surrounded with lighted tapers; after the office for the dead, mass is
                    sai&lt;l; then the officiating priest sprinkles the corpse thrice with holy
                    water, and as often throws incense on it. The body being laid in the grave, the
                    clergyman sprinkles it with holy water.</p><p>The funeral ceremonies of the Greek church are much the same with those of the
                    Latin. It needs only to be observed, that, after the funeral service, they kiss
                    the crucifix, and salute the mouth and forehead of the deceased; after which
                    each of the company eats a bit of bread and drinks a glass of wine in the
                    church, wishing the soul a good repose, and the afflicted family all
                    consolation.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Funeral</hi><hi rend="italic">Games,</hi> a part of the
                    ceremonial of funerals amongst the ancients.</p><p>It was customary for persons of quality amongst the ancient Greeks and Romans to
                    institute games with all sorts of exercises, to render the death of their
                    friends more remarkable. This practice was generally received, and is frequently
                    mentioned by ancient writers. Patroclus’s funeral games occupy the greater part
                    of one book of the</p><p>H⅛d; and Agamemnon’s ghost is introduced by Homer, telling the ghost of Achilles,
                    that he had been a spectator at a great number of such solemnities.</p><p>The celebration of these games amongst the Greeks mostly consisted of
                    horse-races; the prizes were of different sorts and value, according to the
                    quality and magnificence of the person who celebrated them. The garlands given
                    to victors on this occasion usually consisted of parsley, which was thought to
                    have some relation to the dead.</p><p>These games, amongst the Romans, consisted chiefly of processions, and sometimes
                    of mortal combats of gladiators around the funeral pile. They, as well as the
                    Greeks, had also a custom, though very ancient, of cutting the throats of a
                    number of captives before the pile, as victims to appease the manes of the
                    deceased. Caesar relates that the Gauls also observed this sanguinary
                    custom.</p><p>The funeral games were at length abolished by the Emperor Claudius.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Funeral</hi><hi rend="italic">Oration,</hi> a discourse
                    pronounced in praise of a person deceased, at the ceremony of his funeral.</p><p>This custom is very ancient. In the latter part of the account given of the
                    Egyptian ceremonies of interment may be perceived the first rudiments of funeral
                    orations, which were afterwards moulded into a more polite and regular form by
                    other nations who adopted this custom. Nor can we omit remarking, that those
                    funeral solemnities were attended not only with orations in praise of the
                    deceased, but with prayers for him; which prayers, it seems, were made by one
                    who personated the deceased.</p><p>The Grecians received the seeds of superstitious and idolatrous worship from the
                    Egyptians, through Cecrops, Cadmus, Danaus, and Erechtheus; and amongst other
                    customs transplanted from Egypt into Greece, were the solemnities used at the
                    burial of the dead. Of these an encomium on the deceased always formed part, as
                    particularly noticed under the preceding article.</p><p>From the Egyptians and Grecians, especially from the latter, the Romans received
                    many of their lawsand customs, as well as much of their polytheism and
                    idolatrous worship. It is well known that the custom of pronouncing funeral
                    orations in praise of the dead obtained amongst them; and the manner in which
                    their funeral services were performed has been already described. The corpse
                    being brought into their great oratory, called the <hi rend="italic">rostra,</hi> the nearest relation <hi rend="italic">laudabat dejunctum</hi><hi rend="italic">pro</hi><hi rend="italic">rostris,</hi> that is, made a funeral
                    oration, in commendation principally of the party deceased, but touching the
                    worthy acts also of those his predecessors whose images were there present. The
                    account given by Dr Kennet is in these words: “In all the funerals of note,
                    especially in the public or indictive, the corpse was first brought with a vast
                    train of followers into the forum; here one of the nearest relations ascended
                    the rostra, and favoured the audience with an oration in praise of the deceased.
                    If none of the kindred undertook the office, it was discharged by some of the
                    most eminent persons in the city for learning and eloquence, as Appian reports
                    of the funeral of Sylla. And Pliny the younger reckons it as the last addition
                    to the happiness of a very great man, that be had the honour to be praised at
                    his funeral by the eloquent Tacitus, then consul; and this is agreeable to
                    Quintilian’s account of this matter. “For the funeral orations,” says he,
                    “depend very often on some public office, and, by order of the senate, are many
                    times given in charge to the magistrates, to be performed by themselves in
                    person. The invention of this custom is generally attributed to Valerius
                    Poplicola, soon after the expulsion of the regal family. Plutarch tells us, that
                    honouring his colleague’s obsequies with a funeral oration, it so pleased the
                    Romans that it became customary for the best men to celebrate the funerals of
                    great persons with speeches in their commendations.” Thu*</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:193517347" xml:id="kp-eb0710-7347-0260"/><p>Julius Caesar, according to custom, delivered an oration in the rostra in praise
                    of his wife Cornelia, and his aunt Julia, when dead; showing that his aunt’s
                    descent, by her mother’s side, was from kings, and by her father’s from the
                    gods. Plutarch says that “he approved of the law of the Komans, which ordered
                    suitable praises to be given to women as well as to men after death.” But from
                    what he says in another place it appears that the old Korean law provided that
                    funeral orations should be made only for the elder women; and therefore he says
                    that Caesar was the first who made one upon his own wife, it not being then
                    usual to take notice of younger women in that way; but by that action he gained
                    much favour from the populace, who afterwards looked upon him, and loved him, as
                    a very mild and good man. The reason why such a law was made in favour of the
                    women, Livy tells us, was this, that when there was such a scarcity of money in
                    the public treasury, that the sum agreed upon to give the Gauls to break up the
                    siege of the city and capitol could not be raised, the women collected amongst
                    themselves and made it up; for which cause they had not only thanks given them,
                    but this additional honour, that after death they should be solemnly praised as
                    well as the men; which looks as if, before this time, the men only had those
                    funeral orations made for them.</p><p>Tlι is custom of the Romans very early obtained amongst the Christians. Some of
                    their funeral sermons or orations are now extant, as that of Eusebius on
                    Constantine; and those of Nazianzen on Basil and Caesarius, and of Ambrose on
                    Valentinian, Theodosius, and others. Gregory, the brother of Basil, made
                    inxr∣it∣or λβyor, a funeral ora tion on Melitus, bishop of Antioch. These
                    orations were usually pronounced before the bodies of the deceased were
                    committed to the ground, which custom has been more or less continued ever
                    since.</p><p>Thus it appears that those rites and ceremonies amongst the heathens, which have
                    been delivered from one people to another, are what have given birth to <hi rend="smallcaps">Funeral</hi><hi rend="italic">Sermons and Oration»</hi> among
                    Christians. The method in which the characters of deceased persons are given in
                    our funeral sermons is very much the same with that observed in those pagan
                    orations, where first an account is given of the parentage of the deceased, then
                    of his education; after which we hear of his conduct in riper years; then his
                    many virtues are enumerated, as also his generous, noble, and excellent
                    performances.</p></div></body></text></TEI>