<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0779-0734-06" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">YELLOW FEVER (9th edition, volume 24, page 734)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:923528">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:858405">Cholera</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1939238">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1019244">Mexicans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204607">Suriname</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4542j979">Cholera</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zc7s280">Rushes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n779/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">YELLOW FEVER</label> is a typhus-like fever of certain ports,
                    or of ships hailing from them. It differs from all other existing types of
                    fevers and infections in largely sparing the Negro. It resembles cholera in
                    being endemic in some parts of the world (but only shipping places) and in being
                    importable to others, in being an infection that issues from the soil or some
                    medium equivalent thereto, and in being a virulent filth-disease; but it differs
                    from cholera in having at the outset a violent febrile paroxysm lasting two or
                    three days. As a fever it resembles typhus; but it differs from typhus in all
                    those “exogenous” characters wherein it resembles cholera. The generic place and
                    affinities of yellow fever are perhaps best provided for in the nosology of
                    Cullen: the symptoms are within the sphere of the organic nervous system; they
                    stand for excitement first and prostration afterwards; and they are an effect of
                    human effluvia. Its differentia among the “nervous” fevers due to “human
                    effluvia” would be its maritime or amphibious habitat, its association with
                    tropical heat, the chief part played by the liver in its symptomatology (on the
                    lines of acute yellow atrophy), and the singular immunity of the Negro race.</p>
                <p>An attack of yellow fever may follow definite exposure (such as landing at an
                    endemic port) within a few hours, as in corresponding cases of cholera; but the
                    outbreak of symptoms is more often delayed for a few days, the limit of
                    “incubation” being about eight. The few hours’ languor, chilliness, headache,
                    and muscular pains, which might be the precursors of any febrile attack, are
                    followed by a peculiar look of the eyes and face, which is characteristic: the
                    face is flushed, and the eyes suffused at first and then congested or ferrety,
                    the nostrils and lips red, and the tongue scarlet,—these being the most obvious
                    signs of universal congestion of the skin, mucous membranes, and organs.
                    Meanwhile the temperature has risen to fever heat, and may reach a very high
                    figure (maximum of 110° Fahr., it is said); the pulse is quick, strong, and
                    full, but may not keep up in these characters with the high temperature
                    throughout. There are all the usual accompaniments of high fever, including hot
                    skin, failure of appetite, thirst, nausea, restlessness, and delirium (which may
                    or may not be violent); albumen will nearly always be found in the urine. The
                    fever is a continued one so long as it lasts; but the febrile excitement comes
                    to an end after two or three days. In a certain class of ambulatory or masked
                    cases the febrile reaction may never come out, and the shock of the infection
                    after a brief interval may lead unexpectedly and directly to prostration and
                    death. The cessation of the paroxysm makes the <hi rend="italic">stadium,</hi>
                    or lull, characteristic of yellow fever. The hitherto militant or violent
                    symptoms cease, and prostration or collapse ensues. The internal heat falls
                    below the normal; the action of the heart (pulse) becomes slow and feeble, the
                    skin cold and of a lemon-yellow tint, the act of vomiting effortless, like that
                    of an infant, the first vomit being clear fluid, but afterwards black from an
                    admixture of blood. It is at this period that the prospect of recovery or of a
                    fatal issue declares itself. The prostration following the paroxysm of fever may
                    be no more than the weakness of commencing recovery, with copious flow of urine,
                    which even then is very dark-coloured from the presence of blood. The
                    prostration will be all the more profound according to the height reached by the
                    temperature during the acute paroxysm. Much blood in the vomit and in the
                    stools, together with all other haemorrhagic signs, is of evil omen. Constant
                    hiccough, with loud cries or wailing, is a certain sign of death, which may also
                    be ushered in by suppression of urine, coma, and convulsions, or by fainting
                    from failure at the heart. The proportion of recoveries is usually less than
                    one-half; but it has been now and then very large (as in the New Orleans
                    epidemic of 1878). Convalescence is on the whole rapid; but, if some old
                    disease, such as ague, have been lighted up, or abscesses induced, it may go on
                    slowly for months. One attack of yellow fever confers a high degree of immunity
                    from a second.</p>
                <p>The treatment of yellow fever has been one of the classical subjects of
                    controversy. In the Philadelphia epidemics of the end of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n780/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0780-0735"/> the 18th century, Rush gained much credit for
                    his incessant labours in bleeding the victims during the violence of the
                    paroxysm. Although blood-letting to relieve the congestions has been given up,
                    experience still favours the resort to vigorous measures at the outset. The
                    following practice was adopted with much success by Dr Joseph Jones during the
                    epidemic of 1878 at New Orleans,—an emetic of ipecacuanha, followed by a powder
                    of calomel (10 to 20 grains), with as much quinine added (the latter ingredient
                    of doubtful utility), and that again followed by a full dose of castor oil.
                    Beyond that heroic medication at the outset of the febrile paroxysm, the
                    treatment was directed to assisting the action of the skin and kidneys, by
                    keeping the temperature of the room uniform, by mustard foot-baths, and by
                    copious draughts of lemonade or other aerated water, or of barley water. The
                    diet indicated is fever diet: <hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., it should exclude
                    solid food. For such symptoms as tenderness over the stomach a mustard poultice
                    is applied; for diminished secretion of urine, dry cupping over the loins. When
                    the lull occurs, the patient should on no account be allowed to get up, as
                    sudden failure of the heart is apt to follow exertion. Iced champagne and
                    beef-tea are found to be the best supports for this stage. The only thing to do
                    when black vomit threatens is to give the patient ice to suck, or (more
                    questionably) to place an ice-bag on the abdomen. When the stage of prostration
                    assumes a “typhoid” character, an enema of ice-cold water, with a little
                    turpentine in it, helps to get rid of the flatus and to stimulate the kidneys.
                    Recovery is in all cases more probable where there is abundant cubic space and
                    good ventilation.</p>
                <p>Yellow fever is of the nature of typhus, in the language of older writers, a
                    nervous or putrid fever. The two salient things about it are the internal
                    haemorrhages and the almost complete arrest of the function of the liver; of
                    these the latter would seem to be primary and the former secondary. The state of
                    the liver on examination after death from yellow fever is by far the most
                    significant feature in the morbid anatomy: the bile-ducts and gallbladder are
                    empty, or contain only a clear albuminoid fluid; the organ is bloodless and of a
                    golden yellow colour; and the hepatic cells are everywhere full of fatty
                    granules or other molecular detritus. It shows, in fact, the morbid anatomy of
                    acute yellow atrophy, or that state of the hepatic structure and functions which
                    is due to total inhibition or arrest (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Pathology,</hi>
                    vol. xviii. p. 386), whether the inhibiting influence be phosphorus poisoning,
                    or emotional strain, or something in the pregnant state, or the infective
                    influence of yellow fever. All the other phenomena of this fever are grouped
                    around the liver derangement, as around a centre, namely, the yellow tint of the
                    skin, the fatty degeneration of the heart favouring syncope, the haemorrhages
                    from the mucous membranes (including the black vomit), the degeneration of the
                    renal epithelium with albuminuria, and the coma and convulsions. Yellow fever
                    therefore may be styled a sudden or arbitrary infection imposed from without,
                    the distinctive mark or “note” of which is the same peculiar group of symptoms
                    that is found in the rare and sporadic cases of yellow atrophy. To reach the
                    full and correct doctrine of yellow fever, we have to harmonize the clinical and
                    pathological facts of the disease, as already given, with the historical,
                    geographical, racial, and other associated circumstances now to be stated.</p>
                <p>The first authentic account of yellow fever comes from Bridgetown, Barbados, in
                    1647, where it was recognized as a “nova pestis,” that was unaccountable in its
                    origin, except that Ligon, the historian of the colony, who was then on the
                    spot, connected it with the arrival of ships. It was the same new pestilence
                    that Dutertre, writing in 1667, described as having occurred in the French
                    colony of Guadeloupe in 1635 and 1640; it recurred at Guadeloupe in 1648, and
                    broke out in a peculiarly disastrous form at St Kitt’s the same year, and again
                    in 1652; in 1655 it was at Port Royal, Jamaica; and from those years onwards it
                    became familiar at many harbours in the West Indies and Spanish Main, and in the
                    Atlantic ports of the British American colonies. It is a question whether it had
                    not occurred at Porto Rico, San Domingo, and other places in the Spanish
                    Antilles a good many years before; but the reports from the colonies of New
                    Spain, both for that and subsequent periods, are highly defective as regards the
                    data needed to distinguish yellow fever from the bilious remittent form of
                    malarial fever, which is a non-infective sickness. The Mexican form of typhus,
                    called “matlazahuatl,” which has been an indigenous disease of the native
                    population in the interior for several centuries, has no other connexion with
                    yellow fever than that it belongs to the same family of typhus; its
                    circumstances are quite different, especially in respect that it is a purely
                    inland form of <hi rend="italic">febris pauperum.</hi> In 1853 yellow fever
                    appeared for the first time at Callao and Lima in Peru; and almost in the same
                    months a severe epidemic prevailed among the plantation hands in the sierra
                    region of the interior. The two forms were described as the same disease by Dr
                    Archibald Smith; but the fever of the sierras was afterwards shown to be a form
                    of typhus, analogous to the native Mexican form, and quite unconnected with the
                    yellow fever of the coast.</p>
                <p>In the harbours of the American colonies (United States) the history of yellow
                    fever has been as follows. It begins to be heard of at Charleston in 1693, and
                    at Philadelphia the same year. The South Carolina port has the fullest record of
                    it, next in order in the earlier period being Philadelphia, New York, and
                    Norfolk (Va.). Towards the end of the 18th century the ports of New England, as
                    far north as New Hampshire, have visitations, and it begins to be quite common
                    at Baltimore, Wilmington, Savannah, and New Orleans. At a still later period
                    (within the 19th century) we find the centre of incidence shifting so as to
                    include Mobile, Memphis, Natchez, St Francisville, and Baton Rouge; and in the
                    most recent period outbreaks are recorded at Galveston and other ports of Texas,
                    and at Pensacola, Vicksburg, and Key West. The Atlantic ports gradually lost it
                    and the Gulf ports took up the inheritance, several of them keeping it still.
                    Some of the epidemics were very disastrous, one of the Philadelphia outbreaks
                    corresponding to the pestilence which figures in the last section of
                    Longfellow’s <hi rend="italic">Evangeline:</hi> “Wealth had no power to bribe,
                    nor beauty to charm the oppressor.” In the New Orleans epidemic of 1878 the
                    deaths numbered 4056. The American ports mentioned have been only its principal
                    seats, many other smaller harbours having had outbreaks now and then, such as
                    New Haven (Conn.), Providence (R.I.), Swedesborough (N.J.), Alexandria (Va.),
                    Augusta (Ga.), St Augustine (Fla.), Opelousas (La.), and Houston (Tex.).</p>
                <p>Along with the harbours and anchorages of the West Indies and Spanish Main, the
                    three chief harbours of Guiana (Cayenne, Surinam, and Demerara) have had an
                    equal share, and for almost the same period. But for Brazilian ports there is no
                    record of yellow fever until 1849, when it appeared for the first time at Rio de
                    Janeiro, Bahia, and other places. These ports became endemic seats of the
                    infection from that year, and are now more distinctively the headquarters of the
                    disease than its old West Indian and Mexican Gulf centres. Monte Video had a
                    disastrous epidemic in 1857, and Buenos Ayres a visitation in 1858; but the
                    shipping places of the river Γlate are not in the same class of endemic foci as
                    the harbours of Brazil.</p>
                <p>There have been a few epidemics at trading places on the West Coast of Africa,
                    most of them subsequent to 1820, and all of them confined generally to white
                    residents.</p>
                <p>During the great period of yellow fever (1793-1805), and for some years
                    afterwards, the disease found its way time after time to various ports of Spain.
                    Cadiz, indeed, suffered five epidemics in the 18th century, Malaga one, and
                    Lisbon one; but from 1800 down to 1821 the disease assumed much more alarming
                    proportions, Cadiz being still its chief seat, while Seville, Malaga, Cartagena,
                    Barcelona, Palma, Gibraltar, and other shipping places suffered severely, as
                    well as some of the country districts nearest to the ports. These Spanish
                    outbreaks were clearly connected with the arrival of ships, but for the most
                    part there had not been cases of yellow fever on board the ships. The last
                    severe epidemic on Spanish soil was at Barcelona in the summer of 1821, when
                    5000 persons died. The most recent disastrous epidemic in Europe was at Lisbon
                    in 1857, when upwards of 6000 died in a few weeks. The outbreaks at St Nazaire
                    (1861), Leghorn, Swansea (1864), and Southampton have been carefully studied,
                    but are otherwise of minor importance.</p>
                <p>Yellow fever is dependent upon high summer temperature for its epidemic
                    development, and it requires a good deal of heat to continue even after it has
                    once acquired epidemic intensity. In its endemic centres in the New World it
                    clings peculiarly to the lower quarters of the seaports, to the alluvial
                    foreshores, and to the anchorages; on many occasions it has been prevalent among
                    the crews of men-of-war and of merchantmen at anchor, or moored in the harbour,
                    or lying up in the <hi rend="italic">carénage,</hi> when there has been none of
                    it among the residents ashore. It is admitted that the endemic influence which
                    causes it is effluvial or miasmatic from the harbour mud, or from the
                    bilge-water of a ship that had lain in the harbour, or from the alluvial
                    foundations of houses nearest to the beach. So far as prevalence on shore is
                    concerned, it seems to follow the same laws as cholera and typhoid fever: that
                    is to say, it is an exogenous or soil infection, a fermentation of filth in the
                    ground, with a seasonal activity closely following the movements of the subsoil
                    water. In like manner, when it has been imported to Spain, it has clung to
                    alluvial soil and has spread after the fashion of a soil-borne infection rather
                    than by personal contagion, although in Spanish ports, just as in Philadelphia,
                    according to Rush’s opinion, contagiousness has been found to be “contingent” to
                    it under certain circumstances. To establish an epidemic in a distant port, it
                    has been necessary that there should be carried thither a material quantity of
                    the specifically poisonous harbour-filth in a ship’s bilges, and that the
                    conditions favourable to its increase and diffusion by fermentation should exist
                    in the new soil.</p>
                <p>The next most significant thing in the incidence of this fever is that new
                    arrivals at an indigenous centre are peculiarly liable to take it, and most
                    liable of all the sailors and others from northern latitudes, such as Sweden,
                    Finland, Holland, and Germany. In fact an epidemic outburst in a yellow-fever
                    port or endemic centre <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n781/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0781-0736"/> at the present day is commonly connected with
                    an unusual influx of strangers. It is not to be supposed, however, that the
                    residents acquire immunity by acclimatization: they have no greater immunity in
                    that sense than have the Bengalis from cholera, or than those who permanently
                    reside in unsanitary localities from typhoid fever or diphtheria. The only
                    immunity is that of the Negro race, an immunity all the more striking that the
                    Negroes in yellowfever ports are mostly found living in the favourite haunts of
                    the disease, and that their race is peculiarly liable to all other infections of
                    the kind, including cholera, typhus, and typhoid. Although the protection of the
                    Negro of pure blood is not absolute, it is nearly so. In ordinary circumstances
                    Negroes become liable when of mixed blood, and almost exactly in proportion to
                    the degree of white stock in their breeding. These racial peculiarities have
                    been so often remarked and are so universally admitted in their broad
                    significance that no detailed proofs need be adduced. It may be stated, however,
                    that all African Negroes, whether fresh from Africa or long acclimatized to the
                    New World, have the same natural protection; thus the Nubian regiment in the
                    French service during the Mexican expedition did not lose a single man, and did
                    not even have a single case, in the epidemic at Vera Cruz in 1866. The
                    protection is profoundly racial, and not due to the Negroes being inured to
                    yellow-fever localities. There is no other instance of the same racial immunity
                    in the whole range of infective sickness.</p>
                <p>Two things stand out prominently in the foregoing recital of facts,—(1) that
                    yellow fever, in time and place, has dogged the steps of the African slave
                    trade, and (2) that the African Negro has a very large racial immunity from
                    yellow fever. The first of these facts was generalized by Audouard (Paris,
                    1825), but has been neglected and forgotten; the second fact, which no one
                    seriously disputes, is the complement and confirmation of the historical and
                    geographical induction. The circumstances in Peru, although apparently in
                    contradiction, are really corroborative: a form of yellow fever established
                    itself at certain ports of that country in the wake of a notorious Chinese
                    coolie trade (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Coolie,</hi> vol. vi. p. 334); but the
                    Chinese themselves were exempt from the fever at the time, and would appear not
                    to have suffered from it in the subsequent epidemics on the Peruvian coast. The
                    question thus arises as to the particular connexion between the African slave
                    trade (or the analogous Chinese coolie trade) and yellow fever. The first point
                    is that the fever has not been a fever of the voyage but of the landing place,
                    although there are several authentic instances (<hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>
                    cases of the “Regalia” and “La Pique”) of yellow fever arising at sea from the
                    exposure of white men to the stench of a shipful of Negroes. Again, the filthy
                    condition of a Guineaman on her arrival from Africa was a notorious fact; and
                    the filth of that kind was discharged into the creeks, <hi rend="italic"
                        >carénages,</hi> and anchorages of slave ports in material quantity year
                    after year for a long period. At Havana as many as a hundred slavers would
                    arrive in one year. Steady accretions of the filth of slave-ships from the
                    beginning of the traffic to America down to its abolition in 1808, and its final
                    cessation previous to 1860, would account for a peculiarly pestiferous state of
                    the harbour mud, of the beach, and even of the water; in fact, the water in the
                    Bay of Havana was pestiferous and full of organic matter where it was several
                    fathoms deep, and there was a standing order in the British navy against
                    admitting it into ships. Wherever the harbours were most tideless, as around the
                    Gulf of Mexico and in the West Indian Islands, and wherever the soil was most
                    alluvial, and the movements of the ground-water most extensive, the specific
                    putrefaction or fermentation thus introduced into the harbour would spread
                    farthest on shore, being aided or encouraged always by the abundance of other
                    organic matter which it met with at particular spots, such as the foundations of
                    houses.</p>
                <p>The next step is to consider the connexion between this wholesale befouling of
                    slave ports and the particular type of endemic disease. One of the points most
                    emphasized by Audouard was the fundamental physiological differences between the
                    African Negro race and the white. The discharges of the Negro body might become
                    by their effluvia specifically poisonous, he argued, to white men under special
                    circumstances. A more direct factor in the aetiology was the very common, if not
                    uniform, prevalence of dysentery and diarrhoea in the passage from the Guinea
                    coast to the western shores of the Atlantic: the filth in a slave-ship’s bilges
                    was, in part at least, dysenteric in its source and properties. Now, there is
                    much independent evidence, collected from times of war and famine, to prove a
                    certain correlation or equivalence between dysentery and typhus; according to
                    Blane’s phrase, the one was vicarious to the other. Yellow fever is admittedly a
                    form of typhus, a form distinguished by a haemorrhagic tendency. Thus we find
                    the connexion explained between dysenteric and other evacuations of the Negro
                    race, carried to the mud and alluvial soil of ports under very peculiar
                    circumstances, and a special form of endemic typhus, differing from the ordinary
                    form in being earth-borne instead of airborne. The remaining part of the
                    synthesis concerns the differential type of yellow fever within the genus
                    “typhus Whence did it obtain the “note” or distinctive mark, anatomical and
                    clinical, of an acute yellow atrophy of the liver? The dysenteric filth that was
                    imported into the harbours of the New World represented that almost unique
                    unwholesomeness of life which is summed up in the phrase “horrors of the middle
                    passage.” Among such horrors nostalgia, despair, and the sense of wrong were not
                    the least; and these are among the states of human feeling that have been known,
                    now and then, in the ordinary way of life to assume that peculiar visceral
                    embodiment, or to find that means of expression, which amounts to acute yellow
                    atrophy of the liver, and stands, in fact, for a total arrest of the hepatic
                    functions, biliary and other.</p>
                <p>There is no other theory of yellow fever to contest the field with the
                    slave-trade hypothesis; that alone satisfies all the conditions of a correct
                    synthesis—historical, geographical, ethnological, physiological, and, some would
                    say, even ethical. There have been various other theories put forward from time
                    to time, all of them much too fragmentary, and therefore erroneous, such as the
                    hypothesis of rotting timber (in wharves, ships’ hulls, &amp;c.), of sugar
                    cargoes, of common foul bilge-water, of madrepores, and of bacilli. The
                    bacillary or parasitic hypothesis is the fashionable one at present, but it is
                    much too ambitious, as ordinarily held, and altogether wide of the mark. The
                    part played by putrefactive organisms is a subordinate one. In the general
                    grouping of factors they can only come in after we have found the specific
                    integral of the yellow-fever soil in its endemic seats; they cannot elaborate
                    the miasmatic poison of yellow fever without a definite pabulum, any more than
                    the “lactic bacillus” can produce lactic fermentation without milk-sugar.</p>
                <p>The sanitary or public health aspects of yellow fever have been discussed in
                    great part under <hi rend="smallcaps">Quarantine</hi> (vol. xx. p. 156). In
                    regard to its sanitation at the endemic seats in the West Indies, Guiana,
                    Brazil, Central America, and the Gulf States of the American Union, the same
                    principles apply as to other filth-diseases. The object is to secure a clean
                    soil, and to that end drainage and sewerage serve best. In the sanitation of
                    yellow fever the case is so far peculiar that the harbour bottom, the adjoining
                    mudbanks and mangrove swamps, and even the seawater itself, are apt to retain
                    the specific taint, especially where the cleansing action of the tides is
                    slight. But there is good reason to think that the specific taint in the soil is
                    everywhere slowly disappearing, now that it is no longer reinforced by fresh
                    supplies year after year. It has practically vanished from the Atlantic ports of
                    the United States, and has become almost rare in such harbours as Port Royal,
                    Jamaica. Its headquarters are now the Brazilian ports, which were the last to
                    develop it (in 1849).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> The chief work is that of La Roche, <hi
                        rend="italic">Yellow Fever,</hi> 2 vols., Philadelphia, 1855. A very full
                    bibliography is given by Hirsch at the end of his section on “Yellow Fever,” in
                        <hi rend="italic">Historisch-Geographische Pathologie,</hi> vol. i.,
                    Stuttgart, 1881 (Engl. transl. by Creighton, London, 1883). Recent experience,
                    epidemiological and clinical, is given in the writings (2 vols.) of Dr Joseph
                    Jones of New Orleans, 1887; see also Maclean’s <hi rend="italic">Diseases of
                        Tropical Climates,</hi> London, 1886. Among the numerous monographs may be
                    specially mentioned those of Pym <hi rend="italic">(Observations upon the Bulam
                        Fever,</hi> London, 1815), who showed that one attack gave immunity, and of
                    Daniel Blair <hi rend="italic">(Some Account of the Last Yellow Fever Epidemic
                        of British Guiana,</hi> with plates, 3d ed., London, 1852). A popular
                    exposition of the slave-trade hypothesis of Audouard (with additions by the
                    writer of the present article) will be found in <hi rend="italic">North. Amer.
                        Rev.,</hi> October 18S4. Audouard’s three papers were collected under the
                    title <hi rend="italic">Recueil de Mémoires sur le Typhus Nautique, ou Fièvre
                        Jaune,</hi> Paris, 1825. (C. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
