<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0621-0594-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JASMINE, or Jessamine (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    594)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927866">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174597">White</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174816">Whites</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182641">Yellow</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JASMINE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Jessamine</hi></label>,
                    botanicallyJhsτn⅛ιiW2, a genus of shrubs or climbers constituting the principal
                    part of the natural order <hi rend="italic">Jasminaceae,</hi> and comprising
                    about sixty species, of which forty or more occur in the gardens of Britain. The
                    plants of the genus are mostly natives of the warmer regions of the Old World,
                    but there are one or two South American species. The leaves are pinnate or
                    ternate, or sometimes apparently simple, consisting of one leaflet, articulated
                    to the petiole. The flowers, usually white or yellow, are arranged in terminal
                    or axillary panicles, and have a tubular 5- or 8-cleft calyx, and a cylindrical
                    corollatube, with a spreading limb, two included stamens, and a two-celled
                    ovary.</p>
                <p>The name is derived from the Persian <hi rend="italic">ydsmin.</hi> Linnaeus
                    obtained a fancied etymology from ια, violets, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >οσpη,</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0622-0595"/> smell, but the odour of its flowers bears no
                    resemblance to that of the violet; it is in fact so peculiar as to be
                    incomparable, and is probably the only floral perfume which cannot be imitated
                    by art. The common white jasmine, <hi rend="italic">Jasminum officinale,</hi>
                    one of the best known and most highly esteemed of British hardy ligneous
                    climbers, is said to be a native of India, and to have been introduced about the
                    middle of the 16 th century. In the centre and south of Europe it is thoroughly
                    acclimatized. Although it grows to the height of 12 and sometimes 20 feet, its
                    stem is feeble and requires support; its leaves are opposite, pinnated, and dark
                    green, the leaflets are in three pairs, with an odd one, and are pointed, the
                    terminal one larger and with a tapering point. The fragrant white flowers bloom
                    from June to October; and, as they are found chiefly on the young shoots, the
                    plant should only be pruned in the autumn. Varieties with golden and
                    silver-edged leaves and one with double flowers are known.</p>
                <p>The Zambak or Arabian jasmine, <hi rend="italic">&lt;7asmiηum Sambac,</hi> is an
                    evergreen white-flowered climber, 6 or 8 feet high, introduced into Britain in
                    the latter part of the 17th century. Two varieties introduced somewhat later are
                    respectively 3-leaved and double-flowered, and these, as well as that with
                    normal flowers, bloom throughout the greater part of the year. On account of
                    their exquisite fragrance the flowers are highly esteemed in the East, and are
                    frequently referred to by the Persian and Arabian poets. An oil obtained by
                    boiling the leaves is used to anoint the head for complaints of the eye, and an
                    oil obtained from the roots is used medicinally to arrest the secretion of milk.
                    The flowers of one of the double varieties, known as “Moogree,” are held sacred
                    to Vishnu, and used as votive offerings in Hindu religious ceremonies. In China
                    the flowers of this plant, under the name of “Mo-le-hwa,” are used for scenting
                    tea. The Spanish, or Catalonian jasmine, <hi rend="italic">J. grandi-flomιm</hi>
                    (fig. 2), which grows wild on the island of Tobago, is very like <hi
                    rend="italic">J. officinale,</hi> but differs in the size of the leaflets; the
                    branches are shorter and stouter, and the flowers very much larger, and reddish
                    underneath. By grafting it on two-year-old plants of <hi rend="italic">J.
                    officinale,</hi> an erect bush about 3 feet high is obtained, requiring no
                    supports. In this way it is very extensively cultivated at Cannes and Grasse, in
                    the south of France; the plants are set in rows, fully exposed to the sun; they
                    come into full bearing the second year after grafting; the blossoms, which are
                    very large and intensely fragrant, are produced from July till the end of
                    October, but those of August and September are the most odoriferous. An acre of
                    land is said to yield about 500 tt&gt; of blossoms during the season, value £25
                    to £35. The aroma is extracted by the process known as “enfleurage,” <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> absorption by a fatty body, such as purified lard or
                    olive oil. Square glass trays framed with wood about 3 inches deep are spread
                    over with grease about half an inch thick, in which ridges are made to
                    facilitate absorption, and sprinkled with freshly gathered flowers, which are
                    renewed every morning during the whole time the plant remains in blossom; the
                    trays are piled up in stacks to prevent the evaporation of the aroma; and
                    finally the pomade is scraped off the glass, melted at as low a temperature as
                    possible, and strained. When oil is employed as the absorbent, coarse cotton
                    cloths previously saturated with the finest olive oil are laid on wire-gauze
                    frames, and repeatedly covered in the same manner with fresh flowers; they are
                    then squeezed under a press, yielding what is termed “huile antique au jasmin.”
                    3 lb of flowers will perfume 1 lb of grease,—this is exhausted by maceration in
                    1 pint of rectified spirit to form the “extract.”</p>
                <p>An essential oil is distilled from jasmine in Tunis and Algeria, but its high
                    price prevents its being used to any extent. The East Indian oil of jasmine is a
                    compound largely contaminated with sandalwood-oil. The distinguishing characters
                    of <hi rend="italic">J. odoratissimum</hi> consist principally in the alternate,
                    obtuse, ternate, and pinnate leaves, the 3-flowered terminal peduncles, and the
                    5-cleft yellow corolla with obtuse segments. The flowers have the advantage of
                    retaining when dry their natural perfume, which is suggestive of a mixture of
                    jasmine, jonquille, and orange-blossom. In China the <hi rend="italic">J.
                    paniculatum</hi> is cultivated as an erect shrub, known as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sieu-hinghwa;</hi> it is valued for its flowers, which are used with those of
                    <hi rend="italic">J. Sambac,</hi> in the proportion of 10 lb of the former to 30
                    lb of the latter, for scenting tea—40 ft&gt; of the mixture being required for
                    100 lb of tea. The “narrow leaved jasmine,” &lt;Λ <hi rend="italic"
                    >angustifolium,</hi> is a beautiful evergreen climber 10 to 12 feet high, found
                    in the Coromandel forests, and introduced into Britain during the present
                    century. Its leaves are of a bright shining green; its large terminal flowers
                    are white with a faint tinge of red, fragrant, and blooming throughout the year.
                    The bitter root, ground small and mixed with lime-juice and root of <hi
                    rend="italic">Acorus Calamus,</hi> is considered in India a good remedy for
                    ringworm and herpes. In Cochin China a decoction of the leaves and branches of
                    J∙ <hi rend="italic">nervosum</hi> is taken as a blood-purifier; and the bitter
                    leaves of J^. <hi rend="italic">floribundum</hi> (called in Abyssinia
                    “Habbez-zelim ”) mixed with Kousso is considered a powerful anthelmintic,
                    especially for tape-worm; the leaves and branches are added to some fermented
                    liquors to increase their intoxicating quality. In Sierra Leone a poultice made
                    with the leaves of <hi rend="italic">J. ηoctiflorum</hi> is applied to ulcers.
                    The leaves of <hi rend="italic">J.</hi><hi rend="italic">hirsutum</hi> boiled in
                    oil are applied in India and China in cases of ophthalmia, and its root is said
                    to be a really good remedy for snake bites. In Catalonia and in Turkey the wood
                    of the jasmine is made into long, slender pipestems, highly prized by the Moors
                    and Turks. Syrup of jasmine is made ⅛&gt;y placing in a jar alternate layers of
                    the flowers and sugar, covering the whole with wet cloths and standing it in a
                    cool place; the perfume is absorbed by the sugar, which is converted into a very
                    palatable syrup.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n623/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0623-0596"/>
                <p>The plant known in America as the “Carolina jasmine” (fig. 2) is not a true
                    jasmine (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Gelsemium).</hi> Other hardy species commonly
                    cultivated in gardens are the low or Italian yellow-flowered jasmine, <hi
                    rend="italic">J.</hi><hi rend="italic">humile,</hi> an erect shrub 3 or 4 feet
                    high, with angular branches, alternate and mostly ternate leaves, blossoming
                    from June to September; the common yellow jasmine, <hi rend="italic">J∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">fruticans,</hi> a hardy deciduous shrub, 10 to 12 feet high, with
                    weak, slender stems requiring support, and bearing yellow, odourless flowers
                    from spring to autumn; and <hi rend="italic">J. nudiflorurn,</hi> which flowers
                    before the leaves appear. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j. ch. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
