<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0645-0618-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JEFFREYS, George Jeffreys, Lord (9th edition, volume
                    13, page 618)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cm39">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6494x">Attorneys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:994346">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830288">Benches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n645/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JEFFREYS, <hi rend="smallcaps">George Jeffreys,
                    Lord</hi></label> (c. 1648-1689), lord chancellor of England, was born probably
                    in 1648 at Acton in Denbighshire, of a respectable but not rich family. He was
                    smitten with the desire of becoming a lawyer by seeing, when a boy at St Paul’s
                    school in London, the magnificent procession of the judges to the cathedral;
                    and, although his family was hard put to it by the expense, he spent some time
                    at Westminster school before entering the Inner Temple as a student at sixteen.
                    The allowance he received from home was quite unequal to the demands of the
                    dissolute habits into which he quickly fell, but it is said that the promise of
                    future eminence, afforded by the fits of studiousness which divided his orgies,
                    procured for the dissipated student both long credit and presents of money. He
                    was exceedingly popular as a table companion, especially with the inferior
                    attorneys and attorneys’ clerks with whom, then as afterwards, he preferred to
                    drink; and in the low practice which he began at Old Bailey and the London
                    Sessions immediately on being called to the bar in November 1668, he found his
                    boon companions very useful in procuring him briefs. Voluble, unscrupulous, and
                    overbearing, he rapidly developed in his constant dealings w ith the most
                    degraded criminals the coarse bullying manner which disgraced him throughout his
                    whole career. He sought every means of ingratiating himself with the city
                    aidermen, and in 1671, at the singularly early age of twenty-three, became their
                    common seιjeant, and in 1678 recorder of London. He had by that time pushed his
                    way into the higher courts, where his marvellous address in speaking and
                    cross-examination made up for, if it did not conceal, his shallow legal
                    knowledge. Jeffreys had hitherto nominally belonged to the anti-court or liberal
                    party; but, perceiving that they had but little patronage in their gift, he had
                    opened secret negotiations with Charles II., and immediately on taking the oaths
                    as recorder he openly declared himself a partisan of the court. The year before
                    he had been knighted and appointed solicitor to the duke of York. To reward him
                    for the servility which he displayed, especially in connexion with the Popish
                    plot trials, he was appointed chief justice of Chester, and advanced to a
                    baronetcy. His insolence and intemperance, already notorious, became in his
                    chief-justiceship well nigh intolerable. He received a rebuff in 1680 when for
                    his conduct in obstructing the assembling of parliament he was reprimanded on
                    his knees by the speaker, and forced to resign his recordership in December of
                    the same year. Such indignities were merits in the eyes of the king, to whose
                    favour Jeffreys laid additional claims by his efforts to abrogate the charter of
                    London, and by his activity as counsel against the suspected Rye House
                    conspirators. He received his reward. Lord Campbell remarks, “Jeffreys became
                    chiefjustice of England, as the only man fit to condemn Algernon Sidney.” He was
                    sworn in in November 1683, and shortly became privy councillor and member of the
                    cabinet. In the court of the King’s Bench, the new chiefjustice let few
                    considerations stand between him and his desire to satisfy the king. His
                    iniquitous servility is to be traced in the <hi rend="italic">State Trials.</hi>
                    When Charles died in February 1685, Jeffreys exchanged a master who disliked him
                    as a wretch “with no learning, no sense, no manners, and more impudence than ten
                    carted street-walkers,” for one who found in him a thoroughly congenial tool. In
                    May 1685 Jeffreys was raised to the peerage by the style of Baron Jeffreys of
                    Wem, and in August went into the western counties as president of a special
                    commission appointed to try the numerous cases of treason arising from the duke
                    of Monmouth’s ill-fated rebellion. It was in this “bloody assize” that he was to
                    deepen the stain that already tarnished his fame, and to make the name “Judge
                    Jeffreys” a synonym for a monster of bloodthirsty cruelty, blasphemous rage, and
                    brutish intemperance. In the “campaign” he gave the rein to his ferocity; he was
                    maddened with slaughter, and his appetite for blood grew by what it fed on. The
                    horrible glare of his eye, the savage lines of his face, his fierce shouts of
                    wrath, terrified and confused guilty and innocent alike. With hateful cunning he
                    let it be bruited that the only hope of mercy lay in pleading guilty, and by
                    this cold-blooded artifice lightened his labours. He had a powerful incentive to
                    active butchery: the vacant post of lord chancellor was to be won by good
                    service. The estimates of the numbers of victims of the commission vary: 320 was
                    the official return to the treasury; Lord Lonsdale says 700, and Burnet 600.
                    Upwards of 800 were transported as slaves to the West Indies, while others only
                    escaped by purchasing their pardons from the judge at most exorbitant rates.
                    When the chief-justice returned to Windsor in September, the great seal of
                    England was placed in his blood-stained hands. For the rest of his career the
                    lord chancellor was an unresisting agent of King James in his most illegal
                    schemes. Finding himself losing favour at court, he even revived the
                    ecclesiastical court of high commission, abolished in 1640 by an Act which
                    forbade its revival, and himself engaged to act aspresident. In the attempt
                    against the rights of the fellows of Magdalen College, Oxford, and in the trial
                    of the seven bishops, Jeffreys was the king’s right hand; but, when the
                    proceedings of James had at last roused the indignation that cost him his crown,
                    the lord chancellor was one of the first to advise concession. When the king
                    fled in 1688, Jeffreys was in the utmost consternation. For him, he knew, there
                    could be no mercy. Shaving off his shaggy eyebrows, and disguising himself as a
                    common sailor, he attempted to escape to Hamburg in a small collier, but, while
                    drinking in a low public-house at Wapping, he was recognized by a poor scrivener
                    who had once encountered the wrath of the judge, and had never forgotten the
                    glare of his eye. Jeffreys was only saved from being torn in pieces by the mob
                    by the timely arrival of a strong guard, who conducted the trembling wretch to
                    the Tower. There he lay for some months, tortured by anguish both of mind and
                    body, which he endeavoured to drown in copious draughts of brandy. He died
                    miserably on April 19, 1689. Jeffreys was twice married, and had ten children,
                    but his title became extinct in 1703, in the person of his son John, notorious
                    for having interrupted the funeral of Dryden. It is said that in 1688 Lord
                    Jeffreys was about to be created earl of Flint; and, though <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n646/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0646-0619"/> the patent never passed the great seal, a book
                    was dedicated to him, giving him the title.</p>
                <p>For the character of Jeffreys not even the most impartial historian can say a
                    good word. Of strong intelligence and clear legal head, and, according to Roger
                    North, when he was in temper and matters indifferent came before him, becoming
                    his seat of justice better than any other that author had seen in his place, he
                    might have risen to a high position among the learned luminaries of the bench,
                    had he not prostituted his talents to unworthy ends, and swamped his faculties
                    in the most brutal intemperance. He treated all from whom he had nothing to
                    expect with coarse insolence, taking an especially malicious delight in giving,
                    as he phrased it, “a lick with the rough side of his tongue” to those whom his
                    maudlin caresses of the night before had encouraged to presume. No less was he
                    pleased to revile at dissenters; “Show me,” be said, “a Presbyterian, and I will
                    engage to show a lying knave.” He is remarkable as the only politically
                    prominent lawyer of his century who never sat in the House of Commons, nor left
                    a single publication behind him. In the House of Lords he once attempted to use
                    the insolent abuse of his court habits, but was compelled humbly to apologize,
                    in tears of maudlin chagrin, to all whom he had attacked.</p>
                <p>The chief sources for particulars about Jeffreys are the <hi rend="italic">State
                    Trials</hi> and North’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Lord Keeper Guildford,</hi>
                    together with contemporary pamphlets and squibs. These materials have been
                    skilfully used by Lord Campbell in his <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Lord
                    Chancellors,</hi> and by Macaulay in hrs <hi rend="italic">History.</hi> See
                    also Woolrych’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Judge Jeffreys,</hi> 1827.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
