<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0625-0598-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JAUNDICE (9th edition, volume 13, page 598)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1000617">Liver</term>
                    <term ref="fast:831690">Bile</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gc95">Liver</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04121">Bile</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JAUNDICE</label> (Fr. <hi rend="italic">Jaunisse,</hi> from
                    <hi rend="italic">jaune,</hi> yellow), or <hi rend="smallcaps">Icterus</hi>
                    (from its resemblance to the colour of the golden oriole, of which Pliny relates
                    that if a jaundiced person looks upon it he recovers but the bird dies), a term
                    in medicine applied to a yellow coloration of the skin and other parts of the
                    body, depending in most instances on some derangement affecting the liver. This
                    yellow colour is due to the presence in the blood of bile or of some of the
                    elements of that secretion. Jaundice, however, must be regarded more as a
                    symptom of some morbid condition previously existing than as a disease' <hi
                    rend="italic">per se.</hi></p>
                <p>The manner in which jaundice is produced is still a matter of debate among
                    physicians, but it is generally admitted that there are two classes of causes,
                    either of which may bring about this condition. In the first place any
                    obstruction to the passage of bile from the liver into the intestinal canal is
                    sooner or later followed by the appearance of jaundice, which in such
                    circumstances is due to the excessive absorption of bile into the blood. To this
                    variety the term <hi rend="italic">obstructive</hi> jaundice is applied. But
                    secondly, a form of jaundice may be produced by causes not embracing
                    obstruction, but including a variety of morbid conditions affecting either the
                    secreting structure of the liver or the state of the blood, and to this the term
                    <hi rend="italic">non-obstructive</hi> jaundice is applied.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Obstructive jaundice</hi> may be due to the following causes:
                    —(1) simple catarrh of the hepatic and common bile duct (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Digestive Organs),</hi> whereby the calibre of these channels
                    is narrowed (this is frequently the result of cold or of temporary gastric
                    disturbance, but it may become a chronic condition); (2) impaction of gall
                    stones or plugs of hardened mucus in the ducts; (3) general congestion of the
                    liver, either alone or in connexion with pre-existing disease in the heart or
                    lungs; and (4) pressure of morbid growths either external to the liver or in its
                    substance.</p>
                <p>Obstruction from these causes may be partial or complete, and the degree of
                    jaundice will vary accordingly, but it is to be noted that extensive organic
                    disease of the liver may exist without the evidence of obstructive jaundice.</p>
                <p>The effect upon the liver of impediments to the outflow of bile such as those
                    above indicated is in the first place an increase in its size, the whole biliary
                    passages and the liver cells being distended with retained bile. This
                    enlargement, however, speedily subsides when the obstruction is removed, but
                    should it persist the liver ultimately shrinks and undergoes atrophy in its
                    whole texture. The bile thus retained is absorbed into the system, and shows
                    itself by the yellow staining seen to a greater or less extent in all the
                    tissues and many of the fluids of the body. The kidneys, which in such
                    circumstances act in some measure vicariously to the liver and excrete a portion
                    of the retained bile, are apt to become affected in their structure by the long
                    continuance of jaundice.</p>
                <p>The symptoms of obstructive jaundice necessarily vary according to the nature of
                    the exciting cause, but there generally exists evidence of some morbid condition
                    before the yellow coloration appears. Thus, if the obstruction be due to an
                    impacted gall stone in the common or hepatic duct, there will probably be the
                    symptoms of intense suffering characterizing “hepatic colic” (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Colic),</hi> after which the jaundice appears. In the cases
                    most frequently seen—those, namely, arising from simple catarrh of the bile
                    ducts due to gastro-duodenal irritation spreading on to the liver through the
                    common duct—the first sign to attract attention is the yellow appearance of the
                    white of the eye, which is speedily followed by a similar colour on the skin
                    over the body generally. The yellow tinge is most distinct where the skin is
                    thin, as on the forehead, breast, elbows, &amp;c. It may be also well seen in
                    the roof of the mouth, but in the lips and gums the colour is not observed till
                    the blood is first pressed from them. The tint varies, being in the milder cases
                    faint, in the more severe a deep saffron yellow, while in extreme degrees of
                    obstruction it may be of dark brown or greenish hue. The colour can scarcely, if
                    at all, be observed in artificial light.</p>
                <p>The urine exhibits well marked and characteristic changes in jaundice which exist
                    even before any evidence can be detected on the skin or elsewhere. It is always
                    of dark brown colour resembling porter, but after standing in the air it
                    acquires a greenish tint. Its froth is greenish-yellow, and it stains with this
                    colour any white substance. It contains not only the bile colouring matter but
                    also the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0626-0599"/> bile acids. The former is detected by the play of
                    colours yielded on the addition of nitric acid, the latter by the purple colour
                    produced by placing a piece of lump sugar in the urine tested, and adding
                    thereto a few drops of strong sulphuric acid. This test for the bile acids is
                    dwelt upon by Dr George Harley as an important point in serving to distinguish
                    jaundice with obstruction from jaundice without obstruction, in the latter of
                    which, although there is bile pigment in the urine, the bile acids are
                    absent.</p>
                <p>The contents of the bowels also undergo changes, being characterized chiefly by
                    their pale clay colour, which is in proportion to the amount of hepatic
                    obstruction, and to their consequent want of admixture with bile. For the same
                    reason they contain a large amount of unabsorbed fatty matter, and have an
                    extremely offensive odour.</p>
                <p>Constitutional symptoms always attend jaundice with obstruction. The patient
                    becomes languid, drowsy, and irritable, and has generally a slow pulse. The
                    appetite is usually but not always diminished, a bitter taste in the mouth is
                    complained of, while flatulent eructations arise from the stomach. Intolerable
                    itching of the skin is a common accompaniment of jaundice, and cutaneous
                    eruptions or boils are occasionally seen. Yellow vision appears to be present in
                    some very rare cases. Should the jaundice depend on advancing organic disease of
                    the liver, such as cancer, the tinge becomes gradually deeper, and the
                    emaciation and debility more marked towards the fatal termination, which in such
                    cases is seldom long postponed. Apart from this, however, jaundice from
                    obstruction may exist for many years, as in those instances where the walls of
                    the bile ducts are thickened from chronic catarrh, but where they are only
                    partially occluded. In the common cases of acute catarrhal jaundice recovery
                    usually takes place in two or three weeks.</p>
                <p>The treatment of this form of jaundice bears reference to the cause giving rise
                    to the obstruction. In the ordinary cases of simple catarrhal jaundice, or that
                    following the passing of gall stones, a light nutritious diet (milk, soups,
                    &amp;c., avoiding saccharine and farinaceous substances and alcoholic
                    stimulants), along with counter-irritation applied over the right side, and
                    after a few days the use of laxatives which tend to promote the flow of bile,
                    will be found to be advantageous. Rhubarb, taraxacum, podophyllum, mercury, are
                    among the remedies which have long been employed for this purpose, but the
                    recent researches of Professor Rutherford have brought to light certain other
                    agents (euonymin, iridin, leptandrin, &lt;fcc.), which exercise a powerful
                    influence as cholagogues, and are now coming into use. Diaphoretics and
                    diuretics to promote the action of the skin and kidneys are useful in jaundice.
                    In the more chronic forms, besides the remedies above named, the waters of
                    Carlsbad are of special efficacy. Where the jaundice depends on changes in the
                    substance of the liver, altering its structure, such as cancerous deposit, all
                    that can be accomplished is the palliation of symptoms, including the jaundice,
                    which may be mitigated by the treatment already indicated. With the view of
                    supplying bile to the alimentary canal, Dr Harley recommends the use of
                    inspissated ox-gall in doses of 5 to 10 grains administered in capsules of
                    gelatin.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Jaundice without obstruction</hi> is observed to occur as a
                    symptom in certain fevers, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> yellow fever, ague, and
                    relapsing fever, and in pyaemia (blood poisoning), also as the effect of the
                    action of certain poisonous substances, such as copper, mercury, antimony,
                    phosphorus, &amp;c., and the venom of snake bites. It is occasionally seen in
                    new-born infants. It is sometimes suddenly induced as the result of strong
                    mental excitement or emotion. Much difficulty has always been felt to account
                    for this form of jaundice, and numerous theories have been advanced to explain
                    its occurrence. Many of such cases might probably, as Virchow observes, be found
                    on careful investigation to depend on some obstruction in the biliary passages;
                    but there can be no doubt that many others admit of no such explanation, and as
                    regards these it is generally held that they are probably connected with some
                    alteration in the colouring matter of the blood, the source, it is believed, of
                    the bile pigment. Others suppose this form of jaundice to be due to an excess in
                    the normal reabsorption of bile into the blood. The pathology, however, is still
                    unsettled. Jaundice of this kind is almost always slight, and neither the urine
                    nor the discharges from the bowels exhibit changes in appearance to such a
                    degree as in the obstructive variety. Grave constitutional symptoms are often
                    present, but they are less to be ascribed to the jaundice than to the disease
                    with which it is associated.</p>
                <p>The uame <hi rend="italic">malignant jaundice</hi> is sometimes applied to that
                    very fatal form of disease otherwise termed acute yellow atrophy of the liver.
                    See <hi rend="smallcaps">Atrophy. (j. o. a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
