<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0659-0632-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JERROLD, Douglas William (9th edition, volume 13, page
                    632)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937258">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039784">Novelle</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914131">Epigrams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914130">Epigram</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91b3s">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90b98">Epigrams</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n659/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JERROLD, <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas William</hi></label>
                    (1803-1857), dramatist, satirist, and one of the most brilliant of the English
                    wits who distinguished the first half of the 19th century, was born in London,
                    January 3, 1803. His father, Samuel Jerrold, actor, was at that time lessee of
                    the little theatre of Wilsby near Cranbrook in Kent, but in 1807 he removed to
                    Sheerness. There, among the blue-jackets who swarmed in the port during the war
                    with France, little Douglas grew into boyhood, a stout, well made, rosy-cheeked,
                    white-haired urchin, fond of reading and pugnacious withal. Familiarity with the
                    tinsel and glitter of his father’s profession robbed it of its chief attractions
                    for the boy; but the glorious renown of Nelson and the anti-Gallic enthusiasm of
                    his father’s naval patrons filled his susceptible bosom, and wooed him to his
                    majesty’s uniform. From December 1813 till October 1815 Douglas Jerrold served
                    his country as a midshipman. He saw nothing of the war save a cargo of maimed
                    warriors from Waterloo; but till his dying day there lingered traces of his
                    early passion for salt water. The peace of 1815 ruined poor Samuel Jerrold;
                    there was no more prize money. On January 1, 1816, he removed with his family to
                    London, where the plucky little exmidshipman began the world again as a
                    printer’s apprentice, studying hard in the grey of the early morning at Latin,
                    pinching himself to get the <hi rend="italic">Waverley Novels</hi> from the
                    library, and finding unspeakable delight in the pages of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shakespeare.</hi> In 1819 Douglas Jerrold was a compositor in the
                    printing-office of the <hi rend="italic">Sunday Monitor.</hi> Several short
                    papers and copies of verses by him had already appeared in the sixpenny
                    magazines, but he aspired now to contribute to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Monitor·,</hi> and stealthily one evening he dropped into the editor’s box a
                    critique of the opera <hi rend="italic">Der Freischütz.</hi> Next morning he
                    received his own copy to set up, together with a flattering note from the
                    editor, requesting further contributions from the anonymous author.
                    Thenceforward Jerrold was engaged in journalism.</p>
                <p>He soon entered another field where he was to reap no less honourable laurels. In
                    1821 he had the satisfaction of seeing a comedy that he had composed in his
                    fifteenth year brought out at Sadler’s Wells Theatre, under the title <hi
                    rend="italic">More Frightened than Hurt.</hi> Other pieces followed, and in 1825
                    the popular young dramatist was engaged for a few pounds weekly to produce
                    dramas and farces to the order of Mr Davidge of the Coburg Theatre. By his
                    marriage in the autumn of 1824 the “little Shakespeare in a camlet cloak,” as he
                    was called, had found a less fitful incentive to industry than his mere
                    ambition; and, while he was engaged with the drama at night, he was steadily
                    pushing his way as a journalist by his daily labours. For a short while he was
                    part proprietor of a small Sunday newspaper. In 1829, through a fortunate
                    quarrel with the exacting Davidge, Jerrold left the “Coburg,” and <hi
                    rend="italic">Black-Eyed Susan</hi> was brought out on the “Surrey” boards. The
                    success of the piece was enormous. With its free gallant sea-flavour, it took
                    the town by storm, and “all London went over the water to see it” On the three
                    hundredth night the theatre was illuminated. Elliston, manager of the “Surrey,”
                    made thousands of pounds; T. P. Cooke, who played William, made his reputation;
                    Jerrold received about £70. But his fame as a dramatist was achieved. In 1830 it
                    was proposed that he should adapt something from the French for Drury Lane.
                    “No,” was his reply to the offer, “I shall come into this theatre as an original
                    dramatist or not at all.” In December of the following year he was received on
                    his own terms; <hi rend="italic">The Bride of Ludgate</hi> was the first of a
                    number of plays which found their way to Drury Lane stage. The other patent
                    houses threw their doors open to him also (the Adelphi had already done so); and
                    in 1836 Jerrold himself became co-manager of the Strand Theatre with Mr Hammond
                    his brother-in-law. The venture was not successful; and the partnership was
                    dissolved. While it lasted Jerrold wrote his only tragedy, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Painter of Ghent,</hi> and appeared himself in the title rôle, without <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n660/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0660-0633"/> any very marked success. His pen continued to be
                    fruitful of sparkling comedies till 1854, when his last piece, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Heart of Gold,</hi> was written.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile he had won his way to the pages of numerous periodicals,—before 1830 of
                    the second-rate magazines only, but after that to those of more importance; and
                    he had almost reached comfort and ease when an obligation, undertaken for an
                    unfortunate friend, drove him forth to fresh years of hard toil. When at last he
                    could settle in comfort he found himself the centre of a host of friends, whose
                    affection was his no less than their admiration; and his last years were spent
                    in peaceful happiness. The <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine,
                    Blackwood'</hi><hi rend="italic">'s,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">New
                    Monthly,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> all welcomed his
                    brilliant articles. To <hi rend="italic">Punch,</hi> the publication which of
                    all others is associated with his name, he contributed from its second number in
                    1841 till within a few days of his death. He founded and edited for some time,
                    though with indifferent success, the <hi rend="italic">Illuminated Magazine,
                    Jerrold's Shilling Magazine,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Douglas Jerrold's Weekly
                    Newspaper,</hi> and under his editorship <hi rend="italic">Lloyd's Weekly
                    Newspaper</hi> rose from almost nonentity to a circulation of 182,000. The
                    history of his later years is little more than a catalogue of his literary
                    productions, interrupted now and again by brief flights to the Continent or to
                    the country. Douglas Jerrold died at his house, Kilburn Priory, in London, on
                    June 8, 1857.</p>
                <p>Jerrold’s figure was small and spare, and in later years bowed almost to
                    deformity. His features were strongly marked and expressive from the thin
                    humorous lips to the keen blue eyes gleaming from beneath the shaggy eyebrows.
                    He was brisk and active, with the careless bluffness of a sailor. Open and
                    sincere, he concealed neither his anger nor his pleasure; to his simple
                    frankness all polite duplicity was distasteful. Hating the conventionalities of
                    the town, he loved to make his home in some rural retreat where he could roam at
                    ease, with loose coat and straw hat. To his house, always hospitable, he was
                    especially fond of attracting young men, whom he encouraged with strong, cheery
                    words, and often with more material aid. The cynical side of his nature he kept
                    for his writings; in private life his hand was always open. In politics Jerrold
                    was a Liberal, and he gave eager sympathy to Kossuth, Mazzini, and Louis Blanc.
                    In social politics especially he took an eager part he never tired of declaiming
                    against the horrors of war, the luxury of bishops, and the iniquity of capital
                    punishment.</p>
                <p>Douglas Jerrold is now perhaps better known from his reputation as a brilliant
                    wit in conversation than from his writings. In animated talk his retorts and
                    fancies flew from his lips like a shower of sparks. His jests were
                    unpremeditated and unforced; their spontaneity, which not seldom surprised
                    Jerrold himself, was one of their most telling characteristics, and often robbed
                    his sharpest retorts of their sting. For he let no sentimental or polite
                    consideration stand in the way of a brilliant rejoinder. As Dr Charles Mackay
                    expresses it, “when his jest came to the tip of his tongue, it had to explode
                    though the heavens should crack, and his best friend should take it amiss.” Yet
                    no one can accuse Jerrold of being spiteful. Ill-advised and thoughtless, even
                    unjust, his wit often was; but it was not barbed. It did not rankle in the
                    wound. Jerrold’s wit was of a tolerably high intellectual order. It is said that
                    no pun is to be found in his writings. Their wit is the wit of burnished epigram
                    and quaint conceit, of happy phrase and lightning retort. But the puns that
                    abounded in his talk were often wise as well as witty. The well-known
                    description of dogmatism as “puppyism come to maturity” is an excellent example
                    of the flashing insight that gave life and meaning to his jests.</p>
                <p>As a dramatist Jerrold was very popular, and struck out quite a line for himself
                    in the domestic drama. Here he dealt with rather humbler forms of social life
                    than had commonly appeared on the stage; and it is worthy of note that plays of
                    this kind have had the greatest run in modern times. Jerrold was one of the
                    first and certainly one of the most successful of those who in defence of the
                    native English drama endeavoured to stem the tide of translation from the
                    French, which threatened early in the 19th century altogether to drown original
                    native talent. Thoroughly English in motive, action, and atmosphere, his plays,
                    whether comedy or domestic drama, are all effective from their freshness, point,
                    and spirit. The author is at his best in construction as well as in sparkling
                    epigram and brilliant dialogue in <hi rend="italic">Bubbles of the Day,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Time Works Wonders.</hi> The latter perhaps excels in plot and
                    human interest. The tales and sketches which form the bulk of Jerrold’s
                    collected works vary much in skill and interest; but, although the artistic
                    symmetry is here and there marred, by traces of their having been composed from
                    week to week, they are always marked by keen satirical observation and pungent
                    wit. While reading them it is well to remember that they have a higher aim than
                    the beguiling an idle hour by the mere interest of the story; for the author is
                    always trying to call attention to some wrong, to rouse pity for some hardship,
                    to stir up indignation against some form of social oppression or abuse.</p>
                <p>Jerrold’s writings are scattered over all the periodical literature of his day;
                    but perhaps his most important works are in the following list. <hi
                    rend="italic">Men of Character</hi> are seven sketches (collected in 1838), in
                    which he throws sarcastic ridicule on various foibles and hypocrisies of
                    every-day men; <hi rend="italic">Cakes and Ale,</hi> a collection of short
                    papers of all sorts made in 1842, contains whimsical tales directed against the
                    tyranny of riches, the folly of judging by appearances, with similar thrusts at
                    the weaknesses and vices of humanity; <hi rend="italic">The Story of a
                    Feather,</hi> which originally appeared in <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> in
                    1842-43, tracing the career of an ostrich feather as it passes to successive
                    owners, affords the author opportunites of exposing shams, lashing vice, and
                    gibbeting successful villany in every rank of life. In <hi rend="italic">The
                    Chronicles of Clovernook</hi> he ventilates his philosophy of life, and his
                    objections to existing social and political institutions; in <hi rend="italic">A
                    Man made of Money,</hi> where the supernatural forms the basis for a story of an
                    eminently matter-of-fact character, he fulminates against the blind worship of
                    lucre; <hi rend="italic">St Giles and St James,</hi> perhaps his best work of
                    this class, is described in his own words as “an endeavour to show in the person
                    of St Giles the victim of an ignorant disregard of the social claims of the poor
                    upon the rich, . . . to present . . . the picture of the infant pauper reared in
                    brutish ignorance.” Of his professedly satirical papers the chief are <hi
                    rend="italic">Punch's Leiters to his Son, Punch's Complete Letter-Writer,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Sketches of the English. Mrs Caudle's Curtain
                    Lectures,</hi> possibly the most widely known of all Jerrold’s writings, explain
                    themselves by their title. Besides the “Q Papers,” which began in the second
                    nu⅛ιber of <hi rend="italic">Punch,</hi> Jerrold wrote various political
                    articles for his own and other newspapers.</p>
                <p>Were a reader now to go to Jerrold’s writings, he would find much that seems
                    commonplace and trite. The fault is not with Jerrold, but with the host of his
                    imitators who have sought with more or less success to reproduce in the pages of
                    every magazine the social cynicism which is apt at first view to be taken for
                    the essence of Jerrold’s style. But Jerrold has his own happy knack of handling
                    ordinary subjects, his own singular method of regarding things. His truths may
                    sometimes be commonplaces, and his moralizings trite; his descriptions may
                    sometimes drag on to tedium, and his characters stiffen into lay figures; even
                    his passion may sometimes attenuate to fustian, but every paragraph is lit up by
                    quaint phrase or happy conceit; <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n661/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0661-0634"/> every page is illumined by some gleaming epigram
                    or flash of originality. Jerrold seems to revel in the sarcastically satirical,
                    perhaps the easiest and most directly effective of all satire. He appears to
                    have reserved the softer side of his nature for his private life. He is far more
                    at home in satirizing the foibles of men than in praising their good points.
                    Here and there there are tender gleams of rarest pathos in his pages; but these
                    do not occur in scenes elaborated to move pity, but in the simple half
                    unconscious finishing touch to some little picture, drawn from the author’s
                    heart. That Jerrold has painted for us no full-length portrait of a thoroughly
                    noble character is due to his ultra-keen perception of the bad in human nature.
                    “Mr Capstick” in <hi rend="italic">St Giles and St James,</hi> who is perhaps
                    the most truly benevolent of all his personages, escapes the difficulty of
                    revealing his excellence in consistent speech by becoming an amiable hypocrite,
                    and poses as “the man with gall in his words and balm in his deeds.”</p>
                <p>A writer in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> for 1859 accuses Jerrold
                    of being a “sentimentalist,”—of writing “to gratify his sympathies and
                    antipathies, and not to bring out the truth.” That is an extreme statement,
                    which has some foundation in fact. Jerrold often attacked what he considered an
                    abuse without stopping to weigh the ultimate consequences, and without being
                    swayed by very satisfactory or conclusive reasons. Sometimes too the epigram or
                    the jest seems to have suggested the opinion, rather than the opinion the
                    epigram. That he generally espoused the healthy side was due more to his
                    instinct than to his reason, more to his heart than to his head. His keen
                    feelings often carried him to great lengths in invective. He did not escape the
                    besetting sin of all social reformers. He is tempted to elaborate and intensify
                    the peculiar aspect of the question that best suits the lesson he seeks to read;
                    and although it is impossible to doubt his perfect sincerity and honest
                    intention, yet the darkening of the shadows has a disingenuous air, and we are
                    tempted to suspect that he has been unconsciously impelled to exaggerate reality
                    or distort fact in order to justify his diatribe. Such a suspicion is fatal to
                    satire. It enlists our sympathies, on a most healthy principle, on the side of
                    what is attacked; and it is the cause why so much of what Jerrold wrote has
                    missed fire. This fault of colouring, which earnest social satire can scarcely
                    escape, has been commonly translated by critics as “bitterness”; but bitterness
                    is far too ill-natured a word to describe the vivid, quivering feeling in which
                    there is not the faintest tincture of personal animus, and in which all the
                    sharpness is on behalf of the poor and the.oppressed, with whom his own life had
                    taught him sympathy.</p>
                <p>Douglas Jerrold’s <hi rend="italic">fVorks wore</hi> collected by himself in 8
                    vols. 8vo., 1851-55, and again in 4 vols. 8vo in 1859. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Life and Remains of Douglas Jerrold,</hi> by his son Blanchard Jerrold, was
                    published in 1858; 2d ed., 1869. (F. MU.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
