<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0789-0756-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JOVIUS, Paulus, or Paolo Giovio (9th edition, volume
                    13, page 756)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957686">Historians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100080">Romanies</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n789/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JOVIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Paulus</hi>, or <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Paolo Giovio</hi></label> (1483-1552), an Italian historian and
                    biographer, was born of an ancient and noble family at Como, April 19, 1483. His
                    father died when he was a child, and Giovio owed his education to his brother
                    Benedetto. After studying the humanities, he applied himself to medicine and
                    philosophy at his brother’s request. He was Pomponazzi’s pupil at Padua; and
                    afterwards he took a medical degree in the university of Pavia. But the
                    attraction of literature proved irresistible for Giovio, and he was bent upon
                    becoming the historian of his age. Some time, probably in or after 1516, he went
                    to Rome, with a portion of his history already finished. This he presented to
                    Leo X., who read the MS., and pronounced it superior in elegance to anything
                    which had been produced since the decades of Livy. Giovio, encouraged by the
                    success of his first step in authorship, took up his residence in Rome, and
                    attached himself to the court of the cardinal Giulio de’ Medici. The next pope,
                    Adrian VI., gave him a canonry in his native town of Como, on the condition, it
                    is said, that Giovio should mention him with honour in his history. This
                    patronage from a pontiff who was averse to the current tone of Italian humanism,
                    proves that Giovio at this period passed for a man of sound learning and sober
                    manners. After Adrian’s death, Clement VII. assigned him chambers in the
                    Vatican, with maintenance for servants befitting a courtier of rank. In addition
                    to other benefices, he finally, in 1528, bestowed on him the bishopric of
                    Nocera. Giovio had now become in a special sense dependent on the Medici. He was
                    employed by that family on several missions,—as when he accompanied Ippolito to
                    Bologna on the occasion of Charles V.’s coronation, and Caterina to Marseilles
                    before her marriage to the duke of Orleans. During the siege of Rome in 1527 he
                    attended Clement in his flight from the Vatican. While crossing the bridge which
                    connected the palace with the castle of S. Angelo, Giovio threw his mantle over
                    the pope’s shoulders in order to disguise his master.</p>
                <p>In the sack he suffered a serious literary loss if we may credit his own
                    statement. The story runs that he deposited the MS. of his history, together
                    with some silver, in a box at S. Maria Sopra Minerva for safety. This box was
                    discovered by two Spaniards, one of whom secured the silver, while the other,
                    named Herrera, knowing who Giovio was, preferred to hold the MSS. for ransom.
                    Herrera was so careless, however, as to throw away the sheets he found in paper,
                    reserving only that portion of the work which was transcribed on parchment. This
                    he subsequently sold to Giovio in exchange for a benefice at Cordova, which
                    Clement VII. conceded to the Spaniard. Six books of the history were lost in
                    this transaction. Giovio contented himself with indicating their substance in a
                    summary. Perhaps he was not unwilling that his work should resemble that of
                    Livy, even in its imperfection. But doubt rests upon the whole of this story.
                    Apostolo Zeno affirms that in the middle of the last century three of the
                    missing books turned up among family papers in the possession of Count Giov.
                    Batt. Giovio, who wrote a panegyric on his ancestor. It is therefore not
                    improbable that Giovio possessed his history intact, but preferred to withhold
                    those portions from publication which might have involved him in difficulties
                    with living persons of importance. The omissions were afterwards made good by
                    Curtio Marinello in the Italian edition, published at Venice in 1581. But
                    whether Marinello was the author of these additions is not known.</p>
                <p>After Clement’s death Giovio found himself out of favour with the next pope, Paul
                    III. The failure of his career is usually ascribed to the irregularity of the
                    life he led in the literary society of Rome. We may also remember that Paul had
                    special causes for animosity against the Medici, whose servant Giovio had been.
                    Despairing of a cardinal’s hat, Giovio retired to his estates at Como, where he
                    spent the wealth he had acquired from donations and benefices in adorning his
                    villa with curiosities, antiquities, and pictures. He died upon a visit to
                    Florence in 1552.</p>
                <p>Giovio’s principal work was the <hi rend="italic">History of his own Times,</hi>
                    from the invasion of Charles VIII. to the year 1547. It was divided into two
                    parts, containing altogether forty-five books. Of these, books v.-xi∙iof part i.
                    were said by him to have been lost in the sack of Rome, while books xix.-xxiv.
                    of part ii., which should have embraced the period from the death of Leo to the
                    sack, were never written. Giovio supplied the want of the latter six books by
                    his lives of Leo, Adrian, Alphonso I. of Ferrara, and several other personages
                    of importance. But he alleged that the history of that period was too painful to
                    be written in full. His first published work, printed in 1524 at Rome, was a
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Piscibus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Romanis.</hi> After his retirement to Como he produced a valuable
                    series of biographies, entitled <hi rend="italic">Elogia Virorum
                    Illustrium.</hi> They commemorate men distinguished for letters and arms,
                    selected from all periods, and are said to have been written in illustration of
                    portraits collected by him for the museum of his villa at Como. Besides these
                    books, we may mention a biographical history of the Visconti, lords of Milan; an
                    essay on mottoes and badges; a dissertation on the state of Turkey; a large
                    collection of familiar epistles; togetherwith descriptions of Britain, Muscovy,
                    the Lake of Como, and Giovio’s own villa. The titles of these miscellanies will
                    be found in the bibliographical note appended to this article.</p>
                <p>Giovio preferred Latin in the composition of his more important works. Though
                    contemporary with Machiavelli, Guicciardini, and Varchi, he adhered to
                    humanistic usages, and cared more for the Latinity than for the matter of his
                    histories. His style is fluent and sonorous, rather than pointed or grave.
                    Partly owing to the rhetorical defects <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n790/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0790-0757"/> inherent in this choice of Latin, when Italian
                    had gained the day, but more to his own untrustworthy and shallow character,
                    Giovio takes a lower rank as historian than the bulk and prestige of his
                    writings would seem to warrant. He professed himself a flatterer and a
                    lampooner. The old story that he said he kept <hi rend="italic">a</hi> golden
                    and an iron pen, to use according as people paid him, condenses the truth in
                    epigram. He had the faults of the elder humanists, in combination with that
                    literary cynicism which reached its height in Aretino; and therefore his
                    histories and biographical essays are not to be used as authorities, without
                    corroboration. Yet Giovio’s works, taken in their entirety and with proper
                    reservation, have real value. To the student of Italy they yield a lively
                    picture of the manners and the feeling of the times in which he lived, and in
                    which he played no obscure part. They abound in vivid sketches, telling
                    anecdotes, fugitive comments, which unite a certain charm of autobiographical
                    romance with the worldly wisdom of an experienced courtier. A flavour of
                    personality makes them not unpleasant reading. While we learn to despise and
                    mistrust the man in Giovio, we appreciate the litterateur. It would not be too
                    far-fetched to describe him as a sort of 16th century Horace Walpole.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> The sources of Giovio’s biography are—his
                    own works; Tiraboschi’s <hi rend="italic">History of Italian Literature</hi>;
                    Litta’s <hi rend="italic">Genealogy of Illustrious Italian Families</hi>; and
                    Giov. Batt. Giovio’s <hi rend="italic">Uomini</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >illustri</hi><hi rend="italic">della Dioccsi Comasca,</hi> Modena, 1784.
                    Cicogna, in his <hi rend="italic">Delle</hi><hi rend="italic">Inscrizioni
                    Veneziane Raccolta</hi> (Venice, 1830), gives a list of Giovio’s works, from
                    which the following notices are extracted :— 1. Works in Latin:—(1) <hi
                    rend="italic">Pauli</hi><hi rend="italic">Jovii Historiarum sui temporis,</hi>
                    Florence, 1550-52, the same translated into Italian by L. Domenichi, and first
                    published at Florence, 1551, afterwards at Venice; (2) <hi rend="italic">Leonis
                    X.,</hi><hi rend="italic">Hadriani</hi><hi rend="italic">VI., Pompeii</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Columnae</hi><hi rend="italic">Card.,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Vitae,</hi> Florence, .1548, translated by Domenichi, Florence, 1549; (3) <hi
                    rend="italic">Vitae</hi><hi rend="italic">XII.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Vicecomitum</hi><hi rend="italic">Mediolani</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >principum,</hi> Paris, 1549, translated by Domenichi, Venice, 1549; (4) <hi
                    rend="italic">Vita</hi><hi rend="italic">Sfortiae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >clariss.</hi><hi rend="italic">ducis,</hi> Rome, 1549, translated by Domenichi,
                    Florence, 1549; (5) <hi rend="italic">Vita Fr. Ferd. Davali,</hi> Florence,
                    1549, translated by Domenichi, <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1551; (6) <hi
                    rend="italic">Vita</hi><hi rend="italic">magni</hi><hi rend="italic">Consalvi,
                    ibid.,</hi> 1549, translated by Domenichi, <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1550;
                    (7) <hi rend="italic">Alfonsi Atestensi,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic"
                    >ibid.,</hi> 1550, Italian translation by GioV. Batt. Gelli, Florence, 1553; (8)
                    <hi rend="italic">Elogia virorum bellica virtute illustrium,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1551, translated by Domenichi, <hi rend="italic"
                    >ibid.,</hi> 1554; (9) <hi rend="italic">Elogia clarorum virorum,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">kc.,</hi> Venice, 1546 (these are biographies of men of letters),
                    translated by Hippolito Orio of Ferrara, Florence, 1552; (10) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Libellus</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">legatione</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Basilii Magni</hi><hi rend="italic">Principis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Moscoviae,</hi> Rome, 1525; (11) <hi rend="italic">Descriptio
                    Larii Lacus,</hi> Venice, 1559; (12) <hi rend="italic">Descriptio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Britannia,</hi> &amp;c., Venice, 1548; (13) <hi rend="italic">De
                    Romanis</hi><hi rend="italic">Piscibus,</hi> Rome, 1524. 2. Works in
                    Italian:—(1) <hi rend="italic">Dialogo</hi><hi rend="italic">delle Imprese
                    militari et amorose,</hi> Rome, 1555; (2) <hi rend="italic">Lettere
                    Volgari,</hi> Venice, 1560. Some minor works and numerous reprints of those
                    cited have been omitted from this list; and it should also be mentioned that
                    some of the lives, with additional matter, are included in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vitae</hi><hi rend="italic">Illτιstrium</hi><hi rend="italic">Virorum,</hi>
                    Basel, 1576. (J. A. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
