<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0652-0625-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JERBOA (9th edition, volume 13, page 625)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:982308">Jerboas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:930458">Food</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130905">Spring</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204724">Missouri</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w32c">Jerboas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n652/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JERBOA</label>, a family of rodent mammals <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Dipodidae),</hi> chiefly characterized by the great length of the hind limbs
                    as compared with those in front, the disproportion being, in most cases, greater
                    even than in the kangaroos. Like the latter, the jerboas, or jumping mice, as
                    they are also called, raise themselves when disturbed on their hind legs, and
                    execute enormous leaps by the aid of a long muscular tail. When undisturbed,
                    however, they make use of all their <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n653/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0653-0626"/> limbs in walking, while the front pair are also
                    employed by many species as hands for the conveyance of food to the mouth. The
                    jerboas, of which there are three genera and twenty-two species known, occur
                    chiefly throughout northern and central Africa, south-eastern Europe, and
                    central and southern Asia, while one genus <hi rend="italic">(Pedetes)</hi> is
                    confined to South Africa and another <hi rend="italic">(Jaculus)</hi> to North
                    America. Of the third genus <hi rend="italic">(Dipus)</hi> there are twenty
                    known species, a typical example of which is the Egyptian jerboa <hi
                    rend="italic">(Dipus segyptius).</hi> The length of its body is 8 inches, and of
                    its tail, which is long, cylindrical, and covered with short hair, terminated by
                    a tuft, 10 inches. Its front limbs are pentadactylous, and only 1 inch in
                    length, the hind pair three-toed and six times as long. When about to spring, it
                    raises its body by means of the hinder extremities, and supports itself at the
                    same time upon its tail, while the fore feet are so closely pressed to the
                    breast as to be scarcely visible. Hence probably the name <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dipus,</hi> or two-footed. It then leaps into the air and alights upon its four
                    feet, but instantaneously erecting itself, it makes another spring, and so on in
                    such rapid succession as to appear as if rather flying than running. It is a
                    gregarious animal, living in considerable colonies in burrows, which it
                    excavates with its nails and teeth in the sandy soil of Egypt and Arabia. In
                    these it remains during great part of the day, emerging at night in search of
                    the herbs on which it feeds. It is exceedingly shy, and this, together with its
                    extraordinary agility, renders it difficult to capture. The Arabs, however,
                    succeed, it is said, in this by closing up all the exits from the burrows with a
                    single exception, by which therefore they are forced to come, and over which a
                    net is placed for their capture. When confined, they will gnaw through the
                    hardest wood in order to make their escape. The Indian jerboa <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Dipus</hi><hi rend="italic">indiens)</hi> is also a nocturnal burrowing
                    animal, feeding chiefly on grain, which it stores up in underground
                    repositories, closing these when full, and only drawing upon them when the
                    supply of food above ground is exhausted. The natives in some parts of India are
                    in the habit of searching for and robbing those granaries. The South African
                    form, known as the spring haas or jumping hare of the colonists <hi
                    rend="italic">(Pedetes capensis),</hi> is the largest member of the family,
                    measuring about a foot in length, exclusive of the tail, which is somewhat
                    longer, and is bushy throughout. Its molar teeth are rootless, while its toes,
                    which are three in number on each hind foot, are armed with long hoof-like
                    nails. It is a powerful animal, nearly as large as a hare, and progresses when
                    pursued by a series of leaps, each usually from 20 to 30 feet in length. Those
                    jumping hares are found abundantly in the rocky plateaus of South Africa, where
                    colonies of them form extensive burrowings somewhat similar to the rabbit
                    warrens of Britain. Like other jerboas it is chiefly nocturnal, and occasionally
                    it does considerable injury to the grain crops on which it feeds. Of the
                    American genus <hi rend="italic">(Jaculus)</hi> there is only a single
                    species—the Labrador jumping mouse <hi rend="italic">(Jaculus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">hudsonius).</hi> It occurs over a wide area of North America,
                    extending from Missouri northward to Labrador, and from the Atlantic westward to
                    the Pacific coast. It resembles the spring haas, and differs from all other
                    jerboas in having the metatarsal bones separated, and also in having its feet
                    fivetoed. It is a small creature, measuring about 5 inches in length, exclusive
                    of the much longer and very rat-like tail, and lives chiefly in the
                    neighbourhood of woods and shrubby places, where it conceals itself by day but
                    roams in companies at night. Its agility is extraordinary; one kept in
                    confinement by General Davies took, he says, “progressive leaps of from 3 to 4
                    and sometimes of 5 yards”; while Audubon considered it as probably the most
                    agile of all wild animals. On the approach of winter the American jumping mouse
                    retires into its burrow, and there encloses itself within a hollow ball of mud,
                    in which it passes the cold season in a state of complete torpidity. The North
                    American Indians neither eat its flesh nor make any use of its skin.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
