<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0784-0751-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JOSÉPHINE (9th edition, volume 13, page 751)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821339">Aunts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:909415">Empresses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4057cr7r">Convents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz4b">Conventions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42n4zk6c">Complexion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n784/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JOSÉPHINE</label> (1763-1814), empress of the French, was
                    born at Trois-Ilets, Martinique, on the 23d of June 1763, and was the eldest of
                    three daughters born to Joseph Tascher de la Pagerie, lieutenant in the
                    artillery, and his wife Rose-Claire Des Vergers de Sannois. She was educated at
                    a local convent, from which she was withdrawn in her fifteenth year, knowing how
                    to dance, sing, and embroider, but little else. Au aunt, resident in France, was
                    godmother to the second son of the Marquis de Beauharnais, once the governor of
                    Martinique; and she suggested a marriage between her god-child and niece. After
                    much negotiation between the families, in which the second and youngest
                    daughters were both preferred to Joséphine, her father carried her to Havre in
                    1779, she being already described to her aunt and the Beauharnais as possessing
                    a fine complexion, beautiful arms and eyes, and with a sweet voice and a
                    remarkable taste for music—altogether “très-avancée et formée pour son âge.” On
                    the 13th of December she was married to the Vicomte Alexandre Beauharnais at
                    Noisy-le-Grand. Her son Eugène was born at a time when her relations with her
                    husband were embittered by jealousy; and after the birth of her daughter
                    Hortense-Eugénie he sought a separation, but, though he carried his request to
                    the parliament, his petition was dismissed. Joséphine went back to her parents
                    in June 1788, and was with them when the Revolution broke out. At the request of
                    the vicomte she returned, however, to France in 1790. He was then a member of
                    the constituent assembly, receiving at his house the chiefs of the
                    constitutional party; and Joséphine was admired by all of them for her dignity,
                    simplicity, and sweetness. As the crisis became more acute, her husband thought
                    it prudent to withdraw to Ferté-Beauharnais, in Sologne, where he left his
                    family when he went to command the army of the Rhine. After his execution by
                    order of the Convention, Joséphine was reduced to great straits, and not till
                    the end of 1795 did regular remittances from Martinique begin again. She was
                    living in the Rue Chautereine, Paris, in a house of her own, when she paid her
                    first visit ta Napoleon, to thank him for restoring the sword of her husband.
                    She was in the full flower of her womanhood; Napoleon was at once drawn to her;
                    on the 9th of March 1796 they were married. In twelve days he left her to take
                    command of the army in Italy; but in J une, at his earnest request, she joined
                    him at Milan and went on to Brescia. After the peace of Léoben they lived at
                    Montebello near Milan, and Joséphine was for some time the queen of a court
                    frequented by great officers and diplomatists. Having visited Rome, she went
                    back to Paris, and at her house assembled the most distinguished men of the day.
                    During the expedition to Egypt she moved between the capital and Plombières; but
                    she had her first quarrel with Napoleon on his return, because, by an oversight,
                    she omitted meeting him. Social duties of the most brilliant and difficult sort
                    began to accumulate round her during the consulate. At the palace of the
                    Luxembourg and the Tuileries her drawing-room was again the centre of attraction
                    in Paris; her receptions were ruled by the old traditions of regal ceremony, and
                    there was an endless round of fetes, entertainments, and plays. Her beauty and
                    amiability won upon everybody; and when she wanted rest she retired to
                    Malmaison, a country seat she had bought, and amused herself with a variety of
                    light studies in botany and natural history. Rumours now began to reach her that
                    Napoleon, in despair of offspring, meant to sue for a divorce. She had long
                    known that his relatives were trying to undermine her position; and even when
                    she knelt beside him at Notre Dame, and received ’the triple unction at the
                    ceremony which crowned her empress, she knew it to be a concession wrung from
                    him. After the coronation he gave her less and less of his society. It was not,
                    however, until the winter of 1809 that he deliberately proposed to dissolve the
                    connexion. He divorced her with much show of tenderness, and she retired to
                    Malmaison with an annual grant of two million francs for her establishment. Her
                    affection for Napoleon, and her anxiety for his success, remained strong to the
                    hour of her death, on May 24, 1814; and but for his inordinate ambition he would
                    never have sought to live apart from her. She often provoked him by a certain
                    mild duplicity in her character; she was extravagant and superstitious; yet, to
                    fulfil the high destiny to which she was called, she brought much gentleness,
                    courage, and sweetness, qualities which carried her through her reverses with
                    admirable dignity.</p>
                <p>See Aubenas, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de Vlmpératrice Joséphine,</hi>
                    1858-59.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
