<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0640-0617-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RODNEY (9th edition, volume 20, page 617)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:951741">Harrows</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qm80">Dolphins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209745">Grenada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202945">Dominica</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n640/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RODNEY</label> George Brydges Rodney, Baron (1718-1792),
                    English admiral, second son of Henry Rodney of Walton-on-Thames, was born there
                    on 19th February 1718. His father had served in Spain under the earl of
                    Peterborough, and on quitting the army obtained command of the king’s yacht.
                    George was sent to Harrow when quite young, and on leaving entered the navy. By
                    warrant dated 2lst June 1732 he was appointed as volunteer on board the
                    “Sunderland,” a fourth-rate. While serving on the Mediterranean station under
                    Admiral Haddock he was made lieutenant in the “Dolphin,” his promotion dating
                    15th February 1739. In 1742 he attained the rank of post-captain, having been
                    appointed to the “Plymouth,” 9th November. After minor services of an active
                    character in home waters, he obtained command of the “Eagle,” sixty guns, and in
                    this ship took part in Hawke’s victory off Ushant, 14th October 1747, over the
                    French fleet under L’Etanduère. On that day Rodney gained his first laurels for
                    gallantry, under a chief to whom he was in a measure indebted for subsequent
                    success. On 9th May 1749 he was appointed governor and commander-in-chief of
                    Newfoundland, with the rank of commodore, it being usual at that time to appoint
                    a naval officer, chiefly on account of the fishery interests. Returning home, he
                    was elected M.P. for Saltash in May 1751, and married his first wife, Jane
                    Compton, sister to the earl of Northampton, 3d February 1753. During the Seven
                    Years’ War Rodney rendered important service. In 1757 he had a share in the
                    expedition against Rochefort, commanding the “Dublin,” seventy-four. Next year,
                    in the same ship, he served under Admiral Boscawen at the taking of Louisburg
                    (Cape Breton). On 19th May 1759 Rodney became a rear-admiral and was shortly
                    after given command of a small squadron intended to destroy a large number of
                    flat-bottomed boats and stores which were being collected at Havre for an
                    invasion of the English coasts. He bombarded the town for two days and nights
                    without ceasing, and inflicted great loss of war-material on the enemy. In July
                    1760, with another small squadron, he succeeded in taking many more of the
                    enemy’s flat-bottomed boats and in blockading the coast as far as Dieppe.
                    Elected M.P. for Penryn in 1761, he was in October of that year appointed
                    commander-in-chief of the Leeward Islands station, and within the first three
                    months of 1762 had reduced the important island of Martinique, while both St
                    Lucia and Grenada had surrendered to his squadron. During the siege of Fort
                    Royal his seamen and marines rendered splendid service bn shore. At the peace of
                    1763 Admiral Rodney returned home, having been during his absence made
                    vice-admiral of the Blue and voted the thanks of both Houses of Parliament.</p>
                <p>In 1764 Rodney was created a baronet by patent of 21st January, and the same year
                    he married Henrietta, daughter of John Clies of Lisbon. From 1765 to 1770 he was
                    governor of Greenwich Hospital, and on the dissolution of parliament in 1768 he
                    successfully contested Northampton at a ruinous cost. When appointed
                    commander-in-chief of the Jamaica station in 1771 he lost his Greenwich post,
                    but a few months later received the office of rear-admiral of Great Britain.
                    Till 1774 he held the Jamaica com <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n641/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0641-0618"/>mand, and during a period of quiet was active
                    in improving the naval yards on his station. Sir George struck his flag with a
                    feeling of disappointment at not obtaining the governorship of Jamaica, and was
                    shortly after forced to settle in Paris. Election expenses and losses at play in
                    fashionable circles had shattered his fortune and now broke up his family till
                    the eve of war with France. In February 1778, having just been promoted admiral
                    of the White, he used every possible exertion to obtain a command from the
                    Admiralty, to free himself from his money difficulties. By May he had, through
                    the splendid generosity of his Parisian friend Maréchal Biron, effected the
                    latter task, and accordingly he returned to London with his children. Sir George
                    was enabled to remit at once to his benefactor the full loan, and it is worthy
                    of record that the English Government in later years awarded pensions to the
                    maréchal’s daughters in recognition of their father’s chivalrous act. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Barrow’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Life of Anson,</hi> pp. 328-329. </p></note> That an
                    attempt was made by the French ministry during the war crisis to seduce Rodney
                    into accepting high rank in the French navy is undeniable from the evidence we
                    possess, but the details of the common version must be accepted with reserve,
                    excepting the undoubted instant rejection of the offer. To the English cabinet
                    the honour of both Rodney and Biron remained untarnished, if we may judge of the
                    former by his letters, public and private, and of the latter by the pension
                    awarded to his relatives. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>See <hi rend="italic">Naval Chronicle,</hi> 1799, i. 369-370; Mundy,
                                <hi rend="italic">Life of Rodney,</hi> i. 183; <hi rend="italic"
                                >United Service Journal,</hi> 1830, pt. ii. pp. 37-38, for divergent
                            evidence about the French offer of service. See also <hi rend="italic"
                                >Academy,</hi> 4th October 1884, for the identification of a letter
                            which perhaps bears upon Sir G. Rodney’s prospects in 1778.
                    </p></note></p>
                <p>Sir George was appointed once more commander-in-chief of the Leeward Islands, 1st
                    October 1779, but did not sail till 29th December. He captured a Spanish convoy
                    bound to Cadiz on 8th January 1780, and eight days later defeated the Spanish
                    admiral Don Juan de Langara off Cape St Vincent, taking or destroying seven
                    ships. On 17th April an action, which, owing to the carelessness of some of
                    Rodney’s captains, was indecisive, was fought off Martinique with the French
                    admiral Guichen. Rodney, acting under orders, captured the valuable entrepot of
                    St Eustatius, and by his strong measures for stopping illegal and contraband
                    trade evoked an attempt at censure on the part of his political opponents. After
                    a few months in England, recruiting his health and defending himself in
                    parliament, Sir George returned to his command in February 1782, and a running
                    engagement with the French fleet on 9th April led up to his crowning victory off
                    Dominica, when on 12th April with thirty-five sail of the line he defeated Comte
                    de Grasse, who had thirty-three sail. The French inferiority in numbers was more
                    than counterbalanced by the greater size and superior sailing qualities of their
                    ships, yet five were taken and one sunk, after eleven hours’ fighting. This
                    important battle saved Jamaica and ruined French naval prestige, while it
                    enabled Rodney to write— “Within two little years I have taken two Spanish, one
                    French, and one Dutch admirals.” A long and wearisome controversy exists as to
                    the originator of the manoeuvre of “breaking the line” in this battle, but the
                    merits of the victory have never seriously been affected by any difference of
                    opinion on the question. A shift of wind broke the French line of battle, and
                    advantage was taken of this by the English ships in two places.</p>
                <p>Rodney arrived home in August to receive unbounded honour from his country. He
                    had already been created Baron Rodney of Rodney Stoke, Somerset, by patent of
                    19th June 1782, and the House of Commons had voted him a pension of £2000 a
                    year. From this time he led a quiet country life till his death, which occurred
                    on 24th May 1792, in London, while on a visit to his son. Next to Nelson we may
                    fairly place Rodney, not only because of his well-merited successes, but for
                    masterly decision and confident boldness in grappling with fleets of the three
                    chief maritime states of Europe while in the plenitude of their power. He fought
                    his equals in naval science, but conquered by superior practical skill.</p>
                <p>See General Mundy, <hi rend="italic">Life and Correspondence of Admiral Lord
                        Rodney,</hi> 2 vols., 1830; Rodney letters in 9th <hi rend="italic"
                        >Report</hi> of Hist. MSS. Com., pt. iii.; “Memoirs” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Naval Chronicle</hi> i. 353-393; and Charnock, <hi rend="italic">Biographia
                        Navalis</hi> v. 204-228. Lord Rodney published in his lifetime (probably
                    1789) <hi rend="italic">Letters to His Majesty's Ministers, dee., relative to St
                        Eustatùts, &lt;kc.,</hi> of which there is a copy in the British Museum.
                    Most of these letters are printed in Mundy’s <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> vol.
                    ιi., though with many variant readings. (G. F. II.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
