<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0581-0562-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RIO DE JANEIRO (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    562)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h03c">Exports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f0m">Negroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918764">Exports</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n581/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RIO DE JANEIRO</label> (in full form SÀo Sebastiäo do Rio de
                    Janeiro, and colloquially shortened to Rio), the capital of Brazil, and one of
                    the principal seaports of South America, is situated on the western side of one
                    of the finest natural harbours in the world in 25° 54' 23" S. lat. and 43° 8'
                    34'' W. long, (the position of the observatory). Along with its environs it is
                    separated from the province of Rio de Janeiro (whose chief town is Nitherohi)
                    and constitutes an independent municipality (municipio neutro), with an area of
                    about 540 square miles, divided into nineteen (formerly sixteen) parishes or
                    frequezias. Most of the streets are narrow and meanlooking; even the fashionable
                    Rua do Ouvidor, which is lined on both sides with handsome shops, is a mere
                    alley. The Rua Direita, or, as it is now called officially, Rua Primeiro de
                    Março, is the principal business street, and is wide and pleasant.</p>
                <p>It runs from the gate of the royal palace (a building of small pretensions) to
                    the convent of Sào Bento, and contains the exchange, the post office, and the
                    custom-house, as well as the imperial chapel (1761) and several other churches.
                    The churches and monastic buildings of Rio de Janeiro number upwards of fifty,
                    mostly built in the “Jesuit” style, but striking from their size and the
                    barbaric magnificence of their decorations, as well as on account of their
                    well-chosen sites. La Candellaria (17th century) is conspicuous from the height
                    of its towers, and La Gloria crowns a beautiful eminence on the bay. The
                    monastery of Sào Bento is reputed to be the wealthiest in the empire, with large
                    possessions in land and mines; and its chapel is not unworthy of that
                    reputation. Besides the famous hospital of Dorn Pedro IL, better known as La
                    Miseri-cordia, because built (1841) on ground belonging to the fraternity of
                    that name, there are several smaller institutions of the same class in the city;
                    and a large and handsome lunatic asylum, founded in 1841 with funds obtained by
                    selling titles of nobility at a fixed tariff, occupies a good position in the
                    Botafogo suburb. The military hospital is also an extensive establishment. Among
                    the literary and scientific institutions of the city, the College Dorn Pedro <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n582/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0582-0563"/>II. (which is well organized), national
                    museum, institute of history, geography, and ethnology (1838), polytechnic
                    institute, national educational museum, polytechnic school, military, naval, and
                    normal schools, lyceum of arts, musical conservatory, geographical society, and
                    astronomical and meteorological observatory deserve special mention. The great
                    national library owes its foundation to the bequest of Joao VL, and now numbers
                    upwards of 120,000 volumes open to the public daily (see Libraries, vol. xiv. p.
                    530, where the lesser libraries are also mentioned). One of the pleasant
                    features of the city is the abundant supply of excellent water distributed to
                    numerous stately fountains in the streets and public squares. The chief
                    aqueduct, begun in the middle of the 17th century, starts at Tijuca, about 12
                    miles distant, and crosses the valley (740 feet wide and 90 feet deep) between
                    Monte de Santa Theresa and Monte de Santo Antonio by a beautiful double tier of
                    arches (erected in 1750), which form a striking feature in some of the finest
                    views of the city. Its entire length being covered in with stone work, the water
                    is kept remarkably cool. As the city has extended, other aqueducts of less
                    architectural pretensions have had to be constructed; and a good deal has been
                    done by an English company in recent years to provide a proper system of sewers.
                    The bay of Rio de Janeiro has been the subject of poetic panegyric ever since it
                    was discovered; and the traveller who comes to it after a voyage round the world
                    seems as susceptible to its charm as if it were his first tropical experience.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“This bay,” says Mr
                            Gallenga, “is the very gate to a tropical paradise. There is nowhere so
                            bold a coast, such a picturesque cluster of mountains, such a maze of
                            inlets and outlets, such a burst of all-pervading vegetation. The city
                            itself is like Lima or Buenos Ayres, a mere chess-board of shabby narrow
                            streets. But the environs all round—the Botafogo Bay, the vale of
                            Larangerias, the height of Tejuca, San Cristoval, Santa Teresa, and
                            others .... may well challenge comparison with any of the loveliest
                            localities of either hemisphere. You are bidden drive out to the Botanic
                            Gardens (at Botafogo), but the whole road inland or along the water is
                            nothing but a continuous garden.” </p></note> The actual entrance,
                    between Fort St Juan and Fort Santa Cruz, is 1700 yards wide. Within there are
                    fifty square miles of anchorage, or even more for vessels of light draught, the
                    bay having a width varying from 2 to 7 miles and stretching inland from the sea
                    for 16 miles. Its coast-line, neglecting minor indentations, measures 60 miles.
                    Such a sheet of water would be beautiful anywhere; but, when on all sides it is
                    surrounded by hills of the most varied contour, the beauty is enhanced a
                    thousandfold. Its surface is broken by a large number of islands—from the Ilha
                    do Governador (6 miles long and 2 broad; population 2500) down to the little
                    cluster of the Jerubahibas.</p>
                <p>Rio is the seat of the principal arsenal in the empire, and most of the Brazilian
                    cruisers have been built in its dockyards. The roadstead for vessels of war is
                    between Villegagnon Island, with its fort, and the islands at the north-east
                    angle of the town called respectively Ilha das Cobras (Snake Island) and Ilha
                    dos Ratos (Rat Island). On the north side of Ilha das Cobras is the naval
                    arsenal with two large docks. On Ilha das Enchadas (Coaling Island) there is a
                    fine commercial dock 385 feet long, on keel blocks, 45 feet wide at the entrance
                    and 23 feet deep. Between 1846 and 1855 the average number of vessels that
                    cleared from the port of Rio was over 680 with an average total burden of
                    221,280 tons. In 1867 1311 vessels (522,407 tons) entered and 1032 (596,663
                    tons) cleared; in 1883 1218 (1,220,330 tons) entered and 1067 cleared, while,
                    besides, the coasting trade was represented by 1414 vessels (454,739) entering.
                    England has the greatest share of the foreign shipping trade, Germany ranking
                    next, and France third. How completely (in spite of the fact that Santos and Rio
                    Grande have become more independent) Rio de Janeiro is the commercial as well as
                    the political capital of Brazil is evident from the fact that the exports from
                    Rio are on the average fully equal in value to those from the rest of Brazil;
                    for instance, the value of the exports from the capital in 1859-60 was
                    £5,933,850 out of £11,826,121 from the empire, in 1879-80 £10,566,800 out of
                    £18,928,635, and in 1881-82 £7,550,966 out of £18,522,050. To this large total
                    coffee has long contributed 40-50 per cent., and in 1880-81 (an exceptional
                    year) the ratio rose to 86 per cent. Though the coffee plant was not introduced
                    till 1770, Brazil is the greatest coffee-producing country in the world, and Rio
                    de Janeiro is consequently the largest coffee-exporting city. The other exports
                    of moment are brandy (in decreasing quantities), sugar, hides, diamonds, tapioca
                    (mainly to France), tobacco and cigars, medicinal herbs, gold dust, and
                    jacaranda, rosewood, and other timbers. The imports comprise cotton goods,
                    machinery, pitch pine, and petroleum. Among the comparatively few local
                    industries are the weaving of coloured buckskins (by a German firm) and other
                    woollen and half woollen stuffs, the extensive manufacture of artificial mineral
                    waters and liquors, brewing, carriage-building, and hat-making. Rio de Janeiro
                    is the terminus of the Dorn Pedro II. Railway, and thus of nearly the whole
                    railway system of the country; and it communicates regularly by steamer with
                    Nitherohi on the other side of the bay, which is the terminus of another line.
                    The population of the municipality of Rio de Janeiro was in 1850 stated at
                    266,466, of which 205,906 were in the town proper; but this, like most of the
                    earlier figures, appears to be an exaggeration, as the census in 1872 gave only
                    274,972, of which about 190,000 were in the town and suburbs, the slaves
                    numbering 48,939 and the foreigners (mainly Germans, French, and Italians)
                    84,279. The Italian element has been rapidly increasing. The bulk of the
                    population is Portuguese with a mixture of Negro blood. The native Indian races
                    are scarcely represented.</p>
                <p>The annual rainfall at Rio de Janeiro is about 60 inches, the greatest
                    precipitation taking place in February (12 inches), and the least in August
                    (under 1 inch). The monthly ranges of temperature for 1882 were—January 97° -68°
                    , February 95°-68°; March 95°-69°; April 87° -64°; May 84°-60°; June 82° -59°;
                    July 85° -59°; August 98°-54°; September 80° -50° j October 92°-59 <hi
                        rend="superscript">J</hi>; November 97° -59°; December 96° -62°.</p>
                <p>The bay of Rio de Janeiro, the Nitherohi or “Hidden Water” of the natives, was
                    first observed on 1st January (hence the name) by Alphonso de Souza, who
                    supposed, as the Rio indicates, that he had discovered the mouth of a large
                    river. How Villegagnon in 1558 took possession of the island which now bears his
                    name but was then called after his patron Coligny, and how his colony was
                    destroyed by the Portuguese, has been told in the article Brazil (vol. iv. p.
                    229). The city of Rio de Janeiro did not become the capital of the viceroyalty
                    till 1763, when José I. chose it in preference to Bahia because it was a better
                    centre for defensive operations against the Spaniards. In 1711 it had been
                    captured by· Duguay-Trouin, who exacted 70,000 cruzados as ransom. It became the
                    residence of the Portuguese royal family in 1808; in the same year its port was
                    declared free to foreign trade; and in the course of a short time it was made by
                    Dorn Joâo VI. the seat of so many important institutions that Portugal became
                    jealous at finding the relation between mother country and colony practically
                    reversed. When Joâo VI. returned to Portugal and Pedro was declared emperor of
                    Brazil in 1822, Rio de Janeiro naturally remained the capital of the new state.
                    Ecclesiastically the city was at first (from the foundation of the church of Sào
                    Sebastiäo by Mendo de Sa in 1567) subject to the diocese of Bahia (San
                    Salvador). It was made a suffragan bishopric of Bahia by papal bull of 19th July
                    1576; and when Bahia was by the bull of 16th November 1676 created the
                    metropolitan archbishopric of Brazil, Rio de Janeiro was (along with Pernambuco)
                    declared a bishopric, the bishop’s authority extending over the province of
                    Espirito Santo northwards and southwards to the Rio de la Plata (Rio da Prata).
                    The first bishop relinquished his dignity without taking possession; and the
                    second did not reach his diocese till 1682, when he made the church of St
                    Sebastian on the Castle Hill his cathedral. This distinction was in 1734
                    transferred to the Church of the Cross and in 1738 to that of the Rosary. A new
                    cathedral was begun in 1749 by D. Frei Antonio do Desterro, but the works were
                    discontinued on his death, and in 1840 the materials served for the military
                    academy.</p>
                <p>See Milliet de Saint-Adolphe, <hi rend="italic">Biccionarw . . . . do Imp. do
                        Brazil,</hi> Paris, 1845; G. Gardiner, <hi rend="italic">Travels in the
                        Interior of Brazil,</hi> 1846; Burmeister, <hi rend="italic">fteise nach
                        Brasilien,</hi> Berlin, 1853; Herbert H. Smith, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Brazil,</hi> 1880; C. Γ. van Delden Laerne, <hi rend="italic">Brazil and
                        Java,</hi> 1885. (H. A. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
