<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0570-0551-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RIESENGEBIRGE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 551</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:851789">Chains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1064206">Pine</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RIESENGEBIRGE</label> (Bohemian <hi rend="italic"
                    >Krkonose),</hi> or Giant Mountains, a lofty and rugged group on the common
                    boundary of Silesia and Bohemia, between the upper courses of the Elbe and the
                    Oder. They form the highest portion of the Sudetic system, which separates
                    south-east Prussia from the Austrian empire, and finds its natural continuation
                    towards the north-west in the Erzgebirge, the Thuringian Forest, and the Harz
                    Mountains. Adjoining the Isergebirge and the Lausitzergebirge on the west, and
                    the Eulengebirge and the Adlergebirge on the east and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0571-0552"/>south-east, the Riesengebirge proper run
                    south-east and north-west between the sources of the Zacken and the Bober, for a
                    distance of 23 miles, with a breadth of 14 miles. They cover an area of about
                    425 square miles, three-fourths of which is in Austrian and the remainder in
                    Prussian territory. The boundary line follows the crest of the principal chain
                    or ridge (Riesenkamm), with the highest summits, which stretches along the
                    northern side of the group, with an average height of over 4000 feet. Its
                    principal peaks are the Reifträger (4430 feet), the Hohe Rad (4968 feet), the
                    Great Sturmhaube (4862 feet), the Little Sturmhaube (4646 feet), and, near the
                    east extremity, the Schneekoppe or Riesenkoppe (5266 feet), the loftiest
                    mountain in northern or central Germany. Roughly parallel to this northern
                    ridge, and separated from it by a long narrow valley known as the Siebengründe,
                    there extends on the south a second and lower chain, of broad massive “saddles,”
                    with comparatively few peaks. The chief heights here are the Kesselkoppe (4708
                    feet), the Krkonose (4849 feet), the Ziegenrücken, and the Brunnenberg (5072
                    feet). From both ridges spurs of greater or less length are sent off at various
                    angles,—those from the Bohemian ridge being longer, broader, and less abrupt
                    than those from the Riesenkamm. On its northern side this mountain group rises
                    ruggedly and precipitously from the Hirschberg valley; but on its southern side
                    its slope towards Bohemia is very much more gradual. The scenery is in general
                    bold and wild,— the projecting crags and deep rocky gorges and precipices often
                    presenting striking, sometimes even sublime, landscapes. The Bohemian ridge is
                    cleft about the middle by a deep gorge through which pour the headwaters of the
                    river Elbe, which finds its source in the Siebengründe. The Iser, Bober, Aupa,
                    Zacken, Queiss, and a great number of smaller streams also rise among these
                    mountains or on their skirts; and small lakes and tarns are not unfrequent in
                    the valleys. The Great and Little Schneegruben,—two deep rocky gorge-like
                    valleys in which snow remains all the year round—lie to the north of the Hohe
                    Rad. Nearly the whole of the Riesenkamm and the western portion of the southern
                    chain are granite; the eastern extremity of the main ridge and several mountains
                    to the south-east are formed of a species of gneiss; and the greater part of the
                    Bohemian chain, especially its summits, consists of mica-slate. Blocks of these
                    minerals lie scattered on the sides and ridges of the mountains and in the beds
                    of the streams; and extensive turf moors occupy many of the mountain slopes and
                    valleys. The lower parts of the Riesengebirge are clad with forests of oak,
                    beech, pine, and fir; above 1600 feet only the last two kinds of trees are
                    found, and beyond about 3950 feet only the dwarf pine <hi rend="italic">(Pinus
                    Pumilio).</hi> Various alpine plants are found on the Riesengebirge,—some having
                    been artificially introduced on the Schneekoppe. "Wheat is grown at an elevation
                    of 1800 feet above the sea-level, and oats as high as 2700 feet. The inhabitants
                    of this mountain region, who are tolerably numerous, especially on the Bohemian
                    side, live for the most part, not in villages, but in scattered huts called
                    “Bauden.” They support themselves by the rearing of cattle, tillage,
                    glass-making, and linen-weaving. Mining is carried on only to a small extent for
                    arsenic, although there are traces of former more extensive workings for other
                    metals. Several spots in the Riesengebirge are a good deal frequented as summer
                    resorts; and the Schneekoppe and other summits are annually visited by a
                    considerable number of travellers, who find shelter in the Bauden. The
                    Riesengebirge is the legendary home of Number Nip (Rübezahl), a half-mischievous
                    half-friendly goblin of German folklore; and various localities in the group are
                    more or less directly associated with his name.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
