<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0546-0527-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RHONE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 527</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1091440">Recluses</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="22" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j916">Passes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n546/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RHONE</label> (Fr. <hi rend="italic">Rhone),</hi> the largest
                    European river flowing directly into the Mediterranean, rises in the Swiss
                    canton of Valais, passes through the Lake of Geneva, strikes across the line of
                    the Jura, and turning southward through France falls into the Gulf of Lyons. It
                    has a length of 447 miles according to Strelbitzky (505 according to other
                    authorities), and its principal affluent the Saône has a length of 268 miles
                    above the confluence, which is 200 miles inland. The drainage area of the whole
                    river-system is 38,000 square miles, and the mean discharge at the river mouth
                    is 60,000 cubic feet per second, the maximum being 428,840 cubic feet and the
                    minimum 19,426.</p>
                <p>The natives give the name of source of the Rhone (locally Rotten or Rodden) to
                    three warm springs that rise in a circular stone basin near the Hôtel du Glacier
                    du Rhône; but the real beginning of the river is the well-known glacier.
                    According to M. Gosset, <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>A -sketch of M. Gosset’s remarkable labours is given in the Alpine Journal,
                    1878-80. </p></note> a Swiss engineer, the Rhone glacier, which at present
                    measures about 9 miles in length by about 3200 feet in width, is proved to have
                    retreated 3028 feet between 1856 and 1881 and sunk upwards of 300 feet. In
                    geological time the Rhone glacier filled the whole valley to a depth of 4800
                    feet and spread out over the Swiss plain now partly occupied by the Lake of
                    Geneva. Obstructed by the Jura, it divided into two branches, one of which found
                    its way (as the river does still) by the “écluse” between the Jura and the
                    western Alps to deposit its erratic blocks on the heights in the neighbourhood
                    of Lyons, while the other branch, bending northward, widened out so as to
                    distribute its burden at Freiburg, Bern, Soleure, and even Aarburg. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Faisan and Chantre,
                    Monographie géologique des anciens glaciers et du terrain erratique de la partie
                    moyenne du bassin du Rhône, 1880. See also the map illustrating Auguste
                    Jaccard’s paper in Bull, de lα Soc. Vaudoise, Feb. 188δ. </p></note></p>
                <p>In the first 30 miles from the foot of the glacier (5751 feet) to Brieg (2214
                    feet) the stream has a fall of 1 in 46; in the next 70 miles to Villeneuve it
                    descends at the rate of 1 in 378. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>A large-scale profile of the upper Rhone accompanies
                    Gerlach’s paper “Die Penninischen Alpen” in Mém. de la Soe. Helv., 1869.
                    </p></note> It passes between the Bernese and the Pennine Alps, receiving the
                    tribute of 260 glaciers, of which the Aletsch is one of the most important. At
                    Martigny, where it is joined by the Drance (a glacier-fed stream memorable for
                    the terrible inundation of 1818 caused by the sudden bursting of the ice barrier
                    by which its waters had been dammed back), the Rhone turns suddenly northwest,
                    and below the defile of St Maurice (about 90 miles from its source) it enters
                    the wide alluvial plain formerly occupied by the south-eastern arm of the Lake
                    of Geneva <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> which has now retreated about 12 miles
                    northward. The limpid character of the Rhone water as it issues from the
                    south-western end of this great settling vat has become a commonplace of
                    geographical illustration, and equally well-known is the contrast afforded at
                    the confluence about a mile below Geneva between the current of the main river
                    and that of its turbulent affluent the Arve, which has found no resting place in
                    its 2000 feet descent by a course of 60 miles from the valley of Chamouni and
                    the glaciers of Mont Blanc. It is the Arve that is mainly responsible for the
                    dangerous inundations of the Rhone valley farther down; while its volume is
                    sometimes not more than 1235 per second, <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Professors Paul Chaix and Plantamour, on one occasion in
                    March, found the volume of the Arve as low as 812 cubic feet per second, and
                    that of the Rhone 1612. </p></note> at other times it pours into the Rhone
                    (whose maximum at this point is 2000 cubic feet) no less than 24,700 cubic feet,
                    sometimes causing the river to flow backwards towards the Lake of Geneva. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See the annual Observations
                    hydrométriques suisses sur le bassin du Rhône issued by the Bureau fédéral des
                    travaux publics. </p></note> To obviate the evils of their irregularity it has
                    been proposed to divert the lower course of the Arve into the Lake of Geneva.
                    The annual maximum of the Rhone at Geneva, according to observations between
                    1806 and 1880, occurs on the 7th of August. Since 1862 there has been an
                    increase of high levels owing to the dyking of the river and the destruction of
                    forests (see Plantamour, “Obs. limniinétriques,” in <hi rend="italic">Mém. de la
                    Soc. de Genève,</hi> 1880). The defile or “écluse” by which the Rhone passes
                    between Grand Credo, the terminal bastion of the Jura, and Mont Vouache, one of
                    the Alps of Savoy, is commanded by one of the great frontier fortresses of
                    France,</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n547/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0547-0528"/>
                <p>Fort de l’Écluse. About 5 j miles farther down occurs the famous Perte du Rhône,
                    a’partially subterranean passage, now considerably modified by blasting.</p>
                <p>“The rocks forming the funnel come so close at one. place that there is only a
                    distance of about two feet from bank to bank, and a man of moderate height could
                    stand with one foot on the French side and the other on the Savoy side and see
                    between the beautiful river trembling as it were with rage and hastening to
                    escape from the defile through which it is doomed to pass. A little way farther
                    down the river lias hollowed out a passage about 30 feet wide, which retains
                    this width for a depth of from 30 to 35 feet, when it contracts considerably. At
                    this depth a stratum of harder rock has resisted the action of the water, which,
                    however, has scooped out beneath it almost as much as above it. Along each side
                    of the ravine the harder rock projects for eight or ten feet like a cornice. At
                    first the water is seen through the opening down the middle; but farther on
                    great masses of rock from the walls of the ravine have fallen down, and, resting
                    on the double cornice, conceal the river for a distance of some 60 paces.” <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>De Saussure, Voyage dans les
                    Alpes (1780-1796), ii. 90 sq. </p></note></p>
                <p>During the summer floods the water filled the ravine far above the level of the
                    fallen blocks, and the Perte du Rhône was no longer visible. <note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See the elaborate papers,
                    with maps and sections, by Renevier in Mém. de la Soc. Helvétique, 1855 (“Mém.
                    Geol. sur la Perte du Rhône et ses environs”), and in Bull, de la Soc.
                    Géologique, 1874-5, 3d ser. vol. iii. </p></note> The rocks through which the
                    “perte” is cut belong to the Urgonian subdivision of the Cretaceous system,—the
                    stratum which has been hollowed out being described as <hi rend="italic"
                    >calcaire gris.</hi> Just below the ravine the Rhone is joined by the Valserine,
                    which a little above Bellegarde passes through a “perte” of a similar character.
                    Since 1871 the motive power of the main river has been utilized for the
                    industries of Belle-garde; a large tunnel 20 feet high and more than half a
                    kilometre long brings the water from the south side of the perte to turbine
                    wheels placed in the bed of the Valserine, and wire ropes transmit the power to
                    the Bellegarde workshops on the plateau 400 feet above. <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Reclus, Noeuv. Geogr. Univ., “La France,”
                    p. 215. </p></note> Below Belle-garde the river is deflected southwards by the
                    western chain of the Jura. It receives from the left the Usses, the Fiar (which
                    drains the lake of Annecy), and the emissary of the Lake of Bourget, the largest
                    of the purely French lakes, and then at the junction of the Guiers (from the
                    Grande Chartreuse) it turns north-west round the southern end of the Jura. The
                    Ain (118 miles long), which joins it from the right, is navigable in the
                    direction of the current, and in its upper waters has a “perte” of some
                    interest. Farther down the main river meanders for a time with shifting channels
                    in a bed about two miles broad, but it gathers into a single stream before its
                    junction with the Saône. This important confluent (the ancient Arar, which
                    according to Caesar flows “incredibili lenitate ”) has its source at Vioménil in
                    the Vosges 1300 feet above the sea, and has been joined by the Doubs, which,
                    rising in the district between the Jura and the Vosges, is famous for the beauty
                    of its upper gorges and for the waterfall (70 feet) known as the Saut du Doubs.
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See “La Saut du Doubs,”
                    in Tenir du Monde, 1880. </p></note> Southwards from Lyons, where it is 530 feet
                    above the sea, the united river continues to be still the “arrowy Rhone”; in the
                    61 miles from the Saône mouth to the Isére it falls 180 feet, in the 18 from the
                    Isére to the Drome 56 feet, in the 38 from the Drome to the Ardèche 164, and in
                    the 34 from the Ardèche to the Durance 88£. Those affluents, all except the last
                    from the Savoy and Maritime Alps, are in general of little importance, but at
                    times become formidable torrents. The same is true of the much shorter streams
                    which bring down the waters from the eastern slopes of the Cevennes. During the
                    inundation of the 10th September 1857, which has been frequently exceeded, the
                    three streams the Doux, the Érieux, and the Ardèche poured into the Rhone 49,000
                    cubic feet per second. At Fourques d’Arles, 25 miles from the sea, the river
                    begins to form its delta, breaking up into two main branches, the Grand Rhone
                    passing from Arles south-east towards the Gulf of Fos, and the Petit Rhone
                    south-west towards the Little Camargue. With all its rapidity of current and
                    mass of waters it is not able to keep a clear passage to the sea through its own
                    alluvium, which, according to M. Reclus’s estimate, has since the Gallo-Roman
                    period added from 75 to 100 square miles to the area of its delta.</p>
                <p>From the time that Marius caused his soldiers to excavate the Fossae Marianae
                    which have left the name of Fos to the bay already mentioned the endeavour to
                    maintain a navigable channel inland from the sea has perplexed successive
                    generations. Vauban himself declared “Les embouchures du Rhône sont
                    incorrigibles.” The method of contracting and embanking a principal channel
                    right out to sea failed, either because the embankments were not carried out far
                    enough, or more probably because the tides of the Mediterranean are not
                    sufficiently strong to aid in removing the alluvium. A canal constructed in
                    1802-1832 from Arles to Bouc (on the east side of the Gulf of Fos) proved too
                    shallow for the new steam traffic. At length in 1863 a scheme brought forward by
                    Hippolyte Peut in 1846 was adopted for the making of a canal, 11,480 feet long,
                    210 feet wide and 19⅜ feet deep at low tide, from Tour St Louis on the left bank
                    of the Grand Rhone to the Anse de Repos in the Gulf of Fos. The canal was
                    completed in 1871, and the quays of the port of St Louis by the close of 1878,
                    at a cost of 26,000,000 francs. Hostile critics maintain that it will be
                    possible to keep this channel open at the seaward end only by continual and
                    costly dredging, but hitherto their fears seem exaggerated. The new port has
                    been very successful, 1261 vessels (313,745 tons) entering in 1881 and 2317
                    vessels (448,757 tons) in 1882. The regulation of the river itself is still a
                    problem. The rapidity of the current from Lyons downwards, the extremely
                    shifting character of the channel, and the variations that take place in the
                    volume of water are the great obstacles to be overcome. Two months of the year
                    are lost for navigation through floods or lack of water or fogs or ice. At
                    present (1885) a scheme combining the two systems of regularization and
                    canalization is being carried out for the purpose of securing everywhere at low
                    water a depth of 5 feet 3 inches.</p>
                <p>In the beginning of the present century even passenger boats used to be hauled up
                    the river by towing ropes, and when steam was introduced it was found that the
                    vessels had to be specially constructed to make head against the current. The
                    laying of a continuous chain all the way from Lyons to Arles is impracticable
                    through the shifting character of the bed; but several methods have been adopted
                    to overcome the difficulties of the ascent. Thus some boats advance by means of
                    long jointed levers which catch into the ground. Or a steel wire cable with one
                    of its ends fixed at a given spot is unwound as a steam tug descends the stream
                    and then the tug with its convoy of boats makes its way up again by simply
                    winding in. Or two tugs are employed, the first going in advance of the other so
                    far that the cable which it pays out takes a sufficient hold of the bottom to
                    enable the second to haul by it. Or, lastly, Dupuy de Lome’s system is adopted,
                    by which the boat grips the river bottom by means of two continuous chains
                    perpetually sunk in front and emerging behind. The Saône is much more easily
                    dealt with than the Rhone. It is navigable as far up as Port-sur-Saône, and a
                    system of movable dams and sluices has been established to secure a depth of 6
                    to 7 feet at low water.</p>
                <p>The basin of the Rhone communicates with the Loire by the Canal du Centre
                    (joining the Saône at Chalons), with the Seine by the Burgundy Canal (joining
                    the Saône at St Jean de Losne), with the Rhine by a canal (1783-1834) which
                    passes from the Saône at Saint Symphorien to the Doubs, and finally ends at
                    Strasburg, and with the Meuse and the Belgian system by a canal (Canal de ΓEst)
                    constructed since 1875 from the Saône to the Moselle.</p>
                <p>See I’oisscl, <hi rend="italic">Voy. pitt. et navigation exécutée sur une partie
                    du Rhône réputée non-navigable,</hi> 1795, and works on the river by Hippolyte
                    Peut (1846), Surell (1847), Desjardins (1866), Adrian German (1872), and De la
                    Rochette. Also Lentheric, <hi rend="italic">Les villes mortes du Golfe de
                    Lyon,</hi> 1875, and a paper in <hi rend="italic">Rev. des Deux
                    Mondes,1880;</hi> Blerzy, <hi rend="italic">Torrents, fleuves, et canaux de la
                    France, 1878.</hi> (H.A.W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
