<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0272-0255-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAINBAND (9th edition, volume 20, page 255)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960197">Horizon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182641">Yellow</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947579">Green</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878051">Cooks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754966">Cooking</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n272/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAINBAND</label>. Every transparent substance is perfectly
                    opaque to some particular kinds of light. A certain shade of orange light is
                    absorbed by the vapour of water, and, when sunlight which has traversed a
                    stratum containing this vapour is decomposed in a spectroscope, the blank caused
                    by the missing rays appears as a black band or group of fine lines. This is
                    called the <hi rend="italic">rainband,</hi> because from its intensity the
                    amount of moisture in the atmosphere may be guessed at, and the occurrence of
                    rain predicted with considerable certainty. It has long been known that the
                    spectrum of sunlight shows lines of telluric as well as of solar origin. The
                    former constitute the absorption-spectrum of the atmosphere (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">SPECtro-</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n273/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0273-0256"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">scoPy);</hi> some are produced by the permanent gases,
                    others by aqueous vapour, which is always present, though in variable amount.
                    The absorption-spectrum of water-vapour has been minutely studied and carefully
                    mapped by Janssen and by Cornu. In Angstrom’s table of normal solar spectra
                    there are numerous groups of lines which appeared most conspicuous when the sun
                    was close to the horizon, and many of these are coincident with the
                    absorption-lines of water-vapour. They are found principally in the red and
                    yellow, and the main group is seen a little to the red side of the <hi
                        rend="italic">D</hi> line. In small spectroscopes the water-vapour lines
                    appear fused together into a band on the red side of <hi rend="italic">D,</hi>
                    or even as a mere widening of that line. There are several variable bands in the
                    spectrum which come to a maximum of intensity when the sun is on the horizon.
                    These are due to absorption by the permanent gases; the one which in a small
                    instrument appears to separate the yellow from the green is frequently mistaken
                    for the water-vapour band, and this is the cause of many incorrect “rainband
                    predictions.” In 1872 Professor Piazzi Smyth noticed a change in the
                    water-vapour lines before and after a sirocco in Palermo, and the same
                    phenomenon was brought before him very strikingly in France before great rains
                    in 1875 <hi rend="italic">(Edin. Ast. Obs.,</hi> vol. xiv.), when he named the
                    main group of water-vapour lines the “rainband.”</p>
                <p>The rainband may be observed with any spectroscope, but direct-vision instruments
                    of medium size are most convenient. It is important that the spectroscope should
                    have as great dispersion as possible and good definition, especially at the red
                    end. To make an observation the slit, which must be kept perfectly clean, should
                    be narrowed down until the spectral lines are sharp and clear. The instrument
                    should be carefully focused to get the maximum absorption effect; but all
                    observers lay stress on noting whether the intensity of the band decreases
                    rapidly or gradually as the altitude is increased. When a dark band is observed
                    at the horizon and at the zenith, heavy rain is almost certain to follow
                    immediately. It is of little importance whether the sky be clear or covered with
                    high clouds at the point of observation; low clouds or haze make the result
                    untrustworthy by shortening the line of sight, thus reducing the strength of the
                    band and equalizing it in all directions. The utility of the spectroscope in
                    meteorology depends on its power of investigating the hygrometrical conditions
                    of the whole slice of atmosphere looked through, and it affords a means of
                    ascertaining the difference of humidity in different directions. The hygrometer
                    only indicates the state, as regards moisture, of the few yards of air
                    surrounding it. The great difficulty in the way of obtaining accurate results
                    with the rainband spectroscope has been the mental scale of comparison employed
                    by most observers. Although some have found it easy to estimate the intensity of
                    the band from 0 to 20, it is beyond the power of many to describe it in figures
                    even from 0 to 5. Professor Piazzi Smyth noted its strength relatively to that
                    of the dry-air band between the green and yellow. The fixed solar lines <hi
                        rend="italic">E, b,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">F</hi> have been used as a
                    closer approximation to a scale in instruments not powerful enough to separate
                    the rainband from the <hi rend="italic">D</hi> line. This compound line appears
                    to vary from something less intense than <hi rend="italic">E</hi> in very dry
                    weather to something considerably darker than <hi rend="italic">F</hi> when rain
                    is imminent. Seven degrees can be discerned, and these may be represented by
                    using the sign = to mean “of equal intensity with,” &gt; to mean “darker than,”
                    and &lt; “less dark than,” as, &lt; <hi rend="italic">E,=E, &gt;E&lt;b, =
                        b,&gt;b&lt;F, = F,</hi> and &gt; <hi rend="italic">F.</hi> When the thin
                    solar lines in the green are seen very distinctly there is less probability of
                    rain falling than when they are indistinct or invisible.</p>
                <p>The following table gives an idea of the intensities corresponding to
                    rain-probabilities at Edinburgh.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Intensity of rainband with <hi rend="italic"
                                    >D.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Temperature.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Prediction.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>&lt;b.</p><p><hi rend="italic">= b.</hi> =
                                b.</p><p>&gt; δ &lt; <hi rend="italic">F</hi> (thin lines distinct).
                                    <hi rend="italic">&gt;b&lt;F(</hi> ,,
                                indistinct),</p><p>&gt;b&lt;f <hi rend="italic">= F.</hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">&gt;F.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Any.</p><p>Below 40’ Fahr. Above 45’ Fahr. Below
                                60’ Fahr.</p><p>Above 60° Fahr. Any.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>No rain.</p><p>Probably rain. Probably no
                                rain.</p><p>Probably rain. Probably no rain. Rain.</p><p>Much
                                rain.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>It appears that the average percentage of fulfilments of predictions of “rain”
                    and “no rain,” made for a period of twelve hours after one observation in the
                    morning, which may be expected in Scotland is about 75. In less variable
                    climates, such as those of the south of Europe and parts of the United States, a
                    much higher degree of accuracy has been attained. The precise strength of
                    rainband which corresponds to the probability of a fall of rain within a
                    definite time depends on the temperature and also on the place of observation;
                    in every case it must be determined by the observer for himself. Very dark
                    rainbands are found to precede rain in more than 95 per cent, of the cases
                    everywhere; entire, or almost entire, absence of the band presages a dry day
                    with equal probability. With a spectroscope powerful enough to split <hi
                        rend="italic">1)</hi> a mental numerical scale must be used in default of a
                    suitable micrometer, and by practice the observer will be able to draw up a
                    table for its conversion into probabilities of rain.</p>
                <p>The production of an artificial absorption-line the intensity of which could be
                    varied by known degrees suggested itself to more than one observer as the
                    principle for a rainband-micrometer. A wedge of didymium glass comes very near
                    success in this direction, but the absorption-line is awkwardly situated.
                    Professor Cook of Dartmouth College, the leading meteorological spectroscopist
                    in the United States, has constructed a micrometer for <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    spectroscope of sufficient power to separate the rainband into lines. A silk
                    fibre is fixed to a frame capable of being moved to and fro in the tube of the
                    spectroscope by a micrometer screw <hi rend="superscript">7</hi> . When brought
                    into focus the fibre appears as two sharp lines, which become fainter and w <hi
                        rend="superscript">τ</hi> ider as it is withdrawn. When the lines appear of
                    equal intensity with the most prominent line of the rainband (α of the <hi
                        rend="italic">D</hi> group in Janssen’s map) the micrometer is read; forty
                    shades of intensity may be indicated by it. The unit proposed for graduating
                    such micrometers on a uniform scale is the intensity of the faintest and least
                    refrangible of a group of three lines in the red ( <hi rend="italic">w. l.</hi>
                    6207) of the spectrum produced by a 1 centimètre column of the gas given off' by
                    heated lead nitrate (mixture of nitrogen peroxide and oxygen) at 25° C. and 760
                    mm. The spectroscope when reinforced by this micrometer has been found to
                    indicate with unfailing accuracy the existence in certain parts of the sky of
                    banks of invisible cloud, which become visible when a fall of temperature and
                    other necessary conditions allow the vapour to condense. In settled weather such
                    masses of vapour are not to be found, the micrometer readings being the same in
                    all directions at the same altitude. Sometimes the rainband grows gradually
                    darker for several days before a period of steady and long-continued rain, while
                    sudden violent showers may give very short notice.</p>
                <p>The spectroscopic history of a thunderstorm observed on 9th June 1884 by
                    Professor Cook is extremely interesting. During its approach the water-vapour
                    line observed at 10° north of the zenith towards the storm was darker by ten
                    degrees of the scale than that observed 10° south of the zenith, although to the
                    eye the clouds presented exactly the same appearance at both places. On this
                    occasion the strength of the line varied as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Hour.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At zenith.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At 30°.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At 20°.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At 10°.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At horizon.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>S a.m. ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>32</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>43</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9 „ ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>34</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>46</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10 „ ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>36</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>47</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11 ,. .∙</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>46</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>43</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11.45 a.m.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Rain commenced 11.30.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12 noon..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>32</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Rain ceased 12.10.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12.45 p.m.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>,, recommenced 12.20.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1.30 „</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Rain ceased at 1. Total rainfall, 1∙6 inches in
                                1⅛ hours.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Some relation has been traced between the variations of the rainband and the
                    appearance of aurorae, but this matter is not yet fully investigated. (H. R.
                    M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
