<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0355-0338-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REFORMATORY AND INDUSTRIAL SCHOOLS (9th edition, volume
                    20, page 338)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h70862m">Mending</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9789n">Girls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222r689">Boys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942866">Girls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837358">Boys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882984">Crime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n355/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REFORMATORY AND INDUSTRIAL SCHOOLS</label>. There exist two
                    classes of schools for the reformation and industrial training of children in
                    Great Britain and Ireland, both under state control when duly certified.
                    Reformatory schools are for the better training of juvenile convicted offenders;
                    industrial schools, in which industrial training is provided, are chiefly for
                    vagrant and neglected children and children not convicted of theft. These
                    schools are of modern but gradual growth, the result in part of humane
                    endeavours to rescue children from evil courses already embarked on or likely to
                    be their lot, in part of the conviction that, as a matter of social economy, the
                    expenditure incurred in early restraint is less costly than the punishment of
                    matured crime.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">England and Scotland</hi> .—The Acts of Parliament relating to
                    reformatory and industrial schools in Great Britain were consolidated and
                    amended in 1866; and these Acts (29 and 30 Yict. cc. 117, 118), with local
                    legislation and some extension and amendment, govern the two classes of schools
                    at the present time. Both reformatory and industrial schools are certified by
                    the home secretary upon the application of the managers, and upon a satisfactory
                    inspection and report, and subject to a yearly visit by inspectors. In both
                    classes industrial training is an essential feature, so as to engender
                    industrious habits in the inmates and give them the means of earning an honest
                    livelihood. Not only local circumstances but reasonable individual inclinations
                    are taken into consideration. In rural districts the cultivation of the soil and
                    in urban districts local trades are obvious sources of employment; the duties of
                    a sailor are taught in training ships near the coast. Occupations that create a
                    distaste for labour or that do not provide a permanent source of profitable
                    labour for adults are avoided. The managers (often a committee of magistrates)
                    make all necessary rules for the management and discipline of the schools,
                    subject to the provisions of the legislature and the intervention of the
                    secretary of state. They have the appointment of officers. Conformity to the
                    rules and residence in the schools may be enforced by imprisonment, the
                    application and limits of which vary somewhat in reformatory and industrial
                    schools, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> such imprisonment for school offences is
                    confined in industrial schools to children above ten, an age almost always
                    exceeded in the inmates of reformatories. Attention is paid in both classes to
                    religious convictions, and as far as possible a selection is made of a school
                    conducted in accordance with the creed professed by the child or its responsible
                    guardians. Children after eighteen months’ detention may be placed out on
                    licence with trustworthy persons and with their own consent. The managers of a
                    reformatory or of an industrial school may decline to receive the youthful
                    offender in the one case and in the other the child proposed to be sent; but the
                    reception of a child operates as an undertaking by the managers to educate,
                    clothe, lodge, and feed him (or her) until he (or she) can be legally discharged
                    or is removed. Reformatory and industrial schools are, hoAvever, essentially
                    distinct in character and governed by distinct Acts of Parliament: a school
                    cannot at the same time be both a certified industrial school and a certified
                    reformatory school. The Middlesex Industrial School for juvenile offenders,
                    established under local Acts, and in part a certified industrial school, is,
                    however, somewhat exceptional in blending the treatment of both classes.</p>
                <p>Any offender under sixteen, convicted of an offence punishable with penal
                    servitude or imprisonment and sentenced to be imprisoned for ten days or a
                    longer tenn, may be sent to a certified reformatory school for not less than two
                    and not more than five years. A youthful offender under ten cannot be sent to a
                    reformatory school unless he has been previously charged with some crime or
                    offence punishable with penal servitude or imprisonment, or is sentenced in
                    England by a judge of assize or court of general or quarter sessions or in
                    Scotland by a circuit court of justiciary or a sheriff. Youthful offenders
                    receiving a conditional pardon may now be sent to a certified reformatory
                    school. Certified industrial schools receive any child apparently under fourteen
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">avIio</hi> is brought by any person before justices as
                    answering to any of the following descriptions :—if found begging or receiving
                    alms (w׳hether actually or under the pretext of selling or offering for sale
                    anything) or being in any street or public place for these purposes; if found
                    wandering and not having any home or settled place of abode, or proper
                    guardianship, or visible means of subsistence; if found destitute, either being
                    an orphan or having a surviving parent who is undergoing penal servitude or
                    imprisonment; if it frequents the company of reputed thieves; if lodging,
                    living, or residing with common or reputed prostitutes, pr in a house resided in
                    or frequented by prostitutes for the purpose of prostitution; if it frequents
                    the company of prostitutes (43 and 44 Yict. c. 15); where a parent or
                    step-parent represents to the magistrates that he is unable to control a child
                    and that he desires that the child be sent to an industrial school; where the
                    guardians of the poor represent that a child maintained in a Avorkliouse or
                    pauper school or poor-house is refractory or the child of a parent convicted of
                    a crime or offence punishable with penal servitude or imprisonment, and that it
                    is desirable that he be sent to an industrial school. To the above cases have to
                    be added a child apparently under twelve <hi rend="smallcaps">avIio</hi> is
                    charged with an offence punishable by imprisonment or a less punishment but has
                    not been in England convicted of felony or in Scotland for theft; and the
                    children of any woman convicted of a crime after a previous conviction, and
                    under her care and control at the time of conviction for the last of such
                    crimes, who have no visible means of subsistence or who are without proper
                    guardianship (Prevention of Crimes Act, 1871).</p>
                <p>A prison authority (a term as regards industrial schools calculated to mislead,
                    as the authority is in general the court of quarter sessions or school boards,
                    and in Scotland commissioners of supply, magistrates of burghs, or county
                    boards) may, with the approval of the secretary of state, establish or
                    contribute toAvards the establishment, building (including borroAving money), or
                    management (and in England may not only contribute to but undertake these
                    matters) of reformatory or industrial schools, or toAvards the support of the
                    inmates, and such authority may contract with the managers for the reception and
                    maintenance of offenders or children. The treasury contributes toAA־ards the
                    custody and maintenance of offenders in reformatory and of children in
                    industrial schools on the recommendation of the secretary of state, the sum
                    being limited as regards children in industrial schools, on the application of
                    their parents or guardians, to 2s. per head per week. The guardians of the poor
                    or the board of management of district pauper schools or parochial boards of a
                    parish or combination may, with the consent in England of the local government,
                    and in Scotland of the board of management, contribute towards the maintenance
                    of children detained in industrial schools. A prison authority in England may
                    contribute toAvards the ultimate disposal of an inmate of a certified industrial
                    school. The parent or other person legally liable to maintain a youthful
                    offender or child in a school is required (if able) to contribute not more than
                    5s. per Aveek, recoverable summarily. The alleged Avant of diligent enforcement
                    of this liability is a great source of complaint.</p>
                <p>The introduction of a system of compulsoiy elementary education rendered it
                    necessary to extend industrial schools. Under <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n356/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0356-0339"/>various Acts passed since 1870 school boards
                    have power, with the consent of the secretary of state, to contribute to or
                    wholly to undertake the establishment, building, and maintenance of industrial
                    schools, and a power exists to transfer industrial schools from other
                    authorities to school boards, but such schools are subject to the jurisdiction
                    of the secretary of state in the same manner as other certified industrial
                    schools. The machinery for bringing children, the subjects of certified
                    industrial schools, before the proper tribunal for making orders has been and is
                    a vexed question. Legislative powers given to “any one” are apt to fall into
                    abeyance or into the hands of the police. School boards have a discretionary
                    power to appoint officers to bring children before justices to be sent to
                    industrial schools (33 and 34 Yict. c. 75, s. 36). A school board or school
                    attendance committee (as the local authority) is required, after due warning to
                    the parents, to complain to a court of summary jurisdiction of the
                    non-attendance of a child coming within the elementary education Acts, and must
                    so complain at the instance of any person. The court may then make an attendance
                    order for the child at some certified efficient school, and, in case of
                    non-compliance, may order the child to be sent to a certified day or other
                    industrial school. The expenses of industrial schools, established by or
                    contributed to by school boards, form part of the general expenses of the school
                    fund. As in the case of other industrial schools, parents are liable to
                    contribution, and where a child is ordered upon complaint made by a school
                    attendance committee to be sent to a certified industrial school the council,
                    guardians, or sanitary authority appointing such committee have, on the
                    recommendation of the committee, the same power of contri-buting towards the
                    maintenance as if they were a school board (42 and 43 Vict. c. 48, s. 4).</p>
                <p>In 1876 a fresh class of industrial schools was introduced called “certified day
                    industrial schools,” in relation to which prison authorities and school boards
                    have the same powers as in the case of industrial schools; and towards the
                    custody, industrial training, elementary education, and meals of children
                    attending these schools parliament may contribute a sum limited to Is. per head
                    per week, on conditions recommended by the secretary of state, with a limited
                    power over the contribution of parents. In certain cases of non-compliance with
                    an attendance order the child is sent to a day industrial school rather than to
                    an industrial school of the class described above (39 and 40 Vict. c. 79, s.
                    16). In large cities day industrial schools are calculated to be of great
                    service in dealing with the class of poor neglected children. The children are
                    found to be managed without much difficulty, and to respond to any efforts made
                    on their behalf; they compare favourably with children kept for years in close
                    confinement, and are often their superiors in spirit and intelligence (27th <hi
                        rend="italic">Report</hi> of inspector). Another description of certified
                    schools has sprung up in connexion with school boards,—“truant schools.” The few
                    which at present are established in London and some large towns are on the whole
                    doing a good work. The necessary adaptation of certified industrial schools to
                    the school-board system must necessitate the placing of all reformatory and
                    industrial schools on a clearer system of classification. Crime must be
                    distinguished from pauperism. However crime may arise from neglect of parents,
                    it is neither desirable nor fair to compel as the price of poverty children
                    unconvicted of crime to associate with juvenile delinquents even after the
                    punishment of crime has ceased. On the other hand, the actual incarceration of
                    boys and girls in a jail should be avoided as far as possible.</p>
                <p>The total number of schools under Government inspection at the close of 1883 was
                    200, viz., 61 reformatory and 139 industrial schools, of which last 7 were
                    specially certified as truant and 12 as day industrial schools. The number of
                    children under detention in 1883 in reformatory schools in Great Britain was
                    6657, at a total school expenditure of £126,122, of which £85,635 was paid by
                    the treasury, £6140 by parents, £23,183 by rates, and £4943 by subscriptions and
                    legacies. In industrial schools the number was 18,780 and the expenditure
                    £359,821, of which £176,733 was paid by the treasury, £17,596 by parents,
                    £40,052 by rates, £65,542 by school boards, and £42,129 by subscriptions. The
                    total admissions (excluding transfers) to reformatory schools to the end of 1883
                    amounted to 42,669, viz., 34,640 boys and 8029 girls. The total discharges
                    (excluding transfers) were 36,111, viz., 29,235 boys and 6876 girls. They were
                    disposed of as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Boys.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Girls.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Employment or service................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="5"
                                ><p>9,962</p><p>9,663</p><p>2,317</p><p>4,291</p><p>693</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3814</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13,776</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2115</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="4"
                            ><p>11)778</p><p>2,465</p><p>4,291</p><p>693</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Emigrated......7.....................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>148</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sent to
                            sea............................</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Enlisted....................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Discharged from disease ..............</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>374</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>181</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>555</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Discharged as incorrigible
                            ............</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>213</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>91</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>304</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Died ..............7..........</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>781</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>299</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="3"><p>1,080</p><p>1,169</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Absconded, and not recovered ........</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>941</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>228</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>29,235</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6S76</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>36,111</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The total admissions to industrial schools (excluding transfers)</p>
                <p>to the end of 1883 were 61,260, viz., 48,959 boys and 12,301 girls. The total
                    discharges (excluding transfers) were 42,412, viz., 33,877 boys and 8535 girls.
                    They were disposed of as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Boys.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Girls.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Employment or service................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12,513</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5248</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17,761</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>To friends............................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10,212</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1995</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12,207</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Emigrated............................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>737</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>130</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>867</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sent to sea.........................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,325</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,325</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Enlisted.........................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>921</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>921</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Discharged as diseased, or on special</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>grounds............................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>859</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2S1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,140</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Committed to reformatories ..........</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>885</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>153</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,038</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Died..................................</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,405</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>557</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,962</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Absconded, and not recovered ........</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,020</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>171</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1,191</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>33,877</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8535</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>42,412</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ireland</hi> .—Reformatory schools were established in Ireland
                    in 1858, and ten years afterwards were placed mainly on their present footing
                    (Irish Reformatory Schools Act, 1868); whilst the establishment and regulation
                    of industrial schools were provided for by the Industrial Schools Act (Ireland),
                    1868, extending to Ireland, with certain modifications, the English Act of 1866.
                    The differences between the Acts applicable in Ireland and Great Britain relate
                    chiefly to minor matters. The rule requiring a young offender or a child to be
                    sent to a school under the same religious management is much more rigid in
                    Ireland than in Great Britain, and the Irish Act does not limit the power of
                    sending a child under ten to a reformatory school where the child has not been
                    previously charged with an offence punishable with penal servitude or
                    imprisonment. The power to contract with managers for the reception and
                    maintenance of young offenders is in general vested in grand juries and in some
                    town councils. The number of reformatory schools in Ireland at the close of 1883
                    was 9, viz., 5 for boys and 4 for girls, with 907 boys and 192 girls. Of
                    industrial schools there were 62, viz., 17 for boys, 44 for girls, and 1 for
                    young boys and girls, with a total of 2409 boys and 3759 girls. The disposal on
                    discharge follows the lines given in the tables for Great Britain. Much the
                    larger proportion of girls in industrial schools in Ireland, as might be
                    anticipated, find their subsequent career in employment or service, or are
                    placed out through Mends. Emigration also is absolutely far larger (and has been
                    from the establishment of industrial schools) in the case of girls than of boys.
                    The reported results of the training of girls discharged from reformatory
                    schools are very satisfactory, and among the 1526 girls discharged during the
                    three years 1880-82 there was only one conviction for crime during 1883. The
                    total receipts for the maintenance of reformatory schools in 1883 were £28,116,
                    of which £17,555 was contributed by the treasuiy vote and £7920 from local
                    rates. The average cost per head for maintenance (including rent and disposal)
                    was £23, 9s. for boys and £27, 2s. 2d. for girls. For industrial schools the
                    receipts in 1883 ־were £126,820, of which the treasuiy contributed £77,259 and
                    rates £27,960. Parental contributions to reformatory and industrial schools were
                    £1018.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States</hi> .—The institutions in the United States and
                    of other civilized countries, having for their object or effort the reclamation
                    of the young, are too closely connected with the education of poor and destitute
                    children generally to allow of examination here, or of useful comparison with
                    the reformatory and industrial schools of Great Britain under state control.</p>
                <p>In 1882 a royal commission was issued to inquire into the management generally of
                    all certified reformatories and industrial schools in the United Kingdom. The
                    commission, in the following year, suggested a simplification of the law and the
                    removal of some anomalies and defects, including the vexed question as to the
                    treatment of boys and girls in relation to imprisonment, and the distinctions
                    already adverted to. The commissioners expressed their opinion that these
                    schools were having a salutary effect in reducing the amount both of juvenile
                    and of adult crime. The memoranda of the earl of Dalhousie and Lord Norton
                    attached to the <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> are worthy of special attention.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">(j. E. D.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
