<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0523-0506-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RHEA (9th edition, volume 20, page 506)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946724">Grasses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843v7w">Grasses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n523/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RHEA</label> (or Rheea) FIBRE is a textile material yielded
                    by one or more species of <hi rend="italic">B'ohmeria</hi> (nat. ord. <hi
                        rend="italic">Urticaceae),</hi> plants found over a wide range in India,
                    China, the Malay Peninsula and islands, and Japan. Rhea is also capable of being
                    grown in temperate latitudes, and has been experimentally introduced into the
                    south of France and Algeria. The most important source of rhea fibre, known also
                    very inappropriately as China grass, or by its Malay name Ramie, is <hi
                        rend="italic">B. ηiυea.</hi> It is a shrubby plant growing to the height of
                    from 5 to 8 feet with foliage and inflorescence like the common nettle, but
                    destitute of stinging hairs. Some authorities consider the variety cultivated in
                    China to be specifically distinct from the Indian plant. An allied plant called
                    Pooalι or Puya, <hi rend="italic">B. Puya,</hi> found growing wild in the north
                    of India, is also a source of rhea fibre. Among the Chinese much care is
                    bestowed on the cultivation of Chu or Tchou Ma, as rhea is called by them, and
                    they prepare the fibre by a tedious and costly process of selection and manual
                    labour. The plant thrives in hot, moist, shaded situations; propagated from
                    slips or root cuttings, it throws up from three to five crops of stems in the
                    course of a season, although not more than three crops are commonly reckoned on.
                    Each such crop may yield about 250 lb of marketable fibre per acre, that total
                    output being exceeded only by the jute crop. The stems when ripe are cut down,
                    stripped of leaves and branchlets, and, either split or whole, are freed from
                    their cortical layers till the bast layer is exposed. In this state they are
                    made up in small bundles and placed where they receive strong sunlight by day
                    and dews by night for several days, after which the fibrous bast layer is peeled
                    with ease off the woody core, and the separated fibres are thereafter treated
                    with boiling water to remove as far as possible adherent gummy and resinous
                    matter in which the fibres are embedded in the stalks. The fibre so obtained is
                    usually bleached by exposure on the grass, and it comes into the market as
                    brilliant white filaments with a fine silky gloss, having a strength, lustre,
                    and smoothness unequalled by any other vegetable fibre.</p>
                <p>The fibre first appeared in the European market in 1810, and a cord then spun
                    from it was found to sustain a weight of 252 lb, while a similar cord of Russian
                    hemp was estimated by Admiralty test not to bear more than 87 lb. A fibre
                    possessed of such strength and beauty immediately attracted great attention, and
                    throughout the early half of the century numerous efforts were made by the East
                    India Company to introduce it as a textile staple. But many difli<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n524/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0524-0507"/>culties have been encountered in its working,
                    some of which are not yet overcome. The fibre itself is very difficult of
                    extraction owing to the large amount of adhesive matter in which it is embedded,
                    and it is proportionately so expensive that it practically comes into
                    competition only with silk and wool. Further, rhea is hard and inelastic, and on
                    the machinery adapted for spinning other textiles it can only be spun into a
                    rough, harsh, and hairy yarn, while fabrics into which it is woven are rigid,
                    and show permanent creases at every fold. In the form of cordage, moreover, it
                    cuts and gives way at sharp knots and twists. Notwithstanding all
                    disappointments and drawbacks, the Indian Government considered the fibre of
                    such importance that in 1869 two prizes of £5000 and £2000 and again in 1877
                    prizes of £5000 and £1000 were offered for machinery or processes by which the
                    fibre could be prepared at such a cost per ton as would render its introduction
                    into the market practicable. Competitive trials were made at Saharanpur in 1872
                    and 1879, but no machine was found to satisfy the conditions of success,
                    although in 1872 a reward of £1500 wasgranted to Mr John Greig, jun., of
                    Edinburgh, and in 1879 £500 and £100 respectively were paid to two of the
                    competitors. The extraction of rhea continues to attract attention, and quite
                    recently (1885) it has been announced that Prof. Frémy of Paris, assisted by M.
                    Urbain, has successfully overcome all difficulties. The raw material used by
                    Prof. Frémy is obtained by a process devised by M. Fevier, which consists in
                    submitting the newly cut stems to low-pressure steam for twenty minutes, after
                    which the whole rind is separated in ribands from its woody core with the utmost
                    ease. These ribands are then dried, and on them Prof. Frémy operates with
                    alkaline solutions which are varied in strength according to the appearance of
                    the material dealt with, and a pure fibre in fine working condition is thus
                    obtained. Rhea has yet to establish its position among European textiles, but in
                    the East its value is well recognized. It is extensively used for cordage,
                    fishing nets, &amp;c.; and it is very little affected by water. The Chinese
                    prepare an exceedingly fine “grass cloth” from single filaments of rhea, knotted
                    or gummed end to end in the way they employ the finest filaments of Manila hemp
                    for making ‘ ‘ Pina” gauze.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
