<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0491-0474-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RESINS (9th edition, volume 20, page 474)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk2p">Resins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd1m">Copal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf67">Balsam</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35f3t">Rosin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw2z">Gums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04032">Alcohol</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878297">Copal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1019244">Mexicans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:949358">Gums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:826212">Balsams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804414">Alcoholics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804361">Alcoholates</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n491/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RESINS</label>. A resin is a secretion formed in special
                    resin canals or passages of plants, from many of which, such as, for example,
                    coniferous trees, it exudes in soft tears hardening into solid masses in the
                    air. Otherwise it may be obtained by making incisions in the bark or wood of the
                    secreting plant. Resin can also be extracted from almost all plants by treatment
                    of the tissue with alcohol, and it is formed by the oxidation of essential oils,
                    many authorities being of opinion that all true resins, which are in chemical
                    composition oxidized hydrocarbons, result primarily from the action of oxygen on
                    essential oils. Resinous substances are further produced by the dry distillation
                    of numerous organic compounds and by the drying of fatty drying oils. Certain
                    resins are obtained in a fossilized condition, amber being the most notable
                    instance of this class, and African copal and the kaurie gum of New Zealand are
                    also procured in a semi-fossil condition. The resins which are obtained as
                    natural exudations are in general compound bodies containing more than one
                    simple resin and varying proportions of essential oil. These compounds when soft
                    are known as oleo-resins, and when imperfectly fluid they are called balsams.
                    Other resinous products are in their natural condition mixed with gum or
                    mucilaginous substances and known as gum-resins. Varying in constitution as
                    these bodies do, they also difler widely in physical properties; but the general
                    conception of a resin is a noncrystalline body, insoluble in water, mostly
                    soluble in alcohol, essential oils, ether, and hot fatty oils, combining -with
                    alkalies to form resin soap, softening and melting under the influence of heat,
                    not capable of sublimation, and burning with a bright but smoky flame. A typical
                    resin is a transparent or translucent mass, with a vitreous fracture and a
                    faintly yellow or brown colour, inodorous or having only a slight turpentine
                    odour and taste. Many compound resins, however, from their admixture with
                    essential oils, are possessed of distinct and characteristic odours. A series of
                    gradations among resins may be traced from the hard glassy transparent copals
                    through soft elemis and oleo-resins, semi-fluid balsams and fluid wood oils, to
                    the most limpid essential oils. The hard transparent resins are principally used
                    for varnishes and cement, while the softer odoriferous oleo-resins and
                    gum-resins coutaining essential oils are more largely used for pharmaceutical
                    purposes and incense. No systematic classification of resins lias yet been
                    attempted, and there is much uncertainty as to the botanical source of some
                    well-known commercial varieties, while the chemical constitution and relations
                    of many still require elucidation. The following list embraces the principal
                    resins of commerce, and particulars regarding the more important of these will
                    be found under their respective headings. See also Rosin, Gum, and Balsam.</p>
                <p>I. Copalline or Varnish Resins :—African Copal or Gum Animé (see Copal, vol. vi.
                    p. 342); Mexican Copal, from Hymemcα sp.; Brazilian Copal, from Hyrnenxa sp. and
                    Trαchylοbium MarUanum; Piney Resin, or White Dammar, Valeria incUca and V.
                    αeuminαtα; Sal Dammar, Shorea robusta and other species; Dammar of Hopea
                    robusta; Black Dammar, from Canarium strictum; Mastic, Pistaeia Lentiseus (vol.
                    xv. p. 621); Lac (vol. xiv. p. 181); East Indian Dammar (see Dammar, vol. vi. p.
                    795); Kaurie or Coudie Resin, Dammam australis (see Turpentine); Sandarach, from
                    Callitris guαdrivalvis (see Sandarach); Dragon’s Blood (v∙ol. vii. p. 389).</p>
                <p>II. ∕S⅛∕7 or Oleο-Resins :—Manila Elemi, from Ciαjιαriwn commune (see Elemi, vol.
                    viii. p. 122); Mexican Elemi, Amyris elemi∙ fera·, Brazilian Elemi, Idea
                    Icieariba and other sp.; Tacamahac (American), Elaρhrium tomentosum; Tacamahac
                    (East Indian), Calophyllum lηophyllum; Wood Oil, Dipterocarpus turbinatus; Chian
                    Turpentine, Pistaeia Terebiηthus; Turpentine, Common Frankincense, and Thus from
                    various Coniferae (see Frankincense, Turpentine, and Rosin); Balsam of Canada,
                    Abies canadensis (see Balsam).</p>
                <p>III. Fragrant Oleo-Resins and Gum-Resins:—Myrrh, Balsamo-deηdroη Myrrha (vol.
                    xvii. p. 121); Bdellium or Googul, Balsamo-dendroη Roxburghii; Balsam of Gilead
                    or Mecca Balsam, Balsamo-dendron Berryi; Olibanum or Frankincense, Bosτoellia
                    Cartcri, &amp;c. (see Frankincense, vol. ix. p. 709); Benzoin, Styrax Benzoin
                    and Bαlsamodendron Mιιkul (vol. iii. p. 581); Solid Styrax, Styrax officinalis
                    (see Storax); Liquid Storax, Liquidambar orientalis (see Storax); Balsam of
                    Peru, Myrosperrnum perniferum (see Balsam); Balsam of Tolu, Myrosperrnum
                    toluiferum; Labdanum or Ladanum, Cistux cretieus, var. labdaηiferus.</p>
                <p>IV. Fetid Cum Resins :—Ammoniacum, Dorema ammoniacum (vol. i. p. 742);
                    Asafoetida, Ferula Karthxx and F. Scorodosma {vo↑. ii. p. 675); Galbanum, Ferula
                    galbanifiua and F. ruhrieaulis (vol. x. p. 22); Opoponax, Opoponax Chiroηium;
                    Sagapenum, Ferula sp.; Sarcocol.</p>
                <p>V. Medicinal Resins :—Gamboge, Garcinia sp. (vol. x. p. 60); Guaiacum, Gιιaiacum
                    officinale (vol. xi. p. 230); Euphorbium, Euphorbia resinifera; Balsam of
                    Copaiba, Copaifcra ofiicinalis (see Balsam).</p>
                <p>VI. Extract Resins form a class of products principally important from a
                    medicinal point of view. They embrace Scammony from Convolvulus Scammonia, Jalap
                    Resin from Ipornea Jalapa, Podophyllum Resin from Podophyllum peltatum, Churros
                    from Indian Hemp {Cannabis saliva'), Cubeb Resin from Cubeba officinal i&gt;;
                    and many other medicinal products owe their virtues to resinous bodies present
                    in them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
