<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0511-0494-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">REUTER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 494</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1029870">Murres</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v131">Pastors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n511/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REUTER</label> Fritz (1810-1874), the greatest writer in
                    Platt Deutsch, was born on the 7th November 1810, at Stavenhagen, in
                    Mecklenburg-Schwerin, a small country town which had few means of communication
                    with the rest of the λvorld. His father was burgomaster and sheriff
                    (Stadtrichter), and in addition to his official duties carried on the work of a
                    farmer. Until his fourteenth year Reuter was educated at home by private tutors.
                    He was then sent to the gymnasium at Friedland, in Mecklenburg-Strelitz, and
                    afterwards he passed through the higher classes of the gymnasium at Parchim. He
                    had a considerable talent for drawing, and wished to become an artist; but, as
                    his father decided that he should be a lawyer, he began in 1831 to attend
                    lectures on jurisprudence at the university of Rostock. In the following year he
                    went to the university of Jena. The German Governments, alarmed by the
                    revolutionary agitation of 1830, were on the alert to detect symptoms of popular
                    discontent; and a formidable riot at Frankfort in 1833 gave them an excuse for
                    treating the universities with great harshness. Reuter, as a member of the
                    Burschenschaft “Germania” at Jena, was arrested by the Prussian Government; and,
                    although the only charge which could be proved against him was that he had been
                    seen wearing the German colours, he was condemned to death for high treason.
                    This monstrous sentence was commuted by King Frederick William III. of Prussia
                    to imprisonment for thirty years in a Prussian fortress. Reuter accepted his
                    fate calmly, and he had need of all his courage, for during the next few years
                    he was taken from one Prussian fortress to another, in each of which he was kept
                    in close confinement. In 1838, through the personal intervention of the
                    grand-duke of Mecklenburg, he was delivered over to the authorities of his
                    native state, but on condition that he should still be a prisoner. The next two
                    years he spent in the fortress of Dömitz. In 1840 to his great joy he was set
                    free, an amnesty having been proclaimed after the accession of Frederick William
                    IV. to the Prussian throne.</p>
                <p>Although Reuter was now thirty years of age, he went to Heidelberg to resume his
                    legal studies; but he soon found it necessary to return to Stavenhagen, where he
                    aided in the management of his father’s farm. During his imprisonment he had
                    studied many works on agriculture and on the sciences related to it, and hö was
                    able to make good use of the knowledge he had thus obtained. After his father’s
                    death, however, he was compelled by want of capital to abandon farming, and in
                    1850 he settled as a private tutor at the little town of Treptow in Pomerania.
                    Here he married Luise Kunze, the daughter of a Mecklenburg pastor. They had been
                    betrothed when Reuter was at Stavenhagen, and their union proved to be one of
                    uninterrupted happiness.</p>
                <p>At Treptow he had to work hard as a private tutor for small pay, but in the
                    evenings he found time to amuse himself by writing, in Platt Deutsch, in prose
                    and verse, a number of tales and anecdotes. This collection of miscellanies was
                    published in 1853 in a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Lauschen und
                    Riemels.</hi> The book contains many lively sketches of manners in North
                    Germany, and it was received with so much favour that Reuter was encouraged to
                    make new ventures in literature. Fortunately he decided to go on writing in
                    Platt Deutsch. There are so many abstract terms in High German that few writers
                    succeed in the attempt to use it as a vehicle for the powerful utterance of
                    simple and natural feeling. Platt Deutsch, on the contrary, although limited in
                    its range, is fresh and vigorous, and in direct contact with the motives which
                    give unfading charm to old popular songs and ballads. All the resources of this
                    strong and expressive dialect were at Reuter’s service. He thought in Platt
                    Deutsch, and in his greatest efforts was always able to find the right word for
                    that exquisite blending of humour and pathos which is one of the most
                    characteristic notes of his writings.</p>
                <p>The work which succeeded <hi rend="italic">Lauschen und Riemels</hi> was <hi
                    rend="italic">Polterabendgedichte,</hi> and in the same year (1855) appeared <hi
                    rend="italic">De Reis nach Belligen,</hi> a humorous poem describing the
                    adventures of some Mecklenburg peasants who resolve to go to Belgium (which they
                    never reach) to learn the secrets of an advanced civilization. These writings
                    attracted much attention, and Reuter was so confident of success that in 1856 he
                    left Treptow and established himself at Neubrandenburg, resolving to devote his
                    whole time to literary work. His next book (published in 1858) was 7fe⅛ <hi
                    rend="italic">Hilsung,</hi> a poem in which he presents with great force and
                    vividness some of the least attractive aspects of village life in Mecklenburg.
                    This was followed, in 1859, by <hi rend="italic">Hanne Eilte un de lutte
                    Pudel,</hi> the best of the works written by Reuter in verse. The qualities of
                    those who have a part to play in the story are brought out with remarkable
                    distinctness, and the action provides the poet with many opportunities of giving
                    free expression to his ardent love of nature.</p>
                <p>In 1861 Reuter’s popularity was largely increased by <hi rend="italic"
                    >Schurr-Murr,</hi> a collection of tales, some of which are in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n512/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0512-0495"/>High German, but this work is of slight importance
                    in comparison with the series of stories which he had already begun, and by
                    which he was to establish his fame as one of the foremost writers of his age. To
                    this series he gave the general title <hi rend="italic">Olle Kamellen.</hi> The
                    first volume, <hi rend="italic">Zwei Lustige Geschichte,</hi> published in 1860,
                    contained <hi rend="italic">Woans ik tau ’ ηe Fru kamm</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Ut de Franzosentid. Ut mine Festungstid</hi> (1861) formed the
                    second volume; <hi rend="italic">Ut Mine Stromtid</hi> (1864) the third, fourth,
                    and fifth volumes; and <hi rend="italic">D'orchlauchting</hi> (1866) the sixth
                    volume. <hi rend="italic">Woans ik tau ’ ne Fru kamm</hi> is a bright little
                    tale, in which Reuter tells, in a half serious half bantering tone, how he wooed
                    the lady who became his wife. In <hi rend="italic">Ut de Franzosentid</hi> he
                    undertook a more difficult task, which enabled him for the first time to do full
                    justice to his genius. The scene is laid in and near Stavenhagen (Platt Deutsch,
                    Stemhagen) in the year 1813, and the principal complications spring from the
                    disappearance of a Frenchman, which gives rise to suspicions of foul play. In
                    this powerful tale the characters are depicted by means of a few bold and rapid
                    strokes, and our interest in them is heightened by the fact that their personal
                    fortunes are associated with the great events which at the beginning of the 19th
                    century stirred the heart of Germany to its depths. <hi rend="italic">Ut mine
                    Festungstid</hi> is of less general interest than <hi rend="italic">Ut de
                    Franzosentid,</hi> but it is not less vigorous either in conception or in style.
                    It contains a narrative of Reuter’s hardships during the term of his
                    imprisonment, and it awakens sympathy all the more effectually because it is
                    brightened by many a gleam of kindly and humorous feeling. <hi rend="italic">Ut
                    mine Stromtid</hi> is by far the greatest of Reuter’s writings, and ranks with
                    the most famous masterpieces of modern fiction. He records few incidents which
                    might not happen in the lives of ordinary men and women, yet he never loses his
                    hold over the imagination of his readers, so full of vitality are the characters
                    of his story, and so deep is his insight into the enduring facts of human
                    nature. The most original character in the book is Bräsig, an eccentric old
                    bachelor, fond of gossip and apt to interfere too much in the affairs of his
                    neighbours, but humorous, loyal to the core, and coming out most brightly when
                    his good qualities are put to the severest test. There is a touch of romance,
                    too, in this simple and genial nature, for he retains to the last his love for
                    the woman who had fascinated him in his youth, and is always at hand to serve
                    her when she needs his help. Another powerfully conceived character is
                    Havermann, a man of solid and serious judgment, calm and undemonstrative, of
                    sterling rectitude, and revealing at the great crises of life infinite depths of
                    love and pity. Equally attractive in their own way are the good pastor and his
                    wife, who bring up Havermann’s daughter, Louise, in their quiet parsonage; and
                    we come to know intimately every member of the pleasant household in which
                    Havermann’s frank and comely sister (whom Bräsig secretly loves) is the central
                    figure. In this great book Reuter displays imaginative power of the highest
                    order in the expression of every mood and passion within the proper range of his
                    art; and he fails, or at least does not perfectly succeed, only when he deals
                    with characters belonging to classes he had never had an opportunity of studying
                    closely. As in <hi rend="italic">Ut de Franzosentid</hi> he describes the deep
                    national impulse in obedience to which Germany rose against Napoleon, so in <hi
                    rend="italic">Ut mine Stromtid</hi> he presents many aspects of the
                    revolutionary movement of 1848. He shows little sympathy with some of the most
                    characteristic aspirations of the period, but in many passages he indicates by
                    slight but significant touches the strength of the forces which had begun to
                    make for social as distinguished from merely political reorganization.</p>
                <p>In 1863 Reuter transferred his residence from Neubrandenburg to Eisenach; and
                    here he died on the 12th June 1874. In the works produced at Eisenach he did not
                    maintain the high level of his earlier writings. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Horchlauchting,</hi> although it contains some striking passages, lacks the
                    freshness and spontaneity of the other tales of the series to which it belongs;
                    and admirers of his genius found little to interest them in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die Μontechi unfit Capuleti in Konstantinopel,</hi> which he wrote after a
                    visit to the Turkish capital.</p>
                <p>Reuter is the most realistic of the great German writers. To the dreamers of the
                    romantic school he has not the faintest resemblance, nor does he ever attempt to
                    describe ideally perfect characters. The men and women of his stories are the
                    men and women he knew in the villages and farmhouses of Mecklenburg, and the
                    circumstances in which he places them are the circumstances by which they were
                    surrounded in actual life. His fidelity to facts is as exact as that of the
                    Dutch school of painters, and, like them, he thinks nothing too minute for his
                    use, if by small details he can give variety and animation to his pictures. But
                    he does not merely glide over the surface of life; he penetrates to the inmost
                    springs of feeling, and in simple peasant folk finds characteristics which in
                    his hands become types of universal qualities. The sources of tears and the
                    sources of laughter he touches with equal ease; but, while his humour is
                    sometimes rather extravagant, his pathetic passages are always marked by perfect
                    truth and delicacy. His description of the death of the old pastor in <hi
                    rend="italic">Ut mine Stromtid</hi> is one of the gems of modern literature, and
                    the scene in which Bräsig dies, holding the hand of the woman he has loved all
                    his life, is in a different way not less impressive. Reuter’s only serious
                    defect as an artist is that he fails to maintain the due proportion between the
                    different parts of his stories. If an idea attracts him, he cannot resist the
                    temptation to unfold its full significance, whether or not it is in organic
                    relation with his scheme as a whole. To some extent, however, the reader is
                    compensated for these interruptions by happy strokes of humour which would have
                    been rendered impossible had Reuter forced himself to adopt a more rigid
                    method.</p>
                <p>Reuter’s <hi rend="italic">Särnrntliche Werke</hi> in thirteen volumes (edited by
                    Ad. w∏dbrandt) were published in 18C3-68. To these were added in 1875 two
                    volumes of <hi rend="italic">Nachgelassene Schriften,</hi> with a biography; and
                    in 1878 a comedy, <hi rend="italic">Die drei Langhänse.</hi> See Glagau, <hi
                    rend="italic">Fritz Reuter und Seine Dichtungen,</hi> 1866; Ebert, <hi
                    rend="italic">Fritz Reuter,</hi> 1874; and Zeil, “Fritz Reuter,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Unsere Zeit,</hi> 1875. (J. SI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
