<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0308-0291-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RATISBON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 291</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1025892">Monuments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n308/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RATISBON</label> (German <hi rend="italic">Regensburg</hi> ),
                    an ancient city of Bavaria, the seat of a bishop, and the capital of the Upper
                    Palatinate, is pleasantly situated on the right bank of the Danube, opposite the
                    influx of the Regen, from which it derives its German name. It lies almost
                    exactly in the centre of the kingdom, about 65 miles to the north-east of Munich
                    and 53 miles to the south-east of Nuremberg. On the other side of the river is
                    the small town of Stadt-am-Hof, connected with Ratisbon by a long stone bridge
                    of the 12th century, above and below which are the islands of the Obere and
                    Untere Worth. In external appearance Ratisbon is quaint and romantic, presenting
                    almost as faithful a picture of a town of the early Middle Ages as Nuremberg
                    does of the later. Most of the streets are narrow and irregular, but spacious
                    promenades have been laid out on the site of the old fortifications. One. of the
                    most characteristic features in its architecture is the number of strong
                    loopholed towers attached to the more ancient dwellings, recalling a day when
                    civic broils were of frequent recurrence. The interesting “street of the
                    ambassadors” is so called because it contained the residences of most of the
                    ambassadors to the German diet, whose coats-of-arms may still be seen on many of
                    the houses.</p>
                <p>The cathedral of Ratisbon, though small in size, is a very interesting example of
                    pure German Gothic, diverging in several points from the type elaborated in
                    France. It was founded in 1275 and completed in 1634, with the exception of the
                    towers, which were added during a recent restoration. The details are very
                    harmonious and pleasing, and the interior contains numerous interesting
                    monuments, including one of Peter Yischer’s masterpieces. Adjoining the
                    cloisters are two chapels of earlier date than the cathedral itself, one of
                    which, known as the “old cathedral,” goes back perhaps to the 8th century. The
                    Schotten-kirche, a plain Romanesque basilica of the 12th century, derives its
                    name from the monastery of Irish Benedictines (“Scoti”) to which it was
                    attached; the principal doorway is covered with very singular grotesque
                    carvings, the meaning of which remains a mystery. The old parish church of St
                    Ulrich is a good example of the Transition style of the 13th century. Other
                    specimens of the Romanesque basilica style are the church of Obermiinster,
                    dating from 1010, and the abbey church of St Emmeran, built in the 13th century
                    and remarkable as one of the few German churches with a detached belfry. The
                    beautiful cloisters of the ancient abbey, one of the oldest in Germany, are
                    still in fair preservation. In 1809 the conventual buildings were converted into
                    a palace for the prince of Thurn and Taxis, hereditary postmaster-general of the
                    old German empire. The town-house, a somewhat gloomy pile, dating in part from
                    the 14th century, contains the rooms occupied by the imperial diet of Germany
                    from 1663 to 1806. An historical interest also attaches to the Golden Cross Inn,
                    where Charles Y. made the acquaintance of the fair Barbara Blumberger, the
                    mother of Don John of Austria (b. 1547). The promenade is adorned with a bust of
                    Kepler, who died at Ratisbon in 1630. Perhaps the most pleasing modern building
                    in the city is the Gothic villa of the king of Bavaria on the bank of the
                    Danube. Among the chief manufactures of Ratisbon are iron and steel wares,
                    pottery, parquet flooring, and lead pencils. Boat-building is also prosecuted,
                    and a brisk transit trade is carried on in salt, grain, and timber. In 1880 the
                    town contained 34,516 inhabitants, of whom 27,844 were Roman Catholics, 5995
                    Protestants, and 675 Jews. Stadt-am-Hof, which practically forms a suburb of
                    Ratisbon, contained 3392 inhabitants.</p>
                <p>Near Ratisbon are two very handsome classical buildings erected by Louis I. of
                    Bavaria, with the aid of the architect Klenze, as national monuments of German
                    patriotism and greatness. The more imposing of the two is the Walhalla, a costly
                    reproduction of the Parthenon, erected as a Teutonic temple of fame on a hill
                    rising from the Danube at Donaustauf, 6 miles to the east. The massive
                    substructions of the temple somewhat dwarf the building itself when seen from a
                    distance, and the choice of a classic model for a German Pantheon seems somewhat
                    incongruous, but after these deductions are made it still remains a magnificent
                    and imposing structure. The interior, which is as rich as coloured marbles,
                    gilding, and sculptures can make it, contains the busts of more than a hundred
                    German worthies. The second of King Louis’s buildings is the Befreiungshalle at
                    Kelheim, 14 miles above Ratisbon, a large circular building, which has for its
                    aim the glorification of the heroes of the war of liberation in 1813.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n309/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0309-0292"/>
                <p>The early Celtic settlement of <hi rend="italic">Radcspona</hi> was chosen by the
                    Romans, who named it <hi rend="italic">Castra Regina,</hi> as the centre of
                    their power on the upper Danube, and it soon attained considerable importance.
                    It afterwards became the seat of the dukes of Bavaria and one of the main
                    bulwarks of the East Frankish monarchy; and it was also the focus from which
                    Christianity spread over southern Germany. St Emmeran .founded an abbey here in
                    the middle of the 7th century, and St Boniface established the bishopric about a
                    hundred years later. Ratisbon acquired the freedom of the empire in the 13tli
                    century and was for a time the most flourishing city in southern Germany. It
                    became the chief seat of the trade with India and the Levant, and the boatmen of
                    Ratisbon are frequently heard of as expediting the journeys of the crusaders.
                    The city was loyally Ghibelline in its sympathies and was a favourite residence
                    of the German emperors. .Numerous diets were held here from time to time, and
                    after 1663 it became the regular place of meeting of the German diet. The
                    Reformation found only temporary acceptance at Ratisbon and was met by a
                    counter-reformation inspired by the Jesuits. Before this period the city had
                    almost wholly lost its commercial importance, owing to the changes in the great
                    highways of trade. Ratisbon had its due share in the Thirty Years’ and other
                    wars, and is said to have suffered in all no fewer than seventeen sieges. In
                    1807 the town and bishopric were assigned to the prince primate Dalberg and in
                    1810 they were ceded to Bavaria. After the battle of Eggmiihl (1809) the
                    Austrians retired upon Ratisbon, and the pursuing French defeated them again
                    beneath its walls and reduced great part of the city to ashes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
