<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0283-0266-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAMSAY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 266</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25g11">Dialects</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w849">Dialectics</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4251ft9s">Tea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:892462">Dialectic</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1734394">Peasants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n283/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAMSAY</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Allan</hi> (1686-1758),
                    author of the <hi rend="italic">Gentle Shepherd,</hi> a pastoral drama in the
                    Lowland Scotch dialect, was born in Lanarkshire in 1686. An Edinburgh barber set
                    agoing the literary movement in Scotland that culminated in the poetry of Burns.
                    This peasant-poetry is often spoken of as if it were a spontaneous indigenous
                    product, but the harvest that ripened towards the close of the 18th century had
                    its seed-time earlier, and the seeds were imported from England. Allan Ramsay
                    was a peasant by birth (although he claimed kinship with the noble family of
                    Dalhousie)—the son of a manager of lead-mines in Lanarkshire; but the
                    country-bred lad was transplanted to a town, being apprenticed at the age of
                    fifteen to a barber in Edinburgh. In this calling he somehow made the
                    acquaintance of a band of Jacobite young gentlemen of literary tastes, was
                    admitted to the convivialities of their “Easy Club,” and formally adjudged “a
                    gentleman.” The basis of the club seems to have been literary, the members
                    taking fancy names of celebrities,—Buchanan, Boece, Bickerstaff, and so forth.
                    Ramsay’s name was Bickerstaff, and the fact is of some importance as showing how
                    he was brought into contact with the discussion of the theory of pastoral poetry
                    among the London wits of the time. Ramsay’s connexion with the Easy Club lay
                    between 1712 and 1715, and in the course of that period occurred the dispute
                    about pastoral poetry occasioned by the great publication of Pope’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Windsor Forest</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope).</hi> The <hi
                    rend="italic">Guardian</hi> for 7tli April 1713 (No. 23) contained a description
                    of a true pastoral poem, which was afterwards realized by Ramsay in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Gentle Shepherd</hi> with such scrupulous fidelity in every detail
                    that the criticism might fairly be described as the recipe from which the poem
                    was made. There is not a clearer case in literary history of the influence of
                    criticism on creation; Ramsay’s great pastoral— and it well deserves the
                    epithet—was the main outcome of the prolonged discussion of that kind of poetry
                    by the Queen Anne wits. “Paint the manners of actual rustic life,” said the <hi
                    rend="italic">Guardian</hi> critic to the poet, “not the manners of artificial
                    shepherds and shepherdesses in a fictitious golden age; use actual rustic
                    dialect; instead of satyrs and fauns and nymphs introduce the supernatural
                    creatures of modern superstition.” These precepts Ramsay diligently observed,
                    and the result was that his <hi rend="italic">Gentle Shepherd</hi> not only
                    attracted attention among the learned students of poetry as a literary
                    curiosity, the first genuine pastoral after Theocritus, but at once became a
                    favourite and a living force among the peasantry in whose dialect it was written
                    and for wdiose characters it furnished ideal models. There was hardly a
                    farmhouse in Scotland in which a copy of the poem was not to be found, and the
                    moral force of the ideal exhibited in the hero Patie may be traced in the
                    character of Burns and many another Scottish peasant-bard in whom ostentatious
                    libertinism is not redeemed by the same genius. From a moral point of view a
                    better exemplar than Ramsay’s ideal hero might well have been desired. The
                    poct-laureate of the Easy Club took his moral tone from the poets of the
                    Restoration, with whom his Jacobite boon companions were in full sympathy; and
                    thus through the genial, convivial, quick-witted, and slily humorous barber the
                    spirit of the Restoration passed into the homes of the Scotch peasantry to do
                    battle with the austere spirit of the kirk.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n284/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0284-0267"/>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Gentle Shepherd</hi> is the only production of Ramsay’s
                    that has much claim to remembrance. His lyrics for the most part are poor
                    artificial imitations, adorned here and there with pretty fancies, but devoid of
                    sincerity of feeling. He is happier in his humorous descriptions of character
                    and occasional personal poems; “renowned Allan, canty callan,” as his admirers
                    loved to call him, had a quick sense of the ridiculous and a firm touch in the
                    exhibition of what amused him. Once he had established a character as a poet he
                    abandoned the trade of wig-making, set up as a bookseller, and was the first to
                    start a circulating library in Scotland. From his shop in High Street opposite
                    Niddry Street he issued his incidental poems in broadsheets, and made a volume
                    of them in 1721, and another in 1728. The nucleus of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gentle Shepherd</hi> was laid in separately issued pastoral dialogues; round
                    these the complete drama was built and published as a whole in 1725. As a
                    collector, editor, imitator, and publisher of old Scottish poetry Ramsay gave an
                    impetus to vernacular literature at least as great as that given by his
                    principal original poem. His <hi rend="italic">Tea-Table Miscellany</hi> ,
                    published in 1724, for which English as well a3 Scottish poets and moderns as
                    well as ancients were laid under contribution, was extremely popular; and his
                    <hi rend="italic">Evergreen</hi> (1724), a collection of poems written prior to
                    1G00, was the precursor of Bishop Percy’s <hi rend="italic">Reliques</hi> in a
                    similar field. A collection of <hi rend="italic">Fables,</hi> published complete
                    in 1730, part original, part translated from La Motte and La Fontaine, was
                    Ramsay’s last literary work, but he lived to an advanced age, dying in 1758, the
                    year before the birth of Burns. One of the speculations of the enlightened and
                    enterprising man of business was a theatre, which was opened in 1736, but soon
                    shut up by the magistrates.</p>
                <p>A complete edition of Ramsay’s poems was issued by A. Gardner in 1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
