<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0278-0261-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RÁJSHÁHÍ or Rajeshaye (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    261)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970275">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829528">Beds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k440">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n278/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RÁJSHÁHÍ or <hi rend="smallcaps">Rajeshaye</hi></label>, a
                    district of India, in the lieutenant-governorship of Bengal, forming the
                    southwestern corner of the Rfijshfihf with Kuch Behar division. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Rajshahi with Kuch
                            Behar division comprises the seven districts of Dinajpur, Rajshahi,
                            Rangpur, Bogra, Pabna, Darjiling, Jal-paiguri, and the native state of
                            Kuch Behar. Its total area is 18,735 square miles, and its population
                            (1881) 8,336,399 (males 4,237,388, females 4,099,011). </p></note> It
                    lies between 24° 3' and 24° 59' N. lat. and between 88° 21' and 89° 24' E.
                    long., and is bounded on the N. by the districts of Din&amp;jpur and Bogra, on
                    the E. by Bogra and Pabna, on the S. by the Ganges and Nuddea district, and on
                    the W. by Maldah and Murshidabiid. The area of 2359 square miles is one alluvial
                    plain seamed with old river-beds and studded with marshes. The Ganges and the
                    Mah&amp;nandfi are its principal rivers; the former constitutes a great natural
                    boundary-line to the south and south-west, and the latter, which rises in the
                    Himalayas, borders the district on the w <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> est for a
                    few miles before joining the Ganges. Other rivers are the Narad and Baral,
                    important offshoots of the Ganges; the Atrai, a channel of the Tista; and the
                    Jamuna, a tributary of the Atrai. Both the Atrai and the Jamuna belong to the
                    Brahmaputra system and are navigable throughout the year for small cargo boats.
                    The drainage of Rdjshahi is not carried off by means of its rivers, but through
                    the chains of marshes and swamps, the most important of which is the Chalan <hi
                        rend="italic">“</hi> bil <hi rend="italic">”</hi> or lake, which discharges
                    itself into the Brahmaputra. The climate of Raj shdhf does not differ from that
                    of other districts of Lower Bengal; its average rainfall for the five years
                    ending 1882/83 equalled 68 inches. The Northern Bengal State Railway intersects
                    the district from north to south.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population</hi> .—The census of 1881 gave a population, almost
                    entirely rural, of 1,338,638 (males 660,226, females 678,412). Of this number
                    288,749 were returned as Hindus, 1,049,700 as Mohammedans, and only 121 as
                    Christians. The only town with over 10,000 inhabitants was Rampur Beauleah
                    (19,228), which is the chief town and administrative headquarters of the
                    district. This town is situated on the north bank of the Ganges in 24° 22' N.
                    lat. and 88° 39' E. long.; it is of modern growth and is built for the most part
                    on river alluvia. It was formerly the seat of the Dutch and East India Company’s
                    factories, and is still a centre of the silk and indigo trade.</p>
                <p>Rice is the staple crop of the district; other cereal crops are wheat, barley,
                    and Indian corn, which are grown to a small extent; among miscellaneous crops
                    are indigo, sugar-cane, mulberry, and tobacco. Ganja is also grown in a small
                    tract to the north of the district. Silk spinning and weaving and the
                    preparation of indigo are the chief manufactures, but these are now both
                    declining. The total revenue of Rajshahi in 1883-84 amounted to £123,098,
                    towards which the land-tax contributed £88,584.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History</hi> .—When the East India Company took over the
                    administration of Bengal in 1765 Rajshahi was one of the largest and most
                    important districts in the province. It appears to have extended from Bhagulpur
                    on the west to Dacca on the east, and to have included an important subdivision
                    called Nij-Chakla Rajshahi on the south of the Ganges, which extended over a
                    great portion of what now lies within the districts of Murshidabad, Nuddea,
                    Jessore, Birbhum, and Burdwan. The total area was estimated at 12,909 square
                    miles, or more than five times the size of the present district. Having been
                    found much too large to be effectually administered by one central authority,
                    Rajshahi was stripped by Government in 1793 of a considerable portion of its
                    outlying territory, and a natural boundary-line was drawn to the west, south,
                    and east along the Ganges and Brahmaputra. Its north-western limits were reduced
                    in 1813, when the present district of Maldah was constituted. The erection of
                    Bogra into a separate jurisdiction in 1821 still further reduced its area; and
                    in 1832 the limits of Rajshahi were finally fixed very much at their present
                    lines by the constitution of Pabna into an independent jurisdiction.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
