<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0506-0489-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">REUCHLIN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 489</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4td9n76g">Loans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n506/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REUCHLIN</label> John (1455-1522), the first great German
                    humanist and the restorer of Hebrew and in large measure also of Greek letters
                    among his countrymen, was born February 22, 1455, at Pforzheim in the Black
                    Forest, where his father was intendant of the Dominican monastery. In the
                    pedantic taste of his time the name was Graecized by his Italian friends into
                    Capnion, a form which Reuchlin himself uses as a sort of transparent mask when
                    he introduces himself as an interlocutor in the <hi rend="italic">De Verbo
                    Mimfico.</hi> For his native place Reuchlin always retained an affection; he
                    constantly writes himself Phorcensis, and in the <hi rend="italic">De
                    Verbo,</hi> when he tells how he had sojourned at Paris and almost all the great
                    schools of France and Germany, as well as at several Italian seats of learning
                    and finally at Rome, the “caput studiorum,” he does not forget to ascribe to
                    Pforzheim his first disposition to letters. Here he began his Latin studies in
                    the monastery school, and, though in 1470 he was a short time in Freiburg, that
                    university seems to have taught him little. Reuchlin⅛ career as a scholar
                    appears to have turned almost on an accident; his fine voice gained him a place
                    in the household of the margrave of Baden, and by and by, having already some
                    reputation as a Latinist, he was chosen to accompany to the university of Paris
                    the third son of the prince, a lad some years his junior, who was destined for
                    an ecclesiastical career. This new connexion lasted but a year or so, but it
                    determined the course of Reuchlin’s life. He now began to learn Greek, which had
                    been taught in the French capital since 1470, and he also attached himself to
                    the leader of the Paris realists, John à Lapide, a really worthy and learned
                    man, whom he presently followed to the vigorous young university of Basel
                    (1474). At Basel Reuchlin took his master’s degree (1477), and began to lecture
                    with success, teaching a more classical Latin than was then common in German
                    schools, and also explaining Aristotle in Greek. His studies in this language
                    had been continued at Basel under Andronicus Contoblacas, and here too he formed
                    the acquaintance of the bookseller Amorbach, for whom he prepared a Latin
                    lexicon ( <hi rend="italic">Vocabulamus Breviloquus,</hi> 1st ed. 1475-76),
                    which did good service in its time and ran through many editions. This first
                    publication and Reuchlin’s account of his teaching at Basel in a letter to
                    Cardinal Hadrian, February 1518, show that he had already found the work which
                    in a larger sphere occupied his whole life. He was no original genius, but a
                    born teacher. He had neither brilliant literary power like Erasmus nor
                    epoch-making ideas like Luther, but he was the great master of all Germany,
                    guiding his countrymen to sound learning, first in Latin and then in Greek and
                    in Hebrew. But this work of teaching was not to be done mainly from the
                    professor’s chair. Reuchlin soon left Basel to seek further Greek training with
                    George Hieronymus at Paris, and learn to write a fair Greek hand that he might
                    support himself by copying MSS. And now he felt that he must choose a
                    profession. His choice fell on law, and he was thus led to the great school of
                    Orleans (1478), and finally to Poitiers, where he became licentiate in July
                    1481, and so could look forward to honourable office in his native country,
                    where he could pursue his scholarly tastes in an independent position. From
                    Poitiers Reuchlin came in December 1481 to Tübingen. There he found friends to
                    recommend him to Count Eberhard of Würtemberg, who was about to journey to Italy
                    and required an interpreter. Reuchlin was selected, and in February 1482 left
                    Stuttgart for Florence and Rome. The journey lasted but a few months, but it
                    brought the German scholar into contact with several learned Italians, and his
                    connexion with the count became permanent. On his return to Stuttgart he was
                    named Geheimrath, and soon after he became doctor of laws and assessor in the
                    high court. About this time he appears to have married, but little is known of
                    his married life. He left no children; butin later years his sister’s grandson
                    Melanchthon was almost as a son to him till the Reformation estranged them.
                    Reuchlin’s life at Stuttgart was often broken by important missions, and in 1490
                    he was again in Italy. Here he saw Pico, to whose Cabbalistic doctrines he
                    afterwards became heir, and also made the friendship of the pope’s privy
                    secretary, Questemberg, which was of service to him in his later troubles. Again
                    in 1492 he was employed on an embassy to the emperor at Linz, and here he began
                    to read Hebrew with the kaiser’s Jewish physician Loans. He knew something of
                    this language before, but Loans’s instruction laid the basis of that thorough
                    knowledge which he afterwards improved on his third visit to Rome in 1498 by the
                    instruction of Obadiah Sforno of Cesena.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n507/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0507-0490"/>
                <p>In 1496 Count Eberhard died, and enemies of Reuchlin had the ear of the new
                    prince. He was glad therefore hastily to follow the invitation of John of
                    Dalburg the scholarly bishop of Worms, and flee to Heidelberg, which was then
                    the seat of the “Rhenish Society,” a lively and active circle of humanists under
                    Dalburg’s presidency, equally zealous in the service of Apollo and Bacchus. In
                    this court of letters Reuchlin’s appointed function was to make translations
                    from the Greek authors, in which his reading was already extremely wide. Many of
                    these versions were never printed, but a considerable number of pieces were
                    given to the press at intervals down to the year 1519, and formed an important
                    element in his efforts to spread a knowledge of Greek. For, though Reuchlin had
                    no public office as teacher, and even at Heidelberg was prevented from lecturing
                    openly, he was during a great part of his life the real centre of all Greek
                    teaching as well as of all Hebrew teaching in Germany. No young man of promise
                    who came to him for help was rejected; he taught many and found teachers for
                    others, or gave direction and solution of difficulties to more advanced
                    scholars. Thus he was a sort of unofficial general director of the studies of
                    Germany, and to carry out this work he found it necessary to provide a series of
                    helps for beginners and others. He never published a Greek grammar, though he
                    had one in MS. for use with his pupils, but he put out several little elementary
                    Greek books; and these with the series of translations were in fact the text
                    books of the German youth. Reuchlin, it may be noted, pronounced Greek as his
                    native teachers had taught him to do, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> in the modern
                    Greek fashion. This pronunciation, which he defends in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dia-logus de Recta Lat. Graecique Serm. Pron.,</hi> 1519, came to be known, in
                    contrast to that used by Erasmus, as the Reuchlinian.</p>
                <p>At Heidelberg Reuchlin had many private pupils, among whom Franz von Sickingen is
                    the best known name; and all his relations, except with the monks who stopped
                    his attempt to lecture on Hebrew, were very pleasant. With the monks he had
                    never been well; at Stuttgart also his great enemy was the Augustinian
                    Holzinger. On this man he took a scholar’s revenge in his first Latin comedy <hi
                    rend="italic">Sergius,</hi> a satire on -worthless monks and false relics which
                    his young Heidelberg friends were eager to act. But, Dalburg thinking this
                    unsafe, he wrote for them a new piece, <hi rend="italic">Scenica
                    Progymnasmata</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Henno,</hi> based on the old French play
                    of <hi rend="italic">Maître Pathelin,</hi> which is not without humour and
                    sparkle of language, and much better constructed than the French piece.</p>
                <p>Through Dalburg, Reuchlin came into contact with Philip of the Pfalz, who
                    employed him to direct his son’s studies, and in 1498 gave him the mission to
                    Rome which has been already noticed as fruitful for Reuchlin’s progress in
                    Hebrew. He came back laden with Hebrew books, and found when he reached
                    Heidelberg that a change of Government had opened the way for his return to
                    Stuttgart. His wife had remained there all along; so that we may assume that he
                    never looked on his exile as more than temporary. His friends were the party of
                    order and good government, who could not long remain powerless. They had now
                    again the upper hand, and knew Reuchlin’s value. In 1500, or perhaps in 1502, he
                    was named “triumvir of Swabia,” a very high judicial office in the Swabian
                    League, which he held till 1512, when he retired to a small estate near
                    Stuttgart. By this time the long conflict which gives Reuchlin’s life its chief
                    interest had already begun.</p>
                <p>For many years Reuchlin had been increasingly absorbed in Hebrew studies, which
                    had for him more than a mere philological interest. Though he was always a good
                    Catholic, and even took the habit of an Augustinian monk when he felt that his
                    death was near, he was too thorough a humanist to be a blind Catholic. He knew
                    the abuses of monkish religion, and was interested in the reform of preaching
                    <hi rend="italic">(De Arte Predicandi,</hi> 1503—a book which became a sort of
                    preacher’s manual); but above all as a scholar he was eager that the Bible
                    should be better known, and could not tie himself to the authority of the
                    Vulgate. To him the Old Testament Scriptures meant the Hebrew text, and this he
                    was determined to study with an independent love for truth: “I honour St Jerome
                    as an angel; I value Lira as a master; but I worship truth as my God.” The key
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Hebraea veritas</hi> was the grammatical and exegetical
                    tradition of the mediaeval rabbins, especially of Kiιnhi, and when he had
                    mastered this himself he was resolved to open it to others. In 1506 appeared his
                    <hi rend="italic">Rudimenta Hebraica—</hi> grammar and lexicon—mainly after
                    Kimhi, yet not a mere copy of one man’s teaching. The edition was costly and
                    sold slowly. In 1510 he was glad to offer Amorbach seven hundred and fifty
                    copies at the reduced price of a florin for three copies. Even then Amorbach
                    could hardly find purchasers, but Reuchlin bade him be patient, “for if I live
                    Hebrew must with God’s help come to the front.” One great difficulty was that
                    the wars of Maximilian in Italy prevented Hebrew Bibles coming into Germany. But
                    for this also Reuchlin found help by printing the Penitential Psalms with
                    grammatical explanations (1512), and other helps followed from time to time. But
                    Reuchlin had yet another interest in Hebrew letters. His Greek studies had
                    interested him in philosophy, and not least in those fantastical and mystical
                    systems of later times with which the Cabbala has no small affinity. Following
                    Pico, he seemed to find in the Cabbala a profound theosophy which might be of
                    the greatest service for the defence of Christianity and the reconciliation of
                    science with the mysteries of faith—an unhappy delusion indeed, but one not
                    surprising in that strange time of ferment, when the old and the new
                    intellectual life had not yet clearly discriminated themselves, and when men of
                    progress sought less to free themselves from mere tradition than to find an
                    ancient tradition of truth which had been lost in the darkness of mediaeval
                    ignorance. Reuchlin’s mystico-cabbalistic ideas and objects were expounded in
                    the <hi rend="italic">De Verbo Mirifico,</hi> 1494, and finally in the <hi
                    rend="italic">De Arte Cabba-listica,</hi> 1517. We see therefore that not only
                    the philological tradition but the most esoteric wisdom of the rabbins was in
                    his eyes of the greatest value.</p>
                <p>Unhappily many of his contemporaries held other views, and thought that the first
                    step to the conversion of the Jews was to conquer their obstinacy by taking from
                    them their books. This view had for its chief advocate the bigoted John
                    Pfefferkorn, himself a baptized Hebrew. Pfefferkorn’s plans were backed by the
                    Dominicans of Cologne; and in 1509 he got from the emperor authority to
                    confiscate all Jewish books directed against the Christian faith. Armed with
                    this mandate, he visited Stuttgart and asked Reuchlin’s help as a jurist and
                    expert in putting it into execution. Reuchlin evaded this demand, mainly because
                    the mandate lacked certain formalities, but he could not long remain neutral.
                    The execution of Γfeffer-korn’s schemes led to difficulties and to a new appeal
                    to Maximilian. It was resolved to call in the opinion of experts, and in 1510
                    Reuchlin was summoned in the name of the emperor to give his formal opinion on
                    the suppression of the Jewish books. His answer is dated from Stuttgart,
                    November 6, 1510; in it he divides the books into six classes—apart from the
                    Bible which no one proposed to destroy—and, going through each class, he shows
                    that the books openly insulting to Christianity are very <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n508/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0508-0491"/>few and viewed as worthless by most Jews
                    themselves, while the others are either works necessary to the Jewish worship,
                    which was licensed by papal as well as imperial law, or contain matter of value
                    and scholarly interest which ought not to be sacrificed because they are
                    connected with another faith than that of the Christians. Instead of destroying
                    a whole literature, which was what Pfefferkorn proposed, he proposed that the
                    emperor should decree that for ten years there be two Hebrew chairs at every
                    German university for which the Jews should furnish books. The other experts and
                    all the universities consulted, except Heidelberg, proposed that all books
                    except Bibles should be taken from the Jews to be investigated by a commission;
                    and, as the emperor still hesitated, the bigots threw on Reuchlin the whole
                    blame of their ill success. Pfefferkorn circulated at the Frankfort fair of 1511
                    a gross libel (the <hi rend="italic">Handspiegek)</hi> declaring that Reuchlin
                    had been bribed; and Reuchlin, burning with the indigation of a man of unsullied
                    integrity, retorted as warmly in the <hi rend="italic">Augenspiegel</hi> (1511).
                    His adversary’s next move was to declare the <hi rend="italic">Augenspiegel</hi>
                    a dangerous book; the Cologne faculty, with their dean the grand inquisitor
                    Hochstraten, took up this cry, and, encouraged perhaps by some signs of timidity
                    in letters from Reuchlin to two of the Cologne theologians, they called on him
                    to recant not a few dangerous utterances and misapplications of Scripture.
                    Reuchlin was timid, but he was honesty itself. He was willing to receive
                    corrections in theology, which was not his subject, but he could not unsay what
                    he had said; and as his enemies tried to press him into a corner he at length
                    turned and met them with open defiance in a <hi rend="italic">Defeηsio contra
                    Calumniatores,</hi> 1513. The universities were now appealed to for opinions,
                    and were all against Reuchlin. Even Paris (August 1514) condemned the <hi
                    rend="italic">Augenspiegel,</hi> and called on Reuchlin to recant. Meantime a
                    formal process had begun at Mainz before the grand inquisitor, but Reuchlin by
                    an appeal succeeded in transferring the question to Rome. It is needless to
                    follow the long windings of ecclesiastical process; judgment was not finally
                    given till July 1516; and then, though the decision was really for Reuchlin, the
                    trial was simply quashed. The result had cost Reuchlin years of trouble and no
                    small part of his modest fortune, but it was worth the sacrifice. For far above
                    the direct importance of the issue was the great stirring of public opinion
                    which had gone forward. All who loved learning and progress were banded together
                    as they had never been before against the bigots and the stupid universities;
                    and all humanists felt that the victory was theirs. And if the obscurantists
                    escaped easily at Rome, λvith only a half condemnation, they received a crushing
                    blow in Germany. No party could survive the ridicule that was poured on them in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Epistolae Obscurorum Virorum.</hi> Reuchlin did not long
                    enjoy his victory in peace. In 1519 Stuttgart was visited by famine, civil war,
                    and pestilence. Frbm November of this year to the spring of 1521 the veteran
                    statesman, whom the universal respect felt for his scholarship could not secure
                    against the dangers involved in his political relations, sought refuge in
                    Ingolstadt and taught there for a, year as professor of Greek and Hebrew. It was
                    forty-one years since at Poitiers he had last spoken from a public chair; but
                    the old man of sixty-five had not lost his gift of teaching, and hundreds of
                    scholars crowded round him. This gleam of autumn sunshine was again broken by
                    the plague; but now he was called to Tübingen and again spent the winter of
                    1521-22 teaching in his own systematic solid way. But he was now in shaken
                    health; in the spring he found it necessary to visit the baths of Liebenzell,
                    and here he was seized with jaundice, of which he died 30th June 1522, leaving
                    in the history of the new learning a name only second to that of his younger
                    contemporary Erasmus.</p>
                <p>The authorities for Reuchlin’s life are enumerated in L. Geiger, <hi
                    rend="italic">Johann Reuchlin,</hi> 1871, which is the standard biography. The
                    controversy about the books of the Jews is well sketched by Strauss, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ulrich vοn HιMeη.</hi> Some interesting details about Reuchlin are
                    given in the autobiography of PellicaNVS (⅛.γ.), which was not published when
                    Geiger’s book appeared. (W. R. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
