<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0413-0396-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RENI</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 396</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:846504">Capitols</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27px1w">Lamentations</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fx7409k">Laments</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n413/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RENI</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Guido</hi> (1575-1642), a
                    prime master in the Bolognese school of painting, and one of the most admired
                    artists of the period of incipient decadence in Italy, was born at Calvenzano
                    near Bologna on 4th November 1575. He is most usually named Guido. His father
                    was a musician of repute, a player on the flageolet; he wished to bring the lad
                    up to perform on the harpsichord. At a very childish age, however, Guido
                    displayed a determined bent towards the art of form, scribbling some attempt at
                    a drawing here, there, and everywhere. He was only nine years of age when Denis
                    Calvart took notice of him, received him into his academy of design by the
                    father’s permission, and rapidly brought him forward, so that by the age of
                    thirteen Guido had already attained marked proficiency. Albani and Domenichino
                    became soon afterwards pupils in the same academy. With Albani Guido was very
                    intimate up to the earlier period of manhood, but they afterwards became rivals,
                    both as painters and as heads of ateliers, with a good deal of asperity on
                    Albani’s part; Domenichino was also pitted against Reni by the policy of
                    Annibale Caracci. Guido was still in the academy of Calvart when he began
                    frequenting the opposition school kept by Lodovico Caracci, whose style, far in
                    advance of that of the Flemish painter, he dallied with. This exasperated
                    Calvart. Him Guido, not yet twenty years of age, cheerfully quitted,
                    transferring himself openly to the Caracci academy, in which he soon became
                    prominent, being equally skilful and ambitious. He had not been a year with the
                    Caracci when a work of his excited the wonder of Agostino and the jealousy of
                    Annibale. Lodovico cherished him, and frequently painted him as an angel, for
                    the youthful Reni was extremely handsome. After a while, however, Lodovico also
                    felt himself nettled, and he patronized the competing talents of Guercino. On
                    one occasion Guido had made a copy of Annibale’s Descent from the Cross;
                    Annibale was asked to retouch it, and, finding nothing to do, exclaimed
                    pettishly, “He knows more than enough” (“Costui ne sa troppo”). On another
                    occasion Lodovico, consulted as umpire, lowered a price which Reni asked for an
                    early picture. This slight determined the young man to be a pupil no more. He
                    left the Caracci, and started on his own account as a competitor in the race for
                    patronage and fame. A renowned work, the story of Callisto and Diana, had been
                    completed before he left.</p>
                <p>Guido was faithful to the eclectic principle of the Bolognese school of painting.
                    He had appropriated some<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n414/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0414-0397"/>thing from Calvart, much more from Lodovico
                    Caracci; he studied with much zest after Albert Dürer; he adopted the massive,
                    sombre, and partly uncouth manner of Caravaggio. One day Annibale Caracci made
                    the remark that a style might be formed reversing that of Caravaggio in such
                    matters as the ponderous shadows and the gross common forms; this observation
                    germinated in Guido’s mind, and he endeavoured after some such style, aiming
                    constantly at suavity. Towards 1602 he went to Rome with Albani, and Rome
                    remained his headquarters for twenty years. Here, in the pontificate of Paul V.
                    (Borghese), he was greatly noted and distinguished. In the garden-house of the
                    Rospigliosi Palace he painted the vast fresco which is justly regarded as his
                    masterpiece— Phoebus and the Hours preceded by Aurora. This exhibits his second
                    manner, in which he had deviated far indeed from the promptings of Caravaggio.
                    He founded now chiefly upon the antique, more especially the Niobe group and the
                    Venus de’ Medici, modified by suggestions from Raphael, Correggio, Parmigiano,
                    and Paul Veronese. Of this last painter, although on the whole he did not get
                    much from him, Guido was a particular admirer; he used to say that he would
                    rather have been Paul Veronese than any other master—Paul was more nature than
                    art. The Aurora is beyond doubt a work of pre-eminent beauty and attainment; it
                    is stamped with pleasurable dignity, and, without being effeminate, has a more
                    uniform aim after graceful selectness than can readily be traced in previous
                    painters, greatly superior though some of them had been in impulse and personal
                    fervour of genius. The pontifical chapel of Montecavallo was assigned to Reni to
                    paint; but, being straitened in payments by the ministers, the artist made off
                    to Bologna. He was fetched back by Paul V. with ceremonious éclat, and lodging,
                    living, and equipage were supplied to him. At another time he migrated from Rome
                    to Naples, having received a commission to paint the chapel of S. Gennaro. The
                    notorious cabal of three painters resident in Naples—Corenzio, Caracciolo, and
                    Ribera—offered, however, as stiff an opposition to Guido as to some other
                    interlopers who preceded and succeeded him. They gave his servant a beating by
                    the hands of two unknown bullies, and sent by him a message to his master to
                    depart or prepare for death; Guido waited for no second warning, and departed.
                    He now returned to Rome; but he finally left that city abruptly, in the
                    pontificate of Urban VIII., in consequence of an offensive reprimand
                    administered to him by Cardinal Spinola. He had received an advance of 400 scudi
                    on account of an altarpiece for St Peter’s, but after some lapse of years had
                    made no beginning with the work. A broad reminder from the cardinal put Reni on
                    his mettle; he returned the 400 scudi, quitted Rome within a few days, and
                    steadily resisted all attempts at recall. He now resettled in Bologna. He had
                    taught as well as painted in Rome, and he left pupils behind him; but on the
                    whole he did not stamp any great mark upon the Roman school of painting, apart
                    from his own numerous works in the papal city.</p>
                <p>In Bologna Guido lived in great splendour, and established a celebrated school,
                    numbering more than two hundred scholars. He himself drew in it, even down to
                    his latest years. On first returning to this city, he charged about ¿621 for a
                    full-length figure (mere portraits are not here in question), half this sum for
                    a half-length, and <hi rend="italic">£5</hi> for a head. These prices must be
                    regarded as handsome, when we consider that Domenichino about the same time
                    received only ¿610, 10s. for his very large and celebrated picture, the Last
                    Communion of St Jerome. But Guido’s reputation was still on the increase, and in
                    process of time he quintupled his prices. He now left Bologna hardly at all; in
                    one instance, however, he went off to Ravenna, and, along with three pupils, he
                    painted the chapel in the cathedral with his admired picture of the Israelites
                    Gathering Manna. His shining prosperity was not to last till the end. Guido was
                    dissipated, generously but indiscriminately profuse, and an inveterate gambler.
                    The gambling propensity had been his from youth, but until he became elderly it
                    did not noticeably damage his fortunes. It grew upon him, and in a couple of
                    evenings he lost the enormous sum of 14,400 scudi. The vice told still more
                    ruinously on his art than on his character. In his decline he sold his time at
                    so much per hour to certain picture dealers; one of them, the Shylock of his
                    craft, would stand by, watch in hand, and see him work. Half-heartedness,
                    half-performance, blighted his product: self-repetition and mere mannerism, with
                    affectation for sentiment and vapidity for beauty, became the art of Guido. Some
                    of these trade-works, heads or halffigures, were turned out in three hours or
                    even less. It is said that, tardily wise, Reni left off gambling for nearly two
                    years; at last he relapsed, and his relapse was followed not long afterwards by
                    his death, caused by malignant fever. This event took place in Bologna on 18th
                    August 1642; he died in debt, but was buried with great pomp in the church of S.
                    Domenico.</p>
                <p>Guido was personally modest, although he valued himself on his position in the
                    art, and would tolerate no slight in that relation; he was extremely upright,
                    temperate in diet, nice in his person and his dress. He was fond of stately
                    houses, but could feel also the charm of solitude. In his temper there was a
                    large amount of suspiciousness; and the jealousy which his abilities and his
                    successes excited, now from the Caracci, now from Albani, now from the
                    monopolizing league of Neapolitan painters, may naturally have kept this feeling
                    in active exercise. Of his numerous scholars, Simone Contarini, named II
                    Pesarese, counts as the most distinguished; he painted an admirable head of
                    Reni, now in the Bolognese Gallery. The portrait in the Uffizi Gallery of
                    Florence is from Reni’s own hand. Two other good scholars were Giacomo Semenza
                    and Francesco Gessi.</p>
                <p>The character of Guido’s art is so well known as hardly to call for detailed
                    analysis, beyond what we have already intimated. His most characteristic style
                    exhibits a prepense ideal, of form rather than character, with a slight mode of
                    handling, and silvery, somewhat cold, colour. In working from the nude he aimed
                    at perfection of form, especially marked in the hands and feet. But he was far
                    from always going to choice nature for his model; he transmuted <hi
                    rend="italic">ad libitum,</hi> and painted, it is averred, a Magdalene of
                    demonstrative charms from a vulgar-looking colour-grinder. His best works have
                    beauty, great amenity, artistic feeling, and high accomplishment of manner, all
                    alloyed by a certain core of commonplace; in the worst pictures the commonplace
                    swamps everything, and Guido has flooded European galleries with trashy and
                    empty pretentiousness, all the more noxious in that its apparent grace of
                    sentiment and form misleads the unwary into approval, and the dilettante dabbler
                    into cheap raptures. Both in Rome and where-ever else he worked he introduced
                    increased softness of style, which was then designated as the modern method. His
                    pictures are mostly Scriptural or mythologic in subject, and between two and
                    three hundred of them are to be found in various European collections—more than
                    a hundred of these containing life-sized figures. The portraits which he
                    executed are few,—those of Sixtus V., Cardinal Spada, and the so-called Beatrice
                    Cenci being among the most noticeable. The identity of the last-named portrait
                    is very dubious; it certainly cannot have been painted direct from Beatrice, who
                    had been executed in Rome before Guido ever resided there. Many etchings are
                    attributed to him—some from his own works, and some after other masters; they
                    are spirited, but rather negligent.</p>
                <p>Of other works not already noticed, the following should be named :—in Rome (the
                    Vatican), the Crucifixion of St Peter, an example of the painter’s earlier
                    manner; in Forli, the Conception; in Bologna, the Alms of St Roch (early), the
                    Massacre of the Innocents, and the Pieta, or Lament over the Body of Christ (in
                    the church of the Mendicanti), which is by many regarded as Guido’s prime
                    executive work; in the Dresden Gallery, an Ecce Homo; in Milan (Brera Gallery),
                    Saints Peter and Paul; in Genoa (church of S. Ambrogio), the Assumption of the
                    Virgin; in the Berlin Gallery, St Paul the Hermit and St Anthony in the
                    Wilderness. The celebrated picture of Fortune (in the Capitol) is one of Reni’s
                    finest treatments of female form; as a specimen of male form, the Samson
                    Drinking from the Jawbone of an Ass (Turin Gallery) might be named beside it.
                    One of his latest works of mark is the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n415/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0415-0398"/>Ariadne, which used to be in the Gallery of the
                    Capitol. The Louvre contains twenty of his pictures, the National Gallery of
                    London seven, and others were once there, now removed to other public
                    collections. The most interesting of the seven is the small Coronation of the
                    Virgin, painted on copper, an elegantly finished work, more pretty than
                    beautiful. It was probably painted before the master quitted Bologna for
                    Rome.</p>
                <p>For the life and works of Hem, see Passeri, <hi rend="italic">Vice</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de' Pittori,</hi> and Malvasia, <hi rend="italic">Felsina
                    Pittvice</hi>; also Lanzi, <hi rend="italic">Storia PiCtorica.</hi> (W. M.
                    Ii.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
