<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0684-0661-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROMANCE LANGUAGES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 661</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="26" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="26" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="23" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="230" ref="fasttopic:980789">Italics</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:1169292">Vowels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205085">Romania</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4px50">Roumanian</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n694">Stresses</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r546">Speech</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n684/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROMANCE LANGUAGES</label> is the name generally adopted for
                    the modern languages descended from the old Roman or Latin tongue, acted upon by
                    inner decay or growth, by dialectic variety, and by outward influence, more or
                    less marked, of all the foreign nations with which it came into contact. During
                    the Middle Ages the old Roman empire or the Latin-speaking world was called
                    Romania, its inhabitants Romani (adj. <hi rend="italic">Romanicus),</hi> and its
                    speech Romancium, Vulgar Romancio, Italian Romanzo, from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romanixe loqui = tο</hi> speak Romance; in Old French nominative <hi
                    rend="italic">romanz,</hi> objective <hi rend="italic">rornαn(t),</hi> Modern
                    French <hi rend="italic">roman, “</hi> a novel,” originally a composition in the
                    vulgar tongue. In English some moderns use Romanic (like Germanic, Teutonic)
                    instead of Romance; some say Neo-Latin, which is frequently used by
                    Romance-speaking scholars. By successive changes Latin, a synthetical language,
                    rich in inflexions, was transformed into several cognate analytical tongues of
                    few inflexions, most of the old forms being replaced by separate form-words. As
                    the literary language of the ancient Roman civilization died out, seemingly
                    extinguished by the barbarism of the Middle Ages, all the forms of the old
                    classical language being confounded in the most hopeless chaos, suddenly new,
                    vigorous, and beautiful tongues sprang forth, ruled by the most regular laws,
                    related to, yet different from, Latin. How was this wonderful change brought
                    about? How can chaos produce regularity? The explanation of this mystery has
                    been given by Diez, the great founder of Romance philology. The Romance
                    languages did not spring from literary classical Latin, but from popular Latin,
                    which, like every living speech, had its own laws, not subject to the changing
                    literary fashions, but only to the slow process of phonetic change and dialectic
                    variety. It is wonderful how like the very oldest archaic Latin is to the
                    youngest, Modern Romance. A great number of old sounds, forms, and expressions,
                    which were discarded or disused by classical Latin, reappear in late vulgar
                    Latin, and live on in the modern languages. Here especially the words of Horace
                    come true;</p>
                <p>“Malta renascentur, quae jam cecidere, cadentque Quae nunc sunt in honore
                    vocabula, si volet usus,</p>
                <p>Quem penes arbitrium est et jus et norma loquendi.”</p>
                <p>The present article, embracing all the Romance languages, dwells chiefly on their
                    common origin and formation. Much of their general history has been treated
                    under <hi rend="smallcaps">Latin; only some points, especially phonetic, which
                    need a fuller discussion, are taken up again here.</hi></p>
                <p>We will now briefly review the fate of popular Latin through its successive
                    stages, showing everywhere the earliest appearance of the germs of Modern
                    Romance.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="italic">First (Pre-Classical) Period: to c.</hi> 80 b.c. <hi
                    rend="italic"> (Cicero).</hi></p>
                <p>Latin, like all other literary languages, began as a living popular speech. There
                    was during this first period practically little difference between the vulgar
                    and the literary language. In the oldest historical time Latin was spoken only
                    in the small territory called Latium. The greater part of Italy proper was
                    occupied by the Umbro-Oscan tribes, whose languages were Italic, related to
                    Latin, yet so different as to be unintelligible to the Romans. The two most
                    distinct types were Umbrian in the north and Oscan in the south. The chief
                    difference between them is that Umbrian was in a much more advanced state of
                    phonetic decay, and was in many respects a precursor of Italian and Romance,
                    while Oscan was still more antique than Latin. When the territories where these
                    dialects were spoken became subject to the Romans, about the beginning of the 3d
                    century b.c., the language of the conquerors was introduced, but of course
                    modified by the speech of the conquered. Thus two groups of provincial dialects
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Latin dialects have
                    been investigated by K. Sittl, <hi rend="italic">Die lokalen Verschiedenheiten
                    der lateinischen Sprache,</hi> Erlangen, 1882. On Latin sounds generally see
                    Seelmann, <hi rend="italic">Die A ussprache des Latein,</hi> Heilbronn, 1885.
                    Both these books, however, must be used with caution. Sittl has the merit of
                    having traced the relations of North Latin, but has many rash assertions; see
                    <hi rend="italic">Zeitschr. f. rorn. Phil.,</hi> vi. 608 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi> Seel-mann is superior to Corssen as a phonetician, but is often
                    obscure and given to elaborating strange theories. Thus he arrives at the absurd
                    conclusion that the differences of quantity did not exist in the classical age,
                    but that the poets judged of quantity by the close or open sound of the vowel.
                    </p></note> were formed. (1) The North or Umbrian and Sabellian Latin, with
                    which Etruscan Latin was closely connected, was peculiarly important, since it
                    spread southwards and extended to the neighbourhood of Rome; thus Falerii,
                    Praeneste, and Tusculum spoke it. Later it spread to Northern Italy. Being
                    really a fuller development of the tendencies of the old popular Latin and
                    easier to pronounce than literary Latin, at last from the surrounding peasantry
                    it reached the people of Rome and became the source of the modern tongues. (2)
                    The South or Oscan Latin was Latin with some slight phonetic modifications,</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n685/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0685-0662"/>
                <p>which, in Modern South Italian, have lived through the levelling influence of the
                    north dialect. Between the Umbrians and the Oscans lay the Sabellians, occupying
                    linguistically as geographically a middle position, yet somewhat nearer to the
                    north dialect than to the south. To the west of Umbria lay the mysterious
                    Etruria, whose language, preserved in numerous inscriptions, has long been an
                    unsolved riddle and is still a matter of dispute, some considering it as utterly
                    unconnected with Italic or even Aryan, some, as Deecke and Sophus Bugge,
                    thinking it Aryan, intermediate between Greek and Italic, but partly decayed. In
                    the last respect it has much in common with Umbrian, but its tendency to a rapid
                    and slovenly utterance is still more distinctly traceable than in Umbrian.</p>
                <p>Of the other languages spoken in old Italy, such as Messapian, Celtic, Venetian,
                    and Ligurian, too little is known to enable us to form an estimate of their
                    phonetic character; but in general we see the peculiarities of North Latin
                    penetrating more or less everywhere, in the north of Italy and in Spain
                    (subjected at the end of the 3d century b.c.), as well as in Gaul, of which the
                    southern part, Pro-vincia (later Provence), was subjected first, and the rest,
                    by Caesar, in the lst century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> All these countries
                    were rapidly Latinized; but the provincial dialects did not always follow the
                    phonetic development of the mother speech, just as American does not always
                    follow the changes of English.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Old Popular Latin.</hi><hi rend="italic">A. Phonetics.</hi> 1.
                    Final consonants, especially <hi rend="italic"> s,</hi><note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>There is nothing to prove that this s was
                    voiced, like Eng. <hi rend="italic">z</hi>; probably it was voiceless and weakly
                    articulated, much the same as in Andalusian Zo(Λ) <hi rend="italic">padre,</hi>
                    for Span, <hi rend="italic"> lοs padres,</hi> “the parents.” </p></note><hi
                    rend="italic">m,</hi> partly <hi rend="italic">t,d,r,</hi> were feebly
                    pronounced and often dropped in writing: s in nominatives, as <hi rend="italic">
                    Cornelio</hi> (T. Scip.), <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Abbreviations— <hi rend="italic">Τ. Scip.,</hi> Tituli (Elogia) Scipionuιn;
                    <hi rend="italic">Col. Postr.,</hi> Columns Rostrata; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Baccħ.,</hi> Eρistola Consolum de Bacchanalibus; <hi rend="italic">T.
                    Pis.,</hi> Tituli Pisaur-enses; L. Low or Late Latin; * before a word means
                    hypothetical. </p></note> —even Ennius wrote <hi rend="italic">eertissimu'
                    nuntrn ’ mortis</hi>; gen. aedem <hi rend="italic">Serapi</hi> (in a law); acc.
                    <hi rend="italic">vird</hi> nostros (Plaut. ). In verse s was not counted in the
                    metre till the manhood of Cicero, who, though he had himself followed the
                    earlier use in his youth, calls it “subrusticum,” which shows that it continued
                    in the country. This agrees with Umbrian, where s was often dropped, as Ikuvinu
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Spaced letters signify
                    the inscriptions in the national character, generally supposed to be older;
                    italics mean the inscriptions in Roman letters, supposed to be younger.
                    </p></note> Iguvini (nom. plur.), <hi rend="italic">agre</hi> agri (gen.),
                    &amp;c.; with North Latin, as <hi rend="italic"> matrοnα Pisaurese</hi> (nom.
                    plur.; at Pisaurum); <hi rend="italic">maxomo</hi> maximus, <hi rend="italic"
                    >zmιatuo</hi> (gen. at Falerii) = Old Lat. senatuos; <hi rend="italic"
                    >nιilitare</hi> (nom.; at Tusculum) looks quite Italian. <hi rend="italic"
                    >M</hi> was often dropped, as in the well-known <hi rend="italic">hone oino
                    duonoro optumo fiuise viro</hi> (T. Scip.). It was, by the express statement of
                    Quintilian, obscurely pronounced (see Latin), and must have been very loosely
                    articulated, the lips probably only approaching, not closing, much like Polish
                    <hi rend="italic">D(ibrowski</hi> (Dombrowski), which gives a sound between a
                    feeble <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and a nasal vowel. In Umbrian this dropping of
                    the <hi rend="italic">nι</hi> is frequent, as <hi rend="italic">poplo</hi> for
                    populum, and in Faliscan <hi rend="italic"> sαeru, data. T,</hi> on the
                    contrary, was generally retained in Old Latin, but frequently dropped in
                    Umbrian, as dede dedit, <hi rend="italic"> habe</hi> habet, habia habeat;
                    likewise in North Latin, as <hi rend="italic">dede</hi> dedit, <hi rend="italic"
                    >dedro</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> dedrot</hi> for dederunt (T. Pis.); <hi
                    rend="italic">dede</hi> (Tibur); <hi rend="italic">cuρa</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">cupat</hi> for cubat (Fal.). Sometimes <hi rend="italic">d</hi>
                    was used, as <hi rend="italic"> fiecid</hi> (Praeneste), in Osc. <hi
                    rend="italic">fief acid, deded.</hi> In the perfects, however, <hi rend="italic"
                    >d</hi> is perhaps the older sound. <hi rend="italic">D</hi> is the final
                    consonant that was first dropped, as in <hi rend="italic">in altod marid</hi>
                    (Col. Rostr.), a <hi rend="italic">Gηaivod paire,</hi> but also <hi
                    rend="italic">longa vita</hi> (T. Scip)., later frequently. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pate(p), soro(p), colο{r),</hi> occur in Plautus with <hi rend="italic">r</hi>
                    dropped or slightly pronounced (not counted in the metre); in <hi rend="italic"
                    >pate(fi)</hi> venit (Terence; see Latin); in Fal. <hi rend="italic">uxo,
                    mate</hi>; in Aequian <hi rend="italic">uxo;</hi> and in Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >firate, suora, moglie.</hi> 2Vwas dropped in <hi rend="italic">tame(n)</hi>
                    sus-picor (Ter.); Umb. <hi rend="italic">nome</hi> and numem, pointing perhaps
                    to a weak nasal vowel; I tai. <hi rend="italic">nome.</hi><hi rend="italic">2.
                    D</hi> after vowels sometimes became <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic">ar</hi> ad, <hi rend="italic">arvorsum</hi> adversum, <hi
                    rend="italic">arfiuise, arger</hi> agger,—rustic <hi rend="italic"> ar</hi> me
                    advenias (Plaut., <hi rend="italic">True.,</hi> ii. 2); it was retained in
                    classical Latin in <hi rend="italic">arbiter, areesso, meridies.</hi> In Old
                    Umbrian <hi rend="italic">d</hi> constantly changes to a peculiar sound, here
                    transcribed d, in Later Umbrian spelt <hi rend="italic">rs,</hi> as ad, <hi
                    rend="italic">ars</hi> ad, <hi rend="italic"> ρetur-pnrsus</hi> quadrupedibus,
                    <hi rend="italic">dupursus</hi> bipedibus. This sound appears to be only a less
                    trilled variety of the Roman sound. In some few instances this old <hi
                    rend="italic">r</hi> reappears later, as in Mediaeval Lat. <hi rend="italic"
                    >armes-sarius</hi> (Lex Salica), in Roum. <hi rend="italic">arm^sariu,</hi> I
                    tai. <hi rend="italic">drgine,</hi> Ven. <hi rend="italic">drzare,</hi> Span,
                    drcen=Lat. arger (agger). In Modern South Italian <hi rend="italic">r</hi> for
                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is quite common, as Neap, <hi rend="italic"
                    >rurece,</hi> Sicil. tZtt∕√d = Ital. dδdici, Lat. duodecim.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Z</hi> for s is found in some unintelligible fragments of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Carmen Saliare,</hi> mentioned by Varro <hi rend="italic">
                    {L.L.,</hi> vii. 26), but in the text he says that the ancients used s for <hi
                    rend="italic">r. Coz(cηιo),</hi> but also <hi rend="italic"> Cosano,</hi> is
                    found on two old coins from Cosa, though here <hi rend="italic">z</hi> may be
                    due to Oscan influence. On the other hand, <hi rend="italic">veter,
                    quirquir,</hi> were found in the ancient augural books, perhaps Etruscan
                    Latin(?). But the ordinary form of Old Latin was <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> as in
                    <hi rend="italic">asa, honos, honosis, fiosem, Loses, Fusius, Papisius,
                    Valesius.</hi> Not <hi rend="italic">z,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">s</hi> or ss
                    was used to render Greek f,— <hi rend="italic"> Saguηtum, cornissor, massa;</hi>
                    in this last word (Fr. <hi rend="italic"> masse)</hi> the present pronunciation
                    still testifies to the old voiceless sound. Thus the whole theory of the ancient
                    Latin <hi rend="italic"> z</hi> becomes somewhat doubtful; yet it is probable
                    that it existed in the oldest prehistoric Latin, and that forms like <hi
                    rend="italic"> *easum resum</hi> were pronounced with <hi rend="italic">z,</hi>
                    like the Ose. <hi rend="italic">eizazune egmazum</hi> (same meaning). Later on s
                    (z) passed into <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> following in this the Umb. urnasiaru,
                    <hi rend="italic">jn∙aeataηιm,</hi> &amp;c. In most words Latin now got <hi
                    rend="italic">r,</hi> even in some where Umbrian retained s; comp. Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">ara</hi> with Umb. <hi rend="italic">asa,</hi> Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">plenarius, Ordinarius</hi> with Umb. plenasier, urnasier. In Lat.
                    <hi rend="italic">nαsus—slaves</hi> the relation must be somewhat like that in
                    À.S. <hi rend="italic">ee6san, ceas—eurem, gecoren</hi> (choose, chose, chosen),
                    probably owing to an original difference of accent. In many cases where Latin
                    retained s it was originally double, as in <hi rend="italic"> caussα,
                    cassus</hi> ( = cad-tus), thus spelt by Cicero and Virgil (Quint., i. 7, 20);
                    <hi rend="italic">fiormonsus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> fiοrmοssus</hi>; this
                    is the reason why Italian has always s hard (voiceless) in <hi rend="italic"
                    >eosa</hi> (Ven. <hi rend="italic">eossa), doloroso,</hi> &amp;c., as Ascoli has
                    shown. Thus, every <hi rend="italic"> z</hi> or voiced s having passed into <hi
                    rend="italic">r,</hi> the sound <hi rend="italic">z</hi> must have disappeared
                    from the language, and it was only much later that it was reintroduced. The
                    sound of <hi rend="italic"> z</hi> seems to be especially at home on Celtic
                    ground; the voiceless sound still exists in the south of Italy (Rome, Naples,
                    Sicily) and of Spain. The English pronunciation of Latin words like <hi
                    rend="italic">morose, jocose,</hi> and of Greek words like <hi rend="italic"
                    >dosis, crisis,</hi> is probably due to ancient tradition.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">N</hi> was often dropped before <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> as
                    <hi rend="italic">cosol</hi> consol, <hi rend="italic">eesor</hi> censor, <hi
                    rend="italic">eosentiont</hi> (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">moOι)strare,
                    Mostellαria</hi> (Plaut.); even <hi rend="italic">fies-tram</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic">fieηestram (fieKstram</hi>; Ennius); <hi rend="italic">
                    Alliesis</hi> dies dicebatur (Fest.); <hi rend="italic">7neses</hi> (inscr.
                    Neap.), &amp;c.; nearly always <hi rend="italic">fiormossus, far-mosus</hi> for
                    <hi rend="italic">fiormonsus</hi> (see 3). This agrees with Umb. <hi
                    rend="italic">Eikvαsese</hi> and N. Lat. <hi rend="italic"> Pisaurese,</hi>
                    Pomp, <hi rend="italic">eastresis, pesa,</hi> and reappears in Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">Milanese, Genovese, mese, ρesare,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">mois,
                    peser.</hi> In Latin <hi rend="italic"> n</hi> generally did not quite
                    disappear, but was feebly pronounced, very like French <hi rend="italic">n</hi>
                    in <hi rend="italic">penser,</hi> or probably still more like the Γolish nasal
                    vowel in <hi rend="italic"> miςso,</hi> “flesh,” <hi rend="italic">gfi,</hi>
                    “goose,” half vowel, half consonant. By this partial absorption of <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> the preceding vowel was lengthened, <hi rend="italic">eo
                    <hi rend="superscript">η</hi> sol.</hi> Cicero expressly mentions <hi
                    rend="italic">insanus,</hi> Gellius <hi rend="italic">pensito,</hi> the
                    grammarians <hi rend="italic"> mans, mens, gens.</hi> The same was the case
                    before ∕, as <hi rend="italic">iηfielix</hi> mentioned by Cicero; <hi
                    rend="italic">n</hi> sometimes dropped before <hi rend="italic">v,
                    eoventionid</hi> (Bacch., 187 b.c.); comp. Umb. kuveitu convehito, kuvertu
                    convertito, Fr. <hi rend="italic"> convent,</hi> Eng. <hi rend="italic">covent,
                    covenant. N</hi> is rarely dropped before <hi rend="italic">t</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">d</hi> except in N. Lat. <hi rend="italic">dedrο(t)</hi> (T.
                    Pis.); but this does not count, as the <hi rend="italic">t</hi> was mute. Cicero
                    testifies to <hi rend="italic">indoetus,</hi> which proves the full sound of <hi
                    rend="italic">η.</hi> The spellings <hi rend="italic">tamtαe, sentemtiam, damda,
                    tuemdam,</hi> &amp;c., of the Lex Julia (45 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>) are
                    probably only analogical from <hi rend="italic">eumdem, eamdem,</hi> &amp;c.,
                    pronounced <hi rend="italic">n. M</hi> disappears in <hi rend="italic">
                    Poρ&gt;oni, Seprοni,</hi> but perhaps only apparently, as Priscian tells us that
                    medial <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic"> umbra,</hi> had a
                    middling force, not the obscure sound of final <hi rend="italic">m.</hi> In most
                    old spellings, as in the Scandinavian Runes, we frequently find nasals dropped
                    before corresponding “mutes” or stops, where there is no suspicion of an
                    obscured sound, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in Run. LAT for <hi rend="italic"
                    >land</hi> the nasal is simply understood. Likewise in Umbrian the older ustetu
                    is shown by the Latin spelling to mean <hi rend="italic"> ostendu,</hi> &amp;c.
                    In Modern Romance only Celtic districts have produced nasal vowels.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">H</hi> is sometimes dropped from the 2d century B.c.
                    downwards— “Parcissime ea <hi rend="italic">[H</hi> littera] veteres usi etiam
                    in vocalibus, quum <hi rend="italic">oedos</hi> [read <hi rend="italic">aedos}
                    ireosque</hi> dicebant” (Quint., i. 5, 20); “in Latio rure <hi rend="italic">
                    edus,</hi> in urbe <hi rend="italic">aedns''</hi> (Varro), for Ancdî&lt;s=Goth.
                    <hi rend="italic">gaits,</hi> “goat”; likewise <hi rend="italic"> olera,
                    asta</hi> (Varro); in Marsian Lat. <hi rend="italic"> Irtisιs</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic">Hirtius, Ostilins;</hi> comp. Umb. eretu = Acn7κ “velit.” <hi
                    rend="italic">H</hi> must have had a rather feeble sound, something like French
                    <hi rend="italic">h aspirée.</hi></p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Rs</hi> is found assimilated in <hi rend="italic">russum
                    {rusum), sussum {susum),</hi> &amp;c., in MSS. of Plautus and Cato, and in some
                    inscriptions, always in 7)r0s(i (but <hi rend="italic">prorsus)</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">eena,</hi> Umb. çersnatur “cenati,” <hi rend="italic">dos∙
                    suarius</hi> (Vario); “sic et <hi rend="italic">dossum</hi> per duo <hi
                    rend="italic">s . .</hi> . quidam ut levins enuntiaverunt” (Vel. Long.). Comp.
                    Umb. <hi rend="italic">Tursee, Tuscom</hi> “Tus-cum”; Ligurian Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">suso</hi> (bronze tablet near Genoa, 117 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi>). But this assimilation was never carried out consistently; we have
                    L. Lat. <hi rend="italic"> susum et jusτιm</hi> (sursum et deorsum), I tai. <hi
                    rend="italic"> su e giiι,</hi> older <hi rend="italic">suso e giuso; dosso,</hi>
                    but <hi rend="italic">corso, verso, orso</hi> (ursus), Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ours,</hi> Span. <hi rend="italic">oso.</hi></p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was doubled between vowels, as in “antiqui <hi
                    rend="italic"> maiiusfi</hi> which Priscian distinctly explains to have been
                    pronounced with the sound of <hi rend="italic">i</hi> consonant (Eng. <hi
                    rend="italic"> y in you),</hi> and “<hi rend="italic">Pompeiii</hi> ut si dicas
                    <hi rend="italic">Γοm-pelliF</hi> Cicero spelt <hi rend="italic">aiio,
                    Maiiam;</hi> “quod si est, etiam jungetur [t] ut consonans” (Quint., i. 4, 11).
                    Comp, also Osc. <hi rend="italic">Pompaiians.</hi> Out of the older and popular
                    <hi rend="italic">ηιαjjus, pejjus</hi> grew Ital. <hi rend="italic"> rnaggio,
                    peggio,</hi> whereas classical Latin had <hi rend="italic"> mαjus, pejus.</hi>
                    For <hi rend="italic">filius —filjus,</hi> see 23 below, p. 664.</p>
                <p>8. <hi rend="italic">V</hi> occurs in Old Lat. <hi rend="italic">perplovere</hi>
                    perpluere (comp, <hi rend="italic">pluvia),</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n686/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0686-0663"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">confiovσnt</hi> (comp, <hi rend="italic">fioviom;
                    fiuvidus,</hi> Lucretius), <hi rend="italic">sοvo, suvo,</hi> suo, <hi
                    rend="italic"> iηgeηuvae, elovacas.</hi> Comp. Umb. tover and <hi rend="italic">
                    tuer,</hi> tui; Osc. <hi rend="italic">suvad,</hi> &amp;c. It reappears in
                    Petronius, urceatim <hi rend="italic">plovebat,</hi> and in Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">ρibvere, rovιna, védova, Gènova, Mantova, chiavica,</hi> Span. <hi
                    rend="italic">llovér,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"> pleuvoir.</hi></p>
                <p>9. In <hi rend="italic">qu</hi> the <hi rend="italic">u</hi> after <hi
                    rend="italic"> q</hi> was only a lip glide, defined by the grammarians as
                    “neither vowel nor consonant,” as it did not count in the metre. It was
                    therefore easily dropped altogether, as in <hi rend="italic">Cinti</hi> for
                    Quincti in an old inscription. This was especially peculiar to Etruscan Latin,
                    as in the very old <hi rend="italic">Aeeetiai</hi> Aequitiae, <hi rend="italic">
                    Tarena,</hi> Etrus. <hi rend="italic">Tarχnas,</hi> Tarquinius. Instances occur
                    later everywhere, as <hi rend="italic">eoeus</hi> for <hi rend="italic">eoqwus,
                    eottidie</hi> (Lex Julia), &amp;c.; L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">cinque,
                    einquaginta</hi> (Edict. Diocl., 301); Ital. <hi rend="italic"> chi</hi> qui,
                    <hi rend="italic">ehe</hi> quid, <hi rend="italic"> eubcere</hi> coquere, <hi
                    rend="italic">eueina =</hi> vulg. Lat. coquina ( = culina), <hi rend="italic"
                    >cinque,</hi> &amp;c. But generally Italian retains <hi rend="italic">qu</hi>
                    with the old sound, <hi rend="italic"> quinto, quanto,</hi> Span, <hi
                    rend="italic">euaηto,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">que, quinto {-k),</hi> Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">qu = k.</hi></p>
                <p>10. The Old Romans, having no aspirates in their own speech,</p>
                <p>, could not pronounce the Greek <hi rend="italic">φ, χ, θ,</hi> but generally
                    turned them into <hi rend="italic">ρ, e, t,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Rilippus
                    Φίλιπποί, Prune Φρύνη, cοlapus, Bacanal.</hi> In some words the old popular
                    pronunciation continued later, as class, <hi rend="italic">ampulla,
                    purpura;</hi> Silver Age, <hi rend="italic">percolopabant</hi> (Petron.);
                    Mediaeval, <hi rend="italic">colopus, eolpus,</hi> I tai. <hi rend="italic"
                    >colριo,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">coup; sρ&gt;aera,</hi> Old I tai. <hi
                    rend="italic"> spera</hi> (Dante), Early Eng. <hi rend="italic">spere</hi>
                    (Chaucer), vulg. Eng. <hi rend="italic">spear,</hi> “sphere”; <hi rend="italic">
                    Josepus,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">Giuseppe; Step&lt;vnus,</hi> Span. <hi
                    rend="italic">Estéban,</hi> Slav. <hi rend="italic"> Stepan.</hi></p>
                <p>11. Greek initial <hi rend="italic">π</hi> was often rendered <hi rend="italic">
                    b,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Βurrus Xlvphbi,</hi> also adj., <hi rend="italic"
                    >“burrum</hi> antiqui quod nunc dicimus rufum” (Fest.); hence, through <hi
                    rend="italic">burtfi)eus,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">bujo,</hi> “dark”;
                    likewise <hi rend="italic">burns πυξ6s,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic"> busso,
                    bosso,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">buis,</hi> “box tree”; from <hi rend="italic"
                    >πυξis,</hi> class, <hi rend="italic">pyxis,</hi> popular and L. Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">buxis, buxida,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"> boîte.</hi></p>
                <p>12. <hi rend="italic">F</hi> after vowels is rare in Latin, but frequent in
                    Umbro-Oscan, as Umb. <hi rend="italic">prufie</hi> probe, Osc. <hi rend="italic"
                    > ampmιfid</hi> improbe, <hi rend="italic">Safinim</hi> Samnium (*Sabinium),
                    corresponding in cognate words to Greek aspirates where Latin commonly had <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi>: Lat. <hi rend="italic">vafier,</hi> “sly,” orig. “varius”;
                    comp, <hi rend="italic">vabmt,m</hi> “varium” (Gloss. Isid.), Umb. vufru. The
                    relation between Lat. <hi rend="italic">rufus,</hi> Umb. rofu and Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">ruber</hi> is very like that between <hi rend="italic">nasus</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">ηrnres,</hi> or that between <hi rend="italic">veho</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">lingo, ligurio</hi> as representing Gr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >χ.</hi> We may suppose that /is the older and stronger common Italic form,
                    sometimes retained in old popular Latin speech, partly by provincial influence.
                    We find <hi rend="italic">sifilare</hi> for <hi rend="italic">sibilare</hi>
                    mentioned as archaic by Nonius, as vulgar in the appendix to Probus, Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">zufiolare,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">siffler. F</hi> is preserved
                    in many provincial names, as <hi rend="italic">Safinius</hi> (Petron. ) and <hi
                    rend="italic">Tifernum,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">Tifierno.</hi> We find this
                    /again in the Italian <hi rend="italic">tafiano</hi> tabanus, <hi rend="italic"
                    >bûfolo</hi> bubalus, Eng. buffalo. The Neapolitan <hi rend="italic">attmιfie,
                    “</hi> October,” has a very Oscan appearance.</p>
                <p>13. Old Latin often prefers short <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> especially original
                    and unaccented, to <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">dedxt,
                    fiuxt</hi> (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">eepet, refecet</hi> (Col. Rostr. ), <hi
                    rend="italic">velet</hi> (Bacch.), <hi rend="italic">Crnuietios</hi> (inscr.),
                    <hi rend="italic">acetare = agetare</hi> (Fest.), <hi rend="italic">
                    dubenτιs</hi> dominus (Fest. ), <hi rend="italic">componeto</hi> (Cato), <hi
                    rend="italic">gcnetmx, mereto, ealecare</hi> (inscr. ), <hi rend="italic">
                    fiamelia, magester</hi> (Quint. ). It stands for radical i, mostly orig. <hi
                    rend="italic">e,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">en, endo-Cχ.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >lv,</hi><hi rend="italic">semul</hi> (Plaut.)—comp. Ital. insieme, Fr.
                    ensemble; <hi rend="italic"> Menerva</hi> (inscr., and mentioned by Quintilian).
                    Sometimes it stands even for original <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic"> tempestatebus, aidiles</hi> (T. Scip. ), <hi rend="italic"
                    >nαvebos, ηavaled,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">marid</hi> (Col. Rostr.), <hi
                    rend="italic">sei ques,</hi> si quis (Bacch.). This is quite Umbrian; comp,
                    kanetu canito, urfetam orbitam, fratreks “fratricus,” ∕αfβ∕eZe = L. Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">fiaxibilis,</hi> Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">fesible</hi> feasible,
                    famedias familiae (nom. plur.), kvêstretie quaestura, formed like Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">segnities.</hi> In North Latin we find Etrus. Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">Aeeetiai</hi> Aequitiae; Umb. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Publeee,
                    menesterium,</hi> (T. Pis.) <hi rend="italic">Apoleηei, dede, Komefiia)</hi>;
                    Mars, <hi rend="italic">dedet, mereto</hi>; and rustic “rustici etiam nunc
                    quoque viam <hi rend="italic">veham</hi> appellant” (Varro). <hi rend="italic"
                    >E,</hi> being more subject to be obscured than <hi rend="italic"> i,</hi> is
                    not unfrequently dropped, as in <hi rend="italic"> eante</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic">*eanete,</hi> class, <hi rend="italic"> αrnιte</hi> (Carm. Sali.),
                    <hi rend="italic">Nurntoriai</hi> (inscr. c. 290 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi>), <hi rend="italic">oinvorsei</hi> (Bacch.), <hi rend="italic"
                    >unversum</hi> (Lucretius), <hi rend="italic">caldus</hi> (Cato), <hi
                    rend="italic"> ardus, frigdaria</hi> (Lucilius); always <hi rend="italic">fieri,
                    fierte=φιρeτe.</hi> Popular Latin here approached the North dialect, where such
                    syncopes were constant: comp. Umb. <hi rend="italic">ηοrnnc</hi> nomine, <hi
                    rend="italic">termnu</hi> termino, <hi rend="italic">postro</hi> postero; they
                    were still more violent in Etruscan, as <hi rend="italic">Elχsentre</hi>
                    Alexander, <hi rend="italic">Sehtmnal</hi> Septimienâ nata, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tarχnas</hi> Tarquinius; Pis. Lat. efe&lt;⅛o(Q dederunt, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lebro</hi> Liberum; Umb. Lat. <hi rend="italic">eedre</hi> cedere, &amp;c.
                    South Latin, on the contrary, favoured <hi rend="italic"> i</hi> (see
                    below).</p>
                <p>14. Of long <hi rend="italic">i</hi> Lucilius distinguishes two kinds—close (i
                    tenue), as in <hi rend="italic">pila, “</hi> mortar,” and open (i ρingue),
                    approaching to <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> written <hi rend="italic">ei,</hi> as
                    in <hi rend="italic">peilum,</hi> “spear,” <hi rend="italic">media,</hi>
                    “thousands”; he might have added <hi rend="italic">fieilius,</hi> “son,” comp,
                    <hi rend="italic">fielare, 6ηλτf∣.</hi> There was an original diphthong <hi
                    rend="italic">eι,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">deicere,</hi> Osc. <hi
                    rend="italic">deicum,</hi> Gr. <hi rend="italic">5eικvbvαn,</hi> which was early
                    contracted into this middle sound, exactly like Eng. <hi rend="italic"> ey</hi>
                    in <hi rend="italic">money</hi> from Old Fr. <hi rend="italic"> rnaneix.</hi>
                    This too is quite Umbrian, spelt <hi rend="italic"> ei</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">ee, e,</hi> as enetu inito, Arch. Lat. eneito, feliuf filios, <hi
                    rend="italic">screihtor, screhto</hi> scripti, <hi rend="italic">ρreve</hi>
                    privus, <hi rend="italic">Ioveine= Ij ovine,</hi> Iguvini; comp, the datives <hi
                    rend="italic">Juve paire, mchs, tefie</hi> (tibi), Ose. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Diuve*, ρatere*</hi>; also Umb. Lat. ∕eZ = filius, and Pis. <hi rend="italic">
                    Lebro.</hi> In North Latin datives in <hi rend="italic">e</hi> are generally
                    constant <hi rend="italic">(Apolenei,</hi> Pis., uncontracted), as <hi
                    rend="italic">Junone matre, Jove, ρatre, Marte,</hi> &amp;c., extending
                    sometimes even farther south; and Gallo-Lat. <hi rend="italic"> nise</hi> (Lex
                    Rubr. de Gall. Cisalp.). Livy used <hi rend="italic"> sibe</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">quase</hi> (originally -ei). This exactly agrees with the rustic
                    pronunciation <hi rend="italic">νella, speca</hi> recorded by Varro, <hi
                    rend="italic">leber</hi> by Festus—“ab antiquis et <hi rend="italic">ameci</hi>
                    et <hi rend="italic">amecae</hi> per e litteram efferebantur” (Fest.). And this
                    again surprisingly agrees with the Modern Emilian (Romagnuolo) pronunciation, as
                    Bolognese <hi rend="italic">mega</hi> mica, <hi rend="italic">dég</hi> dico, <hi
                    rend="italic">méll</hi> mille, plur. τneZα=Ital. mila, <hi rend="italic">
                    véta</hi> vita, <hi rend="italic">maré</hi> marito, <hi rend="italic"> prém</hi>
                    primo. Thus this old rustic sound seems to have extended northwards, but later
                    to have been driven from its old home by the classic close <hi rend="italic"
                    >i,</hi> which penetrated everywhere else, and is generally represented in all
                    the Romance languages.</p>
                <p>15. Old Latin often prefers short <hi rend="italic">o,</hi> especially original
                    and un accented, to <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic"
                    >consol</hi> (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic">tabola</hi> (Bacch.), <hi
                    rend="italic">pocolom</hi> (many old inscr.), <hi rend="italic">popolum</hi>
                    (Tab. Bantina), <hi rend="italic"> cpistola =</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >iπισrολn,</hi><hi rend="italic">Patricoles, Hereοles, eolpa</hi> (Prise. ), <hi
                    rend="italic"> Voleanom</hi> (inscr. 3d century b.c.), <hi rend="italic"
                    >volgo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">volt, &amp;c,c.</hi> (Plaut.; <hi
                    rend="italic"> o</hi> after <hi rend="italic">v</hi> continued in the classical
                    age), <hi rend="italic">sont</hi> sunt, <hi rend="italic">eosentiont</hi> (T.
                    Scip.), <hi rend="italic">deηοηtiari</hi> (Tab. Bant.); in terminations— <hi
                    rend="italic">Venos, ορos, robose, filios,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Luciom,</hi> &amp;c. (T. Scip.); in Umb acc. <hi rend="italic"> ρoplo, salvo,
                    tertio</hi>; even for orig. <hi rend="italic"> u—aseriato eest,</hi> observa-tum
                    ibit; radical—mo‰multa, “fine,” <hi rend="italic"> onse</hi> (h)umero, I tai.
                    <hi rend="italic">0mero,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic">ombro, somo</hi> summo
                    (orig. sup-mo), Ital. <hi rend="italic"> s6mmο</hi>; in North Latin <hi
                    rend="italic">moltaticod</hi> (T. Piceu. ); in Fal. <hi rend="italic">maxomo,
                    zenatuo</hi>; and in Ligurian Latin <hi rend="italic">fioviom, infiumo,
                    suso</hi> (bronze tablet near Genoa, 117 b.c.). <hi rend="italic">0</hi>
                    reappears in Late Latin and Italian <hi rend="italic">m6lto, d6lee,</hi>
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Medial <hi rend="italic">o</hi> is often dropped before <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>
                    as in <hi rend="italic">οrnmpoplo</hi> (Plaut. Pseud.), <hi rend="italic">
                    teglarius</hi> (inscr.), <hi rend="italic">Fostlus</hi> (Faustulus, 114 b.c. ),
                    <hi rend="italic">Herele</hi> (Plaut. ), <hi rend="italic"> singlariter</hi>
                    (Lucr. )—comp. Fr. <hi rend="italic">sanglier,</hi> I tai. <hi rend="italic"
                    >einghiale—eoplata</hi> (Lucr.); in some cases, as <hi rend="italic">poclum,
                    periclum,</hi> the contraction does not appear till the empire; at Pompeii <hi
                    rend="italic">aηglata, subla,</hi> &amp;c. As Umbrian always has contraction,
                    <hi rend="italic">pihaelom, anglom, Treblaηir, vitlu, katlu, stiplo,</hi> whilst
                    Oscan distinguishes diminutive forms like <hi rend="italic">zicolom, zicelei,
                    ziculud</hi> from such forms as <hi rend="italic">sakaraklom, pestlerm,</hi> the
                    strongest impulse must have come from the north, although there must have been a
                    pretty general tendency to syncope everywhere. In Italian contraction is the
                    rule in popular words, as <hi rend="italic">veechio</hi> for <hi rend="italic">
                    vet'lus,</hi> Late <hi rend="italic">veelus, ocehio</hi> oc’lus, &amp;c. In <hi
                    rend="italic">pbpolo, tdvola, isola,</hi> &amp;c., and diminutives like <hi
                    rend="italic">rivolo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">g6ndola,</hi> the original vowel
                    has remained throughout. South Latin favoured <hi rend="italic"> u</hi> (see
                    below).</p>
                <p>16. The use of <hi rend="italic">o</hi> for <hi rend="italic">e</hi> after <hi
                    rend="italic">v</hi> is shown by Old Lat. <hi rend="italic">oinvorsei,
                    vortere;</hi> in <hi rend="italic">vostrum</hi> (Plaut., Ambrosian palimpsest),
                    the original sound (from <hi rend="italic">vos)</hi> occurs, which must have
                    been universal in popular speech, since it reappears in Late Latin and all the
                    Romance languages—Ital. <hi rend="italic">vostro,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >votre,</hi> &amp;c. There was a tradition that Scipio Africanus had been the
                    first to spell these words with <hi rend="italic">e</hi> (Quint., i. 7, 25).
                    Here Umbrian distinguished between <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic"> o,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">vestra, eoιxrtu</hi> (pres.), but
                    <hi rend="italic">covortzιs</hi> (perf.); Lat. <hi rend="italic">vorsare</hi> is
                    perhaps Span. <hi rend="italic">vosar, bosar,</hi> “to vomit”; in other words
                    <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is now universal.</p>
                <p>17. <hi rend="italic">U</hi> occurred for <hi rend="italic">i</hi> before
                    labials; but the old <hi rend="italic">optumo</hi> has scarcely left any trace,
                    yet Ital. has <hi rend="italic">menοmo</hi> besides <hi rend="italic"
                    >minimo.</hi> Later <hi rend="italic">u</hi> was pronounced with the sound of
                    <hi rend="italic">ii,</hi> Gr. <hi rend="italic">υ,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">
                    u,,</hi> which at last was turned into <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> as in <hi
                    rend="italic">optimus,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">ottimx.</hi> But in some few
                    words the old popular form has survived— <hi rend="italic"> stupula,</hi> Ital.
                    <hi rend="italic">st6ppia,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"> étouble,</hi> “stubble,”
                    <hi rend="italic">dissupare,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">sciupare.</hi></p>
                <p>18. <hi rend="italic">U</hi> stands for <hi rend="italic">o—“Frundes,
                    fiuntes</hi> vetustissimi; quae tarnen a primoribus repudiata sunt, quasi
                    rustico more dicta” (Prise.)— contrary to the general rule (see 15). Spellings
                    like <hi rend="italic">muns, muntem, fiuntem</hi> abound in Late Latin, as <hi
                    rend="italic"> puntifiex</hi> (already in 98 a.d.), <hi rend="italic"
                    >∑eπτοpουvτιιρ</hi> (Plut., <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> 100); whence Old Fr. and
                    Old Eng. <hi rend="italic">muηt,</hi> “mount,” Ital. <hi rend="italic"> m6nte,
                    p6nte, fi6nte</hi> with close <hi rend="italic">o.</hi> In Sienese we have even
                    <hi rend="italic">pognxre, poηto,</hi> Ital. and Florentine <hi rend="italic"
                    >pugnere, punto</hi> (pungere, pùnctum); the connexion, however, of <hi
                    rend="italic">ό</hi> with Old Latm <hi rend="italic"> u</hi> is doubtful.</p>
                <p>19. Greek u was pronounced <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bruges Φρbyes, Rurrus, purpmra, gubernum, gιdernare, (nιpressus,—</hi> the last
                    four also classical; otherwise the classical age adopted the Greek sound <hi
                    rend="italic">y,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">Cyprus.</hi> In popular Latin the
                    old sound remained, and <hi rend="italic">u</hi> was sometimes (before <hi
                    rend="italic">r,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">fiore)</hi> even changed into <hi
                    rend="italic">o,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">storαx</hi> (Ter.), <hi
                    rend="italic">aneora</hi> (Naevius). In Low Latin n is frequent: <hi
                    rend="italic">cuprum,</hi> “copper,” for which Pliny used <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cyρriurn</hi> (αes); comp, <hi rend="italic">bursa,</hi> Ital. bôrsa, Fr.
                    bourse, <hi rend="italic">crupta,</hi> Ital. grotta, <hi rend="italic"
                    >tumba,</hi> Ital. tomba, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>In popular Latin there was a general tendency to contract the old diphthongs, in
                    accordance with Umbrian and North Latin.</p>
                <p>20. <hi rend="italic">Au</hi> in North Latin began very early to be contracted
                    into long openo, as <hi rend="italic">Rola</hi> (inscr. Picen., 218 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>). In Umbrian this is a constant law— <hi
                    rend="italic">ote</hi> aut, Ital. <hi rend="italic"> b,</hi> Umb. Zorιt tauros,
                    Ital. <hi rend="italic">tbro,</hi> &amp;c. The only form of the oldest Roman
                    Latin was <hi rend="italic">au,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Taurasia,
                    CP)aulla</hi> (T. Scip.), <hi rend="italic"> Claudi</hi> (Bacch.). When the
                    Umbrian poet whose provincial name was Plot(u)s settled in Rome in the latter
                    half of the 3d century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> his name was Latinized
                    into Plautus. Meanwhile the North Latin ô began to penetrate into Latium as
                    rustic, vulgar, and familiar; Cato and Varro often use it in their books <hi
                    rend="italic">De Re Rustieα,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">coles</hi> (Cato), <hi
                    rend="italic">colis, orata</hi> (Varro): “<hi rend="italic"> Orata</hi> genus
                    piscis appellatur a colore auri, quod rustici <hi rend="italic">orum</hi>
                    dicebant, ut auriculas, <hi rend="italic">amendas”</hi> (Fest.). But in the
                    classical age there was a good deal of reaction against this vulgarism, and
                    there is a well-known anecdote of Mestrius Floras warning the emperor Vespasian
                    against saying <hi rend="italic">plostra,</hi> and being next day facetiously
                    greeted by the emperor as <hi rend="italic"> Flaurus</hi> (Suet., <hi
                    rend="italic">Vesρ.,</hi> 22). At Pompeii</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n687/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0687-0664"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">copo</hi> took the place of <hi rend="italic">cauρo,
                    o(p')scultat</hi> of <hi rend="italic">auscultai.</hi> It is scarcely possible
                    to fix the precise period at which ô for <hi rend="italic">an</hi> became
                    general with the upper classes; but, as it was never changed into <hi
                    rend="italic"> ub</hi> like the original open o, the general contraction of <hi
                    rend="italic">au</hi> is probably later than that of <hi rend="italic"> ae</hi>
                    to <hi rend="italic">è,</hi> which was accomplished about the time of the
                    introduction of Christianity. That the contracted sound is open o, not closed,
                    may be inferred from the Italian ύ in <hi rend="italic">oro, tοro, cosa,
                    poveτo,</hi> in Old French <hi rend="italic">chbse, pbvre,</hi> as is shown by
                    the rhymes, only in Mod. Fr. <hi rend="italic">ch6se, pdvre</hi> (etymologically
                    spelt <hi rend="italic">pauvre).</hi> The Eng. cause, sauce, <hi rend="italic"
                    >poverty,</hi> have kept the Old French sound; the Spanish forms are cosα, <hi
                    rend="italic">oro, pobre.</hi> The old diphthongal pronunciation of <hi
                    rend="italic">au</hi> was never quite lost, but preserved in literary tradition
                    all through the Middle Ages, as in Italian and Spanish literary words like <hi
                    rend="italic">causa.</hi> It even appears to have been popular in some Roman
                    provinces, judging from the Prov. <hi rend="italic">ρaubre, causa,</hi> in Mod.
                    Prov. <hi rend="italic">c6uzο</hi> (spelt by the French “coouso”), and the
                    Portug. <hi rend="italic">ouro, causa</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">oirο,
                    coisa).</hi> Even Fr. <hi rend="italic">chose, chou</hi> presuppose <hi
                    rend="italic">causa, caulis,</hi> not <hi rend="italic"> cosa, eοlis.</hi> In
                    Italian, words like <hi rend="italic">cavolo,</hi> “cabbage,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Paolo,</hi> “Paul,” are rare exceptions. It is to be especially noted that <hi
                    rend="italic">cauda</hi> seems to be false, <hi rend="italic">coda</hi> being
                    the correct Latin form, which is corroborated by Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >c6da</hi> with close <hi rend="italic"> o.</hi> Some philologists, however,
                    think <hi rend="italic">6</hi> is the old contraction, unconnected with ά.</p>
                <p>21. <hi rend="italic">Ae,</hi> oldest form <hi rend="italic">ai,</hi> occurs very
                    early, as in <hi rend="italic">axs, praedad</hi> (Col. Rostr.), and was general
                    at the time of the Gracchi. The difference between <hi rend="italic">ai</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">ae</hi> is really very slight, the sound of <hi rend="italic">
                    i</hi> being open, which is very near “raised c” (both vowels occur in Eng. <hi
                    rend="italic">pity').</hi> The pronunciation must have been essentially the same
                    as in the Osc. <hi rend="italic">aι,</hi> which in the Latin transcription of
                    the Tab. Bantina wavers between <hi rend="italic">ai</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >ax.</hi> The contraction of <hi rend="italic">ax</hi> into é first occurs in
                    the north, where it was constant, for example Umb. <hi rend="italic"> kvestur,
                    pre, mestro</hi> magistra, dat. <hi rend="italic">ase</hi> arae; North Latin—
                    Fal. <hi rend="italic">ρretbοr), Cesilia;</hi> T. Pis. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cesula;</hi> Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Quxeili (= Cecili</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic">Caecilii), Cηevia</hi> Gnaevia, Gnaeja, &amp;c. From the north it
                    spread to Latium, where it first occurs as a rustic pronunciation scoffed at by
                    Lucilius, as quoted by Varro: “Rustici Pappum <hi rend="italic">Mesium,</hi> non
                    <hi rend="italic">Maxsium,</hi> a quo Lucilius scribit— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cecilius Fretσr</hi> ne rusticus fiat.” “In Latio rure <hi rend="italic"
                    >edus,</hi> in urbe <hi rend="italic"> axdus"</hi> (Varro). We finde for <hi
                    rend="italic">ax</hi> quite commonly used in the vulgar dialect of the 1st
                    century A.D.,—at Pompeii <hi rend="italic">letus, queres, elate, presto, tabule,
                    qux.</hi> In Rome <hi rend="italic">e</hi> became the pronunciation of the upper
                    classes only in the Christian period, 3d and 4th centuries, as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Emiliano, φe∖eιe</hi> = filiae (inscr. 3d century), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cesar</hi> (4th century). Servius (4th century) says “2 is pronounced almost
                    like ae,” that is, with the same sound, only shorter (at least in theory), <hi
                    rend="italic">equus</hi> like <hi rend="italic">axquus.</hi></p>
                <p>22. In Old Latin compound words often did not soften their radical vowel; the
                    preposition being then an adverb, and each word having a distinct stress, the
                    compound was separable, as in manum <hi rend="italic">endxjaeito</hi> (XII.
                    Tables) = injicito; <hi rend="italic">ob vossacro,</hi> vosobsecro, and <hi
                    rend="italic"> sub vos placo,</hi> vos supplico, in ancient prayers; <hi
                    rend="italic"> transqux dato =</hi> “et tradito,” in ancient laws. This was
                    imitated by classic poets (tmesis)— <hi rend="italic">vιqux ligatus</hi>
                    (Virg.). Only some of these separable compounds continued later on, such as the
                    intensifying <hi rend="italic">per,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">per ecastor
                    seitus</hi> (Ter.), nobis ista sunt pergrata <hi rend="italic">perqτce
                    juxunda</hi> (Cic., <hi rend="italic">De Or.), per</hi> mihi <hi rend="italic">
                    mirum</hi> visum est (Cic., <hi rend="italic">ibfi,</hi> Platoni <hi
                    rend="italic">per</hi> fuit <hi rend="italic">familiaris</hi> (Gellius).
                    Instances of the unchanged vowel in verbs— écquid placeant, mé rogas? immo vero
                    hercle <hi rend="italic">pérplaxent</hi> (Plaut.), and ea mihi <hi rend="italic"
                    > perplaxet</hi> (Cic.), to which correspond exactly the Old Fr. par <hi
                    rend="italic">est bons, par me plaist.</hi> While the older Latin accentuation
                    was <hi rend="italic">dffakim, ddmodurn,</hi> these words seem at the time of
                    Gellius to have been pronounced <hi rend="italic">affdtim, adm6dum.</hi> We have
                    here a first step towards the modern system of accenting the last element of
                    compounds; comp, the modern Comasco <hi rend="italic">ammb,</hi> Roum. <hi
                    rend="italic">amù,</hi> “just now.” <hi rend="italic">Quo modο</hi> is continued
                    in Ital. cowιc, but is formed anew in the dialectic <hi rend="italic"> eom6dx,
                    cmbd.</hi> In Late Latin and Romance the old system reappears unimpaired; many
                    of the old compounds, having been lost in popular speech, were formed anew with
                    stress on the last element and unchanged vowel: for instance, class, <hi
                    rend="italic">displieet,</hi> vulg. <hi rend="italic"> displdxet,</hi> Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">disρidxe,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic"> despldee,</hi> Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">déplaît</hi>; class. <hi rend="italic">dxcuUt,</hi> vulg. αccddeζ
                    Ital. <hi rend="italic">αccdde</hi> (inf. <hi rend="italic">axcadére);
                    rélégo</hi> becomes Ital. <hi rend="italic">rileggo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p>23. Stress, which in Old Latin was often farther from the end than in classical
                    Latin, seems early to have become pretty strong,</p>
                <p>. so as to induce the voice to hurry over unaccented syllables even though they
                    were long by position (see Latin), as <hi rend="italic">magistratus,
                    ministerium, rotwιtαte,</hi> in Plautus, where <hi rend="italic">st,nt</hi> were
                    pronounced as quickly as in Eng. <hi rend="italic">voluntary, magistrate.</hi>
                    The vowels, too, were hurried over; that <hi rend="italic"> fiériéstra</hi> was
                    pronounced as <hi rend="italic">fieristra</hi> is corroborated by the Ennian <hi
                    rend="italic">fiestra</hi> =fe <hi rend="superscript">n</hi> stra,—comp. Ital.
                    <hi rend="italic">mestiero =</hi> ministerium. Scansions like <hi rend="italic"
                    >sαgUtis, simlllurnax</hi> show that double consonants might count as long or
                    short; position was not regarded so nicely as in Greek till the classical age.
                    The real reason may have been the stress on the first syllable. In accented
                    syllables double consonants cannot have been really short, considering the full
                    length of Italian‘double consonants in <hi rend="italic">bello, anno,
                    saétta,</hi> &amp;c. Likewise final vowels of iambic words were shortened, as
                    <hi rend="italic"> novo, habe, ρuta, bene, homo</hi> (see Latin). This is
                    important, as marking the first step towards the Romance levelling of the old
                    quantities.</p>
                <p>This tendency, too, was carefully restrained during the classical age, but
                    reappears early in the post-classical period. Another effect of the strong
                    popular stress is the pronunciation of <hi rend="italic">i</hi> before vowels as
                    a consonant; thus words like <hi rend="italic">fiilTus</hi> in Plautus often
                    count as two syllables, <hi rend="italic">filjus (fi =</hi> Eng. y).^ This is
                    evidently the preparatory stage to the Romance <hi rend="italic">figlio,</hi>
                    &amp;c., with palatal <hi rend="italic">l,—l</hi> and <hi rend="italic">j</hi>
                    having been fused into one sound. This pronunciation, too, was carefully
                    suppressed by the classics.</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi> We append, in chronological order, a brief
                    selection of archaic words, disused, vulgar, colloquial, or used with a
                    disparaging sense, in the classical age, but reappearing later as quite usual
                    and dignified expressions. The many modern derivatives should be noticed.</p>
                <p>Lιvιus Andronicus (c. 240 b.c.): <hi rend="italic">sortus</hi> surrectus, Ital.
                    sorto, sortire, Fr. sortir de l’eau. Plautus (254-184): <hi rend="italic">
                    bucca,</hi> “mouth” (fam. Cic.), bucca panis (Petron.), Ital. bocca, Fr. bouche;
                    «ιίηα- <hi rend="italic">ciax,</hi> “threats,” Ital. minaccia, Fr. menace; <hi
                    rend="italic">calceolarius,</hi> “shoemaker,” Ital. calzolaio. Diminutives— <hi
                    rend="italic">vidulus, vid ’ lus,</hi> “wallet,” Ital. valigia (*vid ’ litia,
                    Diez), Fr. valise; <hi rend="italic">auricula,</hi> Ital. orecchia, Fr. oreille;
                    <hi rend="italic"> apicuda,</hi> Fr. abeille; <hi rend="italic">hιscinwla,</hi>
                    Ital. usignuδlo, rosi-gnuδlo, Fr. rossignol; <hi rend="italic">sororcula,</hi>
                    Ital. sirocchia, commonly sorella; <hi rend="italic">vitxllus,</hi> Ital.
                    vitello, Fr. veau, Eng. veal; <hi rend="italic">agnellus,</hi> Ital. agnello,
                    Fr. agneau; <hi rend="italic">ρutillus,</hi> “little boy,” Ital. putello <hi
                    rend="italic">(pudus</hi> fam. for <hi rend="italic"> puer,</hi> Virg.).
                    Adjectives— <hi rend="italic">bellus</hi> (later fam. Cic.)—the Romance <hi
                    rend="italic">bello</hi> has quite superseded <hi rend="italic">pulchxr;
                    minutus,</hi> “small,” populus <hi rend="italic"> minutus</hi> (Petron.) = Fr.
                    le <hi rend="italic">menu</hi> peuple; <hi rend="italic">rivalis,</hi>
                    originally a law term, figuratively of a rival in love (class, <hi rend="italic"
                    >aemulus</hi>; fam. Cic.); <hi rend="italic">cFriacus,</hi> “drunk,” Ital.
                    ubbriâco; <hi rend="italic"> suxidus,</hi> “juicy,” “dirty,” Ital. sιicido,
                    sιidicio, Span, sιicio. Verbs— <hi rend="italic">ambulare,</hi> “walk,” “go,”
                    familiar in all ages, lienee according to Dr. Vilh. Thomsen the Romance <hi
                    rend="italic"> andare, aller,</hi> Roum. <hi rend="italic">umbld,</hi> Ladino
                    <hi rend="italic"> amnar; bajulare, <hi rend="superscript">ii</hi> carry,”
                    bαjulus,</hi> “carrier,” L. Lat. “educator,” Ital. <hi rend="italic">bdlio,</hi>
                    “steward,” <hi rend="italic">bdlia,</hi> “nurse,” Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >bailler,</hi> “reach,” “give”; <hi rend="italic">manduxus,</hi> “glutton,” <hi
                    rend="italic">manducare,</hi> “chew,” “eat,” frequent in Old Latin—the emperor
                    Augustus wrote familiarly <hi rend="italic">mandτιcavi duas bucceas=</hi> I tai.
                    mangiai due bocconi—in the Vulgate <hi rend="italic">manducat</hi> et bibit,
                    Ital. mangiare, Fr. manger; <hi rend="italic">auscultare, “</hi> listen” (once
                    Cic., mihi <hi rend="italic">ausculta),</hi> Ital. ascoltare, Span, escuchar,
                    Fr. écouter; <hi rend="italic">cantare,</hi> frequent in Old and classical
                    Latin, the only word in Romance <hi rend="italic"> beanere</hi> has been lost);
                    <hi rend="italic">adjutare,</hi> Ital. ajutare, Fr. aider <hi rend="italic"
                    >iαdjuvarc</hi> lost); <hi rend="italic"> exradixare, eradieare,</hi> Ital.
                    sradicare, Fr. arracher; <hi rend="italic">mendieare,</hi> Ital. mendi-care, Fr.
                    mendier; <hi rend="italic"> batuere, battιcere,</hi> “strike,” Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">bdttere,</hi> Fr. battre <hi rend="italic">{fidtto</hi> from <hi
                    rend="italic"> battuo),</hi> L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">battualia,</hi> Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">battaglia,</hi> Fr. bataille; <hi rend="italic">muttire,</hi>
                    “mutter”—palam <hi rend="italic">mutire,</hi> “speak” (Ennius)— L. Lat. subst.
                    <hi rend="italic">muttum</hi> nullum emiseris, “not a word,” Ital. motto, Fr.
                    mot; <hi rend="italic">sapere,</hi> “understand”—sometimes very near to the
                    modern sense, <hi rend="italic">sapit</hi> scelesta multum (Plaut. )=Ital. la
                    scellerata sa molto, nullam rem <hi rend="italic"> saρis=</hi> Ital. non sai
                    nulla—Ital. <hi rend="italic">sapére,</hi> Span, sabér, Fr. savoir; <hi
                    rend="italic">crnnedxre,</hi> “eat” (Cic. fam.), <hi rend="italic">comedere</hi>
                    numos = Fr. manger son argent, Span, comér; <hi rend="italic">despoliare</hi>
                    (Cic., <hi rend="italic"> Ep.</hi>; Liv. once), Ital. spogliare, Fr. dépouiller;
                    <hi rend="italic"> comparare,</hi> “to procure,” later “to buy” (Suet.), Ital.
                    comprare. Greek words— <hi rend="italic">cοlaphus (eolαρus),</hi> “buffet,” “box
                    on the ear” (fam. Quint., Plin.), <hi rend="italic">ρercolo-pabant</hi>
                    (Petron.), L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">eοlpus,</hi> Ital. colpo, Fr. coup. Ennius
                    (239-169): <hi rend="italic">civitas,</hi> “city” (reappears in Petronius and
                    later), Ital. città, Fr. cité, Eng. city; <hi rend="italic">campsare,</hi>
                    “double (a cape),” a ⅛7τα⅛ <hi rend="italic">∖eyοuevοv,</hi> recognized by Diez
                    in the Ital. <hi rend="italic">{s)cansare,</hi> “to avoid”; <hi rend="italic"
                    >nitidare,</hi> Ital. nettare; <hi rend="italic">ρetra,</hi> “rock,” frequent in
                    Pliny and later —in the Vulgate tu es <hi rend="italic"> Fetrns,</hi> et super
                    hanc <hi rend="italic">Retram</hi> aedificabo ecclesiam meam—Ital. piètra, Fr.
                    pierre. Cato (234-149): <hi rend="italic"> nascere</hi> nasci, Ital. nascere,
                    Fr. naître; <hi rend="italic"> firacidτιs,</hi> “mellow,” “damaged (olives),”
                    Ital. <hi rend="italic"> firdxido, firadicio,</hi> “rotten.” Pacuvius (219-129):
                    <hi rend="italic"> causari,</hi> “to plead,” not classical, reappears in the
                    Silver Age in the sense of pleading as an excuse, still later in that of
                    disputing, discussing, Fr. <hi rend="italic">causer,</hi> “to chat, talk”; comp.
                    Ladino <hi rend="italic">plidar</hi> (plead), “to speak.” Lucilius (c. 148-103):
                    <hi rend="italic">acceptor</hi> for <hi rend="italic">aedpiter,</hi> “a hawk,”
                    frequent in Low Latin, Ital. astôre, Fr. autour; <hi rend="italic">
                    quiritare,</hi> “cry ”—ut <hi rend="italic">quiritαre</hi> urbanorum, <hi
                    rend="italic">Acjubilare</hi> rusticorum est (Varro; fam. Cic.)—Ital. gridare,
                    Fr. crier. Greek words— <hi rend="italic">gubernum,</hi> “rudder,” Ital.
                    governo; <hi rend="italic">sehxdium,</hi> “improvised or unpolished poem,” Ital.
                    <hi rend="italic">sehizzo,</hi> “sketch”; <hi rend="italic"> caballus,</hi>
                    “jade,” seems first to occur here—optât arare <hi rend="italic">caballus</hi>
                    (Hor.)—later “horse,” “steed,” Ital. cavallo, Span, caballo, Fr. cheval, L. Lat.
                    <hi rend="italic">caballarius,</hi> “chevalier,” “knight”; <hi rend="italic"
                    >cyma,</hi> “young sprout of cabbage” (later Plin., Colum.), Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">cima,</hi> “top.” Q. Claudius Quadrigarius —Gellius blames several
                    expressions of his as vulgar or rare: <hi rend="italic">diurnare</hi> diu
                    vivere, comp. Ital. soggiornare, Fr. séjourner, Eng. sojourn, and aggiornare,
                    ajourner, adjourn; <hi rend="italic"> arboretum,</hi> “grove,” Ital. arboreto,
                    Span, arboleda. Varro (116-28), especially in <hi rend="italic">De Re Rustica:
                    belare</hi> balare, Ital. belare, Fr. bêler; <hi rend="italic">olor</hi> odor,
                    Span, olor; <hi rend="italic">capitium,</hi> “bodice,” Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >capezzale,</hi> “cape,” “pillow”; <hi rend="italic">ηervium =</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">veυριοι&gt;,</hi> Span, nérvio; <hi rend="italic">rubeus,</hi>
                    “red” (later Colum., Pallad.), Fr. rouge, Span, <hi rend="italic"> rùbio,</hi>
                    “fair”; <hi rend="italic">badius,</hi> “bay (horse),” a rare word, Ital. bajo,
                    Fr. bai. Laberius (105-43) is blamed by Gellius for using obsolete, rare, and
                    vulgar words: <hi rend="italic">lavandaria</hi> lavanda, later “laundress,”
                    Ital. lavandaja; <hi rend="italic"> gurdus,</hi> “stupid,” a Spanish word, says
                    Quintilian, and in fact we find Old Span.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n688/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0688-0665"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">gordo,</hi> “stupid," Mod. Span, “fat,”—comp, <hi rend="italic"
                    > pinguis</hi> Minerva; <hi rend="italic">pittaeium,</hi> “patch,” “label,” <hi
                    rend="italic">= πvrτ&lt;iιaοv,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic"> ρedazo,</hi>
                    “piece”; <hi rend="italic">nanus,</hi> “dwarf," = j'cwos, Ital. nano, Fr. nain;
                    <hi rend="italic">botulus,</hi> “sausage" (also Petron.), dim. <hi rend="italic"
                    >bοtellus</hi> (Martial), later = “bowels,” Ital. budello, plur. budella, Fr.
                    boyaux. Lucretius (94-55): <hi rend="italic">baubare,</hi> “bark,” Ital.
                    abbajare, Fr. aboyer, Eng. bay; <hi rend="italic">russus,</hi> “red”— a rare
                    word, <hi rend="italic">russa</hi> gingiva (Catull. ), mentioned as usual by
                    Gellius —I tai. <hi rend="italic"> r6sso,</hi> “red,” Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >roux, rousse,</hi> “red-haired.” Old words mentioned by Grammarians: <hi
                    rend="italic">burrus</hi> (see 11, above); <hi rend="italic">artitus=-</hi>
                    bonis instructus artibus, Prov. <hi rend="italic">artisia,</hi> “trade,” Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic"> artisan·, gluto</hi> (Fest.), <hi rend="italic">glu,tto</hi>
                    (Persius and later), Ital. ghiottone, Fr. glouton (comp. Lat. <hi rend="italic">
                    glut glut,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">glouglou); ρlanea</hi> tabula plana, Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">planche,</hi> Eng. plank; <hi rend="italic"> sarpere</hi>
                    putare, “to imp,” Fr. <hi rend="italic">serpe,</hi> “pruning knife."</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="italic">Grammar</hi> (Plautine, when no author quoted).—Gender: <hi
                    rend="italic">coUus</hi> collum, Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">cols,</hi> now <hi
                    rend="italic">eou; dor sus,</hi> &amp;c. Declensions: <hi rend="italic">
                    lade</hi> lac, I tai. latte (Petron. unum <hi rend="italic">laetem</hi>
                    biberunt); <hi rend="italic">vasum,</hi> Umb. <hi rend="italic"> vaso(r),</hi>
                    Ital. vaso; <hi rend="italic">ossum,</hi> Ital. osso, Fr. os; <hi rend="italic"
                    >pauper,-a,-um</hi> (also Petron. ), Ital. povero. Comparison: <hi rend="italic"
                    >magis</hi> pulcer = Span. <hi rend="italic"> mas</hi> hermoso; even <hi
                    rend="italic">magis majores,</hi> as vulg. Ital. <hi rend="italic">ρiiι
                    meglio,</hi> vulg. Fr. <hi rend="italic"> plus meilleur,</hi> vulg. Eng. <hi
                    rend="italic">more better (er).</hi> The ordinary Romance formation with <hi
                    rend="italic">plus</hi> only appears in the 3d period. With ego <hi
                    rend="italic">ipsissumus,</hi> “my very self,” comp, <hi rend="italic"
                    >ipsimus,</hi> “himself,” <hi rend="italic">ix.,</hi> the master of the house
                    (Petron.). Out of <hi rend="italic">(ρgp)md-iρsimυs</hi> grew Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">medesimo,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic">mismo,</hi> Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">même.</hi> Pronouns: dat. fern, <hi rend="italic">illae</hi> for
                    illî, Ital. <hi rend="italic">le</hi>; eccRm = ecce eum, Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >eeeo—</hi> pater eccwmadvenit= <hi rend="italic">eeeo</hi> ehe viene il padre;
                    <hi rend="italic">eeeiste,</hi> eccZsZα = Old Fr. cist, ceste, Mod. Fr. ce, cet,
                    cette; <hi rend="italic">eeeille, eeeilla =</hi> Old Fr. cil, cele, Mod. Fr.
                    celui, celle. In Italian these were replaced by <hi rend="italic">eeeum
                    istum,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">questo,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> eeeum
                    ilium,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">quello,</hi> analogous to the Plautine <hi
                    rend="italic">eeeum ipsum, eeeam eampse, kx.; quotumus,</hi> “which of the
                    number”— <hi rend="italic">quotumo</hi> die hue pervenisti? Ital. lavorare a <hi
                    rend="italic">eöttimo,</hi> “work by the job.” <hi rend="italic">Unus</hi>
                    indefinite was sometimes very like the modern indefinite article—Huic filia <hi
                    rend="italic">una</hi> est, “he has a daughter,” Ital. quest’uomo ha wnα figlia.
                    <hi rend="italic">Ille</hi> was sometimes used very like the modern definite
                    article—Imponit geminorum alterum in nave pater, <hi rend="italic">ilium</hi>
                    reliquit <hi rend="italic">alterum</hi> apud matrem domi, Ital. lasciδ <hi
                    rend="italic">l'altro</hi> colla madré a casa. Note also <hi rend="italic"
                    >ηatus</hi> nemo in aedibus, “not a living soul,” “not a mother’s son,” Span,
                    <hi rend="italic">nαeiie,</hi> “nobody,” likewise from <hi rend="italic"
                    >nata</hi> (res), Span, <hi rend="italic">nada,</hi> “nothing,” whereas the
                    Catalan prefers <hi rend="italic"> res,</hi> Prov. <hi rend="italic">ren,
                    re,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"> rien</hi> (rem). <hi rend="italic">Homo</hi> is
                    sometimes like an indefinite pronoun—Nequior nemo, quisquamst, quern <hi
                    rend="italic">homo</hi> aut amet aut adeat, Fr. <hi rend="italic">on.</hi>
                    Verbs: <hi rend="italic"> moriri</hi> mori, Ital. <hi rend="italic">morire,</hi>
                    Fr. mourir. Active for deponent— <hi rend="italic">joeare,</hi> Ital. giocare,
                    Fr. jouer, <hi rend="italic">part ire</hi> = I tai.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >fabu,lare,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic">hablar.</hi> Perfects in <hi
                    rend="italic"> si—-parsi,</hi> prae- <hi rend="italic">morsi,</hi> Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">morsi</hi>; the formation in <hi rend="italic">si</hi> greatly
                    increased in Romance. <hi rend="italic">Habere</hi> with past part, often
                    approaches to modern compound tenses, Res omnis <hi rend="italic">relidas
                    habeo,</hi> Ital. ho lasciato tutto. Adverbs: <hi rend="italic">A liorsum</hi>
                    ire for alio, Prov. alhors, Fr. ailleurs. Prepositions: <hi rend="italic">
                    de</hi> for genitive, dimidium <hi rend="italic">de praeda</hi> mihi dare, Ital.
                    la meta del bottino; mZ for dative, te <hi rend="italic"> ad patrem</hi> esse
                    mortuom re-nuntiem, Ital. dire <hi rend="italic">al padre; cum</hi>
                    instrumental, <hi rend="italic">eum</hi> virgis caseum rädere, ItaL <hi
                    rend="italic">eon; de</hi> instr., quam ilia <hi rend="italic"> de meis
                    opulentiis</hi> fiat pro-pensior, Ital. <hi rend="italic"> di.</hi> Peculiar
                    local uses are <hi rend="italic">in</hi> Ephesum ire, <hi rend="italic">in</hi>
                    Epheso esse, <hi rend="italic">ab domo, “</hi> from home,” <hi rend="italic">ex
                    Epheso, “</hi> from Ephesus ”; <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi> from (at) one’s house,
                    as Esne tu <hi rend="italic"> ab illo milite,</hi> servus ejus = from (at) the
                    soldier’s, foris concrepuit <hi rend="italic">a vieino sene,</hi> Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic"> dal soldato, dal veeehio vieino</hi><hi rend="italic">Syntax and
                    Phraseology.—</hi> Pater tuus <hi rend="italic">is</hi> erat patruelis meus;
                    comp. Fr. le père est-ZZ, Ital. il padre <hi rend="italic"> lo</hi> conosco.
                    Pone aedem <hi rend="italic">ibi sunt</hi> homines, Ital. <hi rend="italic">vi
                    sono</hi> degli uomini. Scio jam quid <hi rend="italic">vis</hi> dicere, Ital.
                    so (quel) ehe <hi rend="italic">vuoi</hi> dire. <hi rend="italic">Ne time, ne
                    fae,</hi> Fr. ne fais pas cela. <hi rend="italic">Totus</hi> gaudeo, <hi
                    rend="italic">tota</hi> sum misera, even Cic. falsum est id <hi rend="italic"
                    >totum,</hi> “it is all false,” Ital. è tutto falso, son tutta contenta, Fr.
                    elle est toute joyeuse. <hi rend="italic"> Multum</hi> miseri, even Cic. fam.
                    <hi rend="italic">multum</hi> bonus, Ital. molto buono, Span, muy bueno, Port,
                    muito born. <hi rend="italic"> Bene</hi> morigerus (Plaut.), <hi rend="italic"
                    >bene</hi> saepe (Enn.), <hi rend="italic">bene</hi> mane (Cic.), Ital. ben
                    bene, ben tosto, Fr. bien bon, bientôt, bien souvent. <hi rend="italic">Bene
                    velle alieui,</hi> Ital. voler bene ad alcuno. Epityrum estur <hi rend="italic"
                    >insane bene</hi> (Plaut. ), showing that the <hi rend="italic">furieusement
                    bien</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Précieuses</hi> was no novelty. Aequo animo
                    <hi rend="italic">stare,</hi> Ital. star di buon animo; <hi rend="italic"
                    >stabam</hi> tanquam mortuus (Petron.), Ital. <hi rend="italic"> stava</hi> come
                    morto, <hi rend="italic">stare</hi> in letto, <hi rend="italic">star</hi>
                    seduto, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Dictum</hi> (αc) <hi rend="italic">factum</hi>
                    (Ter.), Ital. detto fatto, “said and done.” <hi rend="italic">Cum (bona)
                    gratia,</hi> “with a good grace” (Ter.), Fr. de bonne grâce. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Id restabat (deerat, ut),</hi> used ironically, (Ter.), It. questa mancava
                    aucora, Fr. il ne manquait (plus) que cela.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Second {Classical) Period·.</hi> 80 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi><hi rend="italic"> to</hi> 100 (150) a.d.</p>
                <p>At this time we begin to have an idea of what South Latin was, of which the chief
                    characteristics were—(1) its conservative character, supported by the antique
                    forms of the Oscan language; (2) its preferring <hi rend="italic">i</hi> to <hi
                    rend="italic">e,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">siηaturn, einsuerint, eintum, rim,
                    ris, diibus</hi> (Lex Jul.; Heraclea); <hi rend="italic"> nigatis, tenimus,
                    Lueritivs, dieembres, oeilli</hi> (Pompeii), ZeraZiZMω = Mod. Neap, <hi
                    rend="italic">tenimmo; fmιmiηte), siptim</hi> (Pute-oli); <hi rend="italic"
                    >venirandax</hi> (Nap.); later <hi rend="italic"> sieundo, siptim</hi> (Borgia,
                    386); (3) its preferring <hi rend="italic"> u</hi> to <hi rend="italic">o,</hi>
                    as in <hi rend="italic"> fτι,rtunilla, postera, aliu</hi> (Pompeii). These forms
                    are constant in Modern South Italian. Now classical</p>
                <p>Latin was an approach to South Latin, and there arose a strong reaction against
                    the vulgar North Latin forms. But even a purist like Cicero could not always
                    abstain from using colloquial forms, and he sometimes gives us precious
                    information about familiar pronunciations, as cun <hi rend="italic">nobis</hi>
                    for <hi rend="italic">eum nobis,</hi> showing the assimilation of <hi
                    rend="italic"> mn</hi> to <hi rend="italic">nn.</hi> He hesitates to use the new
                    word <hi rend="italic">medietas,</hi> which later became the ordinary
                    expression, Ital. meta, Span, mitad, Fr. moitié. Catullus has <hi rend="italic"
                    >involare,</hi> “steal,” Ital. involare, Fr. voler, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >basium,</hi> Ital. bacio (for <hi rend="italic">basio, bagio,</hi> like <hi
                    rend="italic">eaxio</hi> caseus), Span, beso, Fr. baiser, and the familiar
                    caressing <hi rend="italic">issa</hi> for <hi rend="italic">ipsa,</hi> Ital.
                    essa. He and Horace have <hi rend="italic">ρlatea, ‘ ‘</hi> street” (for platêa
                    = πλατεία), Ital. piazza, Fr. place. Vitruvius has <hi rend="italic">
                    octuaginta,</hi> Ital. ottanta, <hi rend="italic">aperegre</hi> = <hi
                    rend="superscript">,,</hi> from abroad,” and the Greek words <hi rend="italic">
                    chalare,</hi> Ital. calare, <hi rend="italic">zelus,</hi> Ital. geloso, Fr.
                    jaloux, and <hi rend="italic">sehidia,</hi> “wooden chip,” “splinter,” Ital.
                    scheggia. The transition from <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
                    >v</hi> begins, <hi rend="italic">triumphavit</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >-bit</hi> (Lex Jul. ). Gradually the popular speech undermined the classical
                    correctness of the brief Golden Age, and at the beginning of the empire again
                    rose to the surface. The emperor Augustus was fond of talking slang and bad
                    grammar, as <hi rend="italic">simus</hi> for <hi rend="italic"> sumus,</hi> and
                    he wrote as he spoke in his familiar letters, although he was very hard upon a
                    poor <hi rend="italic">legatus eonsularis</hi> for barbarously writing <hi
                    rend="italic">ixi</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">ipsi (fin&amp;ï., Aug.,</hi>
                    88; comp, <hi rend="italic"> proxirnus</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >propsimus).</hi></p>
                <p>At Pompeii and Herculaneum we find a town dialect fully developed, half South
                    Latin, half vulgar Roman. Final consonants were dropped, for instance <hi
                    rend="italic"> m</hi> in the acc. <hi rend="italic">puella, laudata; t</hi> in
                    the verse “quisquis <hi rend="italic">ama valia, peria</hi> qui <hi
                    rend="italic"> nosei</hi> (? = nescit) amare (Pomp. ); s rarely, <hi
                    rend="italic"> valea =</hi> valeas (Pomp. ). <hi rend="italic">II,</hi> the
                    right pronunciation of which had become a mark of education, just as in English
                    (Rusticus fit sermo, si aspires perperam; Nigid. Figulus), was constantly
                    dropped, as in <hi rend="italic">abeto, abuaerit</hi> (Pomp.), <hi rend="italic"
                    > abiat</hi> (Here.). <hi rend="italic">Nη</hi> took the place of <hi
                    rend="italic">nd: vereeuηnus</hi> (Pomp.), later <hi rend="italic">
                    innulgen.</hi> (Abella, 170 a.d.), <hi rend="italic">αgeηnae</hi> (Puteoli),
                    were generally Italic; comp. Umb. <hi rend="italic"> ρihαηer</hi> piandi <hi
                    rend="italic">(distennite, dispennite,</hi> Plaut. ), Ose. <hi rend="italic"
                    >opsannam</hi> operandam; now South Italian — Roman <hi rend="italic"
                    >monno,</hi> Neap. munno, Sicil. <hi rend="italic">munnu=</hi> Ital. mondo, Lat.
                    mundus. Ns was used for <hi rend="italic">es (x)</hi> as in words in <hi
                    rend="italic">-triss</hi> for <hi rend="italic">-true</hi> (Pomp.). Φ popularly
                    became <hi rend="italic"> p,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Aprodite,</hi> but with
                    those who tried to speak fine <hi rend="italic">f,</hi> just as they made the
                    Greek <hi rend="italic">υ</hi> an <hi rend="italic">i—Iαointus, Amarillis,
                    Dafne, Filetus,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">fisieo, fisonomia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi
                    rend="italic">E</hi> for <hi rend="italic">oe</hi> seems first to occur during
                    the empire, for example, <hi rend="italic">pomerii</hi> (8 <hi rend="italic"
                    >n.c.), ρomerium</hi> (49 a.d. ), <hi rend="italic">Phebιιs</hi> (Pomp.). There
                    is no certain evidence of the sound of Germ, <hi rend="italic">o,</hi> Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">eu;</hi> we see that the first vowel is absorbed by the second.
                    According to Diez, <hi rend="italic">oe</hi> becomes close <hi rend="italic">e,
                    ax</hi> open <hi rend="italic"> e,</hi> which is true for popular words like
                    Ital. <hi rend="italic">pena,</hi> Fr. peine, but untrue for Latinisms like <hi
                    rend="italic">fete, fèdo, amène), eèto, eommèdia, tragèdia, Fèbo, oe</hi> in Low
                    Lat. being constantly confounded with <hi rend="italic">ae.</hi> Original <hi
                    rend="italic"> oe</hi> never becomes <hi rend="italic">ie,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic"> ae</hi> does (cZeZo, <hi rend="italic">fieno).</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi> We remark at Pompeii <hi rend="italic"
                    >exmueeαvit</hi> emunxit, Ital. dial, <hi rend="italic">smoeeare,</hi> “snuff
                    (the candle)”; mi <hi rend="italic">similat,</hi> Ital. mi somiglia, Fr. il me
                    ressemble, elsewhere only in Late Latin. Petronius: <hi rend="italic">
                    bisaeeium,</hi> Ital. bisaccia, Fr. besace; <hi rend="italic">nxsapius,</hi>
                    “unwise,” Ital. sâvio, sâggio, Span, sâbio, Fr. sage; <hi rend="italic"
                    >berbex,</hi> Fr. brebis; <hi rend="italic">peduelus,</hi> Ital. pidocchio, Fr.
                    pou <hi rend="italic">(ρaηus</hi> facit diminutivum yxmwciiZa, Fest., Ital.
                    pannocchia—comp. L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">geηueulum, axucula,</hi> Ital.
                    ginocchio, agocchia, Span, hinojo, aguja, Fr. genou, aiguille); <hi
                    rend="italic"> striga,</hi> “witch,” Ital. strega; <hi rend="italic"
                    >fatuus,</hi> Fr. fat; basiavit me <hi rend="italic">sρissius,</hi> Ital.
                    spésso, “often.” Instances of Petronius’s grammar are— <hi rend="italic">virus,
                    eaelιιs,</hi> comp. Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">vins, ciels</hi>; jacebat tanquam
                    <hi rend="italic">bovis,</hi> Ital. bove, bue; hoc vetare nec <hi rend="italic">
                    Jovis</hi> potest (Old Lat. <hi rend="italic">Jovis pater=</hi> Jupiter), Ital.
                    Giove; munus <hi rend="italic">excellente,</hi> neuter, shows the L. Lat.
                    declension, Ital. eccellente; habet <hi rend="italic">wnele=i∖</hi> a de quoi
                    (vivre); unus <hi rend="italic">de nobis=</hi> uno di noi (see also Latin).
                    Pliny mentions <hi rend="italic">sanguisuga</hi> as vulgar for <hi rend="italic"
                    >hirudo,</hi> Ital. sanguisuga, Fr. sangsue; he has <hi rend="italic"
                    >gyτare</hi> = Ital. girare, “turn,” “roam about.” Persius (34-62) has <hi
                    rend="italic">stloρpo</hi> tumidas rumpere buccas, “a slap,” L. Lat. sclopus,
                    sclupare, Ital. schioppo, “gun.” Quintilian (c. 40-118): <hi rend="italic"
                    >5υvατοv</hi> quod nostri <hi rend="italic">possibile</hi> nominant, quae ut
                    dura videatur appellatio, tarnen sola est, Ital. possibile, &amp;c. Juvenal has
                    buccâ <hi rend="italic">foeulum</hi> excitât, Ital. fuoco, Fr. feu, and Tacitus
                    <hi rend="italic">spatha,</hi> Ital. spada, Fr. épée (see also Latin).</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="italic">Third {Post-Classical) Period·.</hi> 100 (150) <hi
                    rend="italic"> to</hi> 300 (350).</p>
                <p>This period is represented by the latest pagan inscriptions, by Gellius,
                    Apuleius, &amp;c. On the decay of classical Latin, see Latin. In pronunciation
                    only few decided changes appear.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> is inserted before s impurum, as <hi rend="italic">
                    iseripta</hi> (Afr., 197), <hi rend="italic">nστreLρeι,τω = ispirito</hi> (Rome,
                    269); later this was universal, but in Italian only after consonants— <hi
                    rend="italic">non ista</hi> (colloq. <hi rend="italic">non stà), in isρirito, in
                    iscrUto</hi>; Span, always, as espiritu, esta, escribir, escuela; Fr. esprit,
                    écrire, école.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Tt</hi> is put for <hi rend="italic">pt,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic"> Setemb.</hi> (Helvet., 219), <hi rend="italic">Setimus</hi>
                    (Afr., 3d century), later frequent. This assimilation originally came from the
                    north; comp. Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic">Nethunus (th=t),</hi> Etrus. <hi
                    rend="italic">Neθuns,</hi> Neptunus, Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Setχιmnal,</hi> Etrus. <hi rend="italic">Sehtmnal—</hi> Septimienâ nata</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n689/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0689-0666"/>
                <p>(inscr. biling.), <hi rend="italic">Setume, Setimi,</hi> Septimius, Umb. <hi
                    rend="italic"> scrcihtor, serehto,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">Settimo,
                    Xettuno, atto</hi> aptus, <hi rend="italic">cattivo, scritto.</hi></p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Tt</hi> takes the place of <hi rend="italic">et,</hi> as in
                    <hi rend="italic">Beneditus</hi> (204), <hi rend="italic">lattuea</hi> (Edict.
                    Diocl., 301). This too came from the north; <hi rend="italic">Vitoria</hi>
                    occurs on an ancient mirror, probably Etruscan. Comp. Umb. subahtu and <hi
                    rend="italic"> subator,</hi> formally = su bacti, <hi rend="italic">rehte</hi>
                    recte, where/;, originally sounded, had become mute or nearly so, which is
                    further proved by the spellings <hi rend="italic">anibrehtu, ambretu,</hi>
                    ambito, &amp;c.; comp, <hi rend="italic">tettvrn{e),</hi> probably = Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">tetto</hi> tectum, just as Ital. <hi rend="italic">retto</hi>
                    rectus, <hi rend="italic">atto</hi> actus, <hi rend="italic">otto</hi> octo, <hi
                    rend="italic">notte</hi> noctem. This change was restricted to Italy; elsewhere
                    <hi rend="italic">et</hi> became <hi rend="italic"> it,</hi> as Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">fait</hi> factum, Port, <hi rend="italic">feito,</hi> Span, <hi
                    rend="italic">hecho</hi> ( = *feitjo). Likewise <hi rend="italic">cs (x)</hi>
                    became in Italy ss, as in Lat. <hi rend="italic">eossim, vissit,</hi> elsewhere
                    <hi rend="italic">is,</hi> as Span, and Port, <hi rend="italic">seis,</hi> Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">cuisse, laisser.</hi></p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">G</hi> before a single <hi rend="italic">e, i</hi> becomes
                    palatal (like the old-fashioned Eng. <hi rend="italic">gyarden,</hi> &amp;c.) or
                    nearly y (Eng. <hi rend="italic">y</hi> in <hi rend="italic">yσu∖</hi> so that
                    both are confounded— <hi rend="italic">magestati</hi> (inscr. before 243); <hi
                    rend="italic">cogiugi,</hi> conjugi. The sign for <hi rend="italic">J</hi> in
                    the Gothic alphabet, taken from Latin <hi rend="italic"> G,</hi> shows the
                    pronunciation of the 4th century.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Xgη</hi> for <hi rend="italic">gη,</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                    > eongnato, singno,</hi> belongs perhaps to this period— <hi rend="italic">
                    connate,</hi> &amp;c., is also found—E. Ital. <hi rend="italic"> seng no,</hi>
                    now spelt <hi rend="italic">segno,</hi> with palatal <hi rend="italic">n,
                    degno</hi> dignus, <hi rend="italic">regno</hi> regnum, &amp;c., Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">digue,</hi> &amp;c.; sometimes n(τι), as in <hi rend="italic"
                    >eonôseere,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">connaître.</hi> There are traces of some
                    other transitions that appear to have been completed only in the next
                    period.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Apuleius has</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">sapidus,</hi> “savoury” (comp, insipidus), Old Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic"> sadx,</hi> whence Fr. <hi rend="italic">maτcssade</hi>
                    (mal-sade); <hi rend="italic">rnarsicare</hi> = Ital.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >follicare,</hi> “breathe” (like a bellows), Port, <hi rend="italic"
                    >folgar,</hi> J3pan. <hi rend="italic">holgar,</hi> “rest,” “lounge”; <hi
                    rend="italic"> masticare,</hi> Ital. masticare, Fr. mâcher; <hi rend="italic">
                    minari</hi> (equunι baculis), “threaten,” hence “drive,” Ital. menare, Fr.
                    mener; <hi rend="italic">cambiare</hi> (better than <hi rend="italic">
                    eambire),</hi> Ital. cambiare, Fr. changer; <hi rend="italic"> victηαlis</hi>
                    adj., in the 6th century subst. <hi rend="italic"> vietualia</hi> (nom. plur. ),
                    Old Fr. and E. Eng. <hi rend="italic"> vitaille,</hi> Eng. <hi rend="italic"
                    >vittles,</hi> spelt etymologically <hi rend="italic">victuals; aucilla,
                    aueella</hi> for <hi rend="italic"> avieella,</hi> the existence of which had
                    been denied by Varro, L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">aueellus,</hi> Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">uecello,</hi> poet, <hi rend="italic">augello,</hi> Prov. <hi
                    rend="italic"> auzels,</hi> Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">οisel,</hi> Mod. Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">oiseau.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Caelius Aurelianus (2d or 3d
                    century) has</hi><hi rend="italic">testa,</hi> “skull,” frequent in the 4th
                    century, I tai. <hi rend="italic"> testa,</hi> “head,” Fr. tête. Lampridius (c.
                    250): <hi rend="italic"> ρapilio =</hi> pavilion, ∕w∕∕icmMS, Ital. pulcino, Fr.
                    poussin; <hi rend="italic">pipio,</hi> “pigeon”; <hi rend="italic">]datea,</hi>
                    “place.” Tertullian, first Christian author: <hi rend="italic">rememorare,</hi>
                    “remember,” <hi rend="italic">aeternalie,</hi> “eternal,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >eompassio, “</hi> compassion,” and many other modernisms, such as <hi
                    rend="italic">plus miser=</hi> I tai. piu misero, Fr. plus miserable.
                    Diocletian: <hi rend="italic">fata,</hi> parca, Ital. fata, Fr. fée. Solinus (c.
                    3d century): <hi rend="italic">repatriare,</hi> “to repair (to).” Apicius (c. 3d
                    century): <hi rend="italic">exealdare,</hi> I tai. scaldare, Fr. échauder; <hi
                    rend="italic">spatula,</hi> ltal. spalla, Span, espalda, Fr. épaule.</p>
                <p>IV. <hi rend="italic">Fourth Period</hi>: 300 (350) <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 500
                    (550).</p>
                <p>This period extends from the introduction of Christianity to the Middle Ages and
                    the great migrations. Christianity marks an important epoch in the history of
                    the Romance languages. Pagan literature was abhorred, and classical traditions
                    lost. Popular speech got the upper hand; the gospel was preached to the people
                    in the people’s own language, and the New Testament translated into vulgar
                    Latin. Several phonetic changes which formerly had been wavering and uncertain
                    became rapidly fixed and decided. The whole language was revolutionized.</p>
                <p>1. Palatal <hi rend="italic">g οrj</hi> was developed into <hi rend="italic"
                    >dj</hi> (like <hi rend="italic">gy</hi> in Hung. <hi rend="italic">Magyar</hi>
                    =palatal <hi rend="italic">d</hi> + Eng. <hi rend="italic">y)</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">dzh</hi> (Eng. j), sometimes <hi rend="italic"> dz,</hi> and was
                    confounded with original <hi rend="italic">di—Zerax,</hi> Hierax (Cumae, 202);
                    Zoυλιoe (pagan inscr.), comp. <hi rend="italic"> Diuliali</hi> (568), <hi
                    rend="italic">Madias</hi> (364), also <hi rend="italic">Mazas =</hi> majas, <hi
                    rend="italic">Gianuaria</hi> (503), also <hi rend="italic">Zanuari,</hi> &amp;c.
                    Italian still retains the sound of <hi rend="italic">dzh</hi> in <hi
                    rend="italic">giungere</hi> jüngere, <hi rend="italic">Giove</hi> Jovem, <hi
                    rend="italic">gènere, giacére,</hi> &amp;c. Original <hi rend="italic">di</hi>
                    in <hi rend="italic"> Aziabenico</hi> (Afr., 195), <hi rend="italic"
                    >niedius,</hi> pronounced <hi rend="italic">medsius</hi> according to Servius
                    (4th century) and Consentius (5th century), Ital. <hi rend="italic">mezzo,</hi>
                    pronounced <hi rend="italic">med∙zo</hi> (but <hi rend="italic">giorno</hi> from
                    <hi rend="italic">diurnus).</hi><hi rend="italic">2. Ti was</hi> assibilated
                    before vowels; there are no certain pre-Christian instances. In the 4th century
                    the Gothic <hi rend="italic"> laiktjδ=</hi> lectio shows that the change had
                    only begun; <hi rend="italic"> ci</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ti</hi> were
                    sometimes confounded, as in κdλτtos calceus (Plut., c. 100; Ed. Diocl., 301),
                    <hi rend="italic"> ocio</hi> (Rome, 389); we have <hi rend="italic">ti</hi> for
                    <hi rend="italic">si</hi> in <hi rend="italic">aecletiae</hi> (early Christ,
                    inscr.). In the 5th century the change appears as fully accomplished; the
                    grammarian Pompeius (probably a Mauretanian) expressly teaches the pronunciation
                    <hi rend="italic">Titius</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Titsius,</hi> and Consentius
                    (a Gaul) <hi rend="italic">etiam</hi> as <hi rend="italic"> eziam, i.e.,
                    etsiam.</hi> In the 6th century we have the Gothic <hi rend="italic"
                    >kavtsjoη,</hi> cautionem. It is probable that this change too originally came
                    from the north, especially from Etruria, where it was very old: we have Etrus.
                    <hi rend="italic">Ventia Venza, Arηθia Arηza,</hi> Etrus. Lat. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vencsi, Vensius, Arnzius</hi> (while Umbrian has <hi rend="italic">tertio,
                    Martie,</hi> &amp;c. ), Mars. Lat. <hi rend="italic"> Martses,</hi> evidently
                    the source of the Latin <hi rend="italic"> Marsi.</hi> At length this
                    pronunciation reached the capital and became general, mostly expressed by <hi
                    rend="italic">c,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic"> eciarn, ter· eins, milieia,
                    justieia, staeio, ηacioηem,</hi> &amp;c. The pronunciation <hi rend="italic"
                    >ts</hi> is confirmed for Spain by Isidore in the 7th century. This sound is
                    still preserved by Italian in words like <hi rend="italic">piazza, grazia,
                    naziωιe, giustιzia,</hi> likewise by Old French, as <hi rend="italic">naeium,
                    place,</hi> whereas in Spanish <hi rend="italic"> ts</hi> has coalesced into a
                    lisped <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">gracia, nation,</hi>
                    and in Portuguese, Provençal, and Modern French it has been assimilated into a
                    hard (voiceless) <hi rend="italic"> s,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">plαςa,
                    plαssα, place.</hi></p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Ci</hi> was assibilated before vowels. In the 4th century we
                    have the Gothic <hi rend="italic">faskja,</hi> which shows no change. Schuchardt
                    is probably right in supposing that <hi rend="italic">ci</hi> was assibilated a
                    good deal later than <hi rend="italic">ti,</hi> —an inference from the
                    comparative rarity of instances of change, and from the silence of the
                    grammarians. From instances like <hi rend="italic">ocio</hi> (see 2) it would
                    appear that <hi rend="italic">ci</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ti</hi> had the same
                    sound, but this cannot have been the case, as Italian still keeps up a
                    difference, as in <hi rend="italic">piaeeia</hi> placeat, <hi rend="italic"
                    >piazza</hi> platea. Yet there may have been a beginning of a palatal affection,
                    making the two sounds somewhat like each other. In the 6th century we have the
                    Gothic <hi rend="italic">unkjane</hi> (unciarum) and <hi rend="italic">
                    οvvκια</hi> in the Ravenna charters, but on the other hand <hi rend="italic"
                    >πpcκαω=preeio</hi> for <hi rend="italic">pretiο, Urbitcηιs</hi> (533, which,
                    however, may be a miscorrection, <hi rend="italic"> c</hi> being added instead
                    of substituted for ∕), <hi rend="italic"> Mauriscius</hi> on a Gaulish coin,
                    from the same period,—making it probable that the assibilation had been
                    accomplished. In the 7th and 8th centuries spellings like <hi rend="italic"
                    >οnzia</hi> for <hi rend="italic"> uncia</hi> are quite common.</p>
                <p>4. The most important change of all was the victory of stress over quantity and
                    tones. The popular songs of the classical period show a decided prevalence of
                    accent. In the soldiers’ songs from the end of the 3d century stress has quite
                    superseded quantity and is the ruling principle of the metre :—</p>
                <p>“Unus Λ&lt;⅛ι.o mille, mille, mille decollavimus.</p>
                <p>Tantum vini nemo Λtiδei quantum fudit sanguinis.”</p>
                <p>This is just like the metre of early Christian hymns— <hi rend="italic"
                    >“Dies</hi> irae, <hi rend="italic">dies</hi> ilia,” and “O Rex aeterne, <hi
                    rend="italic"> Démine,” tzc.</hi> The old quantities had been levelled. St
                    Augustine (354-430) says that in his time only a few grammarians had kept up the
                    distinction between <hi rend="italic">rnδrae</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >more,</hi> and that the Africans confounded <hi rend="italic">tis</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic"> os.</hi> Servius (4th century) could only find out quantity from
                    stress in words like <hi rend="italic">impius, amicus.</hi> Consentius says that
                    some, especially Africans, said <hi rend="italic">piper</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic"> piper</hi> and <hi rend="italic">δrator</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic"> orator.</hi> This does not necessarily mean that all short
                    accented vowels before single consonants had become long; probably both short
                    and long coalesced to a medial quantity, rather short than long, and there was
                    no very marked difference of quantity between accented and unaccented vowels.
                    This appears plainly from the nature of Romance poetry, where stress has only a
                    moderate importance—namely, in the most prominent parts of the verse — while the
                    chief principle is the number of syllables. In Italian, especially in the Tuscan
                    dialect, we may hear <hi rend="italic">bambino</hi> with short accented <hi
                    rend="italic"> i,</hi> the unaccented <hi rend="italic">o</hi> being rather
                    longer than the accented <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> just as Eng. <hi
                    rend="italic"> y</hi> in <hi rend="italic">pity,</hi> when emphatic, is longer
                    than <hi rend="italic">i.</hi> In Spanish words like <hi rend="italic">mΑno,
                    primêro, senôra</hi> the accented vowel is generally as short as the unaccented
                    or even shorter, which does not prevent the Spaniards from counting it as “<hi
                    rend="italic">dos tiempos”</hi> (duas moras); the unaccented final syllables are
                    often rather longer, as in Eng. <hi rend="italic">pity.</hi> In Italian the
                    longest syllables are those containing two or more consonants after the accented
                    vowel, as <hi rend="italic">tèmpo, paziènza, bôcca, gatto</hi>; the chief
                    difference between <hi rend="italic">fdtto</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fdto</hi>
                    is the length of the <hi rend="italic">t</hi> in the former. In Spanish and
                    French even long consonants are shortened, as Span. <hi rend="italic">bοca,
                    gato,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">chatte·, jette</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >achète</hi> are equally short; vowels are generally short or medial, as <hi
                    rend="italic">une belle ville</hi> (not like wα∕, as the English make it), and
                    are long only by compensation, as in <hi rend="italic">ane, chante</hi> (where
                    the nasal is absorbed by the vowel). The old distinction of tone necessarily
                    disappeared with these, the acute or high even <hi rend="italic">iR,oma)</hi>
                    and the circumflex or high falling tone (A5wα) being dependent on the
                    quantities.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary.—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Ausonius (Burdigala,
                    309-392):</hi><hi rend="italic">burrαe,</hi> nugae, Ital. burla, “joke."
                    Arnobius (Afr.,c. 330): <hi rend="italic">coquina,</hi> I tai. cucina, Fr.
                    cuisine. Firmicus Maternus (c. 340 ?): <hi rend="italic">compti,tτιs,</hi> Ital.
                    conto, Fr. compte. Palladius (c. 350): <hi rend="italic">e&amp;tus,</hi> “cat”;
                    <hi rend="italic"> species=Εv.</hi> épices. Ammianus Marcellinus (end of 4th
                    century): <hi rend="italic">molina,</hi> Ital. molino, Fr. moulin; <hi
                    rend="italic"> impedieare</hi> empêcher; pi∕αrβ=expilare, Fr. piller, Ital.
                    pigliare; <hi rend="italic">proba,</hi> preuve. Vegetius (end of 4th century):
                    <hi rend="italic">burgus,</hi> castellum parvum, Ital. borgo, Fr. bourg. Jerome
                    (331-420): <hi rend="italic">eamisia</hi> (Celtic), Ital. camicia, Span, camisa,
                    Fr. chemise; <hi rend="italic">earrieare,</hi> I tai. caricare, Span, cargar,
                    Fr. charger; <hi rend="italic">impostor</hi> = Eng.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >rancor,</hi> “rancour.” The Vulgate: <hi rend="italic">grossus,</hi> Ital.
                    grosso, Fr. gros (see also Latin). Servius (c. 390): <hi rend="italic"
                    >falco,</hi> Ital. falcone, Fr. faucon. Lactantius (d. c. 330): <hi
                    rend="italic">meridionalis.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Augustine
                    (354-430):</hi><hi rend="italic">combina™; vanitare</hi> vanter. Codex Theodos.
                    (438): <hi rend="italic"> exagium,</hi> Ital. saggio, Fr. essai; <hi
                    rend="italic">paraveredus,</hi> L. Lat. palafredus, I tai. palafreno, Fr.
                    palefroi; <hi rend="italic"> aeueula,</hi> aiguille. Cassiodorus (beginning of
                    6th century): <hi rend="italic">modernus,</hi> “modern.” Codex Justinian.
                    (527-565): <hi rend="italic">amicabilis,</hi> “am iable.”</p>
                <p>V. <hi rend="italic">Fifth Period·.</hi> 500 (550) <hi rend="italic">to c.</hi>
                    900 (1000).</p>
                <p>This period, which extends from the migrations to the first appearance of the
                    modern Romance languages, is the age of Low or barbarous Latin, as written
                    especially in charters and laws. While Christianity had brought vulgar <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n690/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0690-0667"/>Latin into the foreground, barbarism quite made
                    away with literary Latin. Latin was not only dead but forgotten. The old sounds
                    and forms had been lost, and the scribes, ignorant of classical grammar, tried
                    nevertheless to make a show of learning by putting Latin forms at random. This
                    makes the language look much more barbarous than it really was. It is sometimes
                    very hard to find out the living popular form under the Latin varnish, and
                    harder still to find out what is proper to each country, as Low Latin is very
                    much the same everywhere. The following were some of the chief
                    peculiarities.</p>
                <p>1. Old Latin forms reappeared, especially in Italy. Final consonants, especially
                    <hi rend="italic">m, t, s,</hi> were dropped or wrongly put. In Italy the nom.
                    <hi rend="italic">annus</hi> (-os), the ace. <hi rend="italic">annum {-om),</hi>
                    the dat. abl. <hi rend="italic">anno,</hi> the ace. plur. <hi rend="italic">
                    anιws,</hi> coalesced in <hi rend="italic">anno</hi>; as this was the real
                    pronunciation, the scribes confounded the Latin forms. There being no longer any
                    difference between <hi rend="italic">in locum</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> in
                    loco,</hi> both were confounded; even <hi rend="italic">in locus, per
                    locus,</hi> Ac., were written. The prevalence of the type <hi rend="italic">
                    anno</hi> on the one hand and the growing use of the preposition <hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi> for the genitive on the other made the genitive <hi
                    rend="italic">anni</hi> disappear, and <hi rend="italic">anni</hi> (with which
                    <hi rend="italic">annis</hi> coalesced) was used solely for the plural, likewise
                    <hi rend="italic">fiori, month</hi> Sometimes, as in Old French, the objective
                    form <hi rend="italic">anno,</hi> Old Fr. <hi rend="italic"> an,</hi> was used
                    as a genitive, of which <hi rend="italic">Hôtel-Dieu</hi> is still a remnant. In
                    the same way Ital. <hi rend="italic"> rosa</hi> became the common singular, <hi
                    rend="italic">rose</hi> the common plural form. Out of Italy, final s being
                    retained, the plural form was <hi rend="italic">annos, rosas, flores,</hi> which
                    is the Spanish (a»os) and Portuguese form, and partly the French, as <hi
                    rend="italic">roses,</hi> with <hi rend="italic">fleurs</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">ans</hi> as accusatives. In Provençal and Old French <hi
                    rend="italic">s</hi> was kept in the nom. sing, masc., <hi rend="italic"
                    >ans,</hi> but in the nom. plur. the oldest form was <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>
                    retained in some Old French monosyllables— <hi rend="italic">li</hi> illi, <hi
                    rend="italic">did, trei, tuit</hi> from <hi rend="italic">tutti,</hi> used in
                    the Gloss, of Cassel; in polysyllables this <hi rend="italic">i</hi> was lost,
                    and <hi rend="italic"> an</hi> remained, likewise <hi rend="italic">fior
                    Cfiori;</hi> comp, <hi rend="italic">sapienti,</hi> Gloss. Cass.), <hi
                    rend="italic">munt.</hi> The verbs <hi rend="italic">canto, cantos, cantat</hi>
                    in Spanish only lost <hi rend="italic">t</hi>; in Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >cantαs</hi> through <hi rend="italic">eaηtis</hi> (caused by the affinity of
                    <hi rend="italic">s</hi> to i) became <hi rend="italic">eanti.</hi> In French
                    both s and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> were kept— <hi rend="italic">chante,
                    chantes; chaηtet,</hi> later <hi rend="italic">chante; est, vit, vient,</hi> and
                    from the analogy of these Mod. Fr. <hi rend="italic">aime -t -il,
                    chante-t-il.</hi> Many old tenses were lost, as &lt;mα(ι⅝)rαnι, which even in
                    Latin sometimes had the sense of the simple past (see Latin), only in the oldest
                    Fr. <hi rend="italic">rovéret,</hi> roga(ve)rat = rogavit. <hi rend="italic">
                    Ama(fi)i</hi> became Ital. <hi rend="italic">amah</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >aimai,</hi> and was used as simple past (perfectum historicum); the praesens
                    perfectum was expressed by a new tense, as <hi rend="italic"> habeo amatum</hi>
                    (of which early germs are found), Ital. <hi rend="italic">ho amato,</hi> Span,
                    <hi rend="italic">he amαdο,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">fiai aimé.</hi> The old
                    future was destroyed and a new future formed out of <hi rend="italic">aman
                    habeo</hi> (of which early traces are found), Old Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ameraggio,</hi> Mod. I tai. awierô, Span, <hi rend="italic">amuré,</hi> Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">j’aimerai,</hi> Ac. In consequence of the general loss of body,
                    short words dwindled down so much that they became unfit for use, and were
                    superseded by fuller words or reinforced by composition; this is especially the
                    case in pronouns and particles. As αcZ became <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">a, ab</hi> could no longer keep its ground, and was replaced by
                    <hi rend="italic"> de,</hi> likewise <hi rend="italic">vis</hi> by <hi
                    rend="italic"> fortia,</hi> Ac. (see Latin). <hi rend="italic">Hie</hi>
                    disappeared and was replaced by <hi rend="italic">iste,</hi> which remained
                    uncomposed in Span, <hi rend="italic">este,</hi> and in the others was composed
                    with <hi rend="italic">ecce, cecum</hi> (see above). <hi rend="italic">
                    Abαnte,</hi> Mod. Ital. <hi rend="italic">avanti,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >avant,</hi> occurs in a pagan inscription. Lat. <hi rend="italic"> unde</hi>
                    became <hi rend="italic">de unde,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic"> donate</hi>; in
                    Spanish this was further composed with <hi rend="italic"> αd,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic">adonde,</hi> and as this in time came to mean “where” a new <hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi> had to be added,— <hi rend="italic">de adonde, he.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">2. C</hi> became assibilated before single <hi rend="italic"> e,
                    i.</hi> That during all the preceding periods c had the sound of <hi
                    rend="italic"> k</hi> is proved by Old Latin spellings like <hi rend="italic">
                    dekem</hi>; by Greek transcriptions, as <hi rend="italic">'F.ικlρων,
                    Kαισαρ;</hi> by the German renderings <hi rend="italic">Kaiser</hi> (Old Eng.
                    <hi rend="italic">cdsere}, Keller, “</hi> cellar,” <hi rend="italic">
                    Kirsche,</hi> “cherry,” Ac., and by the use of <hi rend="italic"> c</hi> for <hi
                    rend="italic">k</hi> in Old English, as in <hi rend="italic">cynne,</hi> “kin,”
                    <hi rend="italic">cennan,</hi> “ken”; by late Latin spellings like <hi
                    rend="italic">ques-quenti,</hi> quiescenti, <hi rend="italic">pαche</hi> (Rome,
                    408), <hi rend="italic">chingxit</hi> (Gaul, 676), <hi rend="italic">vachis</hi>
                    (Lucca, 722)—in Italian still <hi rend="italic">ch=k,</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                    >chi</hi> quis, <hi rend="italic">ehe</hi> quid; and lastly <hi rend="italic"
                    >dulkisrna</hi> (Pisaur., 410), <hi rend="italic">ofikina</hi> (Gallic vase, end
                    of 6th century; see <hi rend="italic">Romania,</hi> xiii. 485). Yet c before <hi
                    rend="italic">e, i</hi> must early have had a more palatal sound than before <hi
                    rend="italic">a, o, u,</hi> something like the old-fashioned English
                    pronunciation <hi rend="italic">kyard</hi> for <hi rend="italic">card.</hi> But
                    it was not until very late that the difference became so marked as to be
                    expressed by different letters: the palatal sound began to be assibilated into
                    something like Italian <hi rend="italic">ce, ci,</hi> Eng. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ch</hi> (as in <hi rend="italic">child</hi> from Old Eng. <hi rend="italic"
                    >cild},</hi> about the 6th century, although perhaps not equally early
                    everywhere. We find <hi rend="italic">κeιτανe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
                    tzitane</hi> (Ravenna charter, 591), and <hi rend="italic">paze</hi> (inscr.
                    about the same time). Ital. c = Eng. <hi rend="italic">eh</hi> in <hi
                    rend="italic">pace, dieci</hi> (in Central Italy mostly pronounced <hi
                    rend="italic">sh∖ cielo;</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic">paz, diez, cielo</hi>
                    (lisping <hi rend="italic">s</hi> from <hi rend="italic"> ts);</hi> Fr. <hi
                    rend="italic">cixl</hi> (Old <hi rend="italic">ts,</hi> Mod. s).</p>
                <p>1 3. <hi rend="italic">E</hi> for accented ï became frequent. As original î and ï
                    were no longer different in quantity, they had to be distinguished by quality;
                    accordingly <hi rend="italic">rnnum</hi> became Ital. <hi rend="italic">vino,
                    minus {minus,</hi> open i), Ital. <hi rend="italic">meno,</hi> with the same
                    vowel as in <hi rend="italic">véna</hi> from <hi rend="italic">vena</hi>; thus
                    Latin <hi rend="italic">ï</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e</hi> coalesced; likewise
                    we have <hi rend="italic">serivo</hi> scribo, <hi rend="italic"> bevo</hi> bïbo,
                    <hi rend="italic">sévo</hi> sébum, <hi rend="italic"> fido</hi> fidus, <hi
                    rend="italic">féde</hi> fïdes, <hi rend="italic"> eréde</hi> crédit, <hi
                    rend="italic">scritto</hi> scriptum, <hi rend="italic">dette</hi> dictum.</p>
                <p>We find traces of this in the Pomp, <hi rend="italic">veces,</hi> Ital. vece. In
                    Low Latin <hi rend="italic">menus, fedes,</hi> Ac., are constant. But many who
                    had a little more learning retained the Latin spelling <hi rend="italic"
                    >minus,</hi> pronouncing <hi rend="italic">meno{s),</hi> and by this were
                    induced to write constantly <hi rend="italic">i</hi> for close <hi rend="italic"
                    > e,</hi> especially accented, as <hi rend="italic">habire, vedire,</hi>
                    crπ∕cre= Ital. avéré, vedére, crédere; <hi rend="italic">vindere, stüla</hi>
                    =véndere, stëlla, Ital. véndere, stélla, Piedm. esteila, Old Fr. esteile, Fr.
                    étoile. In some few instances this may represent a provincial <hi rend="italic"
                    >i,</hi> as in Sicil. <hi rend="italic">aviri,</hi> or special cases like Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">tenir, plaisir, merci.</hi></p>
                <p>4. Unaccented <hi rend="italic">e</hi> for <hi rend="italic">ï,</hi> which is
                    frequent in Old Latin and not unfrequent in the post-classical age, returns in
                    Low Latin with redoubled force. Thus we find <hi rend="italic">fedelis</hi>
                    (404), later <hi rend="italic">Damenecus, sej&gt;temus, decemus, ancma,
                    deposeta, genetor, capete, soledοs</hi>; in the Ravenna charters <hi
                    rend="italic"> vecedomeno, vendecare, ordenαta,</hi> Ac.; in Frankish charters
                    <hi rend="italic">decemo,</hi> Fr. dime, <hi rend="italic">Domeneeus,
                    venerabelis, nobelis, lacrema, cantate, veretate, femena, ρlacetus,</hi> Ac.
                    This penetrated even into Central Italy, as in the Tuscan Latin of the 8th
                    century, <hi rend="italic">dedet, placetum, homenis, inviolavelis.</hi> In
                    Middle Italian <hi rend="italic">uοrneni,</hi> in Modern Italian <hi
                    rend="italic">DomenedJte, ospedale,</hi> are rare remnants of the earlier form.
                    Generally classical <hi rend="italic">i</hi> has prevailed in Florentine and
                    Italian, as «mi»!, <hi rend="italic">femmina, anima, asino, online,
                    spirite.</hi> In the Sienese dialect <hi rend="italic"> e</hi> has remained, as
                    <hi rend="italic">ordenare, cardenale,</hi> and in North Italian — Venet. <hi
                    rend="italic">δmeni, fèrnena, menèstra, brdene, dseno;</hi> Lomb. <hi
                    rend="italic">innen, asen, ordendri,</hi> Ac. In Spanish it is not unfrequent—
                    <hi rend="italic"> ôrden, ûmedo, nove-ddd, corredôr</hi>; comp. Prov. <hi
                    rend="italic">lagrema, semenar, conoissedor,</hi> and Old Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >aneme,</hi> pronounced <hi rend="italic">dnme</hi> (the spelling points to an
                    older stage).</p>
                <p>5. Unaccented medial <hi rend="italic">e</hi> was often dropped, though less in
                    Italian, except in the north, as in L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">dulkisrna,</hi>
                    dulcissima (Pisaur., 410), answering to modern Bomagnu∂lo forms like <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> sZrissm=illus-trissimo; generally L. Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic"> domnus, domna—ltA. donna,</hi> “lady,” “woman.” In French all
                    proparoxytones are contracted; for instance, Old Fr. (asinum, *as ’ no) <hi
                    rend="italic">asne</hi> âne, (anima, *an ’ ma) <hi rend="italic">anmx</hi> âme,
                    (hominem, *hom ’ ne) <hi rend="italic">homme,</hi> (femina, *fem ’ na),
                    ∕ewυne.</p>
                <p>6. Accented <hi rend="italic">o</hi> for m, not unfrequent in the preceding
                    period, was constant in Low Latin. While Lat. <hi rend="italic">lücem</hi>
                    became Ital. <hi rend="italic">luce,</hi> Lat. <hi rend="italic">crucem, nucem
                    {nucem,</hi> open <hi rend="italic">u)</hi> became <hi rend="italic"> crôee,
                    noce,</hi> like <hi rend="italic">voce</hi> from <hi rend="italic">vδcem</hi>;
                    comp, <hi rend="italic">jùstus,</hi> Ital. giusto, Fr. juste, but <hi
                    rend="italic">augüstus,</hi> Ital. agôsto, Fr. août. This caused many to write
                    <hi rend="italic">u</hi> for close <hi rend="italic"> o,</hi> as oicwrβ uxore,
                    <hi rend="italic">geneture</hi> genitorem, although this may partly represent a
                    provincial <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> as in Sicil. <hi rend="italic">amuri.</hi>
                    In Old Fr. we have <hi rend="italic"> honour, favour,</hi> and still <hi
                    rend="italic">amour,</hi> and in L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">curte</hi> =cohortem,
                    *corte, Ital. corte, Fr. cour, Eng. court.</p>
                <p>7. Unaccented o for <hi rend="italic">ü</hi> as in Old Latin is frequent, as in
                    L. Lat. <hi rend="italic">tubola, popolo, secolom, ηgola, volontate,</hi> Ital.
                    <hi rend="italic">tdvola, popοlo,</hi> Ac.; even for original <hi rend="italic">
                    u,</hi> as <hi rend="italic">mano, spirite.</hi></p>
                <p>8. Unaccented medial <hi rend="italic">o</hi> was often dropped before <hi
                    rend="italic"> l,</hi> in which case the unfamiliar group <hi rend="italic">
                    t’l</hi> was changed into <hi rend="italic">el,</hi> as in L. Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic"> oclus</hi> oculus, Ital. <hi rend="italic">6cchio,</hi> Span, <hi
                    rend="italic">ojo,</hi> Fr. ceil; <hi rend="italic">veelus</hi> vetulus, Ital.
                    <hi rend="italic">vecchio</hi> (Old Ital. <hi rend="italic">veglio∖</hi> Span,
                    vièjo, Fr. vieil, vieux; also L. Lat. <hi rend="italic"> tabla —</hi> Span,
                    tabla, <hi rend="italic">poplom=</hi> Span, puéblo. In French syncope is a law—
                    <hi rend="italic">table, peuple, sangle</hi> cingulum, Ac.</p>
                <p>9. Final unaccented vowels in Italian on the whole obey the general laws. By the
                    loss of the Latin final consonants all words end in a vowel, except such as <hi
                    rend="italic"> per, con, non, in, un bel giorno, buon giomo.</hi> In South
                    Italian <hi rend="italic">i, u</hi> stand for <hi rend="italic">e, o.</hi> In
                    Spanish <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is sometimes dropped, as <hi rend="italic">
                    sed</hi> sitim, Ital. séte; <hi rend="italic">pared</hi> parietem, Ital. paréte;
                    <hi rend="italic">fdcil, 6rden.</hi> In Portuguese <hi rend="italic"> o</hi> is
                    pronounced <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> but often only whispered; <hi rend="italic"
                    >e</hi> is nearly always whispered or mute. In North Italian, Ladino, Catalan,
                    Provençal, and French all final vowels are generally dropped, except <hi
                    rend="italic">a,</hi> which remains in Provençal, as <hi rend="italic"
                    >port,</hi> but <hi rend="italic">porta</hi> (Mod. <hi rend="italic">pδrte∖</hi>
                    In Catalan <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is mostly pronounced as open <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi>; in French this becomes obscure <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>
                    which in modern French is mute except in such cases as <hi rend="italic">table
                    ronde.</hi></p>
                <p>10. Accented <hi rend="italic">ie</hi> stands for <hi rend="italic">é, uo</hi>
                    for <hi rend="italic">8.</hi> As ë and ë, <hi rend="italic">δ</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">δ</hi> were levelled in quantity, they were already distinguished
                    in quality, as in Ital. <hi rend="italic">bène</hi> bêne, <hi rend="italic">
                    véne</hi> vënae; Portuguese has got no further than this. But generally this was
                    not distinct enough for the wants of the speakers, and unconsciously <hi
                    rend="italic">è</hi> (in which <hi rend="italic">è</hi> from Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">ae</hi> was included) became <hi rend="italic">iè,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">δ</hi> (in which <hi rend="italic">i&gt;</hi> from Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">an</hi> was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> included) became <hi
                    rend="italic">uδ,</hi> both diphthongs being generally accented on the last
                    vowel—Ital. and Span, <hi rend="italic">viène,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >vient</hi> venit; Ital. <hi rend="italic"> buδno,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic"
                    >budnο</hi>; Ital. <hi rend="italic"> suδιw,</hi> Span, <hi rend="italic"
                    >sueno</hi> (generally <hi rend="italic">sonido}</hi> sonus, different from
                    Ital. <hi rend="italic"> sδno</hi> sunt, Span. <hi rend="italic">son.</hi> This
                    change must be very old, as it is found in nearly all the Romance languages. In
                    Spanish, Provençal, and French <hi rend="italic">ui&gt;</hi> was changed into
                    <hi rend="italic">ué,</hi> and this in Modern French to <hi rend="italic"> eu,
                    oeu,</hi> contracted into the sound of <hi rend="italic">o.</hi> In Spanish the
                    use of diphthongs is extended to position— <hi rend="italic">tiémpo, siete</hi>
                    septem, Ital. sètte, <hi rend="italic">hiérro,</hi> Ital. fèrro, <hi
                    rend="italic">ciiérpo,</hi> Ital. cδrpo, <hi rend="italic">iiiuérte,</hi> Ital.
                    morte. Mark the displacement of stress in popular Latin— <hi rend="italic"
                    >pariétem</hi> for parietem, Ital. paréte, Span, pared, Fr. paroi; <hi
                    rend="italic">filiδlus</hi> for filiδlus, Ital. figliuδlo, Span, hijuélo, Fr.
                    filleul.</p>
                <p>11. Of <hi rend="italic">mediae</hi> (voiced stops) for <hi rend="italic"
                    >tenues</hi> (voiceless stops), especially between vowels, we find some few
                    earlier instances, as <hi rend="italic">grassus</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >crassus,</hi> Ital. grasso, Fr. gras. This is generally rare in Italian Latin,
                    as <hi rend="italic">gubitus,</hi> cubitus, Ital. gomito, and is still
                    comparatively rare in Italian. Yet it occurs in some of the most familiar words,
                    as <hi rend="italic">ago</hi> acus, <hi rend="italic">lago, luogo,
                    segare,pagare</hi> (pacare, “to satisfy,”</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n691/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0691-0668"/>
                <p>“pay”), <hi rend="italic">pregare, budello, parentado, contadο</hi> (comitatus),
                    <hi rend="italic">contrada, spada, strada; p</hi> from <hi rend="italic"> b</hi>
                    becomes <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic"> riva, riviera,
                    povero, savio;</hi> before <hi rend="italic">r—padre, madre, segreto,
                    lebbra.</hi> This recalls similar changes in Umbrian, and was perhaps originally
                    North Italian and from thence penetrated into Tuscany. In Spanish the voiced
                    sounds are the general rule, as <hi rend="italic"> fuégo,</hi> Ital. fuòco, <hi
                    rend="italic">amigo,</hi> Ital. amico, <hi rend="italic">amado, finido,</hi>
                    Ital. amato, finito, <hi rend="italic"> sabér,</hi> Ital. sapére, &amp;c., yet
                    there are some exceptions, such as <hi rend="italic">poco</hi> (paucum). In Old
                    French the soft sound is the constant law, but this mostly disappears later, as
                    in <hi rend="italic"> aimé, aimée</hi> (see France, vol. ix. p. 632 <hi
                    rend="italic"> sq. ).</hi> A general Romance case is placitum, Old Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">ρiaitο,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">piato,</hi> Span. <hi
                    rend="italic">pleito,</hi> Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">plaid,</hi> through
                    *plagito, *plajeto, which is singularly like the Umbrian <hi rend="italic">
                    feitu, feetu</hi> for <hi rend="italic">façitu.</hi> A limited case is that of
                    such words as Fr. <hi rend="italic">raison,</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ragione</hi> from <hi rend="italic">rationem,</hi> probably first changed to
                    <hi rend="italic">ratsió, *radsióne,</hi> thence to <hi rend="italic"
                    >rasione,</hi> which sometimes occurs in Late Latin, and often in Early Italian,
                    Span, <hi rend="italic">razon</hi>; comp. Ital. <hi rend="italic"> cagione</hi>
                    occasionem.</p>
                <p>12. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e</hi> unaccented before
                    vowels, especially post-tonic, became <hi rend="italic">j,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic"> filjus</hi> (Plautus), <hi rend="italic">olium</hi> pron. <hi
                    rend="italic">οljo. J</hi> coalesced with the preceding consonant, making it
                    palatal, as in Ital. <hi rend="italic">figlio, oglio, figlia, maraviglia</hi>
                    (mirabilia), <hi rend="italic">battaglia</hi>; Span, <hi rend="italic">
                    maraυilla, batalla;</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">fille, merveille, bataille</hi>
                    (in North French the palatal sound is replaced by <hi rend="italic">i</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">j),</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic"> N</hi> —Ital. <hi
                    rend="italic">vigna</hi> vinea, <hi rend="italic"> Spagna</hi> Hispania, <hi
                    rend="italic">ingegno, castagna, campagna, bagnο</hi> balneum; Span. <hi
                    rend="italic">Espana, campa na;</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">vigne,
                    champagne.</hi> In some cases <hi rend="italic"> j</hi> was assibilated, as
                    Span. <hi rend="italic">granja, estranjero,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">songe,
                    grange, étrange.</hi></p>
                <p>13. Sometimes attraction takes place, <hi rend="italic">i</hi> being transposed
                    to the radical syllable, especially in French, as <hi rend="italic">huile, bain,
                    témoin, Antoine, gloire, histoire.</hi> Before and after <hi rend="italic">
                    r</hi> peculiar forms appear—Ital. <hi rend="italic">primaio</hi> (-70); <hi
                    rend="italic">muojo</hi> morior; Ital. <hi rend="italic"> primiero,
                    cavaliere,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">primario,</hi> probably assimilated into
                    * <hi rend="italic">primer(i)o</hi> (Dr Thomsen). Forms like <hi rend="italic"
                    >pαner, sorcerus</hi> are found as early as the 8th century.</p>
                <p>14. <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary. —</hi> During this period the Roman world,
                    after being conquered by the Germanic nations, adopted many words from their
                    conquerors. The German influence was strongest in France; hence we find Germanic
                    expressions for many of the most common words except form-words, though the
                    stock of the language remains Latin. A curious instance, characteristic of the
                    Middle Ages, is <hi rend="italic">rauba,</hi> which from “robbery,” “prey,” came
                    to mean “property,” Ital. <hi rend="italic">roba</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">
                    robba</hi> ) <hi rend="italic">,</hi> “things in general,” Span, <hi
                    rend="italic">ropa,</hi> “linen,” “stuff,” Fr. <hi rend="italic"> robe,</hi>
                    “gown.” In Rumonsch we have <hi rend="italic">la rauba c'aud a mi,</hi> “the
                    property that belongs to me.” The German <hi rend="italic"> h,</hi> as in <hi
                    rend="italic">haïr</hi> , old <hi rend="italic">hadir</hi> = “hate,” is peculiar
                    to French, and is still sounded in Normandy. Some Germanic sounds had to be
                    modified, as <hi rend="italic">w</hi> to <hi rend="italic">gu</hi> , for
                    instance, <hi rend="italic">guerra</hi> from <hi rend="italic">werra,</hi>
                    “war”; <hi rend="italic">guanto,</hi> Old Fr. <hi rend="italic">guant,</hi> Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">gant,</hi> from <hi rend="italic"> want,</hi> Dan. <hi
                    rend="italic">Vante</hi>; in North French <hi rend="italic">w</hi> remained,
                    whence Eng. <hi rend="italic">war,</hi> &amp;c. Among the <hi rend="italic"
                    >leges barbarae,</hi> the Lex Salica is perhaps the most remarkable as a
                    document of Low Latin. It has sentences and words like—hoc sunt <hi
                    rend="italic">pariculas causas=ce</hi> sont pareilles choses; si in dominica <hi
                    rend="italic">ambactia</hi> fuerit occupatus, Ital. ambasciata, Fr. ambassade;
                    si quis alterum voluerit occidere et <hi rend="italic">colpus</hi> praeter <hi
                    rend="italic">fallierit,</hi> Ital. se il colpo fallisce; si quis alterum <hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi> sagitta toxicata percutere voluerit et praeter <hi
                    rend="italic">sclupaverit</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">stloppsιs,</hi> p. 665);
                    si quis <hi rend="italic">cabαllum</hi> extra consilium domini sui <hi
                    rend="italic">caballixaverit,</hi> Ital. caval-care, Fr. chevaucher; si quis per
                    mal0 ingenio in <hi rend="italic"> curie</hi> (Ital. corte, Fr. cour) alterius
                    aut in <hi rend="italic"> casa</hi> (Ital. <hi rend="italic">casa,</hi> “house”)
                    aliquid de furtzzτn miserit; <hi rend="italic">eompanium,</hi> Ital. compagnia;
                    <hi rend="italic">bare, baronis,</hi> “a free man,” Old Fr. nom. <hi
                    rend="italic">ber,</hi> obj. <hi rend="italic">baruη,</hi> “hero,” “baron”; <hi
                    rend="italic">diffaeere,</hi> Ital. disfare, Fr. défaire; <hi rend="italic">
                    exeortieare,</hi> Ital. scorticare, Fr. écorcher. From other laws we have— <hi
                    rend="italic">-fortia,</hi> Ital. forza, Fr. force; <hi rend="italic">
                    hostis</hi> exercitus, Eng. host; <hi rend="italic">vassus</hi> (Celtic), “a
                    vassal”; <hi rend="italic">auca,</hi> Ital. δca, Fr. oie (from <hi rend="italic"
                    >avixa); troppus,</hi> grex (from Germ, <hi rend="italic"> thorp∖</hi> Ital.
                    truppa, Fr. troupe, and also Ital. <hi rend="italic"> troppo,</hi> “too much,”
                    Fr. <hi rend="italic">trop; forestis</hi> (from <hi rend="italic">foris), “</hi>
                    foreign,” Ital. forestiere; <hi rend="italic">marea</hi> (Germ. ), “border,”
                    whence <hi rend="italic"> mαrehensis,</hi> Ital. marchese, Fr. marquis; <hi
                    rend="italic"> tornare</hi> (Greek; also Dacian Latin <note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Greek historians Theophylact (c. 600) and
                    Theophanes relate that the Dacian soldiers said in their native tongue <hi
                    rend="italic">τi&gt;ρvα, τt&gt;pva, φpaτρe, htτbpva.</hi> This has been called
                    by some the earliest trace of Roumanian. </p></note> ). Gregory of Tours (6th
                    century) has <hi rend="italic">ρageηsis,</hi> Ital. paése, Fr. pays. Gregory the
                    Great has mercea, “mercy ”; <hi rend="italic">fiasco,</hi> Ital. fiasco, “a
                    flask.” Coripγus (Afr., c. 570): <hi rend="italic">eara,</hi> ‘‘face” (Gr. <hi
                    rend="italic">κάρα,</hi> “head”), Span, <hi rend="italic"> cara,</hi> Old Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">chixre,</hi> whence <hi rend="italic">bonne chère,</hi> “good
                    cheer” (originally the kind, hospitable countenance of the entertainer).
                    Venantius Fortunatus (c. 580): <hi rend="italic"> eofea,</hi> “coif”; <hi
                    rend="italic">crema,</hi> “cream”; <hi rend="italic">viaticum,</hi> Ital.
                    viaggio, Fr. voyage. Other sources: <hi rend="italic">eamiηus,</hi> “road”
                    (Spanish Latin, 7th century; probably Celtic), Ital. cammino, Fr. chemin; <hi
                    rend="italic">directum,</hi> jus (Italian Latin, 551), Ital. diritto, Fr. droit.
                    The late agrimensores: circαre, Ital. cercare, Fr. chercher. Old glosses (7th
                    and 8th centuries): <hi rend="italic"> αeiarium,</hi> Ital. acciaio, Fr. acier;
                    <hi rend="italic">cosinus,</hi> consobrinus, Ital. cugino, Fr. cousin; <hi
                    rend="italic">gamba,</hi> Ital. gamba, Fr. jambe (Gloss. Cass. ). Isidore: <hi
                    rend="italic"> trudα,</hi> Fr. truite, Eng. trout; <hi rend="italic">cama,</hi>
                    Span, <hi rend="italic">eama,</hi> “bed”; <hi rend="italic">fieatum,</hi>
                    “liver” (properly <hi rend="italic">jeeurfixαtum,</hi> liver of geese fed with
                    figs), Ital. fégato, Span, higado, Fr. foie; and <hi rend="italic">eusire,</hi>
                    consuere, Ital. cuscire, cucire, Span, coser, Fr. coudre (Gloss. Isid. ); <hi
                    rend="italic">selvatieus,</hi> Ital. sel-vaggio, Fr. sauvage; <hi rend="italic"
                    >formaticum,</hi> Ital. formaggio, Fr. fromage.</p>
                <p>VI. <hi rend="italic">Sixth (Last) Period.</hi></p>
                <p>For the sixth and last period—that is, for the history and distinctive traits of
                    the great modern Romance languages —the reader is referred to the separate
                    articles.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi> is distinguished by its harmonious form, its
                    vocalic endings, and the rich fulness of its tones.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Spanish</hi> is distinguished by its regularity, by its
                    short, distinct sounds and its fixed tones, and by many Arabic words. Certain
                    “thick” sounds, as the <hi rend="italic">j</hi> (like Dutch and South German <hi
                    rend="italic">ch,</hi> though in the south of Spain much weaker, almost Λ) and
                    the lisping c, <hi rend="italic">z</hi> seem to be rather modern developments
                    than due to direct Arabic influence.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Portuguese</hi> is, with <hi rend="italic">Gallego</hi> (the
                    dialect of Galicia), the western dialect of Spanish, and has almost the same
                    words, but a very different pronunciation; in sound it approaches somewhat to
                    French, as in the nasal vowels (which, however, are less purely vocalic than in
                    French) and the voiced sounds of s, 2, and <hi rend="italic">j.</hi> It has
                    partly retained the Old Spanish form, as in <hi rend="italic">filho</hi> for
                    Span, <hi rend="italic">hijo,</hi> and partly it has a character of its own
                    owing to its many obscured vowels and contractions, as <hi rend="italic"
                    >boa</hi> for <hi rend="italic">bona, dor</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >dolor.</hi></p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Provençal</hi> in many respects represents the earliest form
                    of French; in others it has peculiar developments (see Provençal). <hi
                    rend="italic"> Catalan</hi> is the southern dialect of Provençal.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">French</hi> makes up for the want of the full forms and
                    tones of Italian by its grace and delicacy. It has more of a history than the
                    other Romance languages, Old French being very different from Modern.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Ladino (Rumonsch,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Rumonsch is properly the dialect of the upper Rhine valley,
                    Ladino that of the Engadine. Ascoli includes all varieties under the common name
                    of Ladino. </p></note><hi rend="italic"/> Germ. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Churwαlsch,</hi> from the town of Chur) or <hi rend="italic">Central
                    Romance</hi> extends from the Grisons to Friuli on the Adriatic. It is not
                    uniform, being only an agglomeration of cognate dialects; and it is scarcely
                    more Latin than any other Romance language. It has chiefly been elucidated by
                    Ascoli.</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Roumanian</hi> has probably not survived from the old Roman
                    colonists of Dacia, but been imported from Istria (which has a cognate dialect)
                    or Northern Italy. It has been greatly mixed up with Slavonic words and sounds
                    (such as the “mixed” vowels), and has some distinctive marks, such as the
                    post-positive article, <hi rend="italic">Romunul =</hi> Romanus ille; compare
                    the similar phenomenon in the Slavonic dialect of Bulgaria and in the Albanian
                    language.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> The real founder of scientific Romance
                    philology and linguistics is Friedrich Diez, in his <hi rend="italic">Grammatik
                    der romanischen Sprachen,</hi> 3 vols., Bonn, 1836-42, and <hi rend="italic">
                    Etymologisches Wörterbuch der romanischen Sprachen,</hi> 2 vols., 1852. He also
                    published <hi rend="italic">Altro∙ manische Sprachdenkmäler,</hi> 1846; <hi
                    rend="italic">Zwei altromanischc Gedichte,</hi> 1852; and <hi rend="italic"
                    >AUromanisehe Glossare,</hi> 1865. Pott contributed several articles on the Low
                    Latin of the <hi rend="italic"> leges barbarae</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Zeitschriften</hi> of Hofer and Kuhn. Other authorities on various branches of
                    the subject are—Ducange, <hi rend="italic">Glossarium mediae et infirnae
                    latinitαtis,</hi> 7 vols.; Marini, <hi rend="italic">Papiri diplomatiei</hi>;
                    Muratori, <hi rend="italic"> Antiquitates Italieae-,</hi> Schuchardt, <hi
                    rend="italic">Der Voealismus des Vulgärlateins,</hi> 3 vols., 1866-68 (a
                    valuable collection of materials), also several minor works by the same author;
                    and Gaston Paris, <hi rend="italic">Étude sur le Rôle de l'Accent Latin dans la
                    Längste Française,</hi> Paris, 1862, and <hi rend="italic">La Vie de St
                    Alexis</hi> (a poem of 11th century), 1872. The principal magazines devoted to
                    the subject are— <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch für romanische und englische
                    Literatur</hi> (ed. Wolff, Ebert, and Lembcke), later only <hi rend="italic">
                    für romanische Literatur; Archiv für das Studium der neueren Sprachen</hi> (ed.
                    Herrig), of a more popular character; <hi rend="italic"> Romania</hi> (a
                    quarterly, cd. Gaston Paris and Paul Meyer, since 1872), contains articles of
                    the most eminent Romanists; <hi rend="italic">Revue des Langues Romanes</hi>
                    (Montpellier, from 1870 onwards), chiefly devoted to Provençal; <hi
                    rend="italic">Romanische Studien</hi> (ed. Boehmer); <hi rend="italic">
                    Zeitschrift für romanische Philologie</hi> (ed. Gröber, since 1877); and <hi
                    rend="italic">Romanische Forschungen</hi> (ed. Vollmöller, since 1884). Mussafia
                    has written many articles and treatises, chiefly in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transadions</hi> of the Vienna Academy of Sciences. Ascoli, author of <hi
                    rend="italic">Studi Critici,</hi> has edited since 1873 the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Archivio Glottologieo,</hi> which has articles by Flecchia. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Rivista di Filologia Romαnza</hi> (ed. Manzoni, Monaci, and
                    Stengel, 1873) in 1878 became <hi rend="italic">Giornαle di Filologia
                    Romαnza</hi> (ed. Monaci). For the etymological dictionaries of the separate
                    languages see the special articles. (J. ST.*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
