<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0645-0622-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROHAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 622</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198950">Revolt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n645/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROHAN</label> Henri de (1579-1638), a general and writer of
                    eminence and one of the last and best representatives of the independent French
                    noblesse, was born at the château of Bleins in Brittany on 21st August 1579. His
                    father was René IL, count of Rohan, and head of a family which had hardly a
                    superior in France for antiquity and distinction, and which was connected with
                    most of the reigning houses of Europe. Rohan was by birth the second son, but
                    his elder brother René dying young he became the heir of the name. He appeared
                    at court and in the army at the age of sixteen, and was a special favourite with
                    Henry IV., after whom, failing the house of Condé, he ∙ might be said to be the
                    natural chief of the French Protestants. Having served till the peace of
                    Vervins, he travelled for a considerable time over Europe, including England and
                    Scotland, in the first of which countries he received the not unique honour of
                    being called by Elizabeth her knight, while in the second he was godfather at
                    Charles I.’s christening. On his return to France he was made duke and peer at
                    the age of twenty-four and married Marguerite de Béthune, Sully’s daughter,
                    receiving lucrative appointments. After the assassination of Henry IV., which
                    was a great blow to him, Rohan fought with success at the siege of Jülich. But
                    from this time onwards he was for the greater part of many years either in
                    active warfare against the Government of his country, or in active though
                    peaceable opposition to it. For a time, however, he abstained from actual
                    insurrection, and he endeavoured to keep on terms with Marie de’ Medici; he
                    even, despite his dislike of De Luynes, the favourite of Louis XIII., reappeared
                    in the army and fought in Lorraine and Piedmont. It was not till the decree for
                    the restitution of church property in the south threw the Bearnese and Gascons
                    into open revolt that Rohan appeared as a rebel. His authority and military
                    skill were very formidable to the royalists, forced them among other checks to
                    raise the siege of Montauban, and brought about the treaty of Montpellier
                    (1623). But Rohan did not escape the results of the incurable factiousness which
                    showed itself more strongly perhaps among the French Huguenots than among any
                    other of the numerous armed oppositions of the 17th century. He was accused of
                    lukewarmness and treachery, though he did not hesitate to renew the war when the
                    compact of Montpellier was broken. Again a hollow peace was patched up, but it
                    lasted hardly any time, and Rohan undertook a third war, the first the events of
                    which are recounted in his celebrated <hi rend="italic">Memoirs.</hi> This last
                    war (famous for the siege of La Rochelle, in which, however, Rohan’s brother
                    Soubise, not Rohan himself, was principally concerned) was one of considerable
                    danger for Rohan: he was condemned to death, and a great reward was offered for
                    him dead or alive. Nor at the close of the war did he think it best to remain in
                    France, but made his way to Venice. Here he lived quietly for some time and is
                    said to have received from the Porte the offer of the sovereignty of Cyprus. It
                    is more certain that his hosts of Venice wished to make him their
                    general-in-chief, a design not executed owing to the peace of Cherasco (1631).
                    Soon afterwards Rohan was again called to serve his lawful sovereign. Richelieu
                    had had experience, though not friendly experience, of his abilities, and when
                    France began once more to take a vigorous part in the Thirty Years’ War Rohan
                    was appointed to the task of occupying the Valtelline, and thus cutting off the
                    communication between Germany and Italy. He was entirely successful and
                    repeatedly beat both the imperialists and the Spaniards. But, despite this
                    service, Rohan was still thought dangerous to the peace of France owing to his
                    influence with the Huguenots, and objection was even made to his residence in
                    Geneva. He therefore joined Bernhard of Saxe-Weimar, and was serving in his army
                    when he met with the wound which caused his death at Rheinfelden on l4th March
                    1638. His body was buried at Geneva and his arms solemnly bequeathed to and
                    accepted by the Venetian republic. Rohan’s wife was a woman of talent and
                    energy, though she did not escape scandal. His younger brother Benjamin,
                    generally known as Soubise, was, like him, a famous Huguenot leader. His
                    daughter and only recognized surviving child, named Marguerite, carried the
                    honours of Rohan into the Chabot family.</p>
                <p>What has chiefly preserved Rohan’s memory is not his military achievements,
                    though they were remarkable, nor his political position, though it was high, but
                    his admirable J/eznoirs. These cover the civil wars in three books, while a
                    fourth contains the narrative of the Valtelline campaigns; and they rank among
                    the best products of the singular talent for memoir-writing which the French
                    aristocracy of the 16th and 17th centuries possessed. Alike in style, in
                    clearness of matter, and in shrewdness of thought they deserve very high praise.
                    The first three books appeared in 1644, that on the Valtelline War not till
                    1758. Some suspicions were thrown on the genuineness of this latter, but it
                    would seem groundlessly. Rohan also wrote <hi rend="italic">Le Parfait
                    Capitaine,</hi> an adaptation of the military precepts and examples of Caesar to
                    modern warfare; an account of his travels; a political tract, <hi rend="italic"
                    >L'Intérêt des États et des Princes de la Chrétienté,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> which alone have continued to bo reprinted, may be
                    conveniently found in the collection of Michaud and Poujoulat, voL xix.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
