<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0321-0304-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REAL ESTATE (9th edition, volume 20, page 304)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205049">Victoria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878670">Copyhold</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n321/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REAL ESTATE</label>. The land law of England and of countries
                    whose law is based upon that of England stands in a peculiar position, which can
                    be understood only by an outline of its history.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History</hi> .—Such terms as “fee” or “homage” carry us far
                    back into feudal times. Rights of common and distress are based upon still older
                    institutions, forming the very basis of primitive law. The conception of tenure
                    is the most fundamental ground of distinction between real and personal estate,
                    the former only being strictly entitled to the name of estate (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Estate).</hi> The division into real and personal is
                    coincident to a great extent with that into immovable and movable, generally
                    used by systems of law founded on the Roman (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Personal
                        Estate).</hi> That it is not entirely coincident is due to the influence of
                    the Roman law itself. The Greeks and the Romans of the republic were essentially
                    nations of citizens; the Teutons were essentially a nation of land-folk; the
                    Roman empire bridged the gulf between the two. It is probable that the English
                    land law was produced by the action of the policy adopted in the lower empire,
                    finally developed into feudalism, upon the previously existing course of
                    Teutonic custom (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Feudalism).</hi> It is sufficient to
                    say here that the distinguishing features of the Teutonic system were enjoyment
                    in common and the absence of private ownership, except to a limited extent. The
                    history of the development of the old English land law before the Conquest will
                    be found under <hi rend="smallcaps">England</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Land.</hi> Its principal features, stated as shortly as possible, were (1)
                    liberty of alienation, either by will or <hi rend="italic">inter vivos</hi> , of
                    such land as could be alienated, chiefly, if not entirely, bocland, subject
                    always to the limits fixed by the <hi rend="italic">hoc·,</hi> (2) publicity of
                    transfer by enrolment in the shire-book or churcli-book; (3) equal partition of
                    the estate of a deceased among the sons, and failing sons among the daughters;
                    (4) cultivation to a great extent by persons in various <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n322/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0322-0305"/>degrees of serfdom, owing money or labour
                    rents; <hi rend="italic">(5]</hi> variety of custom, tending to become uniform,
                    through the application of the same principles in the local courts; (6)
                    subjection of land to the <hi rend="italic">trinoda nécessitas,</hi> a burden
                    imposed for the purpose of defence of the realm. The rudiments of the
                    conceptions of tenure and of the crown as lord paramount were found in the old
                    English system, and laenland was an antici]:&gt;ation of the limited interests
                    which afterwards became of such importance. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>The name has not remained as in Germany and Denmark. A
                            fief is still Lehen in Germany, Lehn in Denmark. </p></note> The
                    connexion of political privileges with the ownership of land is not peculiar to
                    the pre-Conquest or any other period. It runs through the whole of English
                    history. Originally all freeholders seem to have voted in the county court.
                    Finally the Reform Acts of this century, however they may have lowered the
                    qualification, still require (except in the case of the university vote) the
                    vote to be derived from an interest in land. No amount of consols will give a
                    vote at a parliamentary election. A qualification from land is also necessary in
                    the case of sheriff, justices of the peace, and other public officials.</p>
                <p>The elements of feudalism so far existed in England under the Anglo-Saxon and
                    Danish kings as to make it easy to introduce it in full at the Norman Conquest.
                    Feudalism was not so much a distinct and separate creation, developed at once in
                    its maturity, as a collection of institutions whose origin was to be found in
                    unconnected sources. What the Norman Conquest did was not to change all at once
                    allodial into feudal tenure, but to complete the association of territorial with
                    personal dependence in a state of society already prepared for it. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>‘ ‘ The relation of
                            vassalage, originally personal, became annexed to the tenure of land”
                            (Palgrave, Rise and Progress of the English Commonwealth, vol. i. p.
                            505). </p></note> “Nulle terre sans seigneur” was one of the fundamental
                    axioms of feudalism. There might be any number of infeudations and
                    subinfeudations to mesne lords, but the chain of seigniory was complete,
                    depending in the last resort upon the king as lord paramount. Land was not owned
                    by free owners owing only necessary militia duties to the state, but was held of
                    the king by military service of a far more onerous nature. The folkland became
                    the king’s land; the soldier was a landowner instead of the landowner being a
                    soldier. Free owners tended to become tenants of the lord, the township to be
                    lost in the manor. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It
                            is a disputed point whether the manor organization existed before the
                            Conquest; but its full development seems to have been later than that
                            event. </p></note> The common land became in law the waste of the manor,
                    its enjoyment resting upon a presumed grant by the lord. On the other hand, the
                    whole of England did not become manorial; the conflict between the township and
                    the manor resulted in a compromise, the result of which affects English tenure
                    to this day. But it was a compromise much to the advantage of the privileged
                    class, for in England more than in any other country the land law is the law of
                    the nobility and not of the people. One reason of this is that, as England was
                    never so completely feudalized as were some of the Continental states, the
                    burden of feudalism was not so severely felt, and has led to less agitation for
                    reform.</p>
                <p>The land forfeited to the Conqueror was regranted by him to be held by military
                    service due to the king, not to the mesne lord as in Continental feudalism. In
                    1086 at the council of Salisbury all the landholders swore fealty to the crown.
                    In the full vigour of feudalism the inhabitants of England were either free or
                    not free. The free inhabitants held their lands either by free tenure <hi
                        rend="italic">(liberum tenementum,</hi> franktenement) or by a tenure which
                    was originally that of a non-free inhabitant, but attached to land in the
                    possession of a free man. Franktenement was either military tenure, called also
                    tenure in knight service or chivalry (including barony, the highest tenure known
                    to the law, grand serjeanty and the special forms of escuage, castle-guard,
                    cornage, and others), or socage (including burgage and petit serjeanty), or
                    frankalmoign <hi rend="italic">(libera elee-mosyna</hi> ) or divine service, by
                    which ecclesiastical corporations generally held their land. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Frankalmoign was not
                            always regarded as a distinct tenure. Thus Littleton (§ 118) says that
                            all that is not tenure in chivalry is tenure </p></note> The non-free
                    inhabitants were in Domesday Book <hi rend="italic">servi, cotarii,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">bordarii,</hi> later <hi rend="italic">nativi</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">villani,</hi> the last name being applied to both free men and
                    serfs. All these were in a more or less dependent condition. The free tenures
                    all exist at the present day, though, as will appear later, the military tenures
                    have shrunk into the unimportant and exceptional tenure of grand serjeanty. The
                    non-free tenures are to a certain extent represented by <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Copyhold</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> The most important difference
                    between the military and socage tenures was the mode of descent. Whether or not
                    a feudal benefice was originally hereditary, it had certainly become so at the
                    time of the Conquest, and it descended to the eldest son. This applied at once
                    in England to land held by military service as far as regarded the capital fief.
                    The descent of socage lands or lands other than the capital fief for some time
                    followed the old pre-Conquest rule of descent. Thus in the so-called “Laws of
                    Henry I.” the lands other than the capital fief, and in Glanvill, who wrote in
                    the time of Henry II., socage lands, if anciently partible <hi rend="italic"
                        >(antiquitus divisum</hi> ), were divided among all the sons equally. But by
                    the time of Bracton (Henry III.) the course of descent of lands held by military
                    service had so far prevailed that, though it was a question of fact whether the
                    land was partible or not, if there was no evidence either way descent to the
                    eldest son was presumed. Relics of the old custom still remain in the case of
                    gavelkind (see below). The military tenant was subject to the feudal incidents,
                    from which the tenant in socage was exempt. These incidents, especially wardship
                    and marriage, were often of a very oppressive nature. Alienation of lands by
                    will, except in a few favoured districts, became impossible; alienation <hi
                        rend="italic">inter vivos</hi> was restrained in one direction in the
                    interests of the heir, in another in the interests of the lord. At the time of
                    Glanvill a tenant had a greater power of alienation over land which he had
                    purchased <hi rend="italic">(terra acquietatd)</hi> than over land which he had
                    inherited. But by the time of Bracton the heir had ceased to have any interest
                    in either kind of land. The lords were more successful. It was enacted by Magna
                    Charta that a free man should not give or sell so much of his land as to leave
                    an amount insufficient to perform his services to his lord. In spite of this
                    provision, the rights of the lords were continually diminished by subinfeudation
                    until the passing of the Statute of <hi rend="italic">Quia Emptores.</hi>
                    Alienation by a tenant in chief of the crown without licence was a ground of
                    forfeiture until 1 Edw. III. st. 2, c. 12, by which a fine was substituted. The
                    modes of conveyance at this time were only two, feoffment with livery of seisin
                    for corporeal hereditaments, grant for incorporeal hereditaments. Livery of
                    seisin, though public, was not officially recorded like the old English transfer
                    of property. The influence of local custom upon the land law must have become
                    weakened after the circuits of the judges of the King’s Court were established
                    by Henry II. Jurisdiction over litigation touching the freehold was taken away
                    from the lords’ courts by 15 Ric. II. c. 12.</p>
                <p>The common law as far as it dealt with real estate had in the main assumed its
                    present aspect by the reign of Henry III. The changes which have been made since
                    that date have been chiefly due to the action of equity in socage.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n323/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0323-0306"/>
                <p>and legislation, the latter sometimes interpreted by the courts in a manner very
                    different from the intention of parliament. The most important influence of
                    equity has been exercised in <hi rend="smallcaps">Mortgage</hi> ( <hi
                        rend="italic">q.v.)</hi> and trusts (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Trust),</hi>
                    in the doctrine of specific performance of contracts concerning real estate, and
                    in relief from forfeiture for breach of covenant. As to legislation, it is
                    impossible in this place to do more than direct attention to the main provisions
                    of the principal statutes among the mass of those which from Magna Charta
                    downwards have dealt with real estate.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History of Real Estate Legislation</hi> .—The reign of Edward
                    I. is notable for three leading statutes which are still law, all passed in the
                    interests of the superior lords. The Statute of Mortmain (7 Edw. I. st. 2, c.
                    13) is the first of a long series directed against the acquisition of land by
                    religious and charitable corporations (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Charities).</hi>
                    The statute <hi rend="italic">De Donis Conditionalibus</hi> (13 Edw. I. c. 1)
                    forbade the alienation of estates granted to a man and the heirs of his body,
                    which before the statute became on the birth of an heir at once alienable
                    (except in the case of gifts in frankmarriage), and so the lord lost his
                    escheat. For the mode in which the statute was practically defeated and estates
                    tail in their modern form created see <hi rend="smallcaps">Entail.</hi> The
                    statute <hi rend="italic">Quia Emptores</hi> (18 Edw. I. c. 1) preserved those
                    rights of the lords which were up to that time subject to be defeated by
                    subinfeudation, by enacting that in any alienation of lands the alienee should
                    hold them of the same lord of the fee as the alienor. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Tenants in chief of the crown were liable
                            to a fine on alienation until 12 Car. II. c. 24. </p></note> Since 1290
                    it has been impossible to create an estate in fee-simple to be held of a mesne
                    lord, or to reserve a rent upon a grant of an estate in fee (unless in the form
                    of a rent-charge), or to create a new manor. The statute, however, does not bind
                    the crown. The practical effect of the statute was to make the transfer of land
                    thenceforward more of a commercial and less of a feudal transaction. The writ of
                        <hi rend="italic">elegit</hi> w <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> as introduced
                    by the Statute of Westminster II. in 1285 as a creditor’s remedy over real
                    estate. It has, however, been considerably modified by subsequent legislation.
                    From 1290 to the I’eign of Henry VIII. there is no statute of the first
                    importance dealing with real estate. The reign of Henry VIII., like the reign of
                    Edward I., is signalized by three Acts, the effects of which continue to this
                    day. The one which has had the most lasting influence in law is the Statute of
                    Uses, 27 Hen. VIII. c. 10 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Conveyancing, Trust).</hi>
                    The Statute of Uses was intended to provide against secrecy of sales of land,
                    and as a necessary sequel to it an Act of the same year (27 Hen. VIII. c. 16)
                    enacted that all bargains and sales of land should be duly enrolled (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Sale).</hi> Bargain and sale was a form of equitable
                    transfer which had for some purposes superseded the common law feoffment. It
                    applied only to estates of inheritance and not to terms of years. The unforeseen
                    effect of 27 Hen. VIII. c. 16 was to establish as the ordinary form of
                    conveyance until 1841 the conveyance by lease and release. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>From the reign of Edward IV. at latest up
                            to the Fines and Recoveries Act of 1833 fines and recoveries were also
                            recognized as a means of conveyance. They are so regarded in the Statute
                            of Uses. </p></note> Uses having become legal estate by the Statute of
                    Uses, and therefore no longer devisable, 32 Hen. VIII. c. 1 (explained by 34 and
                    35 Hen. VIII. c. 5) was passed to remedy this inconvenience. It is still law as
                    to wills made before 1838 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Will).</hi> In the reign of
                    Elizabeth the Acts of 13 Eliz. c. 5 and 27 Eliz. c. 4 avoided fraudulent
                    conveyances as against all parties and voluntary conveyances as against
                    subsequent purchasers for valuable consideration. Early in the reign of Charles
                    II. the Act of 1661 (12 Car. II. c. 24) turned all the feudal tenures (with the
                    exception of frankalmoign and grand serjeanty) into tenure by free and common
                    socage and abolished the feudal incidents. The Statute of Frauds (29 Car. II. c.
                    3) contained provisions that certain leases and assignments, and that all
                    agreements and trusts relating to land, should be in writing (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Fraud).</hi> The land registries of Middlesex and Yorkshire
                    date from the reign of Anne (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Registration).</hi>
                    Devises of land for charitable purposes were forbidden by the Mortmain Act (9
                    Geo. II. c. 36). In the next reign the first general Inclosure Act was passed,
                    41 Geo. III. c. 109 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Commons).</hi> In the reign of
                    William IV. were passed the Prescription, Limitation, and Tithe Commutation Acts
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Prescription, Limitation, Tithes)</hi>; fines and
                    recoveries were abolished and simpler modes of conveyance substituted by 3 and 4
                    Will. IV. c. 74; and the laws of inheritance and dower were amended by 3 and 4
                    Will. IV. cc. 105, 106 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Inheritance, Husband and
                        Wife).</hi> In the reign of Victoria there has been a vast mass of
                    legislation dealing with real estate in almost every conceivable aspect. At the
                    immediate beginning of the reign stands the Wills Act (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Will).</hi> The transfer of real estate has been simplified by 8 and 9
                    Vict. c. 106 and by the Conveyancing Acts of 1881 and 1882 (see below).
                    Additional powers of dealing with settled estates were given by the Settled
                    Estates Act, 1856, later by the Settled Estates Act, 1877, and the Settled Land
                    Act, 1882 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Settlement).</hi> Succession duty was levied
                    for the first time on freeholds in 1853. The strictness of the Mortmain Act has
                    been relaxed in favour of gifts and sales to public institutions of various
                    kinds, such as schools, parks, and museums. The period of limitation has been
                    shortened for most purposes from tw׳enty to twelve years by the Real Property
                    Limitation Act, 1874 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Limitation).</hi> Several Acts
                    have been passed dealing with the enfranchisement and commutation of copyholds
                    and the preservation of commons and open spaces (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Commons, Copyhold).</hi> The Naturalization Act, 1870 (33 and 34 Vict. c.
                    14), enables aliens to hold and transfer land in England. The Felony Act, 1870
                    (33 and 34 Vict. c. 23), abolished forfeiture of real estate on conviction for
                    felony. The Agricultural Holdings Act, 1883 (46 and 47 Vict. c. 61), gives the
                    tenant of a tenancy within the Act a general right to compensation for
                    improvements, substitutes a year’s notice to quit for the six months’ notice
                    previously necessary, enlarges the tenant’s right to fixtures, and limits
                    distress to a year’s rent. By 47 and 48 Vict. c. 71 the law of escheat is
                    extended to incorporeal hereditaments and equitable estates. Among other
                    subjects which have been dealt with by recent legislation may be mentioned Re
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">gistration, Mortgage, Partition, Excambion,
                        Fixtures</hi><hi rend="italic">(qq.vv.),</hi> taking of land in execution,
                    declaration of title, and apportionment. Not a year passes in which the land law
                    is not altered to a greater or less degree. Bills have been introduced within
                    recent years, but hitherto unsuccessfully, for amending the law by the
                    assimilation of the succession to real and personal estate, and for the
                    compulsory enfranchisement of leaseholds.</p>
                <p>Real estate at the present day is either legal or equitable, a difference resting
                    mainly upon historical grounds (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Equity, Trust).</hi>
                    The following observations apply in general to both kinds of estate. The usual
                    classification of interests in real estate regards either the extent, the time,
                    or the mode of enjoyment. The division according to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >extent</hi> is in the first instance into corporeal and incorporeal
                    hereditaments, a division based upon the Roman law division of <hi rend="italic"
                        >res</hi> into <hi rend="italic">corporales</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >incorporales,</hi> and open to the same objection, that it is unscientific
                    as co-ordinating subjects of rights with the rights themselves. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In spite of this
                            objection the division is adopted by the legislature; see, for instance,
                            47 and 48 Vict. c. 71. </p></note> Corporeal hereditaments, says
                    Blackstone, “consist of such as affect the senses, such as may be seen and
                    handled by the body; incorporeal are not the objects of sensation, can neither
                    be seen nor handled, are creatures of the mind, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n324/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0324-0307"/>exist only in contemplation.” Corporeal
                    hereditaments are all necessarily freehold; <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>In the category of corporeal hereditaments are also
                            included, certain accessories to corporeal hereditaments proper, such as
                            groAving crops, fixtures, title-deeds, &amp;c. </p></note> an interest
                    in land less than freehold, such as a term of years, is personalty only. There
                    Aras no room for such an interest in the feudal gradation of tenure; it was
                    regarded as a mere personal contract and was incapable of the incidents of
                    tenure. By the Conveyancing Act, 1881 (44 and 45 Vict. c. 41, s. 65), the
                    residue of a long term of years may in certain casés be enlarged into the
                    fee-simple. A copyhold is in strict law only a tenancy at the will of the lord
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Copyhold).</hi> Estates of freehold are either estates
                    for life or in fee (called also estates of inheritance), the latter being in
                    fee-tail or in fee-simple. An estate for life may he either for the life of the
                    tenant or for the life of another person, the latter called an estate <hi
                        rend="italic">pur autre vie.</hi> The former kind of estate includes estates
                    of dower and curtesy (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Husband and Wife).</hi> An estate
                    in fee is called a fee simply, an obvious sign of its feudal origin. Estates
                    tail are either general or special, the latter being in tail male or (rarely) in
                    tail female. There may also be a quasi-entail of an estate <hi rend="italic">pur
                        autre vie</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Entail).</hi> An estate in
                    fee-simple is the largest estate known to English laAV. Its ordinary incidents
                    are an oath of fealty (never exacted), <hi rend="smallcaps">Escheat</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">(q.v.</hi> ), and (in a manor) suit of the court baron, and
                    occasionally a small quit-rent and relief. All these are obviously relics of the
                    once important feudal incidents. Incorporeal hereditaments consist chiefly, if
                    not wholly, of rights <hi rend="italic">in alicno solo.</hi> They are divided by
                    Mr Joshua Williams ( <hi rend="italic">Real Property,</hi> pt. ii.) into (1)
                    reversions, remainders, and executory interests, (2) hereditaments purely
                    incorporeal, the last being either appendant, appurtenant, Olin gross. Examples
                    are profits <hi rend="italic">a prendre</hi> (such as rights of common),
                    easements (such as rights of way), <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>It should be noticed that an easement in gross cannot
                            exist. </p></note> seigniories, advoAVSons, rents, tithes, titles of
                    honour, offices, franchises. Before 1845 corporeal hereditaments were said to
                    lie in livery, incorporeal in grant. But by 8 and 9 Vict. c. 106, s. 2, all
                    corporeal hereditaments are, as regards the conveyance of the immediate freehold
                    thereof, to be deemed to lie in grant as well as in livery. With regard to the
                        <hi rend="italic">time</hi> of enjoyment, estates are either in possession
                    or in expectancy, —that is, in reversion or remainder or executory interests
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Remainder).</hi> With regard to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >mode</hi> of enjoyment, estates are either joint, in common, in
                    coparcenary, or in severalty.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Exceptional Tenures.</hi> —It has been already stated that
                    there are still to be found survivals of the old pre-Conquest customary law.
                    They are found both in the tenure and in the conveyance of land. The only
                    customs of which judicial notice is taken are <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Gavelkind</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Borough-English</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> Any other local customs,
                    as in manors, must be proved by evidence. The tenures of frankalmoign and grand
                    serjeanty Avere specially preserved by 12 Car. II. c. 24. Tenure in frankalmoign
                    is the nearest approach in English law to absolute OAvnership. An estate in
                    frankalmoign has no incidents, as it is held simply by divine service and is not
                    subject to escheat. All tenures in frankalmoign must (except where created by
                    the crown) be older than <hi rend="italic">Quia Emptores.</hi> The tenure of
                    grand serjeanty is the holding of lands by doing a personal service to the king,
                    as carrying his banner or sword. Petit serjeanty consists in the payment to the
                    king yearly of a bow, sword, dagger, or such other small things belonging to war
                    (Littleton, § 159). It is in effect socage.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Title.</hi> —This is the name given to the mode of acquisition
                    of rights over real estate. Title may arise either by alienation, voluntary or
                    involuntary, or by succession. Voluntary alienation is either <hi rend="italic"
                        >inter vivos</hi> or by will. The former branch is practically synonymous
                    with conveyance, Avhether by way of sale, settlement, mortgage, or otherwise. As
                    a general rule alienation of real estate <hi rend="italic">inter vivos</hi> must
                    be by deed since 8 and 9 Vict. c. 106. Since that Act a deed of grant has
                    superseded the old forms of feoffment and lease and release. Considerable
                    alterations in the direction of shortness and simplicity have been made in the
                    laAV of transfer of real estate by the Conveyancing Acts, 1881, 1882 (44 and 45
                    Viet, c. 41, 45 and 46 Vict. c. 39). The word “grant” is no longer necessary for
                    a conveyance, nor are the old words of limitation <hi rend="italic">“</hi>
                    heirs” and <hi rend="italic">“</hi> heirs of the body.” It is sufficient to use
                    the words “in fee-simple,” “in tail,” “in tail male,” “in tail female.” Many
                    provisions usually inserted in deeds, such as covenants for title by a
                    beneficial OAvner and powers of appointment of neAV trustees, obtain statutory
                    sanction. Forms of mortgage, conveyance, and settlement are appended to the Act.
                    The Solicitors’ Remuneration Act, 1881 (44 and 45 Vict. c. 44), was passed as a
                    necessary sequel to the Conveyancing Act, and the remuneration of solicitors <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">uoav</hi> stands upon a different and more satisfactory
                    basis. For acquisition by Avili and succession, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Will,
                        Inheritance.</hi> Involuntary alienation is by <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Bankruptcy</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> and by other means of
                    enforcing the rights of creditors over land, such as distress or execution. It
                    may also arise by the exercise by the state of its right of eminent domain for
                    public purposes, as under the Lands Clauses and other Acts. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The right of the state to
                            contribution from land for revenue purposes and </p></note> In sales of
                    real estate title is generally traced in an abstract delivered by the vendor
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sale).</hi><hi rend="italic">Restraints on
                        Alienation.</hi> —The alienation of real estate may be subject to almost any
                    conditions, provided that such conditions do not contravene the law. As a
                    general rule there can be no restrictions upon the alienation of an estate in
                    fee-simple <hi rend="italic">;</hi> the tAvo ideas are incompatible. In the
                    case, hoAvever, of a married Avoman a restraint on anticipation is allowed
                    Avithin certain limits. The poAver of imposing such a restraint is preserved by
                    the Married Women’s Property Act, 1882 (45 and 46 Vict. c. 75, s. 19), subject
                    to the right of the court to bind the interest of the married woman Avhere it
                    would be for her benefit to do so (44 and 45 Vict. c. 41, s. 39). In another
                    direction the imposition of a course of devolution upon property is forbidden by
                    the law against perpetuities, under Avliich no executory interest can be made to
                    commence unless within the period of any fixed number of existing lives, and an
                    additional period of twenty-one years (with a few months added, if necessary,
                    for the period of gestation). Accumulation of income is forbidden (with a feAv
                    exceptions) by the Thelusson Act (39 and 40 Geo. III. c. 98) for any longer term
                    than the life of the grantor or settlor, or twenty-one years from his death, or
                    during a period of minority. Certain persons are by the general policy of the
                    law disabled from exercising full proprietary rights, such as married women (see
                    above), convicts, infants, and lunatics. Estates tail are in general alienable
                    under the Fines and Recoveries Act (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Entail).</hi> But
                    in a few cases estates tail are settled inalienably by Act of Parliament,
                    generally as a reAvard for public services. Estates are thus settled to go Avith
                    the titles of Marlborough, Wellington, Abergavenny, and Shrewsbury.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Exceptional Modes of Alienation.</hi> —In some of these cases,
                    like those of the exceptional tenures, the influence of the old customary law is
                    to be traced. The transfer of copyholds especially depends to a great extent
                    upon the custom of particular manors, but, subject to that, it usually takes
                    place by surrender and admittance (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Copyhold).</hi>
                    Gavelkind lands may be conveyed by feoffment by any infant above the age of
                    fifteen. For mines in the Forest of Dean a peculiar mode of transfer is provided
                    by 1 and 2 Vict. c. 43. In the Isle of Portland there seems to be a distinct
                    survival of the pre-feudal conveyance. The vendor and purchaser meet in the
                    parish church, where a deed is signed by the parties in the presence of two
                    householders of the island. These deeds are called “church gifts.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Procedure.</hi> —In some cases rights attaching to real estate
                    are protected by peculiar remedies. At an early period it became more convenient
                    to try the right to the possession of, rather than the right to the property in,
                    real estate. Possessory tended to supersede proprietary remedies, from their
                    great simplicity and elasticity. The general mode of trying the right to both
                    property and possession Avas from the time of Henry II. the real action, the
                    form called “Avrit of right” (after Magna Charta gradually confined to the Court
                    of Common Pleas) being used to determine the property, that called “assise of
                    novel disseisin” being the general means by Avhich the possession Avas tried.
                    About the reign of Elizabeth the action of ejectment became the ordinary form of
                    possessory remedy. Real actions existed until 3 and 4 Will. IV. c. 27, by which
                    they were finally abolished, with the exception of Avrit of right of dower, writ
                    of dower <hi rend="italic">unde nihil habet, quare impedit,</hi> and ejectment.
                    Of these <hi rend="smallcaps">Quake Impedit</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi>
                    appears to be the only one noAv in use. The assise of novel disseisin, the
                    action of ejectment in both its original and its reformed stage (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Ejectment),</hi> and finally the action for the recovery of
                    land in use since the Judicature Acts are all historically connected as gradual
                    developments of the possessory action (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Possession).</hi> The action for the recovery of land is still subject to
                    special provisions and is not quite in the same position as an ordinary action
                    (see Rules of the Supreme Court, 1883, Ord. xii. rr. 25-29, Ord. xviii. r. 2,
                    &amp;c.). There are certain matters affecting real estate over which the Court
                    of Chancery formerly had exclusive jurisdiction, in most cases because the
                    principles on Avhieli the court acted had been the creation of equity. The
                    Judicature Act, 1873 (36 and 37 Vict. c. 66, s. 34). assigns to the Chancery
                    Division of the High Court of Justice all causes and matters for <hi
                        rend="italic">(inter alia)</hi> the redemption or foreclosure of mortgages,
                    the raising of portions or other charges on land, the sale and distribution of
                    the proceeds of property subject to any lien or charge, the specific performance
                    of contracts betAveen vendors and purchasers of real estates, including
                    contracts for leases, the partition or sale of real estates, and the wardship of
                    infants and the care of infants’ estates. In the case of rent a summary mode of
                    remedy by act of the creditor still exists (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Distress,
                        Rent).</hi></p>
                <p>For the economical aspect of the English law, see Land. For a list of the main
                    points of difference betAA'een real and personal estate, see Personal
                    Estate.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.</hi> —Those cited at the end of <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Land,</hi> and in addition Digby, <hi rend="italic">History
                        of the Law of Real Property;</hi> Elton, <hi rend="italic">Tenures of
                        Kent;</hi> Goodeve, <hi rend="italic">Modern Law of Real Property;</hi>
                    Pollock, <hi rend="italic">Land Laws;</hi> Stephen, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Commentaries,</hi> vol. i.; Seebohm, <hi rend="italic">English Village
                        Community,</hi> Williams, <hi rend="italic">Real Property,</hi> Wolstenholme
                    and Turner, <hi rend="italic">Conveyancing Acts.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Ireland.—</hi> The latv of real estate in Ireland is the English law, to
                    stamp duties on deeds perhaps falls under this head. These imposts are really
                    involuntary alienations of part of the profit of the land.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n325/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0325-0308"/>
                <p>which finally superseded the native law in James I.’s reign, as modified by
                    subsequent legislation. The main difference is in the law of <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Landlord and Tenant</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> and
                    the operation of the Landed Estates Court, merged in the High Court of Justice
                    in Ireland by the Supreme Court of Judicature (Ireland) Act, 1877.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States.</hi> —The law of real estate in the United
                    States is the law of England modified to suit a different state of
                    circumstances. The main point of difference is that in the United States the
                    occupiers of land are generally wholly or in part owners, not tenants, as iu
                    England. This is to a great extent the effect of the homestead laws (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Homestead).</hi> The traces of the feudal origin of the law
                    are, as might be expected, considerably less prominent than in England. Thus
                    estates tail are practically obsolete; in some States they are specially
                    forbidden by the State constitutions. The law of descent is the same in real and
                    personal estate (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Inheritance).</hi> Manors do not
                    exist, except in the State of New York, where they were created by the crown in
                    colonial days (Bouvier, <hi rend="italic">Law Diet.,</hi> “Manor”). Registration
                    of deeds is general (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Registration).</hi> In some States
                    forms of deed are prescribed by statute. Conveyancing is for the most part
                    simpler than in England. The holding of real estate by religious or charitable
                    corporations is generally restricted by the Act creating them rather than by
                    anything like the English law of mortmain. In Pennsylvania such a corporation
                    cannot hold land without an Act of the legislature, and in Territories of the
                    United States it cannot hold real estate of a greater value than $50,000 (Act of
                    Congress of 1st July 1862, c. 126). Perpetuities are forbidden in most States.
                    The right of eminent domain is at once acknowledged and limited by the
                    constitution of the United States. By art. 5 of the Amendments private property
                    is not to be taken for public use without just compensation. A similar provision
                    is found in many of the State constitutions. By an Act of Congress of 9th April
                    1866, c. 31, all citizens of the United States have the same right in every
                    State and Territory as is enjoyed by white citizens thereof to inherit,
                    purchase, lease, sell, hold, and convey real and personal property. In most
                    States aliens may hold land; but in some States they cannot do so without
                    becoming naturalized or at least filing in the specified manner a declaration of
                    intention to become naturalized. For the State laws affecting the capacity of
                    aliens to hold land, see Washburn, <hi rend="italic">Real Property,</hi> vol. i.
                    p. 64.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">International Law</hi> .—The law of the place where real estate
                    is situated <hi rend="italic">(lex loci rei sitae)</hi> governs its tenure aud
                    transfer. The laws of England and of the United States are more strict on this
                    point than the laws of most other countries. They require that the formalities
                    of the <hi rend="italic">locus rei sitae</hi> must be observed, even if not
                    necessary to be observed in the place where the contract was made. The <hi
                        rend="italic">lex loci rei sitae</hi> determines what is to be considered
                    real estate. A foreign court cannot as a general rule pass title to land
                    situated in another country. The English and United States courts of equity have
                    to a certain extent avoided the inconvenience which this inability to deal with
                    laud out of the jurisdiction sometimes causes by the use of the theory that
                    equity acts upon the conscience of the party and not upon the title to the
                    foreign land. Thus in the leading case of Penn <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Lord
                    Baltimore in 1750 (1 Yesey’s <hi rend="italic">Reports,</hi> 444) the Court of
                    Chancery on this ground decreed specific performance of articles for settling
                    the boundaries of the provinces of Pennsylvania and Maryland. The difficulty
                    always arises that, although the court professes to act upon the conscience, it
                    must indirectly act upon the property, and that it cannot carry its decision
                    into execution without the aid of the local tribunals. (J. W+. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
