<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0273-0256-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RAINGAUGE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 256</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1091659">Records</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1090626">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n273/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RAINGAUGE</label><hi rend="smallcaps">(Pluviometer,
                    Hyetometer, Udometer).</hi> The value of the measurement of rainfall (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Meteorology)</hi> has long been understood, although it is only
                    within the last hundred years that trustworthy results have been obtained.
                    Marriotte is claimed as the originator of the raingauge in 1677. The simplest
                    form is an open vessel of uniform diameter exposed to the rain, in which the
                    depth of water collected during any interval of time may be measured. In order
                    to reduce evaporation the mouth of the gauge is usually a funnel of the same
                    diameter as the vessel; and some means, such as an external narrow glass tube
                    graduated in inches and parts to show the height of the water inside, or a float
                    bearing a graduated rod, or, in more delicate forms, a movable scale which may
                    be set by a vernier to the surface of the water, is adopted to facilitate
                    measurement. Raingauges on this plan cannot be very accurate; their one
                    advantage is that the area of the collecting surface does not require to be
                    known. The disadvantages are that so much water is required to wet the sides of
                    the vessel as to make the instrument read too low when a side tube is used, and
                    the tube is liable to <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n274/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0274-0257"/>be broken in frost; when a float and rod are
                    employed, the rod projecting above the funnel catches rain and the resulting
                    reading is too high. Almost all raingauges now used have a circular funnel of
                    known diameter, which conducts the rain-water to a receiver, from which it may
                    be poured into a special narrow measuring-glass so graduated that what would
                    cover a space of the area of the funnel to the depth of 1 inch fills a portion
                    of the glass large enough to be easily graduated into 100 parts. The funnel may
                    have any diameter from 3 to 24 inches without introducing a greater discrepancy
                    than 1 or 2 per cent, of the amount of rain collected, but 5 and 8 inches are
                    the diameters usually employed, and the measuring-glasses are graduated
                    accordingly. Advantage is sometimes taken of the fact that for a funnel 4697־
                    inches in diameter 1 fluid ounce of water collected represents one-tenth of an
                    inch of rain, since the area is 1733־ square inches, and a fluid ounce at 60°
                    Fahr. contains 1733־ cubic inches of water.</p>
                <p>The best form of instrument, Glaisher’s rain and snow gauge recommended by the
                    Royal Meteorological Society, is a cylindrical copper vessel 8 inches in
                    diameter and 18 inches high, in which the funnel is placed about halfway down
                    (see fig. 1).</p>
                <p>The Scottish Meteorological Society largely employ Howard’s raingauge, a plain
                    glass bottle holding about half a gallon and provided with a long 5-inch copper
                    funnel, which has a collar fitting over the neck of the bottle to prevent rain
                    from being blown in laterally by the wind. In some forms the funnel leads to a
                    long glass tube divided into inches, tenths, and hundredths of rainfall. Mr
                    Symon’s storm raingauge on this principle is intended to be read from a
                    distance, and is only graduated into tenths of an inch. The water collected by a
                    raingauge may be weighed instead of measured, but the latter process being much
                    more simple is always adopted, at a slight expense of accuracy, however, as the
                    variation of volume with temperature is not taken into account. Precipitation
                    and evaporation being complementary phenomena, an atmometer or evaporation-gauge
                    ought, strictly speaking, to accompany each raingauge. But none of the
                    instruments yet devised can be regarded as satisfactory, accordingly a number of
                    devices have been introduced to calculate or to minimize the evaporation from
                    raingauges. Dr Garnett in 1795 proposed to use two gauges of unequal size, and
                    recently Prof. Michie Smith has introduced a simplification by making the area
                    of one gauge exactly double that of the other. If the evaporation is the same
                    from each, the difference between the readings of the two gauges gives the true
                    rainfall in the smaller. If <hi rend="italic">A</hi> be the area of the funnel
                    in the smaller, 2 <hi rend="italic">A</hi> that of the funnel in the larger, <hi
                    rend="italic">V</hi> a certain volume of water placed in each gauge, <hi
                    rend="italic">E</hi> the evaporation, and <hi rend="italic">II</hi> the inches
                    of rainfall, then <hi rend="italic">V</hi> + <hi rend="italic">2 All</hi> - <hi
                    rend="italic">E-{V+ AR-E) — AR,</hi> however <hi rend="italic">V</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">E</hi> may vary. The simplest and best method is to use a funnel
                    terminating in a long straight tube, which reaches almost to the bottom of the
                    receiving vessel. Gauges have been constructed for experimental purposes always
                    to face the wind, and with openings capable of being fixed at any angle. For use
                    at sea they may be swung on gimbals; but when so employed the record must be
                    supplemented by the readings of a hydrometer so as to detect and allow for any
                    admixture with sea-spray. Self-registering and self-recording raingauges, as
                    frequently used in meteorological observatories, are constructed on two leading
                    types. In Hermann’s “hyetometrograph,” 1789, a fixed funnel conducts the rain
                    into one of twelve glasses placed on the circumference of a horizontal wheel,
                    which is turned by clockwork so that each glass remains under the funnel for one
                    hour. In Stutter’s more recent instrument the receiving funnel delivers into a
                    smaller funnel, which has a sloping tube and is carried round by clockwork so as
                    to remain for one hour over each of twenty-four fixed glasses arranged in a
                    circle. The second kind of self-registering instrument produces a continuous
                    record of rainfall, indicating the hour of commencement and close of each
                    shower, the amount of rain that has fallen, and the rate at which it fell. In
                    Beckley’s “pluviograph” a pencil, attached to a vessel which sinks as it
                    receives the rain, describes a curve on a sheet of paper fixed round a rotating
                    cylinder; when full the receiver empties itself by means of a siphon and the
                    pencil is carried rapidly upwards, describing a straight vertical line.</p>
                <p>The higher a raingauge is placed above the ground, or rather above a broad flat
                    surface, the smaller is the rainfall registered, as the following figures
                    indicate :—</p>
                <p>Height of funnel above ground in feet. .0 1 10 20 40 200</p>
                <p>Bain registered (average)..............158־0 70־0 90־0 93'0 00־1 07־</p>
                <p>When the mouth of the gauge is on or within a few inches of the ground the
                    insplashing of raindrops increases the amount of water. Minute rain-spherules,
                    which usually float in horizontal or oblique planes, are most numerous near the
                    ground, where consequently they coalesce to form regular drops which fall into
                    the funnel. The raindrops also increase slightly in size by condensing moisture
                    as they fall. But the greatest effect is probably produced by wind, which forms
                    eddies round high and isolated objects, thus more or less interfering with the
                    fall of rain into the gauge. It is obvious that all raingauges intended for
                    comparison should be fixed at the same height, and in Great Britain the standard
                    distance of the mouth of the funnel from the ground or from a broad flat surface
                    is one foot. The situation of a raingauge should be perfectly open, especially
                    in the direction of the prevailing rainbringing winds. In measuring rain it is
                    essential to see that the funnel is not indented or deformed in any way, and
                    that the collecting vessel is inaccessible to air or rain except through the
                    funnel. The temperature of rain as it falls should be observed whenever it is
                    possible to do so. The amount of solid matter collected in the raingauge should
                    be ascertained and recorded as bearing on Mr Aitken’s theory of rain (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Evaporation),</hi> and it should be examined microscopically
                    for volcanic and cosmic dust. (H. R. M.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
