<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0505-0488-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RETZ (9th edition, volume 20, page 488)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n505/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RETZ</label> Jean François Paul de Gondi, Cardinal de
                    (1614-1679), was born at Montmirail in 1614. The family was one of those which
                    had been introduced into France by Catherine de’ Medici, but it had acquired
                    great estates in Brittany and had been connected with the noblest houses of the
                    kingdom. It may be added that Retz himself always spelt his designation “Rais,”
                    and the spelling is not inconvenient for foreigners. He was the third son, and
                    according to Tallemant des Réaux was made a knight of Malta on the very day of
                    his birth. The death of his second brother, however, destined him for a closer
                    connexion with the church. The family of Retz had military traditions, for the
                    cardinal’s father, Philippe Emmanuel, was general of the galleys, and his
                    grandfather Albert was marshal of France. But it had also much church influence,
                    Retz’s uncle being archbishop of Paris, and, despite the very unclerical
                    leanings of the future cardinal, which were not corrected by the teachings of St
                    Vincent de Paul, who was his tutor, the intentions of his family never varied
                    respecting him. It was in vain that, as he has recounted with some vanity in his
                    famous memoirs, he flirted, fought duels, and endeavoured in every way to show
                    that he had no vocation. His friends might have some excuse for doubting his
                    aptitude for a more active career despite his vivacious temperament, for by
                    unanimous consent his physical appearance was not that of a soldier. He was
                    short, near-sighted, ugly (though his ugliness had much in common with that of
                    Wilkes), and exceptionally awkward of hand and gesture. Retz, however, despite
                    the little inclination which he felt towards clerical life, was not a man to
                    leave any kind of career to which he had access untried. He entered into the
                    disputes of· the Sorbonne with vigour, and when he was scarcely eighteen wrote
                    the remarkable <hi rend="italic">Conjuration de Eiesque,</hi> a little
                    historical essay of which he drew the material from the Italian of Mascardi, but
                    which is all his own in the negligent vigour of the style and the audacious
                    insinuation, if nothing more, of revolutionary principles. It is said, though
                    the anecdotes of this time are always suspicious, that Richelieu’s verdict after
                    reading the pamphlet was “voilà un homme dangereux.” However this may be, Retz
                    received no preferment of importance during Richelieu’s life, and even after the
                    minister’s death, though he was presented to Louis XIII. and well received (the
                    king offered him a bishopric), he found a difficulty in attaining the object of
                    his wishes, that is to say, the coadjutorship with reversion of the
                    archbishopric of Paris. But almost immediately after the king’s death Anne of
                    Austria appointed him to the coveted post on All Saints’ Eve, 1643. Retz, who
                    had according to some accounts already plotted against Richelieu, set himself to
                    work to make the utmost political capital out of his position. His uncle, who
                    was old, indolent, and absurdly proud, had lived in great seclusion; Retz, on
                    the contrary, by assiduously cultivating the parish <hi rend="italic">cures</hi>
                    and distributing large sums in alms, gradually acquired a very great influence
                    with the populace of the city. This influence he gradually turned against
                    Mazarin—partly from the general dislike which the French nobles had to that
                    low-born adventurer, but partly also, it would appear, because he himself was
                    not in Mazarin’s place. No one had more to do than Retz with the outbreak of the
                    Fronde in October 1648, and his history for the next four years is the history
                    of that confused and, as a rule, much misunderstood movement. Of the two parties
                    who, sometimes in union and sometimes at variance with each other, opposed the
                    system of absolute monarchy carried on by an omnipotent minister, Retz could
                    only depend on the bourgeoisie, not on the nobles, and even in the case of the
                    bourgeoisie he had little influence out of Paris. The fact, moreover, that
                    although he had some speculative tendencies in favour of popular liberties, and
                    even perhaps of republicanism, he represented no real political principle, as
                    the parliament of Paris did and as did great nobles like La Rochefoucauld,
                    inevitably weakened his position. His adroitness of intrigue and his boldness in
                    action (which was even shown on the field of battle) served him little in the
                    long run, and when the break up of the Fronde came he was left in the lurch,
                    having more than once in the meanwhile been in no small danger from his own
                    party. One stroke of luck, however, fell to him before his downfall. He was made
                    cardinal almost by accident, and under a misapprehension on the pope’s part.
                    Then, in 1652, he was arrested and imprisoned, first at Vincenues, then at
                    Nantes; he escaped, however, after two years’ captivity, and for some time
                    wandered about in England and elsewhere. He made his appearance at Rome more
                    than once, and had no small influence in the election of Alexander VII. He was
                    at last, in 1662, received back again into favour by Louis XIV. and on more than
                    one occasion formally served as envoy to Rome,—commissions which have left
                    abundant records in the shape of official documents. Retz, however, was too
                    shrewd, and perhaps too weary of political intrigue to attempt any interference
                    with the new order of things at home, and he was glad in making his peace to
                    resign his claims to the archbishopric of Paris. The terms were, among other
                    things, his appointment to the rich abbacy of St Denis and his restoration to
                    his other benefices with the payment of arrears.</p>
                <p>The last seventeen years of Retz’s life were comparatively quiet, and were passed
                    partly in his diplomatic duties (he was again in Rome at the papal election of
                    1668), partly at Paris, partly at his estate of Commercy, but latterly at St
                    Mihiel in Lorraine. His retirement to this place was made under circumstances
                    which were unusual for the age. His debts were as enormous as his revenues were
                    large, and, as the latter were almost entirely derived from ecclesiastical
                    appointments, his creditors had no remedy. In 1675 he resolved to make over to
                    them all his income except twenty thousand livres, and, as he said, to “live for
                    his creditors.” This plan he carried out, though he did not succeed in living
                    very long, for he died at Paris on the 24th August 1679. One of the chief
                    authorities for the last years of Retz is Madame de Sévigné, whose connexion he
                    was by marriage. Great friendship existed between them, and the cardinal was
                    especially devoted to Madame de Grignan, who seems to have treated him with her
                    usual selfish indifference.</p>
                <p>Retz and La Rochefoucauld, the greatest of the Frondeurs in literary genius, were
                    personal and political enemies, and each has left a portrait of the other. La
                    Rochefoucauld’s character of the cardinal is on the whole harsh but scarcely
                    unjust, and one of its sentences formulates, though in a manner which has a
                    certain recoil upon the writer, the great defect of Retz’s conduct,—“Il a
                    suscité les plus grands désordres dans l’état sans avoir un dessein formé de
                    s’en prévaloir.” The last two words indicate but too clearly the self-seeking
                    which was the bane of the Fronde and of the French noblesse generally. But it is
                    perfectly true that no general design of benefiting either himself or his
                    country, or even any party or order in his country, can be traced in Retz’s
                    conduct, and that he seems to have kindled the fires of civil war in pure gaiety
                    of heart. He would have been less, and certainly less favourably, remembered if
                    it had not been for his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> which, with Madame de
                    Sévigné’s notices, give a rather high idea of the amiability of his character at
                    the same time that they confirm its levity, and above all prove his possession
                    of remarkable literary faculty. They were <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n506/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0506-0489"/>certainly not written till the last ten years
                    of his life, and they do not go further than the year 1655. They are addressed
                    in the form of narrative to a lady who is not known, though guesses have been
                    made at her identity. In the beginning there are some gaps. They display, in a
                    rather irregular style and with some oddities of dialect and phrase,
                    extraordinary narrative skill and a high degree of ability in that special art
                    of the 17th century—the drawing of verbal portraits or characters. Few things of
                    the kind are superior to the sketch of the early barricade of the Fronde in
                    which the writer had so great a share, the hesitations of the court, the bold
                    adventure of the coadjutor himself into the palace, and the final triumph of the
                    insurgents. Dumas, who has drawn from this passage one of his very best scenes
                    in <hi rend="italic">Vingt Ans après,</hi> has done little but throw Retz into
                    dialogue and amplify his language and incidents. Besides these memoirs and the
                    very striking youthful essay of the <hi rend="italic">Conjuration de
                        Piesque,</hi> Retz has left diplomatic papers, sermons, Mazarinades, and
                    correspondence in some considerable quantity.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> of the Cardinal de Retz were first published
                    in a very imperfect condition in 1717 at Nancy. The first satisfactory edition
                    was that which appeared in the twenty-fourth volume of the collection of Michaud
                    and Poujoulat (Paris, 1836). They were then re-edited from the autograph
                    manuscript by Géruzez (Paris, 1844), and by Champollion-Figeac with the
                    Mazarinades, &amp;c. (Paris, 1859). In 1870 a complete edition of the works of
                    Retz was begun by M. Feillet in the collection of <hi rend="italic">Grands
                        Écrivains.</hi> The editor dying, this passed into the hands of M. Gourdault
                    and then into those of M. Chantelauze, who had already published studies on the
                    connexion of St Vincent de Paul with the Gondι family, &amp;e. The edition is
                    still incomplete, and the critical biography of Retz which it may be expected to
                    contain is much wanted. (G. SA. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
