<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0503-0486-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RESTIF</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 486</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57r7v">Printers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1076585">Printers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n503/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RESTIF</label> Nicolas Edme (1734-1806), called Restif de la
                    Bretonne (the form Retif, though occasionally used by the author himself, and
                    adopted by M. Monselet, has the less authority), was born at Sacy in the present
                    department of the Yonne, France, on 23d October 1734. His father was a farmer of
                    not the lowest rank, and the vanity of Restif has preserved or invented an
                    extraordinary genealogy (supposed to date from his grandfather’s time) in which
                    the family is traced to the Roman emperor Pertinax. This Restif did not take
                    very seriously, but he is himself almost the only authority for the details of
                    his own career, which he has voluminously recorded, and these details are in
                    part so incredible, in part so obviously distorted by various motives, that it
                    is very hard to do more than discover the general outline of his life. He was
                    well educated—partly if not chiefly by his own devotion to books—he was
                    apprenticed to a printer at Auxerre, and, having served his time, went to Paris.
                    Here he worked as a journeyman printer for some time (indeed he continued his
                    manual work for the greater part of his life), and in 1760 he married Anne or
                    Agnes Lebègue, a relation of his former master at Auxerre. He soon tired of her,
                    and has left the most unfavourable pictures of her morals and temper. In the
                    early years of their married life they were but little together, and for the
                    last twenty they never saw each other; but Restif’s own account is sufficient to
                    show that certainly not all, and probably very few, of the faults were on the
                    wife’s side. It was not till five or six years after his marriage that Restif,
                    who by his own account had written voluminously from his earliest youth but had
                    published nothing, appeared as an author, and from that time to his death on
                    February 2, 1806, he produced a bewildering multitude of books (amounting to
                    something like two hundred volumes, and many of them printed with his own hand)
                    on almost every conceivable variety of subject. The most noteworthy are <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Pied de Fanxhette,</hi> a novel (1769); <hi rend="italic">Le
                    Pornographe</hi> (same date), a plan for regulating prostitution which is said
                    to have been actually carried out by the emperor Joseph IL, while not a few
                    detached hints have been adopted by Continental nations; <hi rend="italic">Le
                    Paysan Perverti</hi> (1774), a novel in which much of his own experience is
                    worked in; <hi rend="italic">La Vie de Mon Père</hi> (1779), a really remarkable
                    monument of filial piety; <hi rend="italic">Les Contemporaines</hi> (42 vols.,
                    1780-85), a vast collection of short stories showing at once Restif’s fertility
                    of invention, his narrative faculty, and his accurate observation of the manners
                    of Paris; <hi rend="italic">Ingenue Saxancour&gt;</hi> also a novel (1789); and,
                    lastly, the extraordinary autobiography of <hi rend="italic">Monsieur
                    Nicolas</hi> (16 vols., 1794-97; the last two are practically a separate and
                    much less interesting work), in which at the age of sixty he has set down
                    voluminously his remembrances, his notions on ethical and social points, his
                    hatreds, and above all his numerous or innumerable loves real and fancied. The
                    original editions of these, and indeed of all his books, have long been
                    bibliographical curiosities owing to their rarity, the beautiful and curious
                    illustrations which many of them contain, and the quaint typographic system in
                    which most are composed. The author’s life during this long period was a
                    singular mixture of hard work and perpetual falling in love. He seems to have
                    really seen society of the most varied kind, though in this as in all other
                    matters he certainly exaggerates and perhaps invents in a way which makes it
                    impossible to discern the exact truth. Some of his books sold well, and, as has
                    been said, he was always industrious as an author or a printer and sometimes as
                    both. But he had repeated losses, and though never in actual want was never in
                    easy circumstances. He was arrested once during the Revolution but had no
                    difficulty in getting off; indeed he seems to have been a convinced republican.
                    In 1795 he received a gratuity of 2000 francs from the Government, and just
                    before his death Napoleon gave him a place in the ministry of police, which he
                    did not live to take up. After his death Cubières Palmeaux, a gentleman
                    literary-hack of the day, wrote his life.</p>
                <p>Restif de la Bretonne undoubtedly bolds a remarkable place in French literature,
                    though the rarity and curious character of his books have sometimes induced his
                    editors and commentators to take too high a view of his merits. He was
                    inordinately vain, of extremely relaxed morals, and perhaps not entirely sane.
                    His books were written with such haste and in such bulk that they can only be
                    praised with great allowance. Their licence of subject and language renders some
                    if not most of them r∣uite unfit for general perusal. But when every deduction
                    is made there will remain on a just estimate the facts that Restif had a
                    singular and profound knowledge of the human heart ffhe second title of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Monsieur</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n504/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0504-0487"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Kimlas</hi> is <hi rend="italic">Le Coeur Humain Dévoilé),</hi>
                    that among his random and often chimerical speculations on social, ethical, and
                    political matters thoughts of extraordinary justness now and then occur, that
                    his observation of manners was keen, and that his narrative faculty, at least in
                    short tales and detached passages, was exceptionally good.</p>
                <p>Original editions of Restif are, as has been said, bibliographical curiosities.
                    The works of Oh. Monselet (1853) and P. Lacroix (1875), Assczat’s selection from
                    the <hi rend="italic">Contemporaines,</hi> with excellent introductions (3
                    vols., 1875), and the valuable reprint of <hi rend="italic">Monsieur
                    Nicolas</hi> (14 vols., 1883-84), will be sufficient to enable even curious
                    readers to form a judgment of him. The selection from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Contemporaines</hi> preserves Restif’s curious printing and spelling.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
