<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0510-0493-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">REUSS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 493</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d84h">Sorbs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j33z">Debt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hm52s7v">Production</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:888768">Debt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150508">Thuringians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1126761">Sorbs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n510/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REUSS</label> is the name of two small sovereign
                    principalities of the German empire, with a joint area of 440 square miles,
                    forming part of the complex of Thuringian states, and consisting, roughly
                    speaking, of two principal masses of territory, separated by the Neustadt
                    district of the duchy of Saxe-Weimar. The more southerly and much the larger of
                    the two portions belongs to the bleak mountainous region of the Frankenwald and
                    the Voigtland, while the northern portion is hilly but fertile. The chief rivers
                    are the Elster and Saale. About 37 per cent, of the total surface is occupied by
                    forests, while 40 per cent, is under tillage and 19 per cent, in meadow and
                    pasture. Since 1616 the lauds of Reuss have been divided between an elder and a
                    younger line <hi rend="italic">{Reuss älterer Linie</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Reuss jüngerer Linie)</hi> of the ancient princely house. The male members of
                    both branches of the family all bear the name of Henry (Heinrich), the
                    individuals being distinguished by numerals. In the older line the enumeration
                    begins again when the number one hundred is reached, while in the younger house
                    it opens and closes with the century. Thus the reigning prince of Reuss jüngerer
                    Linie, born in 1832, is styled Henry XIV., and he succeeded his father Henry
                    LXVII., born in 1789. The princes of Reuss are very wealthy, and their private
                    domains comprise great part of the territory over which they rule. In the event
                    of the extinction of either line, its possessions fall to the other. The troops
                    of Reuss furnish a few companies to the seventh regiment of Thuringian
                    infantry.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reuss-Greiz, or Reuss älterer Linie, with an area of 122
                    square miles, belongs to the larger of the two main divisions above mentioned,
                    within which it consists of three large and several smaller parcels of land,
                    bordering on Saxony, Reuss jüngerer Linie, Schwarzburg-Rudolstadt, and the
                    Prussian exclave of Ranis. The soil is on the whole little favourable for
                    agriculture, but cattle-rearing is carried on with some success. No less than 63
                    per cent, of the inhabitants are supported by industrial pursuits, the chief
                    products of which are the woollen fabrics of Greiz, the capital, and the
                    stockings of Zeulenroda, both largely exported. The population of the
                    principality in 1880 was 50,782, of whom only 450 were Roman Catholics and 60
                    Jews. The constitution of Reuss-Greiz dates from 1867, and provides for a
                    representative chamber of twelve members, of whom three are appointed by the
                    prince, while two are elected by the nobles, three by the towns, and four by the
                    rural districts.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n511/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0511-0494"/>
                <p>The revenue and expenditure for 1885 were each estimated at &lt;£36,254, while
                    the public debt in 1884 was £46,886.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reuss-Schleiz, or Reuss jüngerer Linie, with an area of 318
                    square miles, includes part of the southern and the whole of the northern</hi>
                    of the two main divisions above indicated, touching Bavaria on the south and
                    Prussian Saxony on the north. The former portion is known as the Oberland, the
                    latter as the Unterland. Owing to the fertility of the Unterland, agriculture is
                    carried on here with greater success than in Reuss-Greiz, fully one quarter of
                    the population being supported by tillage and cattle-breeding. The industrial
                    activity is, however, also large, supporting one-half of the population. The
                    principal product consists, as in Reuss-Greiz, of woollen goods, and the
                    manufacture centres in the capital, Gera, a busy town with 27,118 inhabitants. A
                    considerable trade is carried on in the products of the manufactories, and in
                    timber, cattle, and slate. The iron mining of the Oberland is limited by the
                    want of sufficient railway communication. Large quantities of salt are yielded
                    by the brine springs of Heinrichshall. In 1880 Reuss-Schleiz contained 101,330
                    inhabitants, including 442 Roman Catholics and 69 Jews. The annual revenue and
                    expenditure for 1885-1886 were calculated at &lt;£66,060; the public debt in
                    1884 was £61,780.</p>
                <p>The history of Reuss stretches back to the times when the German emperors
                    appointed voigts, or bailiffs, to represent them in lands conquered from the
                    Sorbs or other Slavonic races. The forefathers of the present princes of Reuss
                    appear in this capacity at an early period, and the historical head of the
                    family is generally recognized in Henry, voigt of Weida, who flourished about
                    the middle of the 12th century. The name of Reuss came to be applied to the
                    territory ruled over by his descendants from the sobriquet of “Der Russe,” or
                    the Russian, which one of them acquired about 1280 from the nationality of his
                    mother. The district embraced by the name was at one time much more extensive
                    than at present, taking in the Bavarian town of Hof and the whole of the Saxon
                    Voigtland. Of the numerous lines and sub-lines into which the family was divided
                    nearly all became sooner or later extinct, till in 1616 none were left except
                    the two that still subsist. Since 1616 numerous subdivisions have again taken
                    place within these families, and it was not till 1848 that Reuss jüngerer Linie
                    became again a united whole. The rulers of Reuss were created counts of the
                    German empire in 1671 and sovereign princes in 1778. In 1807 both principalities
                    joined the Confederation of the Rhine, and in 1866 Reuss-Greiz had to atone for
                    its active sympathy with Austria by the payment of a fine. Since 1871 both
                    principalities have been members of the German empire, each sending one member
                    to the federal council and one representative to the Reichstag.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
