<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0569-0550-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RIEMANN (9th edition, volume 20, page 550)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47w67b9q">Mathematicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012154">Mathematicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936106">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n569/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RIEMANN</label> Geoeg Feiedeich Beenhaed (1826-1866),
                    mathematician, was born on the 17th September 1826, at Breselenz, near
                    Dannenberg in Hanover. His father Friedrich Bernhard Riemann came from
                    Mecklenburg, had served in the war of freedom, and had finally settled as pastor
                    in Quickborn. Here with his five brothers and sisters Riemann spent his boyhood
                    and received, chiefly from his father, the elements of his education. He showed
                    at an early age well-marked mathematical powers, and his progress was so rapid
                    in arithmetic and geometry that he was soon beyond the guidance not only of his
                    father but of schoolmaster Schulz, who assisted in the mathematical department
                    of his training.</p>
                <p>In 1840 he went to live with his grandmother at Hanover, where he attended the
                    lyceum. After her death, two years later, he entered the Johanneum at Lüneburg,
                    where he finished in four years more his gymnasial education. Notwithstanding
                    some disadvantages due to defects in his earlier training, and more particularly
                    to shyness arising from his rustic upbringing, he speedily distinguished himself
                    in all the branches of the gymnasial course, and was already known by the school
                    authorities as a mathematician of great promise. The director, Schmalfuss,
                    encouraged him in his mathematical studies by lending him books (among them
                    Euler’s works and Legendre’s <hi rend="italic">Theory of Numbers),</hi> and
                    readily understood that he had no ordinary schoolboy to deal with when he found
                    that works of such profoundity were read, mastered, and returned within a few
                    days. In 1846, in his twentieth year, Riemann entered himself as a student of
                    philology and theology in the university of Gottingen. This choice of a
                    university career was dictated more by the natural desire of his father to see
                    his son enter his own profession, and by the poverty of his family, which
                    rendered the speedy earning of his living a matter of importance, than by his
                    own preference. He sacrificed so far to the bent of his genius as to attend
                    lectures on the numerical solution of equations and on definite integrals by
                    Stern, on terrestrial magnetism by Goldschmidt, and on the method of least
                    squares by Gauss. It soon became evident that his mathematical studies,
                    undertaken at first probably as a relaxation, were destined to be the chief
                    business of his life; and he obtained his father’s permission to devote himself
                    entirely to a scientific career. By this time he had exhausted the resources of
                    Göttingen in the shape of mathematical lectures; and he proceeded in the
                    beginning of 1847 to Berlin, attracted thither by that brilliant constellation
                    of mathematical genius whose principal stars were Dirichlet, Jacobi, Steiner,
                    and Eisenstein. He appears to have attended Dirichlet’s lectures on theory of
                    numbers, theory of definite integrals, and partial differential equations, and
                    Jacobi’s on analytical mechanics and higher algebra. It was during this period
                    that he first formed those ideas on the theory of functions of a complex
                    variable which led to most of his great discoveries. One stirring social
                    incident at least marked this part of his life, for, during the revolutionary
                    insurrection in March 1848, the young mathematician, as a member of a company of
                    student volunteers, kept guard in the royal palace from 9 o’clock on the morning
                    of the 24th March till 1 o’clock on the afternoon of the following day.</p>
                <p>In 1850 he returned to Göttingen and began to prepare his doctor’s dissertation,
                    busying himself meanwhile with “Naturphilosophie” and experimental physics. In
                    pursuit of the latter he entered the mathematical and physical seminary, then
                    newly started by Weber, Ulrich, Stern, and Listing. This double cultivation of
                    his scientific powers, doubtless due more to the influence of Göttingen as
                    represented by Gauss than to Berlin, had the happiest effect on his subsequent
                    work; for the greatest achieve; ments of Riemann were effected by the
                    application in pure mathematics generally of a method (theory of potential)
                    which had up to this time been used solely in the solution of certain problems
                    that arise in mathematical physics.</p>
                <p>In November 1851 he obtained his doctorate, the thesis being “Grundlagen für eine
                    allgemeine Theorie der Functionen einer veränderlichen complexen Grösse.” This
                    memoir excited the admiration of Gauss, and at once marked its author’s rank as
                    a mathematician. The fundamental method of research which Riemann employed has
                    just been alluded to; the results will be best indicated in his own words :—</p>
                <p>“The methods in use hitherto for treating functions of a complex variable always
                    started from an expression for the function as its definition, whereby its value
                    was given for every value of the argument; by our investigation it has been
                    shown that, in consequence of the general character of a function of a complex
                    variable, in a definition of this sort one part of the determining conditions is
                    a consequence of the rest, and the extent of the determining conditions has been
                    reduced to what is necessary to effect the determination. This essentially
                    simplifies the treatment of such functions. Hitherto, in order to prove the
                    equality of two expressions for the same function, it was necessary to transform
                    the one into the other, <hi rend="italic">i. e.,</hi> to show that both
                    expressions agreed for every value of the variable; now it is sufficient to
                    prove their agreement to a far less extent” [merely in certain critical points
                    and at certain boundaries].</p>
                <p>The time between his promotion to the doctorate and his habilitation as
                    privat-docent was occupied by researches undertaken for his
                    Habilitationsschrift, by “Naturphilosophie,” and by experimental work partly as
                    Weber’s assistant in the mathematical physical seminary, and partly as
                    collaborateur with Weber and Kohlrausch in special researches on electricity. In
                    connexion with the results of Kohlrausch regarding the residual discharge of
                    condensers, Riemann worked out a theory of this phenomenon which he intended to
                    have published in <hi rend="italic">Poggen-dorff ’ s Annalen.</hi> For some
                    reason not fully explained it was not published at all during his lifetime, and
                    its place in the <hi rend="italic">Annalen</hi> was taken by an elegant little
                    paper on Nobili’s rings.</p>
                <p>The subject he had chosen for his Habilitationsschrift was the “Representation of
                    a Function by means of a Trigonometrical Series,” a subject which Dirichlet had
                    made his own by a now well-known series of researches. It was fortunate no doubt
                    for Riemann that he had the kind advice and encouragement of Dirichlet himself,
                    who was then on a visit at Göttingen during the preparation of his essay; but
                    the result λvas a memoir of such originality and refinement as showed that the
                    pupil was fully the equal of the master. Of the customary three themes which lie
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0570-0551"/>suggested for his trial lecture, that “On the
                    Hypotheses which form the Foundation of Geometry” was chosen at the instance of
                    Gauss, who was curious to hear what so young a man had to say on this difficult
                    subject, on which he himself had in private speculated so profoundly (see
                    Parallels, vol. xviii. p. 254). Dedekind tells us that Riemann’s lecture, which
                    surpassed his utmost expectation, filled him with the greatest astonishment, and
                    that on the way back from the faculty meeting he spoke to Wilhelm Weber with the
                    highest appreciation, and with an excitement rare with him, regarding the depth
                    of the thoughts to which Riemann had given utterance.</p>
                <p>In 1855 Gauss died and was succeeded by Dirichlet, who along with others made an
                    effort to obtain Riemann’s nomination as extraordinary professor. In this they
                    were not successful; but a Government Stipendium of 200 thalers was given him,
                    and even this miserable pittance was of great importance, so straitened were his
                    circumstances. But this small beginning of good fortune was embittered by the
                    deaths of his father and his eldest sister, and by the breaking up of the home
                    at Quickborn, where he had so often found solace when ill and dejected. Meantime
                    he was lecturing and writing the great memoir <hi rend="italic">(Borchardtfi
                        Journal,</hi> vol. liv., 1857) in which he applied the theory developed in
                    his doctor’s dissertation to the Abelian functions. It is amusing to find him
                    speaking jubilantly of the unexpectedly large audience of eight which assembled
                    to hear his first lecture (in 1854) on partial differential equations and their
                    application to physical problems. The rustic shyness which had troubled his
                    schoolboyhood seems still to have haunted him; for he says, speaking of these
                    lectures, “The nervousness which I had at first has pretty well subsided, and I
                    accustom myself to think more of my hearers than of myself, and to read in their
                    faces whether I may go on, or whether the matter requires further
                    explanation.”</p>
                <p>Riemann’s health had never been strong. Even in his boyhood he had shown symptoms
                    of consumption, the disease that was working such havoc in his family; and now
                    under the strain of work he broke down altogether, and had to retire to the Harz
                    with his friends Ritter and Dedekind, where he gave himself up to excursions and
                    “Naturphilosophie.” After his return to Göttingen (November 1857) he was made
                    extraordinary professor, and his salary raised to three hundred thalers. As
                    usual with him, misfortune followed close behind; for he lost in quick
                    succession his brother Wilhelm and another sister. In 1859 he lost his friend
                    Dirichlet; but his reputation was now so well established that he was at once
                    appointed to succeed him. It now seemed for a little as if the world was to go
                    smoothly with him. Well-merited honours began to reach him; and in 1860 he
                    visited Paris, and met with a warm reception there. He married, and married
                    happily, Fräulein Elise Koch in June 1862, but the following month he had an
                    attack of pleurisy which proved the beginning of a long illness that ended only
                    with his death. His physician recommended a sojourn in Italy, for the benefit of
                    his health, and Weber and Sartorius von Waltershausen obtained from the
                    Government leave of absence and means to defray the cost of the journey. At
                    first it seemed that he would recover; but on his return in June 1863 he caught
                    cold on the Splügen Pass, and in August of the same year had to go back to
                    Italy. In November 1865 he returned again to Göttingen, but, although he was
                    able to live through the winter, and even to work a few hours every day, it
                    became clear to his friends, and clearest of all to himself, that he was dying.
                    He was very desirous to finish some of the many investigations which had
                    presented themselves to him, and eagerly asked his doctors to tell him how long
                    he might reasonably expect to live, so that he might take up what he had most
                    chance of finishing. In order to husband his few remaining days he resolved in
                    June 1866 to return once more to Italy. Thither he journeyed through the
                    confusion of the first days of the Austro-Prussian war, and settled in a villa
                    at Selasca near Intra on Lago Maggiore. Here his strength rapidly ebbed away,
                    but his mental faculties remained brilliant to the last. On the 19th of July
                    1866, attended by his wife, he lay under a fig-tree greatly enjoying the
                    beautiful landscape and working at his last unfinished investigation on the
                    mechanism of the ear. The day following he died.</p>
                <p>There are few more pathetic stories than the life of Riemann, few finer instances
                    of victory gained by inborn genius over a host of adverse circumstances. Few as
                    were the years of work allotted to him, and few as are the printed pages covered
                    by the record of his researches, his name is, and will remain, a household word
                    among mathematicians. Most of his memoirs are masterpieces—full of original
                    methods, profound ideas, and far-reaching imagination. Few sources, we imagine,
                    have been fuller of inspiration for the younger mathematicians of our day than
                    the octavo volume of five hundred pages or so that contains his works; and many
                    an advance in mathematical science will yet be made, with increase of reputation
                    to the maker, by carrying out his suggestions.</p>
                <p>The collected works of Riemann were published by IL Weber assisted by R. Dedekind
                    (8vo, Leipsic, 1876). At the end of this volume there is a touching account of
                    his life by the latter, from which the above sketch is almost entirely taken.
                    (G. CH.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
