<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0920-0557-0538-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RICE (9th edition, volume 20, page 538)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:930458">Food</term>
                    <term ref="fast:943747">Gluten</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4cv1c">Gluten</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n557/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RICE</label>. According to Roxburgh the cultivated rice with
                    all its numerous varieties has originated from a wild plant called in India
                    Newaree or Nivara <hi rend="italic">{Oryza saliva).</hi> It is said to grow on
                    the borders of lakes in the Circars and elsewhere in India, and is also native
                    in tropical Australia. The rice plant is an annual grass with long linear
                    glabrous leaves, each provided with a long sharply-pointed ligule. The spikelets
                    are borne on a compound or branched spike, erect at first but afterwards bent
                    downwards. Each spikelet contains a solitary flower with two outer small glumes
                    and two inner, larger and folded lengthwise, the outer one of the two rather
                    larger and sometimes provided with an awn. Within these are six stamens, a hairy
                    ovary surmounted by two feathery styles which ripens into the fruit (grain), and
                    which is invested by the husk formed by the persistent glumes. The cultivated
                    varieties are extremely numerous, some kinds being adapted for marshy land,
                    others for growth on the hill-sides. The cultivators make two principal
                    divisions according as the sorts are early or late. Other subdivisions depend
                    upon the habit of the plant, the presence or absence of an awn, the colour of
                    the grain, and other particulars. Rice has been cultivated from time immemorial
                    in tropical countries. According to Stanislas Julien a ceremonial ordinance was
                    established in China by the emperor Chin-nung 2800 years B.c., in accordance
                    with which the emperor sows the rice himself while the seeds of four other kinds
                    may be sown by the princes of his family. This fact, joined to other
                    considerations, induced Alphonse de Candolle to consider rice as a native of
                    China. It was very early culti vated in India, in some parts of which country,
                    as in tro pical Australia, it is, as we have seen, indigenous. It is not
                    mentioned in the Bible, but its culture is alluded to in the Talmud.</p>
                <p>There is no evi dence of the exist ence of rice in</p>
                <p>Egyptian remains, nor is there any trace of it as a native plant among the
                    Greeks, Ro mans, or ancient</p>
                <p>Persians. There is proof of its culture in the Euphrates valley and in</p>
                <p>Syria four hundred yearsbefore Christ.</p>
                <p>Crawfurd on phi lological grounds considers that rice was introduced into Persia
                    from southern India.</p>
                <p>The Arabs carried the plant into</p>
                <p>Spain under the name “aruz,” the <hi rend="italic">arros</hi> of the Spanish, the
                        <hi rend="italic">mzo</hi> of the Italian, whence our word rice. Ricp was
                    first cultivated in Italy near Pisa in 1468. It was not introduced into Carolina
                    until 1700, and then, as it is said, by accident, although at one time the
                    southern United States furnished a large proportion of the rice introduced into
                    commerce. Rice, says Crawfurd, sports into far more varieties than any of the
                    corns familiar to Europeans, for some varieties grow in the water and some on
                    dry land; some come to maturity in three months, while others take four and six
                    months to do so. The Hindus, however, are not content with such broad
                    distinctions as might be derived from these obvious sources, but have names for
                    varieties the distinctions between which are unappreciable by Europeans; besides
                    terms for this corn founded on variety, on season, and on mode of culture, the
                    grain itself bears one name in the straw, another when threshed, one name in the
                    husk and another when freed from it, and a fifth when cooked. A similar
                    abundance of terms is found in the languages of the Malay and Philippine
                    Islands. Such minute nomen <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n558/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0920-0558-0539"/>clatures seem to point to a great antiquity in
                    the culture of this cereal.</p>
                <p>Rice constitutes one of the most important articles of food in all tropical and
                    subtropical countries, and is one of the most prolific of all crops. The rice
                    yields best on low lands subject to occasional inundations, and thus enriched by
                    alluvial deposits. Λn abundant rainfall during the growing season is also a
                    desideratum. Rice is sown broadcast, and in some districts is transplanted after
                    a fortnight or three weeks. No special rotation is followed; indeed the soil
                    best suited for rice is ill adapted for any other crop. In some cases little
                    manure is employed, but in others abundance of manure is used. No special
                    tillage is required, but weeding and irrigation are requisite. Rice in the husk
                    is known as “paddy.” On cutting across a grain of rice and examining it under
                    the microscope, first the flattened and dried cells of the husk are seen, and
                    then one or two layers of cells elongated in a direction parallel to the length
                    of the seed, which contain the gluten or nitrogenous matter. Within these, and
                    forming by far the largest part of the seed, are large polygonal cells filled
                    with very numerous and very minute angular starch grains. Rice is not so
                    valuable.as a food as some other cereals, inasmuch as the proportion of
                    nitrogenous matter (gluten) is less. Payen gives only 7 per cent, of gluten in
                    rice as compared with 22 per cent, in the finest wheat, 14 in oats, and 12 in
                    maize. The percentage of potash in the ash is as 18 to 23 in wheat. The fatty
                    matter is also less in proportion than in other cereals. Rice, therefore, is
                    chiefly a farinaceous food, and requires to be combined with fatty and
                    nitrogenous substances, such as milk or meat gravy, to satisfy the requirements
                    of the system.</p>
                <p>The imports of rice into the United Kingdom range from 7,000,000 cwt. to
                    8,000,000 cwt. annually, having an estimated value of,from £3,000,000 to
                    £3,500,000. Nearly the whole of this comes from British Burmah and Bengal. A
                    large proportion of the rice brought to Europe is used for starch-making, and
                    some is taken by distillers of alcohol. Rice is also the source of a drinking
                    spirit in India, and the national beverage of Japan—saké—is prepared entirely
                    from the fermented grain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
