<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0639-0616-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RODBERTUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 616</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1115271">Sharing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1169492">Wages</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n639/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RODBERTUS</label> Karl Johann (1805-1875), by some considered
                    to be the founder of scientific socialism, was born at Greifswald on 12th August
                    1805, his father being a professor at the university there. He studied law at
                    Göttingen and Berlin, thereafter engaging in various legal occupations; and,
                    after travelling for some time, he bought the estate of Jagetzow in Pomerania,
                    whence his name of Rodbertus-Jagetzow. In 1836 he settled on this estate, and
                    henceforward devoted his life chiefly to economic and other learned studies,
                    taking also some interest in local and provincial affairs. After the revolution
                    of March 1848 Rodbertus was elected member of the Prussian national assembly, in
                    which body he belonged to the left centre; and for fourteen days he filled the
                    post of minister of public worship and education. He sat for Berlin in the
                    second chamber of 1849, and moved the adoption of the Frankfort imperial
                    constitution, which was carried. When the system of dividing the Prussian
                    electorate into three classes was adopted, Rodbertus recommended abstention from
                    voting. His only subsequent appearance in public life was his candidature for
                    the first North German diet, in which he was defeated. His correspondence with
                    Lassalle was an interesting feature of his life. At one time Rodbertus had some
                    intention of forming a “social party” with the help of the conservative
                    socialist Rudolf Meyer and of Hasencleve⅛, a prominent follower of Lassalle; but
                    no progress was made in this. Rodbertus was neither disposed nor qualified to be
                    an agitator, being a man of a quiet and critical temperament, who believed that
                    society could not be improved by violent changes, but by a long and gradual
                    course of development. He warned the working men of Germany against connecting
                    themselves with any political party, enjoining them to be a “social party” pure
                    and simple. He died on 8th December 1875.</p>
                <p>The general position of Rodbertus was “social, monarchical, and national.” With
                    his entire soul he held the purely economic part of the creed of the German
                    social-democratic party, but he did not agree with their methods, and had no
                    liking for the productive associations with state help of Lassalle. He regarded
                    a socialistic republic as a possible thing, but he cordially accepted the
                    monarchic institution in his own country and hoped that a German emperor might
                    undertake the rôle of a social emperor. He was also a true patriot and was proud
                    and hopeful of the career that lay before the regenerated empire of Germany. The
                    basis of the economic teaching of Rodbertus is the principle laid down by Adam
                    Smith and Ricardo and insisted on by all the later socialists, that labour is
                    the source and measure of value. In connexion with this he developed the
                    position that rent, profit, and wages are all parts of a national income
                    produced by the united organic labour of the workers of the community.
                    Consequently there can be no talk of the wages of labour being paid out of
                    capital; wages is only that part of the national income which is received by the
                    workmen, of a national income which they have themselves entirely produced. The
                    wages fund theory is thus summarily disposed of. But the most important result
                    of the theory is his position that the possession of land and capital enables
                    the landholders and capitalists to compel the workmen to divide the product of
                    their labour with those nonworking classes, and in such a proportion that the
                    workers only obtain as much as can support them in life. Thus the iron law of
                    wages is established. Hence also Rodbertus deduces his theory of commercial
                    crises and of pauperism, and in the following way. In spite of the increasing
                    productivity of labour, the workers obtain in general only sufficient to support
                    their class, and therefore a smaller relative share of the national income. But
                    the producers form also the large mass of consumers, and, with the decline of
                    their relative share in the national income, must decline the relative
                    purchasing power of this large class of the people. The growing production is
                    not met by a correspondingly growing consumption; expansion is succeeded by
                    contraction of production, by a scarcity of employment, and a further decline in
                    purchasing power on the part of the workers. Thus we have a commercial crisis
                    bringing with it pauperism as a necessary result. In the meantime the purchasing
                    power of the non-producing capitalists and landholders continues relatively to
                    increase; but, as they have already had enough to buy <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n640/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0640-0617"/>all the comforts of life, they spend the more in
                    the purchase of luxuries, the production of which increases.</p>
                <p>A fundamental part of the teaching of Rodbertus is his theory of social
                    development. He recognized three stages in the economic progress of mankind: (1)
                    the ancient heathen period in which property in human beings was the rule; (2)
                    the period of private property in land and capital; (3) the period, still
                    remote, of property as dependent on service or desert. The goal of the human
                    race is to be one society organized on a communistic basis; only in that way can
                    the principle that every man be rewarded according to his work be realized. In
                    this communistic or socialistic state of the future land and capital will be
                    national property, and the entire national production will be under national
                    control; and means will be taken so to estimate the labour of each citizen that
                    he shall be rewarded according to its precise amount. An immense staff of state
                    officials will be required for this function. As we have already said, Rodbertus
                    believed that this stage of social development is yet far distant; he thought
                    that five centuries will need to pass away before the ethical force of the
                    people can be equal to it.</p>
                <p>From temperament, culture, and social position Rodbertus was averse to agitation
                    as a means of hastening the new era; and, in the measures which he recommends
                    for making the transition towards it he showed a scrupulous regard for the
                    existing interests of the capitalists and landholders. He proposed that those
                    two classes should be left in full possession of their present share of the
                    national income, but that the workers should reap the benefit of the increasing
                    production. To secure them this increment of production he proposed that the
                    state should fix a “normal working day” for the various trades, a normal day’s
                    work, and a legal wage, the amount of which should be revised periodically, and
                    raised according to the increase of production, the better workman receiving a
                    better wage. By measures such as these carried out by the state in order to
                    correct the evils of competition would Rodbertus seek to make the transition
                    into the socialistic era.</p>
                <p>The economic work of Rodbertus is therefore an attempt made in a temperate and
                    scientific spirit to elucidate the evil tendencies inherent in the competitive
                    system, especially as exemplified in the operation of the iron law of wages. The
                    remedy he proposes is a state management of production and distribution, which
                    shall extend more and more, till we arrive at a complete and universal
                    socialism,—and all based on the principle that as labour is the source of value
                    so to the labourer should all wealth belong. It is therefore an attempt to place
                    socialism on a scientific basis; and he is certainly entitled to be regarded as
                    one of the founders of “scientific socialism” (see Socialism).</p>
                <p>The following are the most important works of Rodbertus :— <hi rend="italic">Zur
                    Erkenntniss unserer staatswirthschaftliehen Zustände</hi> (1842); <hi
                    rend="italic">Sociale Briefe an von Kirchmann</hi> (1850); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Creditnoth des Grundbesitzes</hi> (2d ed., 1876); “Der Normal-Arbeitstag,” in
                    <hi rend="italic">Tiib. Zeitschrift</hi> (1878); <hi rend="italic">letters</hi>
                    to A. wagner, &amp;C., <hi rend="italic">Tüb. Zeitschrift</hi> (1878-79); <hi
                    rend="italic">Letters</hi> to Rudolf Meyer (1882). within recent years Rodbertus
                    has received great attention in Germany, especially from Adolf Wagner <hi
                    rend="italic">(Tiib. Zeitschrift,</hi> 1878); see also Kozak’s work on Rodbertus
                    (1S82), and an excellent monograph by G. Adler (Leipsic, 1884).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
