<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0586-0567-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">RIPLEY, GEORGE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 20, page 567</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4639k84f">Farms</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qp5f">Farming</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4280519t">Dialing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921422">Farms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1161461">Unitarians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:883769">Critics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n586/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RIPLEY, GEORGE</label> (1802-1880), critic and man of
                    letters, was born at Greenfield, in western Massachusetts, on October 3, 1802.
                    He was educated at local schools and at Harvard College, where he took his
                    degree in 1823, ranking first in his class, and then studying theology was in
                    1826 ordained pastor of a Unitarian church in Boston. Here his success as a
                    thoughtful preacher was marked; but in 1840 he resigned his charge, and he
                    subsequently retired from the active ministry altogether.</p>
                <p>It was during those years that there grew up in New England that form of thought
                    or philosophy known as Transcendentalism—a name, as Emerson said, “given nobody
                    knows by whom, or when it was applied.” Its growth was part of what Dr Holmes
                    has termed the “intellectual or, if we may call it so, spiritual revival” which
                    during the period from 1820 to 1840 was so strongly marked in the New England
                    “churches, in politics, in philanthropy, in literature.” Ripley w <hi
                    rend="superscript">τ</hi> as prominent, if not the leader, in all practical
                    manifestations of the movement; and it was by his earnestness and practical
                    energy that certain of its more tangible results were directed. The first
                    meeting of the Transcendental Club was held at his house in September 1836. He
                    was a founder and a chief supporter of the famous magazine <hi rend="italic">The
                    Dial,</hi> which was the organ of the school from 1840 to 1844. Most important
                    of all, however, he was the originator and conductor of an experiment which was
                    the most interesting practical result of the thought and tendencies of the
                    time,—the foundation of “The Brook Farm Association for Education and
                    Agriculture.” This project, in the words of its originator, was intended “to
                    insure a more natural union between intellectual and manual labour than now
                    exists; to combine the thinker and the worker, as far as possible, in the same
                    individual; to guarantee the highest mental freedom by providing all with labour
                    adapted to their tastes and talents, an&lt;i securing to them the fruits of
                    their industry; to do away with the necessity of menial services by opening the
                    benefits of education and the profits of labour to all; and thus to prepare a
                    society of liberal, intelligent, and cultivated persons w <hi rend="superscript"
                    >τ</hi> hose relations with each other w <hi rend="superscript">τ</hi> ould
                    permit a more simple and wholesome life than can be led amidst the pressure of
                    our competitive institutions.” In short, its aim was to bring about the best
                    conditions for an ideal civilization, reducing to a minimum the labour necessary
                    for mere existence, and by this and by the simplicity of its social machinery
                    saving the maximum of time for mental and spiritual education and development.
                    At a time when Emerson could write to Carlyle, “We are all a little wild here
                    with numberless projects of social reform; not a reading man but has a draft of
                    a new community in his waistcoat pocket,”—the Brook Farm project certainly did
                    not appear as impossible a scheme as many others that were in the air. At all
                    events it enlisted the co-operation of men whose subsequent careers show them to
                    have been something more than visionaries. The association bought a tract of
                    land in West Roxbury, some ten miles from Boston, and with about twenty members
                    actually began its enterprise in the summer of 1841.</p>
                <p>For three years the undertaking went on quietly and simply, subject to few
                    outward troubles other than financial difficulties, the number of associates
                    increasing to seventy or eighty. Pictures of the life they led have been
                    preserved by many hands. It <hi rend="superscript">-</hi> was during this period
                    that Hawthorne had his short experience of Brook Farm, of which so many
                    suggestions appear in the <hi rend="italic">Rlithedale Romance,</hi> though his
                    preface to later editions effectually disposed of the idea—which gave him great
                    pain—that he had either drawn his characters from persons there, or had meant to
                    give any actual description of the colony. Emerson, though he refused in a kind
                    and characteristic letter to join in the undertaking, and though he afterwards
                    wrote of Brook Farm with not uncharitable humour as·“a perpetual picnic, a
                    French Revolution in small, an age of reason in a patty-pan,” yet spoke of the
                    design as “noble and generous,” and among its founders were many of his near
                    friends.</p>
                <p>In 1844 the growing need of a more scientific organization, and the influence
                    which Fourier’s doctrines had gained in the minds of Ripley and many of his
                    associates, combined to change the whole plan of the community. It was
                    transformed, with the strong approval of all its chief members and the consent
                    of the rest, into a Fourierist “phalanx” in 1845. There was an accession of new
                    members, a momentary increase of prosperity, a brilliant new undertaking in the
                    publication of a journal, <hi rend="italic">The Harbinger,</hi> in which Ripley,
                    Charles A. Dana, Francis G. Shaw, and John Dwight were the chief writers, and to
                    which Lowell, Whittier, George William Curtis, Parke Godwin, Story, Channing,
                    Higginson, Horace Greeley, and many more now and then contributed. But the
                    individuality of the old Brook Farm was gone. The association was not rescued
                    even from financial troubles by the change. With increasing difficulty it kept
                    on till the spring of 1846, when a fire which destroyed its building or
                    “phalanstery” brought losses which caused, or certainly gave the final
                    ostensible reason for, its dissolution. Its failure left Ripley poor and feeling
                    keenly the defeat of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n587/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0587-0568"/>his project; but the event forced him at last to
                    devote himself to that career of literary labour in which the real success of
                    his life was achieved. He wrote for <hi rend="italic">The Harbinger</hi> during
                    the year of its continuance, but in 1849 he joined the staff of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Tribune,</hi> founded eight years before by Horace Greeley in
                    New York, and in a short time became its literary editor. This position, which,
                    through his steadiness, scholarly conservatism, and freedom from caprice as a
                    critic, soon became one of great influence, he held until his death on July 4,
                    1880.</p>
                <p>During the greater part of the time of his connexion with <hi rend="italic">The
                    Tribune,</hi> Ripley was also the adviser of a leading publishing house, an
                    occasional contributor to the magazines, and a co-operator in several literary
                    undertakings. The chief of these, and the most lasting work that bears his name,
                    λvas the <hi rend="italic">American Cyclopaedia.</hi> Begun under the editorship
                    of Ripley and Charles A. Dana in 1857, the first edition was finished in 1862,
                    under the title of the <hi rend="italic">New American Cyclopaedia—</hi>
                    distinguishing it from its only important American predecessor in the field, the
                    small <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia Americana</hi> of many years before, which
                    Dr Francis Lieber had edited, and which had been largely an adaptation of
                    Brockhaus’s <hi rend="italic">Conversations-Lexikon.</hi> The new undertaking
                    was upon a much larger scale, and enlisted a great number of well-known
                    contributors. It proved exceedingly popular; and its commercial success led the
                    publishers to undertake a complete revision of it ten years later—still under
                    the same editors—the result of which, with the dropping of the word “new” from
                    the title, was the <hi rend="italic">American Cyclopaedia</hi> now before the
                    public.</p>
                <p>Ripley’s <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> written by the Rev. 0. β. Frothinghanι,
                    forms one of the volumes of the series <hi rend="italic">American Men of
                    Letters.</hi> (E. L. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
