<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0754-0723-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SUSSEX (9th edition, volume 22, page 723)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dv6c">Rye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nf5d">Beacons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102628">Rye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829141">Beacons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n754/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SUSSEX</label>, a maritime county in the south of England,
                    lying between 50° 43' and 51° 9' N. lat. and 0° 49' E. and 0° 58' W. long. It is
                    76 miles from Lady Holt Park to Kent Ditch, and 28 miles from Tunbridge Wells to
                    Beachy Head, and adjoins Kent on the N.E., Surrey on the N., Hampshire on the
                    W., and the English Channel on the S. Its total area is 933,269 acres or 1458
                    square miles.</p>
                <p>The range of chalk hills known as the South Downs divides the county into two
                    districts—that of the coast and that of the Wealden—which are of unequal extent
                    and possess very different characteristics. In the western part of the county
                    the South Downs are about 10 miles distant from the sea; they continue eastwards
                    for about 45 miles, and terminate in the bold headland of Beachy Head. Their
                    average height is about 500 feet, though some of the summits reach 700
                    (Ditchling Beacon, 813 feet; Chanctonbury Ring, 783; Firle Beacon, 700; and the
                    Devil’s Dyke, 697). The Forest Ridge extends through the northern part of the
                    county from Petworth to Crowborough, reaching the coast in Fairlight Down. The
                    principal summits are Crowborough Beacon (796 feet), Brightling Hill (647), and
                    Fairlight Down (528). The county has suffered greatly from incursions of the
                    sea. The site of the ancient cathedral of Selsey is now a mile out at sea.
                    Between 1292 and 1340 upwards of 5500 acres were submerged. In the early part of
                    the 14th century Pagham harbour was formed by a sudden irruption of the sea,
                    devastating 2700 acres. Recently all this land has been reclaimed and again
                    brought under cultivation.</p>
                <p>There is considerable reason for believing that the whole coast-line of the
                    county has been slightly raised in the last 800 years (possibly by earthquake
                    shock), as the large estuaries at the river mouths no longer exist, and the
                    archipelago round Pevensey <hi rend="italic">(eye</hi> signifies “island ”) has
                    only a slight elevation above the neighbouring marsh land.</p>
                <p>The rivers are small and unimportant. The principal are the Rother, the Cuckmere,
                    the Ouse, the Adur, the Arun, and the Lavant. The Rother rises in the Forest
                    Ridge, in the parish of Rotherfield, and enters the sea near Rye, its course
                    having been diverted by a great storm on 12th October 1250, before which date
                    its exit was 12 miles to the east, beyond Dungeness. The Cuckmere also rises in
                    the Forest Ridge, near Heathfield, and empties itself into the sea a little to
                    the east of Seaford. The Ouse rises in St Leonards Forest, to the north-west of
                    Lindfield, and, passing through Isfield and Lewes, enters the sea at Newhaven,
                    now the principal port in the county. The former outlet was at Seaford, but in
                    the reign of Elizabeth the sea broke through the beach bank at some warehouses
                    just below Bishopstone and formed what is now called the old harbour, which was
                    in use until the Newhaven one was made a safer exit. The Adur has three sources,
                    all in the neighbourhood of St Leonards Forest, and flows southwards, entering
                    the sea at Southwick. The mouth of the river formerly shifted from year to year,
                    ranging both east and west over a distance of 2 miles. The Arun rises in St
                    Leonards Forest, in the parish of Slinfold, flows through Amberley and Arundel,
                    and enters the sea at Littlehampton. The Lavant has its source in Charlton
                    Forest and encircles Chichester on all sides except the north, entering the sea
                    through creeks in the extreme south-west corner of the county.</p>
                <p>The portion of the county to the north of the South Downs is called the Weald; it
                    formerly formed part of the forest of Andredsweald (“the wood or forest without
                    habitations”), which was 120 miles in length and about 30 in breadth. The total
                    area of forests in 1885 was 113,043 acres, being the greatest of any county in
                    England. About 1660 the total was estimated at over 200,000 acres. The chief
                    remains of the ancient forests are Tilgate, Ashdown, and St Leonards, but the
                    names in many parts indicate their former wooded character, as Hurstpierpoint
                    <hi rend="italic">(hurst</hi> meaning “wood”), Midhurst, Fernhurst,
                    Billingshurst, Ashurst, and several others. The forests were interspersed with
                    lagoons, and the rainfall being very great caused marshes and the large river
                    estuaries; the rainfall, however, abated in consequence of the cutting down of
                    the Wealden forests for fuel in the extensive ironworks that formerly existed in
                    that district. The wood was exported in the reign of Edward VI.</p>
                <p>The greater portion of the county is occupied by the Chalk formation, of which
                    the South Downs are almost entirely composed. Firestone is found in the west,
                    and Steyning is built upon it. At the base of the Downs the Greensand crops up,
                    but is of small extent. The Wealden formations occupy nearly all the inland
                    district of the county, and in these was found the ironstone from which iron was
                    extracted. Sussex was at one time the centre of the English iron manufacture;
                    before 1653 there were 42 iron-forges or mills (reduced to 18 before 1667) and
                    27 furnaces (reduced to 11 before 1664), which employed 50,000 men<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Suss. Arch.
                    Coll.,</hi> xxxii. pp. 22-25</p></note> and furnished the main supply of
                    ordnance for the national defence. The last forge at Ashburnham was not
                    extinguished until 1809. Between 1872 and 1876 boring was carried on at
                    Netherfield, near Battle, with the object of discovering what beds were below
                    the V ealden, and if possible of reaching the Palaeozoic rocks, which at<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n755/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0755-0724"/> Kentish Town, Harwich, Ostend, and Calais had
                    been found at a depth of about 1000 feet below the sea-level. Some slight hope
                    was entertained of the occurrence of Coal-measures, as in the Boulonnais the
                    Carboniferous limestone, where last seen, dips south. The boring was continued
                    to a depth of 1905 feet, the Oxford Clay being reached. The chief result was the
                    discovery of the unusual thickness of the Kimmeridge Clay, which began at 275
                    feet from the surface and continued to a depth of about 1469 feet. The most
                    practical result was the finding of thick beds of gypsum (at about 160 feet),
                    which were before unknown in the Weald and are now worked at Netherfield. From
                    Beachy Head to Selsey Bill there lies, south of the Downs, a low and level tract
                    belonging to the Tertiary period, of which there is no such record at any other
                    place in England. The towns of Hove, Worthing, Littlehampton, Bognor, &amp;c.,
                    are built on gravel, sand, and loam of the Post-Pliocene or Pleistocene series,
                    and these superficial beds overlie the Eocene series in patches and contain a
                    large fossil fauna. Remains of the mammoth occur in the mud deposit (or <hi
                    rend="italic">Lutraria</hi> clay) of this district, and the Chichester museum
                    contains the greater portion of a fine skeleton of the <hi rend="italic">Elephas
                    antiquus</hi> obtained off Selsey Bill. Of the British Quaternary fossils
                    forty-five are peculiar to Selsey, and twenty others probably find here their
                    earliest place in British geological history. The Bracklesham beds occur at the
                    bay of that name, and their main divisions extend from Wittering on the west to
                    the Barn Rocks, east of Selsey Bill, a distance of 7 miles. They are full of
                    fossil shells, particularly nummulitic.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Address to Geological Section of British Association,
                    1882.</p></note></p>
                <p>An analysis of the flora of the county was placed before the British Association
                    in 1872 by Mr W. B. Hemsley (<hi rend="italic">Report,</hi> 1872 p. 128), who
                    stated the total number of indigenous plants to be 1000, to which 59 introduced
                    species must be added. The most interesting features of the flora are the number
                    of species to the county area, the species peculiar to certain formations, viz.,
                    the Chalk (56), maritime species (76), and the rare species, especially of the
                    Atlantic and Scottish types. Amongst the rarer marsh plants are <hi
                    rend="italic">Isnαrdiα palustris, Scirpus triqueter, S. carinatus, Pyrola media,
                    Habeneria albida, Festuca sylvatica</hi> of the “Scottish” type of Watson; this
                    last is not found in adjoining counties. A prominent feature of the Wealden
                    flora is the extent of heath land and the large size the heath attains. The
                    fauna includes 29 species of <hi rend="italic">Mammalia.</hi> The birds are very
                    numerous, no less than 291 species having been recorded. There are about 76
                    species of general migratory visitors. Of the 216 species of marine fishes found
                    round the British coasts 106 have been observed off Sussex, and there are also
                    19 freshwater fish.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Good
                    lists of fauna and flora of certain parts of the eastern divi sion of the county
                    have been published by the Hastings Literary and Philosophical Society and the
                    Eastbourne Natural History Society.</p></note></p>
                <p>The county presents two distinct climates, that of the coast district being mild,
                    equable, and dry, whilst that of the Wealden district is continental, extreme,
                    and rainy. The coast rainfall is about 25 to 26 inches annually and that of the
                    Weald about 33 inches; this is due partly to the South Downs, which rise up in
                    the path of the rain-clouds, and partly to the large extent of forest. In the
                    wet years of 1852 and 1872 the rainfall at several Wealden stations exceeded 50
                    inches. At Crowborough Beacon the average yearly rainfall from 1871 to 1884 was
                    38T6 inches; at Brighton during the same period it was only 28·87. Temperature
                    in the Weald at Uckfield has ranged from 98° Fahr. on 14th July to - 4° on 20th
                    January 1838. The mean daily range of temperature in the Weald is about half as
                    much again as on the coast. The influence of the sea in modifying the
                    temperature of the coast district is specially noticeable in the autumn months,
                    when the temperature is higher than in the Weald and other parts of England
                    northwards, and fashion has (perhaps unconsciously) selected the period from
                    September to November for the Brighton season. Sea-bathing, first introduced
                    about the middle of the 18th century, together with the fresh pure air, has
                    turned the stream of health-seekers from Bath and Tunbridge Wells and other
                    watering-places into Sussex. The poor but populous fishing-town of
                    Brighthelmston developed into the fashionable town of Brighton; the new town of
                    Worthing sprang up in Broadwater parish; and the fishing village of Eastbourne
                    rose in importance. The Cinque Port town of Hastings afterwards developed its
                    fashionable suburb St Leonards, and Seaford was also resorted to; in the western
                    part of the county the hamlet of Bognor became a fashionable place. The opening
                    of the railway from London to Brighton in 1840, soon followed by coast lines
                    from east to west, occasioned a great increase in the coast towns, and now
                    almost the entire coast (except in its steep parts) presents a line of
                    fashionable “health resorts” unequalled in any English county; these indeed form
                    the special distinguishing feature of Sussex amongst other counties.</p>
                <p>Sussex is divided into the six rapes<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Probably derived from the Icelandic <hi rend="italic"
                    >hreppr,</hi> signifying laud divided by a rope. It is first mentioned in the
                    Domesday survey.</p></note> of Hastings, Pevensey, Lewes, Bramber, Arundel, and
                    Chichester. The only rapes which exist for practical purposes are that of
                    Hastings, which has a separate coroner, and the last three, in which the
                    liability to repair bridges falls as of common right upon the rape instead of
                    the county division. The Act 19 Hen. VII. cap. 24 directed that for convenience
                    the county court should be held at Lewes as well as at Chichester, and this
                    apparently gave rise to the division of Sussex into east and west parts, and
                    separate quarter sessions are now held for these two divisions. The boroughs of
                    Hastings, Rye, Brighton, and the city of Chichester have separate commissions of
                    the peace and courts of quarter sessions. There are eighteen petty and special
                    sessional divisions. At the time of the Domesday survey the county contained 65
                    hundreds, but the modem total is 68. Of the 7 municipal boroughs which the
                    county contains Arundel, Chichester, Hastings, and Bye existed long before the
                    passing of the Municipal Corporations Act, 1835; Brighton was incorporated in
                    1854, Lewes in 1881, and Eastbourne in 1883. Winchelsea, Seaford, Pevensey, and
                    Midhurst were unreformed corporations existing under old charters, the first
                    being governed by a mayor and the last three by bailiffs, but all their
                    privileges have lately been abolished. “Sussex,” as Mr Freeman observes,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">English
                    Towns and Districts,</hi> p. 125.</p></note> “is no shire, no department, but a
                    component element of England, older than England.” The diocese of Chichester is
                    nearly coextensive with the county and the old kingdom of Sussex. In the year
                    681 the county was converted to Christianity by St Wilfrid (afterwards
                    archbishop of York), who founded the see of Selsey, but in 1075 the see was
                    transferred from Selsey to Chichester. The diocese consists of two
                    archdeaconries, Lewes and Chichester, and five deaneries. There are 322 civil
                    parishes, with parts of seven others.</p>
                <p>Prior to the Reform Bill of 1832 Sussex returned twenty-eight members to the
                    House of Commons, two for the county and two each for the boroughs of Arundel,
                    Bramber, Chichester, East Grinstead, Hastings, Horsham, Lewes, Midhurst, New
                    Shoreham (with the rape of Bramber), Rye, Seaford, Steyning, and Winchelsea. The
                    borough of New Shoreham was in 1771 added to the rape of Bramber. In 1832
                    Bramber, East Grinstead, Seaford, Steyning, and Winchelsea were entirely
                    disfranchised, the first-named being classed with the worst of the “rotten”
                    boroughs; Arandel, Horsham, Midhurst, and Rye were each deprived of one member;
                    the county was divided into two parts (East and West), each returning two
                    members; and a new borough, Brighton, was created, to which two members were
                    allotted. Chichester and Lewes were each deprived of one member in 1867, and
                    Arundel was disfranchised in 1868. The Redistribution of Seats Act, 1885,
                    disfranchised Chichester, Horsham, Midhurst, New Shoreham (with the rape of
                    Bramber), and Rye, and deprived Hastings of one member. It also divided the
                    county into six (instead of two) divisions, viz., Lewes, Southern or Eastbourne,
                    Eastern or Rye, South-western or Chichester, Northern or East Grinstead,
                    North-western or Horsham, each returning one member. Brighton still retains two
                    members.</p>
                <p>According to the latest owners of land <hi rend="italic">Return</hi> (1873),
                    there were 11 proprietors with more than 10,000 acres each; 8 of 5000 to 10,000;
                    1015 of 100 and less than 5000; of 10 and less than 100 acres, 1677; of 1 and
                    less than 10, 2347; and of less than an acre, 14,675,— making a grand total of
                    19,733 landowners, having a gross estimated rental of £2,418,522; there were in
                    addition 23,738 acres of common or waste lands. The eleven principal landowners
                    were— Lord Leconfield, 30,221 acres; the duke of Norfolk, 19,217; the duke of
                    Richmond, 17,117; the earl of Chichester, 16,232; the marquis of Abergavenny,
                    15,364; Rev. John Goring, 14,139; the earl of Ashburnham, 14,051; the earl of
                    Egmont, 14,021; Viscount Gage, 13,739; the Earl De la Warr, 11,185; and the duke
                    of Devonshire, 11,062. At the time of the Domesday survey there were 15 tenants
                    <hi rend="italic">in capite,</hi> 534 under-tenants, and 2497 <hi rend="italic"
                    >bordarii</hi> (or cottagers), also 765 <hi rend="italic">cotarii</hi> (or
                    cottars). The custom of borough-English, by which land descends to the youngest
                    son, prevailed to an extraordinary degree in Sussex, and no less than 140 manors
                    have been catalogued in which it was found.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Suss. Arch. Coll.,</hi> vi.
                    164.</p></note> Gavelkind tenure existed in Rye, in the large manor of Brede,
                    and in Coustard manor (in Brede parish).</p>
                <p>The coast district has been under cultivation from the time of the Romans and is
                    very fertile, being specially suitable for market gardens and for growing fruit
                    trees. The fig gardens of West Tarring are celebrated. Marshall,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Rural
                    Economy of the Southern Counties,</hi> &amp;c.</p></note> describing the Weald
                    in 1788,<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n756/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0756-0725"/> says: “The townships of the Weald are in general
                    very large, owing, as it would seem, to the fewness of sites fit for
                    habitation.</p>
                <p>. . . A large portion of the vale lands remain in a state of commonage,
                    particularly on the outskirts and towards the extremities of the district. . . .
                    There is scarcely an acre of natural herbage or old grass-land”; of the coast
                    district he observes that there is strong circumstantial evidence that the lands
                    were not only brought to their present form but cultivated before the laying out
                    of townships. He also mentions that in the Isle of Selsey he observed some
                    common field land, as well as about Chichester. The South Downs afford excellent
                    pasture for sheep, Sussex being famed for a special breed of blackfaced sheep.
                    The total number in 1886 was 518,665,—seventh in order amongst English counties.
                    The total area of land and water in Sussex is 933,269 acres (1881), of which in
                    1886 there were 682,072 under crops, bare fallow, and grass, made up of 74,518
                    acres of wheat, 18,067 of barley, 66,509 of oats, 399 of rye, 6307 of beans, and
                    9493 of pease,—the total of corn crops being 175,293 acres. The green crops were
                    73,315 acres in extent, including 3405 of potatoes, 28,686 of turnips and
                    swedes, 12,152 of mangolds, 326 of carrots, 11,847 of cabbage, kohl-rabi, and
                    rape, and 16,899 of vetches and other green crops. Clover, sainfoin, and grasses
                    under rotation occupied 63,724 acres (47,851 for hay). Permanent pasture or
                    grass amounted to 340,352 acres (117,956 for hay), included chiefly in the South
                    Downs and used for sheep pasture, and the extensive pastures of Pevensey Marsh,
                    used for fattening stock. The total area cultivated with hops was 10,391 acres,
                    Sussex ranking next to Kent. In 1833 the total of hops was only 7701 acres. The
                    number of horses in 1886 was 24,964, of which 20,473 were used solely for
                    agricultural purposes. Cattle in the same year numbered 115,633, of which 40,693
                    were cows and heifers in milk or in calf. The total of pigs was 41,064. Poultry
                    in 1885 included 317,712 fowls, the fattening of which for the London market
                    forms an important industry in the northeastern part of the county, the centre
                    being at Heathfield.</p>
                <p>The earliest statement as to the population of Sussex is made by Bede, who
                    describes the county as containing in the year 681 land of 7000 families;
                    allowing ten to a family (not an unreasonable estimate at that date), the total
                    population would be 70,000. At the time of the Domesday survey (about 400 years
                    later) the total number of tenants <hi rend="italic">in capite,</hi>
                    under-tenants, bordarii, cotarii, servi, villani, &amp;c. (in fact all
                    able-bodied males), was 10,410.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Sir H. Ellis, <hi rend="italic">General Introduction to
                    Domesday Book.</hi></p></note> Assuming each of these to represent a family of
                    ten, the total population was then 104,100. In 1693 the county is stated<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Account by
                    John Houghton, F.R.S., of Acres and Houses in each County</hi> (King's
                    Pamphlets, Brit. Mus.).</p></note> to have contained 21,537 houses. If seven
                    were allowed to a house at that date, the total population would be 150,759. It
                    is curious, therefore, to observe that in 1801 the population was only 159,311.
                    The decline of the Sussex iron-works probably accounts for the small increase of
                    population during several centuries, although after the massacre of St
                    Bartholomew upwards of 1500 Huguenots landed at Rye, and in 1685 (after the
                    revocation of the Edict of Nantes) many more refugees were added to the county.
                    In 1881 the total population was 490,505, of whom 232,331 were male and 258,174
                    female. The principal towns were Brighton (population, 107,546; 128,440 in
                    parliamentary borough), Hastings (42,258; 47,738 in parliamentary borough),
                    Chichester (8114), Lewes (10,815), and Rye (4667).</p>
                <p>. Bede records that St Wilfrid, when he visited the county in 681, taught the
                    people the art of net-fishing. At the time of the Domesday survey the fisheries
                    were extensive, and no less than 285 salinae (or salt-works) existed. The
                    customs of the Brighton fishermen were reduced to writing in 1579. The census of
                    1851 returned 915 fishermen, but a parliamentary return in 1869 stated the
                    number of men and boys to be 2236, and they manned 780 boats. The census of 1881
                    returned 1471 fishermen. The approximate value of the fish landed at Brighton
                    yearly is about £20,000.</p>
                <p>There are now no important industries; the chief is the brick, tile, and pottery,
                    the main centre of which is St John’s Common. The census of 1881 returned 1485
                    brickmakers in the county. The London, Brighton, and South Coast Railway Company
                    have extensive works at Brighton. There is a daily service of passenger steamers
                    from Newhaven to Dieppe in France, and large quantities of fruit, vegetables,
                    butter, and eggs are conveyed from France to London.</p>
                <p>The earliest settlers in the county were the Celtic tribes whose memorials are
                    found in the hill-forts of Mount Caburn, Hollingbury, White Hawk, Ditchling
                    Beacon, Devil’s Dyke, Chanctonbury Hill, Cissbury, &amp;c., the latter being a
                    great factory for flint implements. They gave the names to the rivers. Little
                    is, however, known respecting them beyond the fact that they had a distinct
                    coinage some two centuries before the Roman invasion,—a coarse imitation of the
                    Greek stater of Philip II. of Macedon. These coins have been found in various
                    parts of Sussex. At the time of Caesar’s landing (55 B.c. ) the Belgic tribe of
                    the Regni inhabited the county and had their capital at Regnum (Chichester). Sir
                    G. B. Airy fixed on Pevensey as the place of Caesar’s landings in 55 and 54 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>; this is, however, much disputed, and opinion
                    generally puts the landing near Deal. A few years after this Sussex appears to
                    have formed part of the kingdom of Commius, a British chieftain, and upon his
                    death seems to have been allotted to his son Tincommius. These two are the only
                    British rulers of the county whose coins have been found. Upon the conquest of
                    Britain under Claudius the Romans found a ready tool in a king named Cogidubnus,
                    who is mentioned by Tacitus, and who was created imperial legate, and may
                    probably be identified with the king of that name mentioned in the celebrated
                    inscription on the temple of Neptune and Minerva found at Chichester. Sussex was
                    reduced to submission prior to the reign of Vespasian, and Major-General
                    Pitt-Rivers suggests that the hill-fort of Mount Caburn may have been one of the
                    twenty oppida Suetonius states to have been reduced by that emperor. Roman
                    settlements became numerous in the county and villas sprang up, the remains of
                    which are still occasionally found, the chief being that at Bignor, near Stane
                    Street, the Roman road connecting Chichester with London and still partly
                    traceable. A fortress was erected at Anderida (Pevensey), and there was another
                    town named Mutu-antonis, which is thought to be Lewes; but, having regard to the
                    Antons in West Sussex, it may have been situated farther west than Lewes,
                    perhaps at Littlehampton. Sussex was the first county invaded by the Saxons, who
                    in 477 landed under Aelle at Keynor near Chichester. After fourteen years of
                    struggle they reached the point where the South Downs abut on the sea at Beachy
                    Head, and in 491, as the <hi rend="italic">Saxon Chronicle</hi> grimly records,
                    “Aelle and Cissa beset Audredes-ceaster (Anderida), and slew all that were
                    therein, nor was there a Briton left there any more.” This resulted in the
                    formation of a distinct kingdom of South Saxons, whence its name of <hi
                    rend="italic">Sussex.</hi> The subjugation of the county was very complete, for
                    it is still one of the most thoroughly Saxon counties in England, and its
                    inhabitants, speech, place-names, customs, &amp;c., are almost entirely Saxon.
                    The next important event in the history of the county was the landing of William
                    of Normandy (28th September 1066), followed by the battle of Senlac<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The hill of Senlac is now
                    occupied by the abbey and town of Battle,</p></note> or Hastings (14th October
                    1066). The Conqueror erected on the battlefield a state abbey dedicated to St
                    Martin, but it was not completed until after his death. The next chief event was
                    the battle of Lewes between Henry III. and the barons under Simon de Montfort in
                    1264, which “wiped out the stain—if stain it were—of Senlac.” The only other
                    important events have been the rebellion of Jack Cade in 1450, which received
                    very substantial support in East Sussex, and the naval engagement fought off
                    Beachy Head in 1690, in which the English and Dutch fleets combined were
                    defeated by the French. Charles II. in his flight after the battle of Worcester
                    escaped in 1651 from Brighton in a fishing-boat.</p>
                <p>The foremost place amongst the illustrious natives of Sussex must be assigned to
                    Shelley the poet. Of statesmen we have Richard Cobden and John Selden, and of
                    eminent ecclesiastics Archbishops Frewen, John Peckham, and William Juxon, also
                    Archdeacon Hare. Its poets include Thomas Otway, Thomas Sackville (afterwards
                    earl of Dorset), and John Fletcher. Of antiquaries we find Sir William Burrell,
                    John Elliot, Rev. Thomas W. Horsfield, Mark Antony Lower, Dr Mantell
                    (geologist), and Dr Richard Russell (founder of modern Brighton).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dialect.—</hi> A large number of Saxon words are still retained
                    and pronounced in the old style; thus <hi rend="italic">gate</hi> becomes <hi
                    rend="italic">ge-at.</hi> The letter <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is very broad in
                    all words, as if followed by <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> and in fact converts
                    words of one syllable into words of two, as <hi rend="italic">fails</hi> (face),
                    <hi rend="italic">taust</hi> (taste), &amp;c. Again, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    before double <hi rend="italic">d</hi> becomes <hi rend="italic">ar,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic">arder</hi> and <hi rend="italic">larder</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >adder</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ladder; oi</hi> is like a long <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">spile</hi> (spoil), <hi rend="italic"
                    >intment</hi> (ointment); an <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is substituted for <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> in such words as <hi rend="italic">rag, flag,</hi> &amp;c.
                    The French refugees in the 16th and 17th centuries introduced many words which
                    are still in use. Thus a Sussex woman when unprepared to receive visitors says
                    she is in <hi rend="italic">dishabille</hi> (déshabillé, undress); if her child
                    is unwell, it looks <hi rend="italic">pekid</hi> (piqué), if fretful is a little
                    <hi rend="italic">peter-grievous</hi> (petit-grief); she cooks with a <hi
                    rend="italic">broach</hi> (broche, a spit), and talks of <hi rend="italic"
                    >coasts</hi> (coste, Old French) or ribs of meat, &amp;c. There is an excellent
                    <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of the Sussex Dialect</hi> by the Rev. W. D.
                    Parish.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> Amongst standard historical works dealing
                    with Sussex history are E. A. Freeman’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Norman
                    Conquest</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Life of William Rufus</hi>; J. R. Green’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Making of England</hi>; W. H. Blaauw’s <hi rend="italic">The
                    Barons’ War;</hi> and Kemble's <hi rend="italic">Saxons in England.</hi> The
                    general history of the county is dealt with in Horsfield’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Sussex</hi>; Dallaway and Cartwright’s <hi rend="italic">History of
                    the Western Division of the County of Sussex;</hi> M. A. Lower’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Compendious History of Sussex;</hi> Dudley C. Elwes and Charles J.
                    Robinson’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Castles, Mansions, and Manors of
                    Western Sussex</hi>; P. de Putron’s <hi rend="italic">Nooks and Corners of Old
                    Sussex</hi>; W. R. W. Stephens’s <hi rend="italic">Diocesan Histories (The South
                    Saxon Diocese: Selsey—Chichester); Sussex Archaeological Society's
                    Collections,</hi> 34 vols. , and index to the first 25 vols.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Domesday Book in relation to the County of Sussex</hi> (1886). See also C.
                    Fleet, <hi rend="italic">Glimpses of our Sussex Ancestors,</hi> two series;
                    Swainson, <hi rend="italic">Chichester Cathedral</hi>; Col. Lane-Fox (now
                    Pitt-Rivers), “Examination into the Character and Probable Origin of the Hill
                    Forts of Sussex,” in <hi rend="italic">Archxologia,</hi> xln. 2,, and “Further
                    Remarks,” &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">ib.,</hi> p. 53; G. Slade Butler, <hi
                    rend="italic">Topographιca Sussex-iana</hi>; M. A. Lower, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Churches of Sussex</hi> (illustrated by R. Nibbs) and <hi rend="italic">The
                    Worthies of Sussex;</hi> J. C. Egerton, <hi rend="italic">Sussex Folk and Sussex
                    Ways; Proceedings of the Brighton and Sussex Natural History Society</hi>; W. E.
                    Baxter, <hi rend="italic">The Domesday Book for the County of Sussex, being that
                    portion of a Return of owners of Land in 1873 which refers to Sussex,</hi>
                    Lewes, 1876; J. D. Perry, <hi rend="italic">Historical and Descriptive</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n757/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0757-0726"/><hi rend="italic">Account of the Coast of
                    Sussex</hi>; Frederick Dixon, <hi rend="italic">The Geology of Sussex</hi>; M.
                    A. Lower, <hi rend="italic">Chronicles of Pevensey·,</hi> william Topley, <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs of the Geological Survey of England and IVales: Geology of
                    the Weald, parts of the Counties of Kent, Surrey, Sussex and Hants;</hi> J. G.
                    Bishop, <hi rend="italic">Brighton Pavilion and its Royal Associations;</hi>
                    Merrifield, <hi rend="italic">A Sketch, of the Natural History of Brighton and
                    its Vicinity,</hi> 1864; H. D. Gordon, <hi rend="italic">The History of
                    Harting</hi>; Basil Champneys, <hi rend="italic">A Quiet Corner of England:
                    Studies of Landscape and Architecture in Winchelsea, Rye, and the Romney
                    Marsh</hi> 1874; M. A. Tierney, <hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities of the
                    Castle and Town of Arundel</hi>; Holloway, <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Rye</hi>; Horsfield, <hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities of Lewes; W.
                    D.</hi> Cooper, <hi rend="italic">History of Winchelsea</hi>; M. A. Lower, <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicles of Battle Abbey;</hi> Howard, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hastings Past and Present,</hi> &amp;c. (F. E. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
