<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0480-0457-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STARLING (9th edition, volume 22, page 457)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1120280">Skylark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830969">Betta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1184692">Zoologists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834915">Blue</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903849">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947579">Green</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212489">Bulgaria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc1c">Zoologists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3d540">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n480/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STARLING</label> (A.S. <hi rend="italic">Staer, Stearn,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Sterlyng∙,</hi> Lat. <hi rend="italic">Sturnus;</hi> Fr.
                    <hi rend="italic">Étourneau),</hi> a bird long time well-known in most parts of
                    England, and now, through the extension of its range within the present century,
                    in the rest of Great Britain, as well as in Ireland, where, though not generally
                    distributed, it is very numerous in some districts. It is about the size of a
                    Thrush, and, though at a distance it appears to be black, when near at hand its
                    plumage is seen to be brightly shot with purple, green, and steel-blue, most of
                    the feathers when freshly grown being tipped with buff. These markings wear off
                    in the course of the winter, and in the breeding-season the bird is almost
                    spotless. It is the <hi rend="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</hi> of
                    ornithologists.</p>
                <p>To describe the habits of the Starling<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>They are dwelt ou at some length in Yarrell s <hi
                    rend="italic">British Birds,</hi> ed. 4, vol. ii. pp. 229-241.</p></note> within
                    the limits here allotted is impossible. A more engaging bird scarcely exists,
                    for its familiarity during some months of the year gives opportunities for
                    observing its ways that few others afford, while its varied song, its sprightly
                    gestures, its glossy plumage, and, above all, its character as an
                    insecticide—which last makes it the friend of the agriculturist and the
                    grazier—render it an almost universal favourite. The worst that can be said of
                    it is that it occasionally pilfers fruit, and, as it flocks to roost in autumn
                    and winter among reed-beds, does considerable damage by breaking down the
                    stems.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A most ridiculous
                    and unfounded charge has been, however, more than once brought against it—that
                    of destroying the eggs of Skylarks. There is little real evidence of its sucking
                    eggs, and much of its not doing so; while, to render the allegation still more
                    absurd, it has been brought by a class of farmers who generally complain that
                    Skylarks themselves are highly injurious.</p></note> The congregations of
                    Starlings are indeed very marvellous, and no less than the aerial evolutions of
                    the flocks, chiefly before settling for the night, have attracted attention from
                    early times, being mentioned by Pliny (<hi rend="italic">Hist. Naturalis,</hi>
                    x. 24) in the 1st century. The extraordinary precision with which the crowd,
                    often numbering several hundreds, not to say thousands, of birds, wheels,
                    closes, opens out, rises, and descends, as if the whole body were a single
                    living thing— all these movements being executed without a note or cry being
                    uttered—must be seen to be appreciated, and may be seen repeatedly with
                    pleasure. For a resident, the Starling is rather a late breeder. The nest is
                    commonly placed in the hole of a tree or of a building, and its preparation is
                    the work of some little time. The eggs, from 4 to 7 in number, are of a very
                    pale blue, often tinged with green. As the young grow they become very noisy,
                    and their parents, in their assiduous attendance, hardly less so, thus
                    occasionally making themselves disagreeable in a quiet neighbourhood. The
                    Starling has a wide range over Europe and Asia, reaching India; but examples
                    from Kashmir, Persia, and Armenia have been considered worthy of specific
                    distinction, and the resident Starling of the countries bordering the
                    Mediterranean is generally regarded as a good species, and called <hi
                    rend="italic">S. unicolor</hi> from its unspotted plumage.</p>
                <p>Of the many forms allied to the genus <hi rend="italic">Sturnus,</hi> some of
                    which have perhaps been needlessly separated therefrom, those known as <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Grackles</hi> (vol. xi. p. 26) have been already mentioned, and
                    there is only room here to notice one other, <hi rend="italic">Pastor,</hi>
                    containing a beautiful species <hi rend="italic">P. roseus,</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n481/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0481-0458"/> the Rose-coloured Starling, which is not an
                    unfrequent visitor to the British Islands. It is a bird of most irregular and
                    erratic habits—a vast horde suddenly arriving at some place to which it may have
                    hitherto been a stranger, and at once making a settlement there, leaving it
                    wholly deserted as soon as the young are reared. This happened in the summer of
                    1875 at Villafranca, in the province of Verona, the castle of which was occupied
                    in a single day by some 12,000 or 14,000 birds of this species, as has been
                    graphically told by Sig. de Betta <hi rend="italic">(Atti del R. Ist.
                    Veneto,</hi> ser. 5, vol. ii.);<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>A partial translation of this paper is given in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Zoologist</hi> for 1878, pp. 18-22.</p></note> but similar
                    instances have been before recorded,—as in Bulgaria in 1867, near Smyrna in
                    1856, and near Odessa in 1844, to mention only some of which particulars have
                    been published.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is
                    remarkable that on almost all of these occasions the locality pitched upon has
                    been, either at the time or soon after, ravaged by locusts, which the birds
                    greedily devour. Another fact worthy of attention is that they are often
                    observed to affect trees or shrubs bearing rose-coloured flowers, as <hi
                    rend="italic">Nerium oleander</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Robinia viscosa,</hi>
                    among the blossoms of which they themselves may easily escape notice, for their
                    plumage is rose-pink and black shot with blue.</p></note><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
