<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0101-0086-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SIMPSON, Sir James Young, Bart (9th edition, volume 22,
                    page 86)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p161">Surgeons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zc7rt6g">Chloroform</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:858179">Chloroform</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1739388">Womanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1895887">Womanizers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139336">Surgeons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n101/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SIMPSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir James Young,
                    Bart</hi></label>. (1811-1870), physician, was born in the town of Bathgate,
                    Linlithgow, Scotland, on the 7th of June 1811. His father was a baker in that
                    town, who largely owed a moderate success in business to a shrewd and managing
                    wife. James was the youngest of a family of eight, and for the furtherance of
                    his worldly prospects the others struggled and sacrificed. At the age of
                    fourteen he entered the university of Edinburgh as a student in the arts
                    classes. Two years later he began his medical studies. At the age of nineteen he
                    obtained the licence of the College of Surgeons, and two years afterwards took
                    the degree of doctor of medicine. Dr Thomson, who then occupied the chair of
                    pathology in the university, impressed with the graduation thesis, “On Death
                    from Inflammation,” presented by Simpson, offered him his assistantship. The
                    offer was accepted, and during the session 1837-38 he acted as interim lecturer
                    on pathology during the illness of the professor. The following winter he
                    delivered his first course of lectures on obstetric medicine in the
                    extra-academical school. On February 4, 1840, he was elected to the
                    professorship of medicine and midwifery in the university. Towards the end of
                    1846 he was present at an operation performed by Liston on a patient rendered
                    unconscious by the inhalation of sulphuric ether. The success of the proceeding
                    was so marked that Simpson immediately began to use it in midwifery practice. He
                    continued, however, to search for other substances having similar effects, and
                    in March 1847 he read a paper on chloroform to the Medico-Chirurgical Society of
                    Edinburgh, in which he fully detailed the history of the use of anaesthetics
                    from the earliest times, but especially dwelt upon the advantages of chloroform
                    over ether. He advocated its use, not only for the prevention of pain in
                    surgical operations, but also for the relief of pain in obstetrical practice.
                    His strong and uncompromising advocacy of its use in the latter class of cases
                    gave rise to one of the angriest and most widespread controversies of the time,
                    and, although his views may not have been generally indorsed by later
                    professional practice, anaesthetics in surgical operations have from that time
                    held an indisputed place, and Simpson’s anaesthetic still continues the
                    favourite in the practice of the Edinburgh school. In 1847 he was appointed a
                    physician to the queen in Scotland. In 1859 he advocated the use of acupressure
                    in place of ligatures for arresting bleeding; his views on this subject have,
                    however, given place to improvements in the ligature and to a better knowledge
                    of the conditions influencing its efficiency. His contributions to the
                    literature of his profession and to archaeology, in which latter he took an
                    active interest, were very numerous, and embrace <hi rend="italic">Obstetric
                    Memoirs and Contributions</hi> (2 vols.), <hi rend="italic">Homoeopathy,
                    Acupressure, Selected Obstetrical Works, Anaesthesia and Hospitalism, Clinical
                    Lectures on the Diseases of Women,</hi> and three volumes of essays on
                    archaeological subjects. Simpson, who had been created a baronet in 1866, died
                    on May 6th 1870, and was accorded a public funeral; his statue in bronze now
                    stands in West Princes Street Gardens, Edinburgh.</p>
                <p>Simpson was a man of strong individuality and somewhat hasty temper, an
                    uncompromising and aggressive opponent when he believed himself in the right,
                    yet so tender and sympathetic that he endeared himself to an immense circle of
                    friends and patients. Endowed with great mental power, activity, and
                    receptivity, he performed a very large amount of literary work, much of which
                    was of great value at the time and still continues to be of interest. He will,
                    however, be chiefly remembered in the annals of medicine as a great personality,
                    who brilliantly fought and won the battle for anaesthetics, and introduced
                    chloroform.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
