<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0634-0611-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STURGEON (9th edition, volume 22, page 611)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kx11">Sturgeon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136268">Sturgeons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1431540">Sterlet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208387">Michigan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n634/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STURGEON</label>. Sturgeons <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Acipenser)</hi> are a small group of fishes, of which some twenty different
                    species are known, from European, Asiatic, and North American rivers. The
                    distinguishing characters of this group, as well as its position in the system,
                    have been sufficiently indicated in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Ichthyology</hi> (vol. xii. p. 687). They pass a great part of the year in the
                    sea, but periodically ascend large rivers, some in spring to deposit their
                    spawn, others later in the season for some purpose unknown; only a few of the
                    species are exclusively confined to fresh water. None occur in the tropics or in
                    the southern hemisphere.</p>
                <p>Sturgeons are found in the greatest abundance in the rivers of southern Russia,
                    more than ten thousand fish being sometimes caught at a single fishing-station
                    in the fortnight during which the up-stream migration lasts. They occur in less
                    abundance in the fresh waters of North America, where their capture is not
                    confined to the rivers, the majority being caught in shallow portions of the
                    shores of the great lakes. In Russia the fisheries are of immense value; yet but
                    little is known of the sturgeon’s habits, life, and early stages of development
                    or growth. Early in summer the fish migrate into the rivers or towards the
                    shores of freshwater lakes in large shoals for breeding purposes. The ova are
                    very small, and so numerous that one female has been calculated to produce about
                    three millions in one season. The ova of some species have been observed to
                    hatch within a very few days after exclusion. Probably the growth of the young
                    is very rapid, but we have no knowledge as to the length of time for which the
                    fry remain in fresh water before their first migration to the sea. After they
                    have attained maturity their growth appears to be much slower, although
                    continuing for many years. Frederick the Great attempted to introduce the
                    sterlet into Prussia, and placed a number of this fish in the Görland Lake in
                    Pomerania about 1780; some of these were found to be still alive in 1866, and
                    therefore had reached an age of nearly ninety years. Prof. Von Baer also states,
                    as the result of direct observations made in Russia, that the hausen <hi
                    rend="italic">(Acipenser huso</hi>) attains to an age of from 200 to 300 years.
                    Sturgeons ranging from 8 to 11 feet in length are by no means scarce, and some
                    species grow to a much larger size.</p>
                <p>Sturgeons are ground-feeders. With their projecting wedge-shaped snout they stir
                    up the soft bottom, and by means of their sensitive barbels detect shells,
                    crustaceans, and small fishes, on which they feed. Destitute of teeth, they are
                    unable to seize larger prey.</p>
                <p>In countries like England, where few sturgeons are<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n635/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0635-0612"/> caught, the fish is consumed fresh, the flesh
                    being firmer than that of ordinary fishes, well-flavoured, though somewhat oily.
                    The sturgeon is included as a royal fish in an Act of King Edward II., which
                    assigns to the sovereign all wrecks and whales, although it probably but rarely
                    graces the royal table of the present period, or even that of the lord mayor of
                    London, who can claim all sturgeons caught in the Thames above London Bridge.
                    Where sturgeons are regularly caught in large quantities, as on the rivers of
                    southern</p>
                <p>Russia and on the great lakes of North</p>
                <p>America, their flesh is dried, smoked, or salted. The ovaries, which are of large
                    size, are prepared for caviare; for this purpose they are beaten with switches,
                    and then pressed through sieves, leaving the membranous and fibrous tissues in
                    the sieve, whilst the eggs are collected in a tub. The quantity of salt added to
                    them before they are finally packed varies with the season, scarcely any being
                    used at the beginning of winter. Finally, one of the best sorts of isinglass is
                    manufactured from the air-bladder. After it has been carefully removed from the
                    body, it is washed in hot water, and cut open in its whole length, to separate
                    the inner membrane, which has a soft consistency, and contains 70 per cent. of
                    glutin.</p>
                <p>The twenty species of sturgeons <hi rend="italic">(Acipenser)</hi> are nearly
                    equally divided between the Old and New Worlds. The more important are the
                    following :—</p>
                <p>(1) The Common Sturgeon of Europe (<hi rend="italic">Acipenser sturio)</hi>
                    occurs on all the coasts of Europe, but is absent in the Black Sea. Almost all
                    the British specimens of sturgeon belong to this species; it crosses the
                    Atlantic and is not rare on the coasts of North America. It reaches a large size
                    (a length of 12 feet), but is always caught singly or in pairs, so that it
                    cannot be regarded as a fish of commercial importance. The form of its snout
                    varies with age (as in the other species), being much more blunt and abbreviated
                    in old than in young examples. There are 11-13 bony shields along the back and
                    29-31 along the side of the body.</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Acipenser gülclenslädlii</hi> is one of the most valuable
                    species of the rivers of Russia, where it is known under the name “Ossétr”; it
                    is said to inhabit the Siberian rivers also, and to range eastwards as far as
                    Lake Baikal. It attains to the same large size as the common sturgeon, and is so
                    abundant in the rivers of the Black and Caspian Seas that more than one-fourth
                    of the caviare and isinglass manufactured in Russia is derived from this
                    species.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Acipenser stellatus,</hi> the “Seuruga” of the Russians,
                    occurs likewise in great abundance in the rivers of the Black Sea and of the Sea
                    of Azoff. It has a remarkably long and pointed snout, like the sterlet, but
                    simple barbels without fringes. Though growing only to about half the size of
                    the preceding species, it is of no less value, its flesh being more highly
                    esteemed, and its caviare and isinglass fetching a higher price. In 1850 it was
                    reported that more than a million of this sturgeon are caught annually.</p>
                <p>(4) The sturgeon of the great lakes of North America, <hi rend="italic">Acipenser
                    rubicundus,</hi> with which, in the opinion of American ichthyologists, the
                    sea-going sturgeon of the rivers of eastern North America, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Acipenser maculosus,</hi> is identical, has of late years been made the object
                    of a large and profitable industry at various places on Lakes Michigan and Erie;
                    the flesh is smoked after being cut into strips and after a slight pickling in
                    brine; the thin portions and offal are boiled down for oil; nearly all the
                    caviare is shipped to Europe. One firm alone uses from ten to eighteen thousand
                    sturgeons a year, averaging fifty pounds each. The sturgeons of the lakes are
                    unable to migrate to the sea, whilst those below the Falls of Niagara are great
                    wanderers; and it is quite possible that a specimen of this species said to have
                    been obtained from the Firth of Tay was really captured on the coast of
                    Scotland.</p>
                <p>(5) <hi rend="italic">Acipenser huso,</hi> the “Hausen” of Germany, is recognized
                    by the absence of osseous scutes on the snout and by its flattened, tape-like
                    barbels. It is one of the largest species, reaching the enormous length of 24
                    feet and a weight of 2000 pounds. It inhabits the Caspian and Black Seas and the
                    Sea of Azoff, whence in former years large shoals of the fish entered the large
                    rivers of Russia and the Danube. But its numbers have been much thinned, and
                    specimens of 1200 pounds in weight have now become scarce. Its flesh, caviare,
                    and air-bladder are of less value than those of the smaller kinds.</p>
                <p>(6) The Sterlet (<hi rend="italic">Acipenser ruthenus)</hi> is one of the smaller
                    species, which likewise inhabits both the Black and Caspian Seas, and ascends
                    rivers to a greater distance from the sea than any of the other sturgeons; thus,
                    for instance, it is not uncommon in the Danube at Vienna, but specimens have
                    been caught as high up as Ratisbon and Ulm. It is more abundant in the rivers of
                    Russia, where it is held in high esteem on account of its excellent flesh,
                    contributing also to the best kinds of caviare and isinglass. As early as last
                    century attempts were made to introduce this valuable fish into Prussia and
                    Sweden, but without success. The sterlet is distinguished from the other
                    European species by its long and narrow snout and fringed barbels. It rarely
                    exceeds a length of three feet.</p>
                <p>Sturgeons with the snout prolonged in an extraordinary manner, so as to form a
                    long spade-like or conical process (<hi rend="italic">Spatularia, Polyodon,
                    Psephurus),</hi> occur in the Mississippi and the great rivers of China and
                    Central Asia. None of them have been made objects of trade, but special interest
                    is attached to them from a geographical as well as palaeontological point of
                    view, the two genera last named being represented as far back as the Lias by an
                    allied fossil genus, <hi rend="italic">Chondrosteus,</hi> and all affording a
                    striking proof of the close affinity of the North-American and North-Asiatic
                    faunas of the recent period.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
