<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0568-0545-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STEVINUS, Simon (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    545)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hf8s">Pamphlets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sj6k">Fractions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727h76">Claims</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gv14">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1051866">Pamphleteers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1051868">Pamphlets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933519">Fractions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863204">Claims</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n568/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STEVINUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Simon</hi></label>
                    (1548-1620). This great mathematician was born in 1548 at Bruges (where the
                    Place Simon Stevin contains his statue by Eugen Simonis) and died in 1620 at The
                    Hague or in Leyden. Of the circumstances of his life very little is recorded;
                    the exact day of his birth and the day and place of his death are alike
                    uncertain. It is known that he left a widow with two children; and one or two
                    hints scattered throughout his works inform us that he began life as a
                    merchant’s clerk in Antwerp, that he travelled in Poland, Denmark, and other
                    parts of northern Europe, and that he was intimate with Prince Maurice of
                    Orange, who asked his advice on many occasions, and made him a public
                    officer,—at first director of the so-called “waterstaet,” and afterwards
                    quartermaster-general. The question whether Stevinus, like most of the rest of
                    the prince’s followers, belonged to the Protestant creed hardly admits of a
                    categorical answer. A Catholic, it may be said, would never in those times have
                    risen to so high a position. A Catholic would perhaps not have been so ready as
                    Stevinus to deny the value of all authority, whether of an Aristotle, of an
                    Euclid, or of a Vitruvius. A Catholic could not well have boasted, as Stevinus
                    in a political pamphlet did, that he had always been in harmony with the
                    executive power. But against these considerations it might be urged that a
                    Protestant had no occasion to boast of a harmony most natural to him, while his
                    further remark, in the same pamphlet, to the effect that a state church is
                    indispensable, and that those who cannot belong to it on conscientious grounds
                    ought to leave the country rather than show any opposition to its rites, seems
                    rather to indicate the crypto-Catholic, who wishes for reasons of his own to
                    remain in the Netherlands. The same conclusion is supported by the ascertained
                    fact that Stevinus, a year before his death, bequeathed a pious legacy to the
                    church of Westkerke in Flanders, out of the revenues of which masses were to be
                    said. But, however it may be answered, the question is fortunately of little
                    importance to us, as Stevinus was neither a political personage nor did he
                    engage in religious controversy. He was mainly, as already said, a great
                    mathematician, and it is chiefly in this quality that we must try to get
                    acquainted with him. His claims to fame are most varied. Some of them appealed
                    strongly to the men of his time, but many were such as could not well be
                    understood by most of his contemporaries, and have found due acknowledgment only
                    in later times.</p>
                <p>His contemporaries were most struck by his invention of a carriage with sails, a
                    little model of which was preserved at Scheveningen till 1802. The carriage
                    itself had been lost long before; but we know that about the year 1600 Stevinus,
                    with Prince Maurice of Orange and twenty-six others, made use of it on the
                    sea-shore between Scheveningen and Petten, that it was propelled solely by the
                    force of the wind, and that it acquired a speed which exceeded that of horses.
                    Another idea of Stevinus, for which even Grotius gave him great credit, was his
                    notion of a bygone age of wisdom. Mankind once knew everything knowable, but
                    gradually forgot most of it, till a time came when little by little the
                    forgotten knowledge was reacquired; the goal to be aimed at is the bringing
                    about of a second age of wisdom, in which mankind shall have recovered all its
                    early knowledge. The fellow-countrymen of Stevinus were proud that he wrote in
                    their own dialect, which he thought fitted for a universal language, as no other
                    abounded like Dutch in monosyllabic radical words.</p>
                <p>History has been much less enthusiastic than his con-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n569/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0569-0546"/> temporaries in admiring these claims to fame, but
                    it has discovered in Stevinus’s works various inventions which did not at once
                    receive the notice they deserved. He was the first to show how to fashion
                    regular and semiregular polyhedra by delineating their frames in a plane.
                    Stevinus also distinguished stable from unstable equilibrium. He proved the law
                    of the equilibrium on an inclined plane. He demonstrated before Varignon the
                    resolution of forces, which, simple consequence of the law of their composition
                    though it is, had not been previously remarked. He discovered the hydrostatic
                    paradox that the downward pressure of a liquid is independent of the shape of
                    the vessel, and depends only on its height and base. He also gave the measure of
                    the pressure on any given portion of the side of a vessel. He had the idea of
                    explaining the tides by the attraction of the moon.</p>
                <p>It remains to enumerate those claims of Stevinus to immortality which were
                    recognized from the first and which succeeding ages have not lessened,—his
                    writings on military science, on book-keeping, and on decimal fractions.</p>
                <p>That the man who was quartermaster-general to Maurice of Orange should have been
                    possessed of more than ordinary merit, and have left behind him military papers
                    of lasting value, is hardly more than might have been expected. This
                    expectation, in the case of Stevinus at least, is fully borne out in the opinion
                    of competent judges. Prince Maurice is known as the man who conquered the
                    greatest number of fortresses in the shortest time, and fortification was the
                    principal aim of his adviser. Stevinus seems to be the first who made it an
                    axiom that strongholds are only to be defended by artillery, the defence before
                    his time having relied mostly on small firearms. He wrote upon temporary
                    fortifications, but the excellence of his system was only slowly discerned. He
                    was the inventor of defence by a system of sluices, which proved of the highest
                    importance for the Netherlands. His plea for the teaching of the science of
                    fortification in universities, and the existence of such lectures in Leyden,
                    have led to the impression that he himself filled this chair; but the belief is
                    quite erroneous, as Stevinus, though living at Leyden, never had direct
                    relations with its university.</p>
                <p>Book-keeping by double entry may have been known to Stevinus as clerk at Antwerp
                    either practically or through the medium of the works of Italian authors like
                    Paccioli and Cardan. He, however, was the first to recommend the use of
                    impersonal accounts in the national household. He practised it for Maurice, and
                    recommended it in a small pamphlet to Sully the French statesman; and, if public
                    book-keeping has grown more and more lucid by the introduction of impersonal
                    accounts, it is certainly to Stevinus that the credit of the improvement is
                    due.</p>
                <p>His greatest success, however, was a small pamphlet, first published in Dutch in
                    1586, and not exceeding seven pages in the French translation (which alone we
                    have seen). This translation is entitled <hi rend="italic">La Disme, enseignant
                    facilement expédier par Nombres Entiers sans rompuz, tous Comptes se rencontrans
                    aux Affaires des Hommes.</hi> Decimal fractions had been employed for the
                    extraction of square roots some five centuries before his time, but nobody
                    before Stevinus established their daily use; and so well aware was he of the
                    importance of his innovation that he declared the universal introduction of
                    decimal coinage, measures, and weights to be only a question of time. His
                    notation is rather unwieldy. The point separating the integers from the decimal
                    fractions seems to be the invention of Bartholomaeus Pitiscus, in whose
                    trigonometrical tables (1612) we have found it, and it was accepted by Napier in
                    his logarithmic papers (1614 and 1619). Stevinus printed little circles round
                    the ex ponents of the different powers of one-tenth. For instance, 237 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 578</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 1000</hi> was printed 237 ®
                    5 Q 7 08 0; and the fact that Stevinus meant those encircled numerals to denote
                    mere exponents is evident from his employing the very same sign for powers of
                    algebraic quantities, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> 9 θ-14 ® + 6®-5 to denote 9
                    <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi>-14 <hi rend="italic"
                    >x</hi>; <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> +6 <hi rend="italic">x</hi>-5. He does
                    not even avoid fractional exponents (“Racine cubique de ®) serait <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> en circle ”), and is
                    ignorant only of negative exponents. Powers and exponents have also been carried
                    back to a period several centuries earlier than Stevinus, and it is not here
                    intended to give him any undue credit for having maintained them; but we believe
                    it ought to be recognized more than it generally is, that for our author there
                    was a connexion between algebraic powers and decimal fractions, and that even
                    here Stevinus the profound theorist is not lost to view behind Stevinus the man
                    of brilliant practical talents. <hi rend="smallcaps">(m. ca.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
