<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0216-0201-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SNORRO STURLUSON (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    201)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:902400">Eddas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966645">Icelanders</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103425">Sagas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4959cc6w">Eddas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn10">Icelanders</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sf0p">Sagas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n216/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SNORRO STURLUSON</label> (Snorri, son of Stnrla) (1179-
                    1241), the celebrated Icelandic historian, born in 1179, the youngest son of a
                    chief in the Vestfir‎ðir (western fiords), was brought up by a powerful chief,
                    Jon Loptsson, in Odda, who seems first to have awakened in him an interest for
                    history and poetry. His career begins with his marriage, which made him a
                    wealthy man; in 1206 he settled at Reykjaholt, where he constructed magnificent
                    buildings and a bath of hewn stones, preserved to the present day, to which
                    water was conducted from a neighbouring hot spring. He early made himself known
                    as a poet, especially by glorifying the exploits of the contemporary Norse kings
                    and earls; at the same time he was a learned lawyer, and from 1215 became the
                    “lögsögumaör,” or president of the legislative assembly and supreme court of
                    Iceland. The prominent features of his character seem to have been cunning,
                    ambition, and avarice, combined with want of courage and aversion to effort. By
                    royal invitation he went in 1218 to Norway, where he remained a long time with
                    the young king Hakon and his tutor Earl Skuli. When, owing to disputes between
                    Icelandic and Norwegian merchants, Skuli thought of a military expedition to
                    Iceland, Snorro persuaded him to give up this plan, promising to make the
                    inhabitants submit to Hakon of their own free will. Snorro himself became the
                    “lendrmaör,” vassal or baron, of the king of Norway, and held his lands as a
                    fief under him. On his return home Snorro sent his son to the king as a hostage,
                    and made peace between Norway and Iceland, but his power and influence were used
                    more for his own enrichment and aggrandizement—he was “lögsögumaðr” again from
                    1222 to 1232—than for the advantage of the king. Hakon, therefore, stirred up
                    strife between Snorro’s kinsman Sturla and Snorro, who had to fly from
                    Reykjaholt in 1236; and in 1237 he left the country and went back to Norway.
                    Here he joined the party of Skuli, who was meditating a revolt. Learning that
                    his cousin Sturla in Iceland had fallen in battle against Gissur, Snorro’s
                    son-in-law, Snorro, although expressly forbidden by his liege lord, returned to
                    Iceland in 1239 and once more took possession of his property. Meanwhile Hakon,
                    who had vanquished Skuli in 1240, sent orders to Gissur to punish Snorro for his
                    disobedience either by capturing him and sending him back to Norway or by
                    putting him to death. Gissur took the latter course, attacked Snorro at his
                    residence, Reykjaholt, and slew him on 22d September 1241.</p>
                <p>Snorro is the author of the <hi rend="italic">Edda</hi> and of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Sagas of the Norwegian Kings.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Edda,</hi> now called the Prose Edda, to distinguish it from the Poetic or
                    Saemund’s Edda, was finished in 1222, and consists of three parts. (1) The <hi
                    rend="italic">Gylfaginning,</hi> or the Delusion of Gylfi, with a short preface,
                    gives a summary of the ancient Norse mythology, founded on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Völuspá</hi> and other mythical poems; the author gives a euhemeristic account
                    of the ancient gods, regarding them as chiefs versed in witchcraft who had
                    immigrated to the north and there introduced their special religion. (2) The <hi
                    rend="italic">Skalds-kaparmál,</hi> or Art of Poetry, gives, under the form of a
                    dialogue between the god Bragi and the giant (jötun) Aegir, an explanation of
                    all figurative mythological expressions of the ancient poetry, and the rules for
                    using them. (3) The <hi rend="italic">Háttatal,</hi> or Enumeration of Metres,
                    is a running commentary on three poems composed by Snorro in 1222 in honour of
                    Hakon and Skuli, the stanzas of which, numbering about a hundred, are each in a
                    different metre. In the MSS. the <hi rend="italic">Edda</hi> has received many
                    additions, which are wrongly ascribed to Snorro. For different editions see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Edda.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Sagas of the Norwegian
                    Kings</hi> gives a connected series of biographies of the kings of Norway down
                    to Sverri in 1177; here the author stops, because the history of Sverri and his
                    successors had already been written. The work opens with the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ynglinga Saga,</hi> a brief history of the pretended immigration into Sweden of
                    the Aesir, of their successors in that country, the kings of Upsala, and of the
                    oldest Norwegian kings, their descendants. Next come the biographies of the
                    succeeding Norwegian kings, the most detailed being those of the two missionary
                    kings Olaf Tryggvason and St Olaf. Snorro’s sources were partly succinct
                    histories of the realm, as the chronological sketch of Ari; partly more
                    voluminous early collections of traditions, as the <hi rend="italic">Noregs
                    Konungatal (Fagrskinna)</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Jarlasaga;</hi> partly
                    legendary biographies of the two Olafs; and, in addition to these, studies and
                    collections which he himself made during his journeys in Norway. All these he
                    worked up with great independence and critical sagacity into an harmonious
                    whole. His critical principles are explained in the preface, where he dwells on
                    the necessity of starting as much as possible from trustworthy contemporary
                    sources, or at least from those nearest to antiquity,—the touchstone by which
                    verbal traditions can be tested being contemporary poems. He inclines to
                    rationalism, rejecting the marvellous and recasting legends containing it in a
                    more historical spirit; but he makes an exception in the accounts of the
                    introduction of Christianity into Norway and of the national saint St Olaf.
                    Snorro’s style is peculiar to himself. He strives everywhere to impart life and
                    vigour to his narrative, to express the sentiments and feelings of the actors,
                    and he gives the dialogues in the individual character of each person.
                    Especially in this last he shows a tendency to epigram and often uses humorous
                    and pathetic expressions. Besides his principal work, he elaborated in a
                    separate form its better and larger part, the <hi rend="italic">History of St
                    Olaf</hi> (the great <hi rend="italic">Olafs Saga).</hi> In the preface to this
                    he gives a brief extract of the earlier history, and, as an appendix, a short
                    account of St Olaf s miracles after his death; here too he employs critical art,
                    as appears from a comparison with his source, the Latin legend.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Sagas of the Norwegian Kings</hi> has been preserved in
                    several MSS. of the 13th century; the oldest of these, no longer extant, had
                    lost at an early period its first leaf containing the preface, and thus came to
                    begin with the words, <hi rend="italic">Kringla heimsins</hi> (=orbis terrarum),
                    which caused first this MS. and later (about 1700) the whole work to be called
                    the <hi rend="italic">Heimskringla.</hi> Editions :—by Pering-skiöld, 3 vols,
                    fol., Stockholm, 1697; by Gerhard Schöning and Skule Thorlacius, 3 vols, fol.,
                    Copenhagen, 1777-1783; by C. R. Unger, 1 vol. 8vo, Christiania, 1868. Modern
                    translations :—into Danish, by N. F. S. Grundtvig, 1818-22; Norwegian, by Jacob
                    Aall, 1833-39, and by P. A. Munch, 1859; Swedish, by Richert, 1816- 29, and by
                    H. Hildebrand, 1869-71; German, by Wachter, 1835-36; English, by Laing, 1844.
                    (G. S. †)</p>
                <p>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
