<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0640-0617-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SUCKLING, Sir John (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    617)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f52f">Goblins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc29">Ballads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100852">Royalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944030">Goblins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103306">Sadness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825857">Ballade</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:892884">Diction</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n640/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SUCKLING, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label>
                    (1609-1642), one of the most admired poets and men of fashion at the court of
                    Charles I., and an active spirit in politics as well as in fashionable gaieties,
                    belonged to a Norfolk family. His father was a high official under James I. and
                    a comptroller of the household under Charles I.; finance seems to have been his
                    strong point, and he managed his own affairs so well as to accumulate a
                    considerable fortune, of which the poet was left master at the age of eighteen.
                    His earliest biographers fixed his birth in 1613, and founded on this a<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n641/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0641-0618"/> reputation for extraordinary precocity in school
                    learning. Mr Alfred Suckling, who edited his works in 1836, corrected this
                    error, ascertaining that he was born at Whitton in Middlesex and baptized on
                    10th February 1609. He was sent to Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1623, at what
                    was then the usual age, and thereafter travelled on the Continent, as was also
                    the custom for youths of his birth. Returning to London, he did not long remain
                    inactive at court, but sought experience as a soldier, volunteering into the
                    force raised by the marquis of Hamilton for the support of Gustavus Adolphus in
                    the Palatinate. He reached Germany in July 1631 and was back at Whitehall in May
                    1632; but during this time he saw a good deal of hard service, being present at
                    the battle of Leipsic and the sieges of Crossen, Guben, Glogau, and Magdeburg.
                    Reappearing at court, he at once became a prominent figure. “He had the peculiar
                    happiness of making everything that he did become him.” He was ready of wit,
                    handsome of person, wealthy and generous, a leader in all pastimes, the best
                    bowler and the best card-player at court. His happy skill in verse was only one
                    of the distinctions of a man who excelled in everything; but, as it happened,
                    both the king and the queen had literary tastes, and he aimed at distinction in
                    poetry with the ardent thoroughness which seems to have been part of his
                    character. He became eminent at court just at the time when masques, after being
                    the rage for a few years, had reached the height of their splendour and were
                    beginning to pall; and it occurred to him to apply to the ordinary drama the
                    improved scenery which the taste for masques had developed. We can trace in his
                    plays both the taste for spectacular effect and the admiration for the wit of
                    Shakespeare which he shared with his royal master. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aglaura</hi> was the first of them, and is said to have been the first play
                    produced with elaborate stage scenery. It was produced first at Christmas in
                    1637 with a tragic ending, then reproduced at the following Easter with
                    ingenious changes in the fifth act which made it end happily. With all its
                    clever play on words and images, and its natural felicity of diction, it is not
                    an interesting drama to read; the characters have no body or vitality. But it is
                    full of incident, as if the dramatist were revelling in the newly discovered
                    power of shifting the scenes, and making the most of his advantage in having the
                    co-operation of Inigo Jones. His comedy the <hi rend="italic">Goblins</hi> is
                    much happier, and there the frequent changes of scene are used with great skill
                    to maintain the liveliness of the action. Suckling produced another tragedy in
                    1639, <hi rend="italic">Brennoralt;</hi> it has more body than its predecessor,
                    but shows no mastery of passion or tragic character. He began still another
                    tragedy, the <hi rend="italic">Sad One,</hi> but was abruptly stopped in his
                    literary career by the beginning of a tragedy in real life, the quarrel between
                    Charles and his subjects. Suckling took a prominent part for a time on the
                    Royalist side. When war was levied on the Scottish Covenanters in 1639 Suckling
                    raised a troop of a hundred horse at his own expense and accompanied them on the
                    bloodless expedition to the Border. He was elected member for Bramber to the
                    Long Parliament which met in November 1640; but in May of the following year he
                    got into trouble in connexion with a plot for the escape of Strafford from the
                    Tower and a project for calling in French aid, was charged with high treason,
                    and fled beyond sea. The circumstances of his short life in exile are obscure.
                    He continued to attract attention, and many pamphlets about him were circulated,
                    one in particular describing how he eloped with a lady to Spain and fell into
                    the clutches of the Inquisition. The tradition is that he committed suicide in
                    Paris some time before the end of 1642. Suckling’s reputation as a poet rests
                    not upon his plays but upon his minor pieces. They have wit and fancy and at
                    times exquisite felicity of diction. The happiest as a whole is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ballad upon a Wedding.</hi> “Prithee, why so pale, fond lover ?”
                    is an occasional song in <hi rend="italic">Aglaura.</hi></p>
                <p>A collection of Suckling’s poems was first published in 1646 with the title <hi
                    rend="italic">Fragmenta Aurea.</hi> The so-called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Selections</hi> published by Mr Alfred Suckling in 1836 is really a full
                    edition of his poems, letters, and plays, which was re-edited, with slight
                    additions, by Mr W. C. Hazlitt in 1874.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
