<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0566-0543-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STETTIN (9th edition, volume 22, page 543)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136941">Suburbs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1011191">Mass</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n566/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STETTIN</label>, the chief town of Pomerania, and the leading
                    seaport in Prussia, is situated on the Oder, 17 miles to the south of the
                    Stettiner Haff and 30 miles from the Baltic Sea. The main part of the town
                    occupies a hilly site on the left bank of the river, and is connected by four
                    bridges (including a mass ive railway swing-bridge)</p>
                <p>with the suburbs of La-</p>
                <p>stadie (“lading place,”</p>
                <p>from <hi rend="italic">lastadium, “</hi> bur den,”) and Silberwiese, on an island
                    formed by the Parnitz and Dunzig, which here diverge from the Oder to
                    Dammsche-</p>
                <p>See. Until 1874 Stettin was closely girdled by very extensive and strong
                    fortifications, which pre vented the expansion of the town proper, but the
                    steady growth of its commerce and manufactures encouraged the foundation of
                    numerous industrial suburbs beyond the line of defence. Some of these are
                    themselves “towns,” as Grabow, with 13,672 inhabitants in 1880, and Bredow with
                    11,255 inhabitants; but all combine with Stettin to form one industrial and
                    commercial centre. Since the removal of the fortifications their site has begun
                    to be built upon. Apart from its commerce, Stettin is a comparatively
                    uninteresting city. The church of Sts Peter and Paul, originally founded in 1124
                    and restored in 1816— 17, was the earliest Christian church in Pomerania. St
                    James’s church, dating from the 13th and the two following centuries, is
                    remarkable, like several other Pomeranian churches, for its size. The old
                    palace, now occupied by Government offices, is a large unattractive edifice,
                    scarcely justifying the boast of an old writer that it did not yield in
                    magnificence even to the palaces of Italy. Among the more modern structures are
                    the theatre and the new town-house, superseding an earlier one of 1245. Statues
                    of Frederick the Great and of Frederick William III. adorn one of the five open
                    squares of the old town. As a prosperous commercial town Stettin has numerous
                    educational, benevolent, and scientific institutions.</p>
                <p>The manufactures are very important; many of the largest factories are in the
                    neighbouring villages, beyond Stettin proper. The shipbuilding yards (among
                    which<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n567/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0567-0544"/> that of the Vulcan Company deserves mention) have
                    comparatively recently attained some reputation for their ironclads and
                    war-vessels. Machinery, cement, chemicals, and soap are produced in large
                    quantities, and there are also large sugar-refineries, besides a vast miscellany
                    of other smaller industrial establishments. The trade of Stettin is very
                    flourishing. More than any other harbour it may be regarded as the port of
                    Berlin, from which it is 93 miles north-east by railway; and a larger number of
                    vessels enter and clear at Stettin than at any other German port except Hamburg
                    and Bremerhaven. <hi rend="smallcaps">Swinemünde</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >{q.v.)</hi> serves as its fore-port. The forest and river scenery of the
                    neighbourhood of Stettin is picturesque, but the low level and swampy nature of
                    the soil render the climate bleak and unhealthy. In 1885 the population was
                    99,475; in 1880 it was 91,756, of whom 85,727 were Protestants, 3112 Roman
                    Catholics, and 2388 Jews.</p>
                <p>In 1885 3809 ocean vessels (2207 steamers) and 1965 coasting and river craft,
                    besides 10,039 Oder barges, entered the port. In 1885 Stettin possessed (besides
                    a large number of river craft) a fleet of 127 sea-going ships, with a burden of
                    47,066 tons, of which 26,754 tons were distributed in 59 steamers. The chief
                    exports are grain, spirits, and wood; the chief imports petroleum, train-oil,
                    wine, and herrings. The annual value of the former is about £7,500,000 and of
                    the latter about £6,000,000.</p>
                <p>Stettin is said to have existed as a Wendish fishing-village as early as 830 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> and it appears as Stedyn in the time of the Saxon
                    emperors. From the 12th century it was the seat of the dukes of Pomerania, who
                    became extinct in 1637. Passing then to Sweden, it remained united with that
                    kingdom for eighty-three years, with one brief interval, but in 1720 it was
                    ceded to Prussia. Gustavus Adolphus undertook to improve its fortifications in
                    1630, but Frederick the Great was the first to convert it into a strong modern
                    fortress. From 1806 till 1813 it was held by the French to whom it was
                    surrendered without a blow. Known even in the12th century as the leading
                    trading-town on the Oder, Stettin entered the Hanseatic League in 1360. The
                    development of its trade in modern times dates chiefly from the deepening and
                    protection of the Swine in the former half of last century. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Oder.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
