<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0453-0430-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPOONBILL (9th edition, volume 22, page 430)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:995621">Leggings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995328">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130373">Spoons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955625">Herons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966490">Ibises</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1184692">Zoologists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd0k">Leg</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83v1s">Spoons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3d540">Eggs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz97">Herons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc1c">Zoologists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bv79w67">Bustards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s525">Storks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n453/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPOONBILL</label>. The bird now so called was formerly known
                    in England as the Shovelard or Shovelar, while that which used to bear the name
                    of Spoonbill, often amplified into Spoon-billed Duck, is the <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Shoveler</hi> (see vol. xxi. p. 842) of modern days—the
                    exchange of names having been effected, as already stated <hi rend="italic"
                    >(loc. cit.)</hi> about 200 years ago, when the subject of the present
                    notice—the <hi rend="italic">Platalea leucorodia</hi> of Linnaeus as well as of
                    recent writers—was doubtless far better known than now, since it evidently was,
                    from ancient documents, the constant concomitant of Herons, and with them the
                    law attempted to protect it.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Nothing shows better the futility of the
                    old statutes for the protection of birds than the fact that in 1534 the taking
                    of the eggs of Herons, Spoonbills (Shovelars), Cranes, Bitterns, and Bustards
                    was visited by a heavy penalty, while there was none for destroying the parent
                    birds in the breeding-season. All of the species just named, except the Heron,
                    have passed away, while there is strong reason to think that some at least might
                    have survived had the principle of the Levitical law (Deut. xxii. 6) been
                    followed.</hi></p></note> Mr Harting (<hi rend="italic">Zoologist,</hi> 1886,
                    pp. 81 <hi rend="italic">et seqj)</hi> has cited a case from the “Year-Book” of
                    14 Hen. VIII. (1523), wherein the then bishop of London (Cuthbert Tunstall)
                    maintained an action of trespass against the tenant of a close at Fulham for
                    taking Herons and “Shovelars” that made their nests on the trees therein
                    growing, and has also printed <hi rend="italic">{Zoologist,</hi> 1877, pp. 425
                    <hi rend="italic">et seq.)</hi> an old document showing that “Shovelars” bred in
                    certain woods in west Sussex in 1570. Nearly one hundred years later (<hi
                    rend="italic">circa</hi> 1662) Sir Thomas Browne, in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Account of Birds found in Norfolk (Works,</hi> ed. Wilkin, iv. pp. 315, 316),
                    stated of the <hi rend="italic">“Platea</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Shouelard</hi>” that it formerly “built in the Hernerie at Claxton and Reedham,
                    now at Trimley in Suffolk.” This last is the latest known proof of the breeding
                    of the species in England; but more recent evidence to that effect may be hoped
                    for from other sources. That the Spoonbill was in the fullest sense of the word
                    a “native” of England is thus incontestably shown; but for many years past it
                    has only been a more or less regular visitant, though not seldom in considerable
                    numbers, which would doubtless, if allowed, once more make their home there; but
                    its conspicuous appearance renders it an easy mark for the greedy gunner and the
                    contemptible collector. What may have been the case formerly is not known,
                    except that, according to Belon, it nested in his time (1555) in the borders of
                    Britanny and Poitou; but as regards north-western Europe it seems of late years
                    to have bred only in Holland, and there it has been deprived by drainage of its
                    favourite resorts, one after the other, so that it must shortly become merely a
                    stranger, except in Spain or the basin of the Danube and other parts of
                    south-eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>The Spoonbill ranges over the greater part of middle and southern Asia,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ornithologists have been in doubt as to the recognition of two species from
                    Japan described by Temminck and Schlegel under the names of</hi> P. major <hi
                    rend="italic">and</hi> P. minor. <hi rend="italic">Lately it has been suggested
                    that the former is only the young of</hi> P. leucorodia, <hi rend="italic">and
                    the latter the young of the Australian</hi> P. regia.</p></note> and breeds
                    abundantly in India, as well as on some of the islands in the Red Sea, and seems
                    to be resident throughout Northern Africa. In Southern Africa its place is taken
                    by an allied species with red legs, <hi rend="italic">Ρ. cristata</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">tenuiroslris,</hi> which also goes to Madagascar. Australia has
                    two other species, <hi rend="italic">P. regio,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >melanorhynchus,</hi> with black bill and feet, and <hi rend="italic">P.
                    flaνipes,</hi> in which those parts are yellow. The very beautiful and wholly
                    different <hi rend="italic">P. ajaja</hi> is the Roseate Spoonbill of America,
                    and is the only one found on that continent, the tropical or juxta-tropical
                    parts of which it inhabits. The rich pink, deepening in some parts into crimson,
                    of nearly all its plumage, together with the yellowish green of its bare head
                    and its lake-coloured legs, sufficiently marks this bird; but all the other
                    species are almost wholly clothed in pure white, though the English has, when
                    adult, a fine buff pectoral band, and the spoon-shaped expanse of its bill is
                    yellow, contrasting with the black of the compressed and basal portion. Its legs
                    are also black. In the breeding season, a pendent tuft of white plumes further
                    ornaments the head of both sexes, but is longest in the male. The young of the
                    year have the primary quills darkcoloured.</p>
                <p>The Spoonbills form a natural group, <hi rend="italic">Plataleidse,</hi> allied,
                    as before stated <hi rend="smallcaps">(Ibis,</hi> vol. xii. p. 606), to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ibididae,</hi> and somewhat more distantly to the Storks (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Stork),</hi> —all belonging to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pelargomorphse</hi> of Prof. Huxley. They breed in societies, not only of their
                    own kind, but in company with Herons, either on trees or in reed-beds, making
                    large nests in which are commonly laid four eggs, —white, speckled, streaked, or
                    blotched, but never very closely, with light red. Such breeding-stations have
                    been several times described, and among the more recent accounts of one of them
                    are those of Messrs Sclater and W. A. Forbes (<hi rend="italic">Ibis,</hi> 1877,
                    p. 412), and Mr Seebohm <hi rend="italic">{Zoologist,</hi> 1880, p. 457), while
                    a view of another has been attempted by Schlegel <hi rend="italic">{Vog.
                    Nederland,</hi> taf. xvii.). The latest systematic revision of the group is by
                    Dr Reichenow (<hi rend="italic">Journ, fur Ornithologie,</hi> 1877, pp.
                    156-159), but his views have not been wholly accepted in the present article.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n454/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0454-0431"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
