<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0462-0439-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STAEL, Madame de (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    439)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205503">Finland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b03x">Constants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bc9x">Exiles</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f1p">Jacobins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:958978">Holsteiners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918139">Exiles</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1138503">Summer</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n462/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STAEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Madame de</hi></label> (by her
                    proper name and title <hi rend="smallcaps">Anne Louise Germaine Necker, Baroness
                    of Stael-Holstein),</hi> was born at Paris on April 22, 1766, and died there on
                    July 14, 1817. Her father was the famous financier Necker, her mother Suzanne
                    Curchod, who is almost equally famous as the early love of Gibbon, as the wife
                    of Necker, as the mistress of one of the most popular salons of Paris, and as
                    the mother of Madame de Stael. Between mother and daughter there was, however,
                    little sympathy. Madame Necker, despite her talents, her beauty, and her
                    fondness for <hi rend="italic">philosophe</hi> society, was strictly decorous,
                    somewhat reserved, and disposed to carry out in her daughter’s case the rigorous
                    discipline of her own childhood. The future Madame de Stael was from her
                    earliest years a romp, a coquette, and passionately desirous of prominence and
                    attention. There seems moreover to have been a sort of rivalry between mother
                    and daughter for the chief place in Necker’s affections, and it is not probable
                    that the daughter’s love for her mother was increased by the consciousness of
                    her own inferiority in personal charms. Madame Necker, if her portraits as well
                    as verbal descriptions may be trusted, was of a most refined though somewhat
                    lackadaisical style of beauty, while her daughter was a plain child and a
                    plainer woman, whose sole attractions were large and striking eyes and a buxom
                    figure. She was, however, a child of unusual intellectual power, and she began
                    very early to write though not to publish. She is said to have written her
                    father a letter on his famous <hi rend="italic">Compte-Rendu</hi> and other
                    matters when she was not fifteen, and to have injured her health by excessive
                    study and intellectual excitement. But in reading all the accounts of Madame de
                    Stael's life which come from herself or her intimate friends it must be
                    carefully remembered that she was the most distinguished and characteristic
                    product of the period of <hi rend="italic">sensibilité—</hi> the singular
                    fashion of ultra-sentiment which required that both men and women, but
                    especially women, should be always palpitating with excitement, steeped in
                    melancholy, or dissolved in tears. Still, there is no doubt that her father’s
                    dismissal from the ministry, which followed the presentation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Compte,</hi> and the consequent removal of the family from the
                    busy life of ' Paris, were beneficial to her. During part of the next few years
                    they resided at Coppet, her father’s estate on the Lake of Geneva, which she
                    herself made famous. But other parts were spent in travelling about, chiefly in
                    the south of France. They returned to Paris, or at least to its neighbourhood,
                    in 1785, and Mademoiselle Necker resumed literary work of a miscellaneous kind,
                    including two plays, <hi rend="italic">Sophie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Jane
                    Grey,</hi> which were printed sooner or later. It became, however, a question of
                    marrying her. Her want of beauty was compensated by her fortune, for she was the
                    only child of one of the richest bankers in Europe. But her parents are said to
                    have objected to her marrying a Roman Catholic, which, in France, considerably
                    limited her choice. There is a legend that William Pitt the younger thought of
                    her; the somewhat notorious lover of Mademoiselle de Lespinasse, Guibert, a
                    cold-hearted coxcomb of some talent, certainly paid her addresses. But she
                    finally married Eric Magnus, Baron of Stael-Holstein, who was first an attaché
                    of the Swedish legation, and then minister. For a great heiress and a very
                    ambitious girl the marriage scarcely seemed brilliant, for Stael had no fortune
                    and no very great personal distinction. A singular series of negotiations,
                    however, secured from the king of Sweden a promise of the ambassadorship for
                    twelve years and a pension in case of<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n463/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0463-0440"/> its withdrawal, and the marriage took place on
                    January 14, 1786. The husband was thirty-seven, the wife twenty. Madame de Stael
                    was accused of extravagance, and latterly an amicable separation of goods had to
                    be effected between the pair. But this was a mere legal formality, and on the
                    whole the marriage seems to have met the views of both parties, neither of whom
                    had any affection for the other. They had three children; there was no scandal
                    between them; the baron obtained money and the lady obtained, as a guaranteed
                    ambassadress of a foreign power of consideration, a much higher position at
                    court and in society than she could have secured by marrying almost any
                    Frenchman, without the inconveniences which might have been expected had she
                    married a Frenchman superior to herself in rank. The particular fancy of Marie
                    Antoinette for Sweden, caused by the fantastic devotion of Count Fersen and the
                    king himself to her, secured moreover a reception which might have been
                    otherwise difficult to gain. Madame de Stael was not a <hi rend="italic">persona
                    grata</hi> at court, but she seems to have played the part of ambassadress, as
                    she played most parts, in a rather noisy and exaggerated manner, but not ill.
                    Then in 1788 she appeared as an author under her own name <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Sophie</hi> had been already published, but anonymously) with some <hi
                    rend="italic">Lettres sur J. J. Rousseau,</hi> a fervid panegyric showing a good
                    deal of talent but no power of criticism. She was at this time, and indeed
                    generally, enthusiastic for a mixture of Rousseauism and constitutionalism in
                    politics, and her father’s restoration to power excited extravagant hopes in
                    her, though Necker himself knew better. She exulted more than ever in the
                    meeting of the states-general, and most of all when her father, after being
                    driven to Brussels by a state intrigue, was once more recalled and triumphally
                    escorted into Paris. Every one knows what followed. Her first child, a boy, was
                    born the week before Necker finally left France in unpopularity and disgrace;
                    and the increasing disturbances of the Revolution made her privileges as
                    ambassadress no mere matters of ornamental distinction gratifying to vanity, but
                    very important safeguards. She visited Coppet once or twice, but for the most
                    part in the early days of the revolutionary period she was in Paris taking an
                    interest and, as she thought, a part in the councils and efforts of the
                    Moderates. At last, the day before the September massacres, she fled, befriended
                    by Manuel and Tallien. Her own account of her escape is, as usual, so florid
                    that it provokes the question whether she was really in any danger. Directly it
                    does not seem that she was; but she had generously strained the privileges of
                    the embassy to protect some threatened friends, and this was a serious
                    matter.</p>
                <p>She betook herself to Coppet, and there gathered round her a considerable number
                    of friends and fellow-refugees, the beginning of the quasi-court which at
                    intervals during the next five-and-twenty years made the place so famous. In
                    1793, however, she made a visit of some length to England, and established
                    herself at Mickleham in Surrey as the centre of the Moderate Liberal emigrants,
                    —Talleyrand, Narbonne, Jaucourt, Guibert, and others. There was not a little
                    scandal about her relations with Narbonne; and it is very much to be doubted
                    whether this can safely be set down, as her panegyrists usually set it, to the
                    mere spite of the first or royalist emigrants, to whom she and her party were
                    almost more obnoxious than the Jacobins. It is certain that this Mickleham
                    sojourn (the details of which are known from, among other sources, the letters
                    of Fanny Burney) has never been altogether satisfactorily accounted for. In the
                    summer she returned to Coppet and wrote a pamphlet on the queen’s execution. The
                    next year her mother died, and the fall of Robespierre opened the way back to
                    Paris. M. de Stael (whose mis sion had been in abeyance and himself in Holland
                    for three years) was accredited to the French republic by the regent of Sweden;
                    his wife reopened her salon and for a time was conspicuous in the motley and
                    eccentric society of the Directory. She also published several small works, the
                    chief being an essay <hi rend="italic">De l’Influence des Passions</hi> (1796),
                    and another <hi rend="italic">De la Littérature Considérée dans ses Rapports
                    avec les Institutions Sociales</hi> (1800). It was during these years that
                    Madame de Stael was of chief political importance. Narbonne’s place had been
                    supplied by Benjamin Constant, who had a very great influence over her, as in
                    return she had over him. During the Directory she had some real and more
                    imaginary power as a politician, and both personal and political reasons threw
                    her into opposition to Bonaparte. Her own preference for a moderate republic or
                    a constitutional monarchy was quite sincere, and, even if it had not been so,
                    her own character and Napoleon’s were too much alike in some points to admit of
                    their getting on together. For some years, however, she was able to alternate
                    between Coppet and Paris without difficulty, though not without knowing that the
                    First Consul disliked her. In 1797 she, as above mentioned, separated formally
                    from her husband. In 1799 he was recalled by the king of Sweden, and in 1802 he
                    died duly attended by her. Besides the eldest son Auguste Louis, they had two
                    other children,—a son Albert, and a daughter Albertine, who afterwards became
                    the Duchesse de Broglie.</p>
                <p>The exact date of the beginning of what Madame de Stael's admirers call her duel
                    with Napoleon is not easy to determine. Judging from the title of her book <hi
                    rend="italic">Dix Années d'Exil,</hi> it should be put at 1804; judging from the
                    time at which it became pretty clear that the first man in France and she who
                    wished to be the first woman in France were not likely to get on together, it
                    might be put several years earlier. The whole question of this duel, however
                    (marked as it was by Napoleon’s unscrupulous exercises of power, which reached a
                    climax in the suppression of the <hi rend="italic">De l'Allemagne</hi> after it
                    had been carefully submitted to his censorship), requires consideration from the
                    point of view of common sense. It displeased Napoleon no doubt that Madame de
                    Stael should show herself recalcitrant to his influence. But it probably pleased
                    Madame de Stael to quite an equal degree that Napoleon should apparently put
                    forth his power to crush her and fail. Both personages had the curious touch of
                    <hi rend="italic">charlatanerie</hi> so common in the late 18th century, and
                    “made believe” in a fashion bewildering and a little incredible to posterity. If
                    Madame de Stael had really desired to take up her parable against Napoleon
                    seriously, she need only have established herself in England at the peace of
                    Amiens and have lived quietly there. She did nothing of the kind. She lingered
                    on at Coppet, constantly hankering after Paris, and acknowledging the hankering
                    quite honestly. In 1802 she published the first of her really noteworthy books,
                    the novel of <hi rend="italic">Delphine,</hi> in which the “femme incomprise”
                    was in a manner introduced to French literature, and in which she herself and
                    not a few of her intimates appeared in transparent disguise. In the autumn of
                    1803 she returned to Paris. Whether, if she had not displayed such extraordinary
                    anxiety not to be exiled, Napoleon would have exiled her remains a question;
                    but, as she began at once appealing to all sorts of persons to protect her, he
                    seems to have thought it better that she should not be protected. She was
                    directed not to reside within forty leagues of Paris, and after considerable
                    delay she determined to go to Germany. She journeyed by Metz and Frankfort to
                    Weimar, and arrived there in December. There she stayed during the winter, and
                    then went to Berlin, where she<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n464/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0464-0441"/> made the acquaintance of August Wilhelm Schlegel,
                    who afterwards became one of her intimates at Coppet. Thence she travelled to
                    Vienna, where, in April, the news of her father’s dangerous illness and shortly
                    of his death (April 8) reached her. She returned to Coppet, and found herself
                    its wealthy and independent mistress, but her sorrow for her father was deep and
                    certainly sincere. She spent the summer at the chateau with a brilliant company;
                    in the autumn she journeyed to Italy accompanied by Schlegel and Sismondi, and
                    there gathered the materials of her most famous work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corinne.</hi> She returned in the summer of 1805, and spent nearly a year in
                    writing <hi rend="italic">Corinne</hi>; in 1806 she broke the decree of exile
                    and lived for a time undisturbed near Paris. In 1807 <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corinne,</hi> the first aesthetic romance not written in German, appeared. It
                    is in fact, what it was described as being at the time of its appearance, “a
                    picturesque tour couched in the form of a novel.” The publication was taken as a
                    reminder of her existence, and the police of the empire sent her back to Coppet.
                    She stayed there as usual for the summer, and then set out once more for
                    Germany, visiting Mainz, Frankfort, Berlin, and Vienna. She was again at Coppet
                    in the summer of 1808, and set to work at her book <hi rend="italic">De
                    l'Allemagne.</hi> It took her nearly the whole of the next two years, during
                    which she did not travel much or far from her own house. She had bought property
                    in America and thought of moving thither, but chance or fatality made her
                    determine to publish <hi rend="italic">De l'Allemagne</hi> in Paris. The
                    submission to censorship which this entailed was sufficiently inconsistent, and
                    she wrote to the emperor one of the unfortunate letters, at once undignified and
                    provoking, of which she had the secret. A man less tyrannical or less
                    mean-spirited than Napoleon would of course have let her alone, but Napoleon was
                    Napoleon, and she perfectly well knew him. The reply to her letter was the
                    condemnation of the whole edition of her book (ten thousand copies) as “not
                    French,” and her own exile, not as before to a certain distance from Paris, but
                    from France altogether. The act was unquestionably one of odious tyranny, but it
                    is impossible not to ask why she had put herself within reach of it when her
                    fortune enabled her to reside anywhere and to publish what she pleased. She
                    retired once more to Coppet, where she was not at first interfered with, and she
                    found consolation in a young officer of Swiss origin named Rocca, twenty-three
                    years her junior, whom she married privately in 1811. The intimacy of their
                    relations could escape no one at Coppet, but the fact of the marriage was not
                    certainly known till after her death.</p>
                <p>The operations of the imperial police in regard to Madame de Stael are rather
                    obscure. She was at first left undisturbed, but by degrees the chateau itself
                    became taboo, and her visitors found themselves punished heavily. Mathieu de
                    Montmorency and Madame Récamier were exiled for the crime of seeing her; and she
                    at last began to think of doing what she ought to have done years before and
                    withdrawing herself entirely from Napoleon’s sphere. In the complete subjection
                    of the Continent which preceded the Russian War this was not so easy as it would
                    have been earlier, and she remained at home during the winter of 1811, writing
                    and planning. On May 23 she left Coppet almost secretly, and journeyed by Bern,
                    Innsbruck, and Salzburg to Vienna. There she obtained an Austrian passport to
                    the frontier, and after some fears and trouble, receiving a Russian passport in
                    Galicia, she at last escaped from the dungeon of Napoleonic Europe, swearing
                    never to return thither. It seemed likely that the proclamation of war between
                    France and Russia, on June 22, would help her to keep the vow.</p>
                <p>She journeyed slowly though Russia and Finland to</p>
                <p>Sweden, making some stay at St Petersburg, spent the winter in Stockholm, and
                    then set out for England. Here she received a brilliant reception and was much
                    lionized during the season of 1813. She published <hi rend="italic">De
                    l’Allemagne</hi> (a book much more really remarkable than <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corinne)</hi> in the autumn, was saddened by the death of her second son
                    Albert, who had entered the Swedish army and fell in a duel brought on by
                    gambling, undertook her <hi rend="italic">Considérations sur la Devolution
                    Française,</hi> and when Louis XVIII. had been restored returned to Paris. Both
                    in the summer and in the winter of 1814 she visited Coppet, and was meanwhile a
                    prominent figure in Parisian society. She was in Paris when the news of
                    Napoleon’s landing arrived and at once fled to Coppet, but a singular story,
                    much discussed, is current of her having approved Napoleon’s return. There is no
                    direct evidence of it, but the conduct of her close ally Constant may be quoted
                    in its support, and it is certain that she had no affection for the Bourbons. In
                    October, after Waterloo, she set out for Italy, not only for the advantage of
                    her own health but for that of her second husband, Rocca, who was dying of
                    consumption. Her daughter married Duke Victor de Broglie on February 20, 1816,
                    at Pisa, and became the wife and mother of French statesmen of distinction. The
                    whole family returned to Coppet in June, and Byron now frequently visited Madame
                    de Stael there. He had quizzed her a good deal in London, but liked her better
                    in her own house, though even there he noticed her constant straining to be
                    something different from herself. Despite her increasing ill-health she returned
                    to Paris for the winter of 1816-17, and her salon was much frequented. But in
                    March she is spoken of as “dying,” and she had already become confined to her
                    room, if not to her bed. She died on the 14th of July, and Rocca survived her
                    little more than six months. Nor was her eldest son longlived. After editing a
                    collected edition of his mother’s works he died at the age of thirty-seven in
                    1827.</p>
                <p>Madame de Stael occupies a singular position in French literature. The men of her
                    own time exalted her to the skies, and the most extravagant estimates of her (as
                    “the greatest woman in literary history,” as the “foundress of the romantic
                    movement,” as representing "ideas,” while her contemporary Chateaubriand only
                    represented words, colours, and images, and so forth) are to be found in those
                    histories of literature which faithfully repeat secondhand and traditional
                    opinions. On the other hand, it is acknowledged that she is now very little
                    read. Sainte-Beuve, who professes a “culte” for her, and who has treated her at
                    great length and with much indulgence; M. Scherer, a compatriot and
                    co-religionist, who is strongly prejudiced in her favour; Doudan, a kind of
                    literary retainer of her connexions,—all allow this, and any one who speaks with
                    an intimate knowledge of current French literature must agree that since they
                    spoke neglect of her has increased. No writer of such eminence is so rarely
                    quoted; none is so entirely destitute of that tribute of new and splendid
                    editions which France pays to her favourite classics more lavishly than any
                    other nation; none is so seldom the subject of a literary <hi rend="italic"
                    >causerie.</hi> The abundant documents in the hands of her descendants, the
                    families of Broglie and Haussonville, have indeed furnished material for papers
                    recently, but these are almost wholly on the social aspect of Madame de Stael,
                    not on her literary merit. Nor when the life and works come to be examined
                    independently is the neglect seen to be without excuse. An ugly coquette, an old
                    woman who made a ridiculous marriage, a blue-stocking who spent much of her time
                    in pestering men of genius, and drawing from them sarcastic comment behind her
                    back,—these things are not attractive. Her books are seen to be in large part
                    merely clever reflexions of other people’s views, or views current at the time,
                    and the famous “ideas” turn out to be chiefly the ideas of the books or the men
                    with whom she was from time to time in contact. The sentimentality of her
                    sentiment and the florid magniloquence of her style equally disgust the reader;
                    and, when it is suggested to him that the revolution of taste and manners hurts
                    novels more than anything else, he is tempted to reply that it has not hurt <hi
                    rend="italic">Don Quixote,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gil Blas,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Robinson Crusoe,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Manon Lescaut, or The Antiquary,</hi> and that if it has hurt <hi
                    rend="italic">Corinne</hi> it is simply because these are great books and <hi
                    rend="italic">Corinne</hi> is not a great book. There is truth in this, but to
                    state it alone would be in the highest degree unfair. Madame de Stael’s faults
                    are great; her style is of an age not for<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n465/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0465-0442"/> all time; her ideas are mostly second-hand and
                    frequently superficial. But nothing save a very great talent could have shown
                    itself so receptive. Take away her assiduous frequentation of society, from the
                    later <hi rend="italic">philosophe</hi> coteries to the age of Byron,—take away
                    the influence of Constant and Schlegel and her other literary friends,—and
                    probably little of her will remain. But to have caught from all sides in this
                    manner the floating notions of society and of individuals, to reflect them with
                    such vigour and clearness, to combine them with such not inconsiderable skill
                    into connected books, is not anybody’s task. Her two best books, <hi
                    rend="italic">Corinne</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De l’Allemagne,</hi> are in all
                    probability almost wholly unoriginal, a little sentiment in the first and a
                    little constitutionalism in the second being all that she can claim. But <hi
                    rend="italic">Corinne</hi> is still a very remarkable exposition of a certain
                    kind of aestheticism, and <hi rend="italic">De l'Allemagne</hi> is still perhaps
                    the most remarkable account of one country by a native and inhabitant of another
                    which exists in literature. This praise, and it is very high praise, can be
                    given to Madame de Stael. But the merits which it allows are not merits of the
                    class which secure readers for ever. Neither in style nor in thought was she of
                    the first class or perhaps of the second; and besides thought and style nothing
                    will save books.</p>
                <p>Baron Auguste de Stael edited, as has been said, the complete works of his mother
                    in seventeen volumes (Paris, 1820-1), and the edition was afterwards republished
                    in a compacter form, and, supplemented by some <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres
                    Inédites,</hi> is still obtainable in 3 vols, large 8vo (Didot). The <hi
                    rend="italic">Considérations</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Dix Années
                    d'Exil</hi> had been published after Madame de Stael’s death. There is no recent
                    reissue of the whole, and the minor works have not been reprinted, but <hi
                    rend="italic">Corinne, Delphine,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De l’Allemagne</hi>
                    are easily accessible in cheap and separate forms. Of recent works on Madame de
                    Stael, or rather on Coppet and its society, those of MM. Caro and Othenin
                    d’Haussonville may be mentioned. In English there is an elaborate biography by
                    A. Stevens (London, 1880), full of information, but unluckily not at all
                    critical. (G. SA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
