<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0310-0289-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SOUTHEY, Robert (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    289)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n310/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SOUTHEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>
                    (1774-1843), was born in Bristol on the 12th of August 1774. His father, a
                    native of Somerset, was an unsuccessful draper. To his mother,<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n311/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0311-0290"/> Margaret Hill, Southey owed his buoyant spirits,
                    his practical sense, and his earliest friends. The first of these, Miss Tyler,
                    his mother’s half-sister, took possession of him when he was three; under her
                    care he saw and heard a great deal of theatres and of acting. His solitary life
                    in an old maid’s household threw him upon his own resources and developed a
                    taste for reading. He was sent to several private schools, and had good fortune
                    at none of them; in 1788 he went to Westminster, where he was scarcely more
                    fortunate. After a brief sojourn he was expelled in 1792, because an essay of
                    his on flogging, in a school magazine called <hi rend="italic">The
                    Flagellant,</hi> was resented by Dr Vincent, the head-master. At Westminster he
                    gained the friendship of two boys who were faithful to him and helpful
                    throughout his life; these were Charles Winn and Grosvenor Bedford. About this
                    time his father died; his aunt, however, determined that he should go to Oxford.
                    He was refused at Christ Church on account of the essay in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Flagellant</hi>; but Balliol gave him a home. At Oxford he led his own life,
                    lived in his own thoughts, and got little or nothing from the university. In
                    1794 Coleridge dashed at Southey, took him by storm, and filled his head with
                    plans for an ideal colony in the wilds. The new society, whose members were to
                    have all things in common, was to be called “The Pantisocracy.” Their life was
                    to combine manual labour and domestic bliss; to attain the latter, Southey set
                    his affections on a Miss Edith Fricker, whose sister married Coleridge. All this
                    was intolerable to Miss Tyler, and Southey was banished. He and Coleridge then
                    tried, by lecturing and journalism, to raise money for their American schemes;
                    but luckily Southey’s uncle, who had educated him,—Mr Hill, the English chaplain
                    at Lisbon,—advised him to travel. On the 14th of November 1795, before he
                    started, he was secretly married to Edith Fricker. On his return from Lisbon the
                    marriage was acknowledged, and Southey wandered from one house to another in the
                    south of England. He tried, or was urged to try, the three professions which are
                    by courtesy styled “learned”; it might be more true to call them the technical,
                    the stereotyped professions. Southey was scared from all three,—from clericalism
                    by dogma, from medicine by the dissecting-room, from law by its crabbed dulness.
                    In literature alone he found his proper sphere; and in 1803 he settled down in
                    his lifelong home, Greta Hall, near Keswick. Henceforth his years were even and
                    uneventful. He wrote and read with mechanical, with appalling regularity; his
                    library grew to fourteen thousand volumes. He had children, and lost several;
                    and his house was a refuge for the wife and family of Coleridge. With Wordsworth
                    and Landor he formed close friendships. In 1813 he was made poet-laureate; and
                    some years before his death he was offered a baronetcy—which, however, he with
                    good reason declined. Two great sorrows embittered his life: in 1809 he lost his
                    eldest boy Herbert, and in 1834 his wife was taken to a madhouse, whence she
                    came back to die. In 1839 he married Caroline Bowles. That same year his memory
                    failed, his speech became uncertain, and his power of writing soon went;
                    softening of the brain had taken irremediable hold of the once tireless
                    intellect. To the last he would hover round his books and handle them lovingly.
                    He died on the 21st of March 1843; he is buried, near his first wife and her
                    children, in Crosthwaite churchyard.</p>
                <p>The amount of Southey’s work in literature is enormous. His collected verse, with
                    its explanatory notes, fills ten volumes; his prose occupies about forty. But
                    his greatest works were left uncompleted, and this, in some sense, is typical of
                    Southey’s whole achievement in the world of letters; there is always something
                    unsatisfying, disappointing, about him. He seldom realized or seldom found scope
                    for his true bent in literature. This is most true of his efforts in verse. In
                    his childhood Southey fell in with Tasso, Tasso led him to Ariosto, and Ariosto
                    to Spenser. These beautiful, these luxuriantly imaginative poets captivated the
                    boy; and Southey mistook his youthful enthusiasm for an abiding, a lifelong
                    inspiration. His inspiration was not genuinely imaginative; he had too large an
                    infusion of prosaic commonplace in his nature to be a true follower of Ariosto
                    and Spenser. Southey, quite early in life, resolved to write a series of epics
                    on the chief religions of the world. The subject was dangerous, and one epic is
                    a life’s work; it is not surprising that the too ambitious poet failed. His
                    failure is twofold: he was wanting in artistic power and in poetic sympathy.
                    With regard to the first, he says of himself, “It was long before I acquired
                    this power,”—the power of plan and construction,—“not fairly, indeed, till I was
                    about five or six and thirty.” The fact is, he never acquired it; he never could
                    construct a dramatic plot or mould it into artistic details. When his epics are
                    not wildly impossible they are incurably dull; at the best their interest is
                    extrinsic rather than intrinsic, pervaded by the glamour of historic romance
                    rather than the light of pure poetry. And a man is not fit to write epics on the
                    religions of the world when he can say of the prophet who has satisfied the
                    gravest races of mankind,—Mohammed was “far more remarkable for audacious
                    profligacy than for any intellectual endowments.” Southey’s age was bounded, and
                    had little sympathy for anything beyond itself and its own narrow interests; it
                    was violently Tory, narrowly Protestant, defiantly English. And in his verse
                    Southey truthfully reflects the feeling of his age. This led him to say dreadful
                    things about the Eastern religions in his prefaces to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kehαmα</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Τhalaba∙,</hi> it made <hi rend="italic">Joan
                    of Arc</hi> an incongruous blending of Rousseau, of Horace Walpole’s
                    romanticism, of the Surrey theatre, and of Lady Huntingdon; it gave Madoc, a
                    Celt of the 12th century, the mind of a cold middle-class Saxon evangelical of
                    the regency. In the shorter pieces Southey’s commonplace asserts itself, and if
                    that does not meet us we find his bondage to his generation. This bondage is
                    quite abject in <hi rend="italic">The Vision of Judgment·,</hi> Southey’s
                    heavenly personages are British Philistines from Old Sarum, magnified but not
                    transformed, engaged in endless placid adoration of an infinite George III. When
                    Southey sets himself to fondle the regent, he loses all sense of measure and
                    propriety. In the <hi rend="italic">Funeral Ode</hi> to the Princess he can
                    assert of her father—</p>
                <p>“Such the proud, the virtuous story,</p>
                <p>Such the great, the endless glory Of her father’s splendid reign! "</p>
                <p>This famous ode, “with the grace and beauty of which,” Sir Henry Taylor thinks,
                    “no facts could compete,” is, it must be said, in many of its couplets, too like
                    the average hymn. The twang of the hymn spoils two of Southey’s best pieces. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Holly Tree</hi> ends—</p>
                <p>“That in my age as cheerful I might be As the green winter of the holly
                    tree.”</p>
                <p>The last lines of <hi rend="italic">Stanzas Written in his Library,</hi> a poem
                    dear to the book-lover, are painfully like a rhyme on a tomb-stone :—</p>
                <p>“Yet leaving here a name, I trust,</p>
                <p>That will not perish in the dust.”</p>
                <p>Some of his subjects, <hi rend="italic">The Poet's Pilgrimage,</hi> for instance,
                    he would have treated delightfully in prose; others, like the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Botany Bay Eclogues, Songs to American Indians, The Pig, The Dancing Bear,</hi>
                    should never have been written. <hi rend="italic">The Retrospect,</hi> of which
                    this is a fair specimen,—</p>
                <p>“There where my little hands were wont to rear with pride the earliest salad of
                    the year,”—</p>
                <p>a living critic and biographer of Southey has compared to <hi rend="italic">The
                    Deserted, Village.</hi> Southey was not in the highest sense of the word a poet;
                    but if we turn from his verse to his prose we are in a different world; there
                    Southey is a master in his art, who works at ease with grace and skill.
                    “Southey’s prose is perfect,” said Byron; and, if we do not stretch the
                    “perfect,” or take it to mean the supreme perfection of the very greatest
                    masters of style, Byron was right. For good prose, plain, unassuming, natural,
                    he is not surpassed in English. In his charming story of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Three Bears</hi> a phrase is often used which exactly describes his style; when
                    the old lady finds what is neither too hot nor too cold, too large nor too
                    small, she says it is “just right.” Southey’s prose is “just right,”—it
                    expresses his meaning with simple and admirable precision. In his prose and in
                    his criticism we of a later generation could do worse than learn from Southey;
                    his sober writing is an excellent corrective for our prevailing faults. In prose
                    the real Southey emerges from his conventionality. His interest and his
                    curiosity are unbounded, as his <hi rend="italic">Common-Place Book</hi> will
                    prove; his stores of learning are at his readers’ service, as in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Doctor·,</hi> his patriotism is vigorous and healthy, as in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Life of Nelson</hi>; his criticism is sound, as in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Lives</hi> of Cowper and of Wesley. But the truest Southey is in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>: the loyal, gallant, tenderhearted, faithful
                    man that he was is revealed in them. Southey’s fame will not rest, as he
                    supposed, on his verse; all his faults are in that,—all his own weakness, and
                    all the false taste of his age. But his prose assures him a high place in
                    English literature, though not a place in the first rank even of prose
                    writers.<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n312/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0312-0291"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
