<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0422-0399-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPINOZA, Baruch (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    399)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915833">Ethics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nq7b">Ethics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20s31f">Rainbow</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n422/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPINOZA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Baruch</hi></label>
                    (1632-1677), or, as he afterwards signed himself, Benedict de Spinoza,
                    philosopher, was born at Amsterdam on 24th November 1632. His parents be-</p>
                <p>was customary at a very early period. Theophrastus (c. 314 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi>) states that vessels of lead and alabaster were best for the purpose,
                    on account of their density and coolness, and their power of resisting the
                    penetration of the ointment into their substance. Pliny also recommends
                    alabaster for ointment vases. For small quantities onyx vessels seem to have
                    been used (Horace, <hi rend="italic">Garni.</hi> iv., 12, 11. 10, 17).<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n423/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0423-0400"/> longed to the community of Jewish emigrants from
                    Portugal and Spain who, fleeing from Catholic persecution in the Peninsula, had
                    sought refuge in the nearly emancipated Netherlands. The name, variously written
                    De Spinoza, D’Espinoza, and Despinoza, probably points to the province of Leon
                    as the previous home of the family; there are no fewer than five townships so
                    called in the neighbourhood of Burgos. Of the philosopher’s parents nothing is
                    known. His father is said to have been a tradesman in fair circumstances, and
                    the house is still shown upon the Burgwal where his son Baruch was born; two
                    sisters, Rebekah and Miriam, formed the remainder of the family. Spinoza
                    received his first training under the senior rabbi, Saul Levi Morteira, whose
                    most promising pupil he soon became. Under Morteira he became familiar with the
                    Talmud and, what was probably more important for his own development, with the
                    philosophical writings of Ibn Ezra and Maimonides, Levi ben Gerson, Chasdai
                    Creskas, and other representatives of Jewish mediaeval thought, who aim at
                    combining the traditional theology with ideas got from Aristotle and his
                    Neoplatonic commentators. Latin, still the universal language of learning,
                    formed no part of Jewish education; and Spinoza, after learning the elements
                    from a German master, resorted for further instruction to a physician named
                    Franz van den Ende, who eked out an income by taking pupils. Van den Ende
                    appears to have been distinctly a man of parts, though of a somewhat indiscreet
                    and erratic character. He was eventually hanged in Paris as a conspirator in
                    1674. His enthusiasm for the natural sciences may have been the only ground for
                    the reputation he had acquired of instilling atheistic notions into the minds of
                    his pupils along with the Latin which he taught them. But it is quite possible
                    that his scientific studies had bred in him, as in many others at that time, a
                    materialistic, or at least a naturalistic, turn of mind; indeed we should expect
                    as much in a man of Van den Ende’s somewhat rebellious temperament. We do not
                    know whether his influence was brought to bear in this sense upon Spinoza; but
                    it has been suggested that the writings of Bruno, whose spirit of enthusiastic
                    naturalism and fervid revolt against the church would be especially dear to a
                    man of Van den Ende’s leanings, may have been put into the pupil’s hand by the
                    master. Latin, at all events, Spinoza learned from Van den Ende to use with
                    correctness, freedom, and force, though his language does not, of course,
                    conform to classical canons. The only romance of Spinoza’s life is connected
                    with Van den Ende’s household. The physician had an only daughter, Clara Maria
                    by name, who, besides being a proficient in music, understood Latin, it is said,
                    so perfectly that she was able to teach her father’s pupils in his absence.
                    Spinoza, the story goes, fell in love with his fair instructress; but a
                    fellow-student, called Kerkering, supplanted him in his mistress’s affections by
                    the help of a valuable necklace of pearls which he presented to the young lady.
                    Chronology unfortunately forbids us to accept this little episode as true.
                    Recent investigation has proved that, while the marriage with Kerkering, or
                    rather Kerckkrink, is a fact, it did not take place till 1671, in which year the
                    bride, as appears by the register, was twenty-seven years of age. She cannot,
                    therefore, have been more than eleven or twelve in 1656, the year in which
                    Spinoza left Amsterdam; and as Kerckkrink was seven years younger than Spinoza,
                    they cannot well have been simultaneous pupils of Van den Ende and simultaneous
                    suitors for his daughter’s hand. But, though the details of the story thus fall
                    to pieces, it is still possible that in the five years which followed his
                    retirement from Amsterdam Spinoza, who was living within easy distance and paid
                    visits to the city from time to time, may have kept up his connexion with Van
                    den</p>
                <p>Ende, and that the attachment may have dated from this later period. This would
                    at least be some explanation for the existence of the story; for Colerus
                    expressly says that Spinoza “often confessed that he meant to marry her.” But
                    beyond possibility we cannot go in the matter. There is no mention of the Van
                    den Endes in Spinoza’s correspondence; and in the whole tenor of his life and
                    character there is nothing on which to fasten the probability of a romantic
                    attachment.</p>
                <p>The mastery of Latin which he acquired from Van den Ende opened up to Spinoza the
                    whole world of modern philosophy and science, both represented at that time by
                    the writings of Descartes. He read him greedily, says Colerus, and afterwards
                    often declared that he had all his philosophical knowledge from him. The impulse
                    towards natural science which he had received from Van den Ende would be
                    strengthened by the reading of Descartes; he gave over divinity, we are told, to
                    devote himself entirely to these new studies. His inward break with Jewish
                    orthodoxy dated, no doubt, farther back,—from his acquaintance with the
                    philosophical theologians and commentators of the Middle Ages; but these new
                    interests combined to estrange him still further from the traditions of the
                    synagogue. He was seldomer seen at its services,— soon not at all. The jealousy
                    of the heads of the synagogue was easily roused. An attempt seems to have been
                    made to draw from him his real opinions on certain prominent points of divinity.
                    Two so-called friends endeavoured, on the plea of doubts of their own, to lead
                    him into a theological discussion; and, some of Spinoza’s expressions being
                    repeated to the Jewish authorities, he was summoned to give an account of
                    himself. Anxious to retain so promising an adherent, and probably desirous at
                    the same time to avoid public scandal, the chiefs of the community offered him a
                    yearly pension of 1000 florins if he would outwardly conform and appear now and
                    then in the synagogue. But such deliberate hypocrisy was abhorrent to Spinoza’s
                    nature. Threats were equally unavailing, and accordingly on the 27th of July
                    1656 Spinoza was solemnly cut off from the commonwealth of Israel. The curses
                    pronounced against him may be read in most of the biographies. While
                    negotiations were still pending, he had been set upon one evening by a fanatical
                    ruffian, who thought to expedite matters with the dagger. Warned by this that
                    Amsterdam was hardly a safe place of residence for him any longer, Spinoza had
                    already left the city before the sentence of excommunication was pronounced. He
                    did not go far, but took up his abode with a friend who lived some miles out on
                    the Old Church road. His host belonged to the Col-legiants or Rhijnsburgers, a
                    religious society which had sprung up among the proscribed Arminians of Holland.
                    The pure morality and simple-minded piety of this community seem early to have
                    attracted Spinoza, and to have won his unfeigned respect. Several of his friends
                    were Collegiants, or belonged to the similarly-minded community of the
                    Mennonites, in which the Collegiants were afterwards merged. In this quiet
                    retreat Spinoza spent nearly five years. He drew up a protest against the decree
                    of excommunication, but otherwise it left him unmoved. From this time forward he
                    disused his Hebrew name of Baruch, adopting instead the Latin equivalent,
                    Benedictus. Like every Jew, Spinoza had learned a handicraft; he was a grinder
                    of lenses for optical instruments, and was thus enabled to earn an income
                    sufficient for his modest wants. His skill, indeed, was such that lenses of his
                    making were much sought after, and those found in his cabinet after his death
                    fetched a high price. It was as an optician that he was first brought into
                    connexion with Huygens and Leibnitz; and an optical <hi rend="italic">Treatise
                    on the Rainbow,</hi> written by him and long supposed to be lost, has been
                    recently<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n424/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0424-0401"/> discovered and reprinted by Dr Van Vloten. He was
                    also fond of drawing as an amusement in his leisure hours; and Colerus had seen
                    a sketch-book full of such drawings representing persons of Spinoza’s
                    acquaintance, one of them being a likeness of himself in the character of
                    Masaniello.</p>
                <p>The five years which followed the excommunication must have been devoted to
                    concentrated thought and study. Before their conclusion Spinoza had parted
                    company from Descartes, and the leading positions of his own system were already
                    clearly determined in his mind. A number of the younger men in Amsterdam—many of
                    them students of medicine or medical practitioners—had also come to regard him
                    as their intellectual leader. A kind of philosophical club had been formed,
                    including among its members Simon de Vries, John Bresser, Louis Meyer, and
                    others who appear in Spinoza’s correspondence. Originally meeting in all
                    probability for more thoroughgoing study of the Cartesian philosophy, they
                    looked naturally to Spinoza for guidance, and by-and-by we find him
                    communicating systematic drafts of his own views to the little band of friends
                    and students. The manuscript was read out and discussed at their meetings, and
                    any points remaining obscure were referred to Spinoza for further explanation.
                    An interesting specimen of such difficulties, propounded by Simon de Vries and
                    resolved by Spinoza in accordance with his own principles, is preserved for us
                    in Spinoza’s correspondence. This Simon de Vries was a youth of generous
                    impulses and of much promise. Being in good circumstances, he was anxious to
                    show his gratitude to Spinoza by a gift of 2000 florins, which the philosopher
                    half-jestingly excused himself from accepting. De Vries died young, and would
                    fain have left his fortune to Spinoza; but the latter refused to stand in the
                    way of his brother, the natural heir, to whom the property was accordingly left,
                    with the condition that he should pay to Spinoza an annuity sufficient for his
                    maintenance. The heir offered to fix the amount at 500 florins, but Spinoza
                    accepted only 300, a sum which was regularly paid till his death. The written
                    communications of his own doctrine referred to above belong to a period after
                    Spinoza had removed from the neighbourhood of Amsterdam; but it has been
                    conjectured that the <hi rend="italic">Short Treatise on God, on Man, and his
                    Wellbeing,</hi> which represents his thoughts in their earliest systematic form,
                    was left by him as a parting legacy to this group of friends. It is at least
                    certain, from a reference in Spinoza’s first letter to Oldenburg, that such a
                    systematic exposition was in existence before September 1661.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Various
                    manuscript copies were apparently made of the treatise in question, but it was
                    not printed, and dropped entirely out of knowledge till 1852, when Edward Böhmer
                    of Halle lighted upon an abstract of it attached to a copy of Colerus's</hi>
                    Life, <hi rend="italic">and shortly afterwards upon a Dutch MS. purporting to be
                    a translation of the treatise from the Latin original. This was published in
                    1862 by Van Vloten with a re-translation into Latin. Since then a superior Dutch
                    translation has been discovered, which has been edited by Professor
                    Schaarschmidt and translated into German. Another German version with
                    introduction and notes has been published by Sigwart based on a comparison of
                    the two Dutch MSS.</hi></p></note> There are two dialogues somewhat loosely
                    incorporated with the work which probably belong to a still earlier period. The
                    short appendix, in which the attempt is made to present the chief points of the
                    argument in geometrical form, is a forerunner of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ethics,</hi> and was probably written somewhat later than the rest of the book.
                    The term “Nature” is put more into the foreground in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Treatise,</hi> a point which might be urged as evidence of Bruno’s
                    influence,—the dialogues, moreover, being specially concerned to establish the
                    unity, infinity, and self-containedness of Nature<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">The fact that Spinoza
                    nowhere mentions Bruno would not imply, according to the literary habits of
                    those days, that he was not acquainted with his speculations and even indebted
                    to them. There is no mention,</hi><hi rend="italic">for example, of Hobbes
                    throughout Spinoza’s political writing, and only one casual reference to him in
                    a letter, although the obligation of the Dutch to the English thinker lies on
                    the surface. Accordingly full weight must be allowed to the internal evidence
                    brought forward by Sigwart and others to prove Spinoza’s acquaintance with
                    Bruno’s writings. But in regard to this question, and in regard to the elaborate
                    researches directed to prove that the main determinations of Spinoza’s thought
                    are anticipated in the mediaeval philosophers of his own race, it must be said
                    that these investigations are of comparatively little vital interest. Doubtless
                    Spinoza’s thought was coloured by his Hebraic origin and his Hebraic studies;
                    from these sources, above all, he may have brought with him to the study of the
                    dualistically expressed philosophy of Descartes the need, and the profound
                    conviction, of unity. But the main strain of Spinoza’s thought is sufficiently
                    explained by reference to the Cartesian philosophy itself, the intellectual</hi>
                    milieu <hi rend="italic">of the time. Descartes’s metaphysics can be shown to
                    lead us to the very threshold of Spinoza’s system; not only the general form,
                    but the very terminology—substance, attributes, and modes—lay waiting to be
                    appropriated by an independent student.</hi></p></note>; but the two opposed
                    Cartesian attributes, thought and extension, and the absolutely infinite
                    substance whose attributes they are—substance constituted by infinite
                    attributes— appear here as in the <hi rend="italic">Ethics.</hi> The latter
                    notion—of substance—is said to correspond exactly to “the essence of the only
                    glorious and blessed God.” The earlier differs from the later exposition in
                    allowing an objective causal relation between thought and extension, for which
                    there is substituted in the <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi> the idea of a
                    thoroughgoing parallelism.</p>
                <p>Early in 1661 Spinoza’s host removed to Rhijnsburg near Leyden, the headquarters
                    of the Collegiant brotherhood, and Spinoza removed with him. The house where
                    they lived at Rhijnsburg is still standing, and the road bears the name of
                    Spinoza Lane. Very soon after his settlement in his new quarters he was sought
                    out by Henry Oldenburg, the first secretary of the Royal Society.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Henry
                    Oldenburg (c. 1626-1678) was a native of Bremen, but had settled in England in
                    the time of the Commonwealth. Though hardly a scientific man himself, he had a
                    genuine interest in science, and must have possessed social gifts. He was the
                    friend of Boyle, and acquainted with most of the leaders of science in England
                    as well as with many on the Continent. He delighted to keep himself in this
                    way</hi> au courant <hi rend="italic">with the latest developments, and lost no
                    opportunity of establishing relations with men of scientific reputation. It was
                    probably at the suggestion of Huygens that he bent his steps towards Spinoza’s
                    lodging.</hi></p></note> Oldenburg became Spinoza’s most regular
                    correspondent,—a third of the letters preserved to us are to or from him; and it
                    appears from his first letter that their talk on this occasion was “on God, on
                    infinite extension and thought, on the difference and the agreement of these
                    attributes, on the nature of the union of the human soul with the body, as well
                    as concerning the principles of the Cartesian and Baconian philosophies.”
                    Spinoza must therefore have unbosomed himself pretty freely to his visitor on
                    the main points of his system. Oldenburg, however, was a man of no speculative
                    capacity, and, to judge from his subsequent correspondence, must have quite
                    failed to grasp the real import and scope of the thoughts communicated to him.
                    From one of Oldenburg’s early letters we learn that the treatise <hi
                    rend="italic">De Intellectus Emendatione</hi> was probably Spinoza’s first
                    occupation at Rhijnsburg. The nature of the work also bears out the supposition
                    that it was first undertaken. It is, in a manner, Spinoza’s “organon,”—the
                    doctrine of method which he would substitute for the corresponding doctrines of
                    Bacon and Descartes, as alone consonant with the thoughts which were shaping
                    themselves or had shaped themselves in his mind. It is a theory of philosophical
                    truth and error, involving an account of the course of philosophical inquiry and
                    of the supreme object of knowledge. It was apparently intended by the author as
                    an analytical introduction to the constructive exposition of his system, which
                    he presently essayed in the <hi rend="italic">Ethics.</hi> But he must have
                    found as he proceeded that the two treatises would cover to a large extent the
                    same ground, the account of the true method merging almost inevitably in a
                    state-<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n425/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0425-0402"/> ment of the truth reached by its means. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Amendment of the Understanding</hi> was therefore put aside
                    unfinished, and was first published in the <hi rend="italic">Opera
                    Posthuma.</hi> Spinoza meanwhile concentrated his attention upon the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ethics,</hi> and we learn from the correspondence with his
                    Amsterdam friends that a considerable part of book i. had been communicated to
                    the philosophical club there before February 1663. It formed his main occupation
                    for two or three years after this date. Though thus giving his friends freely of
                    his best, Spinoza did not cast his thoughts broadcast upon any soil. He had a
                    pupil living with him at Rhijnsburg whose character seemed to him lacking in
                    solidity and discretion. This pupil (probably Albert Burgh, who afterwards
                    joined the Church of Rome and penned a foolishly insolent epistle to his former
                    teacher) was the occasion of Spinoza’s first publication,—the only publication
                    indeed to which his name was attached. Not deeming it prudent to initiate the
                    young man into his own system, he took for a text-book the second and third
                    parts of Descartes’s <hi rend="italic">Principles,</hi> which deal in the main
                    with natural philosophy. As he proceeded he put Descartes’s matter in his own
                    language and cast the whole argument into a geometric form. At the request of
                    his friends he devoted a fortnight to applying the same method to the first or
                    metaphysical part of Descartes’s philosophy, and the sketch was published in
                    1663, with an appendix entitled <hi rend="italic">Cogitata Metaphysica,</hi>
                    still written from a Cartesian standpoint (defending, for example, the freedom
                    of the will), but containing hints of his own doctrine. The book was revised by
                    Dr Meyer for publication and furnished by him, at Spinoza’s request, with a
                    preface, in which it is expressly stated that the author speaks throughout not
                    in his own person but simply as the exponent of Descartes. A Dutch translation
                    appeared in the following year.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">The title of the Latin original ran—</hi>
                    Renαti des Cartes Principiorum Philosophise pars <hi rend="italic">i.</hi> et
                    <hi rend="italic">ii.</hi> more geometrico demonstrates per Benedictum de
                    Spinoza Amstelodamensem. Accesserunt ejusdem Cogitata Metaphysica.</p><p>subject
                    to a certain control on the part of the state, whose business it is to see to
                    the preservation of decency and order. But, with such obvious exceptions,
                    Spinoza claims complete freedom of expression for thought and belief; and he
                    claims it in the interests alike of true piety and of the state itself. The
                    thesis is less interesting to a modern reader—because now generally
                    acknowledged—than the argument by which it is supported. Spinoza’s position is
                    based upon the thoroughgoing distinction drawn in the book between philosophy,
                    which has to do with knowledge and opinion, and theology, or, as we should now
                    say, religion, which has to do exclusively with obedience and conduct. The aegis
                    of religion, therefore, cannot be employed to cover with its authority any
                    speculative doctrine; nor, on the other hand, can any speculative or scientific
                    investigation be regarded as putting religion in jeopardy. Spinoza undertakes to
                    prove his case by the instance of the Hebrew Scriptures. Scripture deals, he
                    maintains, in none but the simplest precepts, nor does it aim at anything beyond
                    the obedient mind; it tells us nought of the divine nature, but what men may
                    profitably apply to their lives. The greater part of the treatise is devoted to
                    working out this line of thought; and in so doing Spinoza consistently applies
                    to the interpretation of the Old Testament those canons of historical exegesis
                    which are often regarded as of comparatively recent growth. The treatise thus
                    constitutes the first document in the modern science of Biblical criticism. It
                    was published in 1670, anonymously, printer and place of publication being
                    likewise disguised <hi rend="italic">(Hamburgi apud Hein-ricum Künraht).</hi>
                    The storm of opposition which it encountered showed that these precautions were
                    not out of place. It was synodically condemned along with Hobbes’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> and other books as early as April 1671, and was
                    consequently interdicted by the states-general of Holland in 1674; before long
                    it was also placed on the Index by the Catholic authorities. But that it was
                    widely read appears from its frequent re-issue with false title-pages,
                    representing it now as an historical work and again as a medical treatise.
                    Controversialists also crowded into the lists against it. A translation into
                    Dutch appears to have been proposed; but Spinoza, who foresaw that such a step
                    would only increase the commotion which was so distasteful to him, steadily set
                    his face against it. No Dutch translation appeared till 1693.</p><p>The same
                    year in which the <hi rend="italic">Treatise</hi> was published Spinoza removed
                    from his suburban lodging at Voorburg into The Hague itself. He took rooms first
                    on the Veerkay with the widow Van de Velde, who in her youth had assisted
                    Grotius to escape from his captivity at Loewenstein. This was the house
                    afterwards occupied by Colerus, the worthy Lutheran minister who became
                    Spinoza’s biographer. But the widow insisted on boarding her lodger, and Spinoza
                    presently found the expense too great for his slender purse. He accordingly
                    removed to a house on the Pavelioen Gracht near at hand, occupied by a painter
                    called Van der Spijck. Here he spent the remaining years of his life in the
                    frugal independence which he prized. Colerus gives particulars which enable us
                    to realize the almost incredible simplicity and economy of his mode of life. He
                    would say sometimes to the people of the house that he was like the serpent who
                    forms a circle with his tail in his mouth, meaning thereby that he had nothing
                    left at the year’s end. His friends came to visit him in his lodgings, as well
                    as others attracted by his reputation-—Leibnitz among the rest—and were
                    courteously entertained, but Spinoza preferred not to accept their offers of
                    hospitality. He spent the greater part of his time quietly in his own chamber,
                    often having his meals brought there and sometimes not leaving it for two or
                    three days together when absorbed in his studies. On one occasion he did not
                    leave the house for three</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1663 Spinoza removed from Rhijnsburg to Voorburg, a suburban village about 2
                    miles from The Hague. His reputation had continued to spread. From Rhijnsburg he
                    had paid frequent visits to The Hague, and it was probably the desire to be
                    within reach of some of the friends he had made in these visits—among others the
                    De Witts —that prompted his change of residence. He had works in hand, moreover,
                    which he wished in due time to publish; and in that connexion the friendly
                    patronage of the De Witts might be of essential service to him. The first years
                    at Voorburg continued to be occupied by the composition of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ethics,</hi> which was probably finished, however, by the summer of 1665. A
                    journey made to Amsterdam in that year is conjectured to have had reference to
                    its publication. But, finding that it would be impossible to keep the authorship
                    secret, owing to the numerous hands through which parts of the book had already
                    passed, Spinoza determined to keep his manuscript in his desk for the present.
                    In September 1665 we find Oldenburg twitting him with having turned from
                    philosophy to theology and busying himself with angels, prophecy, and miracles.
                    This is the first reference to the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus
                    Theologico-Politicus,</hi> which formed his chief occupation for the next four
                    years. The aim of this treatise may be best understood from the full title with
                    which it was furnished— <hi rend="italic">Tractatus Theologico-Politicus,
                    continens dissertationes aliquot, quibus ostenditur libertatem philosophandi non
                    tantum salva pietate et reipublicae pace posse concedi sed eandem nisi cum pace
                    reipublicae ipsaque pietate tolli non posse.</hi> It is, in fact, an eloquently
                    reasoned defence of liberty of thought and speech in speculative matters. The
                    external side of religion—its rites and observances—must of necessity be<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n426/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0426-0403"/> months. “When he happened to be tired by having
                    applied himself too much to his philosophical meditations, he would go
                    downstairs to refresh himself, and discoursed with the Van der Spijcks about
                    anything that might afford matter for an ordinary conversation, and even about
                    trifles. He also took pleasure in smoking a pipe of tobacco; or, when he had a
                    mind to divert himself somewhat longer, he looked for some spiders and made them
                    fight together, or he threw some flies into the cobweb, and was so well pleased
                    with the result of that battle that he would sometimes break into laughter”
                    (Colerus). He also conversed at times on more serious topics with the simple
                    people with whom he lodged, often, for example, talking over the sermon with
                    them when they came from church. He occasionally went himself to hear the
                    Lutheran pastor preach—the predecessor of Colerus—and would advise the Van der
                    Spijcks not to miss any sermon of so excellent a preacher. The children, too, he
                    put in mind of going often to church, and taught them to be obedient and dutiful
                    to their parents. One day his landlady, who may have heard strange stories of
                    her solitary lodger, came to him in some trouble to ask him whether he believed
                    she could be saved in the religion she professed. “Your religion is a good one,”
                    said Spinoza; “you need not look for another, nor doubt that you will be saved
                    in it, provided that, while you apply yourself to piety, you live at the same
                    time a peaceable and quiet life.” Only once, it is recorded, did Spinoza’s
                    admirable self-control give way, and that was when he received the news of the
                    murder of the De Witts by a frantic mob in the streets of The Hague. It was in
                    the year 1672, when the sudden invasion of the Low Countries by Louis XIV.
                    raised an irresistible clamour for a military leader and overthrew the
                    republican constitution for which the De Witts had struggled. John De Witt had
                    been Spinoza’s friend, and had bestowed a small pension upon him; he had
                    Spinoza’s full sympathy in his political aims. On receiving the news of the
                    brutal murder of the two brothers, Spinoza burst into tears, and his indignation
                    was so roused that he was bent upon publicly denouncing the crime upon the spot
                    where it had been committed. But the timely caution of his host prevented his
                    issuing forth to almost certain death. Not long after Spinoza was himself in
                    danger from the mob, in consequence of a visit which he paid to the French camp.
                    He had been in correspondence with one Colonel Stoupe, a Swiss theologian and
                    soldier, then serving with the prince of Condé, the commander of the French army
                    at Utrecht. From him Spinoza received a communication enclosing a passport from
                    the French commander, who wished to make his acquaintance and promised him a
                    pension from the French king at the easy price of a dedication to his majesty.
                    Spinoza went to Utrecht, but returned without seeing Condé, who had in the
                    meantime been called elsewhere; the pension he civilly declined. There may have
                    been nothing more in the visit than is contained in this narrative; but on his
                    return Spinoza found that the populace of The Hague regarded him as no better
                    than a spy. The town was full of angry murmurs, and the landlord feared that the
                    mob would storm his house and drag Spinoza out. Spinoza quieted his fears as
                    well as he could, assuring him that as soon as the crowd made any threatening
                    movement he would go out to meet them, “though they should serve me as they did
                    the poor De Witts. I am a good republican and have never had any aim but the
                    honour and welfare of the state.” Happily the danger passed off without calling
                    for such an ordeal.</p>
                <p>In 1673 Spinoza received an invitation from the elector palatine to quit his
                    retirement and become professor of philosophy in the university of Heidelberg.
                    The offer was couched in flattering terms, and conveyed an express assurance of
                    “the largest freedom of speech in philosophy, which the prince is confident that
                    you will not misuse to disturb the established religion.” But Spinoza’s
                    experience of theological sensitiveness led him to doubt the possibility of
                    keeping on friendly terms with the established religion, if he were placed in a
                    public capacity. Moreover, he was not strong; he had had no experience of public
                    teaching; and he foresaw that the duties of a chair would put an end to private
                    research. For all these reasons he courteously declined the offer made to him.
                    There is little more to tell of his life of solitary meditation. In 1675 we
                    learn from his correspondence that he entertained the idea of publishing the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ethics,</hi> and made a journey to Amsterdam to arrange matters
                    with the printer. “But, whilst I was busy with this,” he writes, “the report was
                    spread everywhere that a certain book of mine was in the press, wherein I
                    endeavoured to show that there was no God; and this report found credence with
                    many. Whereupon certain theologians (themselves perhaps the authors of it) took
                    occasion to complain of me to the prince and the magistrates; moreover, the
                    stupid Cartesians, because they are commonly supposed to side with me, desiring
                    to free themselves from that suspicion, were diligent without ceasing in their
                    execrations of my doctrines and writings, and are as diligent still.” As the
                    commotion seemed to grow worse instead of subsiding, Spinoza consigned the
                    manuscript once more to his desk, from which it was not to issue till after his
                    death. His last literary work was the unfinished <hi rend="italic">Tractatus
                    Politicus</hi> and the preparation of notes for a new edition of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Tractatus Theologico-Politicus,</hi> in which he hoped to remove
                    some of the misunderstandings which the book had met with. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tractatus Politicus</hi> develops his philosophy of law and government on the
                    lines indicated in his other works, and connects itself closely with the theory
                    enunciated by Hobbes a generation before. Consumption had been making its
                    insidious inroads upon Spinoza for many years, and early in 1677 he must have
                    been conscious that he was seriously ill. On Saturday the 20th of February he
                    sent to Amsterdam for his friend Dr Meyer. On the following day the Van der
                    Spijcks, having no thought of immediate danger, went to the afternoon service.
                    When they came back Spinoza was no more; he had died about three in the
                    afternoon with Meyer for the only witness of his last moments. Spinoza was
                    buried on the 25th of February “in the new church upon the Spuy, being
                    attended,” Colerus tells us, “by many illustrious persons and followed by six
                    coaches.” He was little more than forty-four years of age.</p>
                <p>Spinoza’s effects were few and realized little more than was required for the
                    payment of charges and outstanding debts. “One need only cast one’s eyes upon
                    the account,” says his biographer, “to perceive that it was the inventory of a
                    true philosopher. It contains only some small books, some engravings, a few
                    lenses, and the instruments to polish them.” His desk, containing his letters
                    and his unpublished works, Spinoza had previously charged his landlord to convey
                    to Jan Rieuwertz, a publisher in Amsterdam. This was done, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opera Posthuma</hi> appeared in the same year, without the
                    author’s name, but with his initials upon the titlepage. They were furnished
                    with a preface written in Dutch by Jarig Jellis, a Mennonite friend of
                    Spinoza’s, and translated into Latin by Dr Meyer. Next year the book was
                    proscribed in a violently worded edict by the states of Holland and West
                    Friesland. The obloquy which thus gathered round Spinoza in the later years of
                    his life remained settled upon his memory for a full hundred years after his
                    death. Hume’s casual allusion to “this famous atheist” and his “hideous
                    hypothesis” is a fair specimen of the tone in which he is usually referred to;
                    people talked about Spinoza, Lessing said, “as if he were a dead dog.” The
                    change of opinion in this respect may be dated from Lessing’s famous
                    conversation with Jacobi in 1780. Lessing, Goethe, Herder, Novalis, and
                    Schleiermacher, not to mention philosophers like Schelling and Hegel, united in
                    recognizing the unique strength and sincerity of Spinoza’s thought, and in
                    setting him in his rightful place among the speculative leaders of mankind.
                    Transfused into their writings, his spirit has had a large share in moulding the
                    philosophic thought<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n427/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0427-0404"/> of the 19th century, and it has also been widely
                    influential beyond the schools. Instead of his atheism Hegel speaks of his
                    acosmism, and Novalis dubs him a God-intoxicated man. Schleierinacher’s fine
                    apostrophe is well known, in which he calls upon us to “offer a lock of hair to
                    the manes of the holy and excommunicated Spinoza.”</p>
                <p>Spinoza’s personal appearance is described by Colerus from the accounts given him
                    by many people at The Hague who knew him familiarly. "He was of a middle size,
                    and had good features in his face, the skin somewhat dark, black curled hair,
                    and the long eyebrows of the same colour, so that one might easily know from his
                    looks that he was descended from the Portuguese Jews.” Leibnitz also gives a
                    similar description: “The celebrated Jew Spinoza had an olive complexion and
                    something Spanish in his face.” These characteristics are preserved in a
                    portrait in oil in the Wolfenbüttel library, which was probably the original of
                    the (in that case unsuccessfully rendered) engraving prefixed to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opera Posthuma</hi> of 1677. This portrait has recently been
                    photographed for Dr Martineau’s <hi rend="italic">Study of Spinoza.</hi> In 1880
                    a statue was erected to Spinoza at The Hague by international subscription among
                    his admirers.</p>
                <p>Spinoza’s philosophy is a thoroughgoing pantheism, which has both a naturalistic
                    and a mystical side. The foundation of the system is the doctrine of one
                    infinite substance, of which all finite existences are modes or limitations
                    (modes of thought or modes of extension). God is thus the immanent cause of the
                    universe; but of creation or will there can be no question in Spinoza’s system.
                    God is used throughout as equivalent to nature (<hi rend="italic">Deus sive
                    natura).</hi> The philosophical standpoint comprehends the necessity of all that
                    is—a necessity that is none other than the necessity of the divine nature
                    itself. To view things thus is to view them, according to Spinoza’s favourite
                    phrase, <hi rend="italic">sub specie aetemitatis.</hi> Spinoza’s philosophy is
                    fully considered in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Cartesianism</hi> (see vol.
                    V. p. 152 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> The
                    contents of the <hi rend="italic">Opera Posthuma</hi> included the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ethics,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus Politicus,</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">De Intellectus Emendatione</hi> (the last two unfinished),
                    a selection from Spinoza’s correspondence, and a <hi rend="italic">Compendium of
                    Hebrew Grammar.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Rainbow,</hi>
                    supposed to be lost, was published anonymously in Dutch in 1687. The first
                    collected edition of Spinoza’s works was made by Paulus in 1802; there is
                    another by Gfrörer (1830), and a third by Brader (1843-46) in three volumes. Van
                    Vloten’s volume, published in 1862, <hi rend="italic">Ad Benedicti de Spinoza
                    opera quae supersunt omnia supplementum,</hi> is uniform with Bruder’s edition
                    so as to complete it by a supplementary volume. It contained the early treatise
                    <hi rend="italic">De Deo et homine,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the
                    Rainbow,</hi> and several fresh letters. A complete and authoritative edition
                    has only recently been achieved by Dr Van Vloten and Professor J. P. N. Land.
                    The work was undertaken by them for the Spinoza Memorial Committee formed in
                    Holland to celebrate the bicentenary of the philosopher’s death; the funds
                    remaining after the erection of the statue mentioned above were devoted to the
                    publication of this handsome edition (2 vols., 1882-83). An English translation
                    of <hi rend="italic">The Chief Works of Spinoza,</hi> by R. H. M. Elwes,
                    appeared in 1883, and a separate translation of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ethics</hi> by W. H. White was published in the same year; previous
                    translations were unscholarly in execution. The main authority for Spinoza’s
                    life is the sketch published in 1705, in Dutch, with a controversial sermon
                    against Spinozism, by Johannes Coleras. The French version of this <hi
                    rend="italic">Life</hi> (1706) has been several times reprinted as well as
                    translated into English and German. The English version, also dating from 1706,
                    has been reprinted by Mr Frederick Pollock at the end of his work, <hi
                    rend="italic">Spinoza, his Life and Philosophy</hi> (1880) <hi rend="italic"
                    >.</hi> Mr Pollock’s book and Dr Martineau’s <hi rend="italic">Study of
                    Spinoza</hi> (1882), both admirable pieces of work, are in a manner
                    complementary, and may with advantage be studied together. In his introduction
                    Mr Pollock gives a list of the biographical sources, and also some account of
                    the early literature relating to Spinoza. The Spinoza literature in more recent
                    times has become so extensive as to forbid quotation. A. van der Linde’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Benedictus Spinoza: Bibliografie</hi> (The Hague, 1871) is a
                    classified catalogue as nearly as possible complete down to that date. (A.
                    SE.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
