<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0392-0369-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SPARROW (9th edition, volume 22, page 369)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1128737">Sparrows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048356">Ornithologists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1054392">Passer</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935238">Fringilla</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15v25">Sparrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g64z">Passeres</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vx1b">Neck</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c21">Thrushes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4857c">Weavers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n392/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SPARROW</label> (A.S. <hi rend="italic">Spearwa</hi>; Icel.
                    <hi rend="italic">Spörr;</hi> Old High Germ. <hi rend="italic">Sparo),</hi> a
                    word perhaps (like the equivalent Latin <hi rend="italic">Passer)</hi>
                    originally meaning almost any small bird, but gradually restricted in
                    signification and nowadays in common English applied to only four kinds, which
                    are further differentiated as Hedge-Sparrow, House-Sparrow, Tree-Sparrow, and
                    Reed-Sparrow—the last being a <hi rend="smallcaps">Bunting</hi> (vol. iv. p.
                    525)—though when used without a prefix the second of these is usually
                    intended.</p>
                <p>1. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Hedge-Sparrow,</hi> called “Dunnock” in many parts of
                    Britain, the <hi rend="italic">Accentor modularis</hi> of ornithologists, is the
                    little brown-backed bird with an iron-grey head and neck that is to be seen in
                    nearly every garden throughout the country, unobtrusively and yet tamely seeking
                    its food, which consists almost wholly of insects, as it progresses over the
                    ground in short jumps, each movement being accompanied by a slight jerk or
                    shuffle of the wings. Though on the Continent it regularly migrates, it is one
                    of the few soft-billed birds that reside throughout the year with us, and is one
                    of the earliest breeders,—its well-known greenish-blue eggs, laid in a
                    warmly-built nest, being recognized by hundreds as among the surest signs of
                    returning spring; but a second or even a third brood is produced later. The cock
                    has a sweet but rather feeble song; and the species has long been accounted,
                    though not with accuracy, to be the most common dupe of the Cuckow. Several
                    other species are assigned to the genus <hi rend="italic">Accentor</hi>; but
                    all, except the Japanese <hi rend="italic">A. rubidus,</hi> which is the
                    counterpart of the British Hedge-Sparrow, inhabit more or less rocky situations,
                    and one, <hi rend="italic">A. collaris</hi> or <hi rend="italic">alpinus,</hi>
                    is a denizen of the higher mountainranges of Europe, though it has several times
                    strayed to England. The taxonomic position of the genus is regarded by some
                    systematists as doubtful; but to the present writer there seems no good reason
                    for removing it from the group which contains the Thrushes and Warblers (<hi
                    rend="italic">Turdidae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sylviidae),</hi> to which it
                    was long referred.</p>
                <p>2. The <hi rend="smallcaps">House-Sparrow,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Fringilla
                    domestica</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Passer domesticus</hi> of
                    modern authors, is far too well known to need any description of its appearance
                    or habits, being found, whether in country or town, more attached to human
                    dwellings than any other wild bird; nay, more than that, one may safely assert
                    that it is not known to thrive anywhere far away from the habitations or works
                    of men, extending its range in such countries as Northern Scandinavia and many
                    parts of the Russian empire as new settlements are formed and land brought under
                    cultivation. Thus questions arise as to whether it should not be considered a
                    parasite throughout the greater portion of the area it now occupies, and as to
                    what may have been its native country. Moreover, of late years it has been
                    inconsiderately introduced to several of the large towns of North America and to
                    many of the British colonies, in nearly all of which, as had been foreseen by
                    ornithologists, it has multiplied to excess and has become an intolerable
                    nuisance, being unrestrained by the natural checks which partly restrict its
                    increase in Europe and Asia. Whether indeed in the older seats of civilization
                    the House-Sparrow is not decidedly injurious to the agriculturist and
                    horticulturist has long been a matter of discussion, and no definite result that
                    a fair judge can accept has yet been reached. It is freely admitted that the
                    damage done to growing crops is often enormous, but as yet the service
                    frequently rendered by the destruction of insect-pests cannot be calculated.
                    Both friends and foes of the House-Sparrow write as violent partisans,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The most recent attacks upon
                    it are contained in the various issues of the <hi rend="italic">Report of
                    Observations of Injurious Insects and Common Crop Pests,</hi> annually made by
                    Miss Eleanor Ormerod, and in a little volume bearing the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">The House Sparrow,</hi> published in 1885, <hi rend="italic">and
                    consisting chiefly of three essays by Mr J. H. Gurney, jun., Lieut. -Col. C.
                    Russell, and Prof. Coues, but the last has only reference to the behaviour of
                    the bird in the United States of America, where, from the reason above assigned,
                    its presence was expected by almost all well-informed persons to be
                    detrimental.</hi></p></note> and the truth will not be known until a series of
                    experiments, conducted by scientifically-trained investigators, has been
                    instituted, which, to the shame of numerous agricultural and horticultural
                    societies, has not yet been done. It is quite likely that the result will be
                    unfavourable to the House-Sparrow, from what has been said above as to its being
                    so dependent on man for its subsistence; but, while the evil it does is so
                    apparent,—for instance, the damage to ripening grain-crops,—the extent of the
                    counterbalancing benefit is quite uncertain, and from the nature of the case is
                    often overlooked. In the South of Europe the House-Sparrow is in some measure
                    replaced by two allied species, <hi rend="italic">P. hispaniolensis</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">P. italiae,</hi> whose habits are essentially identical with its
                    own; and it is doubtful whether the Sparrow of India, <hi rend="italic">P.
                    indicus,</hi> is specifically distinct; but Africa has several members of the
                    genus which are decidedly so.</p>
                <p>3. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Tree-Sparrow,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Fringilla
                    montana</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Passer montanus</hi> of modem
                    writers, in appearance much resembling the House-Sparrow, but easily
                    distinguishable by its reddish-brown crown, the black patch on the sides of its
                    neck, and its doubly-barred wings,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">A more important difference is that the
                    two sexes have almost the same plumage, while in the House-Sparrow they are
                    unlike in this respect.</hi></p></note> is a much more local species, in England
                    generally frequenting the rows of pollard-willows that line so many rivers and
                    canals, in the holes of which it breeds; but in some Eastern countries, and
                    especially in China, it frequents houses, even in towns, and so fills the place
                    of the House-Sparrow. Its geographical distribution is extensive, and marked by
                    some curious characters, among which may be mentioned that, being a great
                    wanderer, it has effected settlements even in such remote islands as the Faeroes
                    and some of the Outer Hebrides.</p>
                <p>That the genus <hi rend="italic">Passer</hi> properly belongs to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Fringill-idse</hi> is admitted by most ornithologists, yet there
                    have been some who would refer it to the Weaver-birds, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ploceidae,</hi> if they are to be accounted as forming a distinct Family,—a
                    matter which is not at all clear. The American birds called “Sparrows” have
                    little in common with the members of the genus <hi rend="italic">Passer,</hi>
                    and probably belong rather to the family <hi rend="italic">Emberizidae</hi> than
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Fringillidae.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
