<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0298-0281-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SOUTH, Robert (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    281)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852224">Chaplains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1113216">Sermons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n298/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SOUTH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label> (1633-1716),
                    one of the wittiest of English divines, was the son of a London merchant, and
                    was born at Hackney, Middlesex, in 1633. He was educated at Westminster school,
                    whence in 1651 he was elected to Christ Church, Oxford. He became B.A. in 1654,
                    and the same year wrote several Latin verses to congratulate Cromwell on
                    concluding peace with the Dutch, which were published in a collection of
                    university poems. The following year he published a Latin poem, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Musica Incantans.</hi> After commencing M.A. in 1657 he was in the
                    habit before obtaining orders in 1658 of preaching as the champion of Calvinism
                    against Socinianism and Arminianism. He was also at this time a strong supporter
                    of Presbyterianism, but on the approach of the Restoration his views on church
                    government under-<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n299/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0299-0282"/> went a change. In fact he adhered successively to
                    the triumphant party as represented by Cromwell, Charles, James, and William,
                    and there are substantial grounds for the assertion of Anthony Wood that he was
                    much indebted for his preferments to his zeal for “the powers that be.” On 10th
                    August 1660 he was chosen public orator of the university, and in 1661 domestic
                    chaplain to Lord Clarendon. In March 1663 he was made prebend of Westminster,
                    and shortly afterwards he received from his university the degree of D.D. In
                    1667 he became chaplain to the duke of York. He was a zealous advocate of the
                    doctrine of passive obedience, and also strongly opposed the Toleration Act,
                    declaiming in unmeasured terms against the various nonconformist sects. In 1676
                    he was appointed chaplain to Lawrence Hyde (afterwards earl of Rochester),
                    ambassador-extraordinary to the king of Poland, and of his visit he sent an
                    interesting account to Dr Edward Pocock in a letter, dated Dantzic, 16th
                    December 1677, which was printed along with South’s <hi rend="italic">Posthumous
                    Works</hi> in 1717. In 1678 he was promoted by the chapter of Westminster to the
                    rectory of Islip, Oxfordshire. Owing, it is said, to a personal grudge, South in
                    1693 published <hi rend="italic">Animadversions on Dr Sherlock’s Book, entitled
                    a Vindication of the Holy and Ever Blessed Trinity,</hi> in which the views of
                    Sherlock were attacked with much sarcastic bitterness. Sherlock, in answer,
                    published a <hi rend="italic">Defence</hi> in 1694, to which South replied in
                    <hi rend="italic">Tritheism Charged upon Dr Sherlock's New Notion of the
                    Trinity, and the Charge Made Good.</hi> The controversy was carried by the rival
                    parties into the pulpit, and occasioned such keen feeling that the king
                    interposed to stop it. During the greater part of the reign of Anne South
                    remained comparatively quiet, but in 1710 he showed himself a keen opponent of
                    Sacheverell. He died 8th July 1716, and was buried in Westminster Abbey.</p>
                <p>The style of South is vigorous, pungent, and brilliant, though tending to
                    exuberance. His sermons are strongly practical, but his theory of life is not
                    ascetic. His wit generally inclines towards sarcasm, and it was probably the
                    knowledge of his quarrelsome temperament that prevented his promotion to a
                    bishopric. If he sacrificed principle to his desire for preferment, his ambition
                    was not of a sordid kind, for he was noted for the extent of his charities. He
                    published a large number of single sermons, and they appeared in a collected
                    form in 1692 in six volumes, reaching a second edition in his lifetime in 1715.
                    His <hi rend="italic">Opera Posthuma Latina,</hi> including his will, his Latin
                    poems, and his orations while public orator, with memoirs of his life, appeared
                    in 1717. His <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> were published with a memoir by the
                    Clarendon press in 1823, and have been several times reprinted. The contemporary
                    notice of South by Wood in his <hi rend="italic">Athenae</hi> is characterized
                    by a strongly hostile tone, partly to be explained by a criticism of South at
                    Wood’s expense.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
