<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0668-0641-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SUMMARY JURISDICTION (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    641)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078061">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078016">Process</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1055703">Payment</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29pg80">Warrants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n668/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SUMMARY JURISDICTION</label>. By a court of summary
                    jurisdiction is meant a court in which cases are heard and determined by a
                    justice or justices of the peace, without the intervention of a jury. Such a
                    court has duties to perform of two different kinds. It either hears and
                    determines a case in a judicial capacity, or it acts rather in a ministerial
                    capacity where a <hi rend="italic">prima facie</hi> case has been established,
                    as by issuing a warrant of distress for nonpayment of poor rate, or by
                    committing an accused person for the decision of a higher court, generally
                    assizes or quarter sessions. It is to the court acting in the former capacity
                    that the term “court of summary jurisdiction” more strictly applies. Ever since
                    the first institution of justices of the peace (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Justice
                    of the Peace),</hi> the tendency of English legislation has been to enlarge
                    their jurisdiction and to enable offences of a less heinous nature to be tried
                    in their courts without a jury. This inroad upon the functions of the jury can
                    only be made by legislation. “The common law is a stranger to it, unless in the
                    case of contempts,” says Blackstone. At common law all offences must be
                    proceeded against by indictment, and an indictment can only be tried before a
                    jury. Even where an offence is created by statute and is unknown to the common
                    law the procedure must be by indictment, unless the statute creating the offence
                    or some other statute specially makes it summary. The history of the gradual
                    growth of summary jurisdiction will be found in Stephen, <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of the Criminal Law,</hi> vol. i. chap. iv. The summary jurisdiction
                    exercised by justices is the only one of much practical importance. It is
                    unnecessary to do more than mention in passing the two other kinds named by
                    Blackstone, that of the commissioners of taxes for revenue offences and that of
                    the superior courts for <hi rend="smallcaps">Contempt of Court</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italic">q.v.</hi>) <hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi> A very remarkable case of
                    the latter is the power given to a judge by 12 Geo. I. c. 29, s. 4, to summarily
                    sentence to seven years’ penal servitude a solicitor practising after conviction
                    for perjury, forgery, or barratry.</p>
                <p>The principal Acts now dealing with summary jurisdiction are the Summary
                    Jurisdiction Act, 1848<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>This name of the Act of 1848 is an example of a title of an Act conferred
                    retrospectively (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Statute).</hi> The name was given to
                    it by the Act of 1879. In the same way the name of the Scotch Summary Procedure
                    Act, 1864, was changed to that of the Summary Jurisdiction Act, 1864, by the
                    Summary Jurisdiction Act, 1881.</p></note> (11 and 12 Vict. c. 43), one of what
                    are called Jervis’s Acts, and the Summary Jurisdiction Act, 1879 (42 and 43
                    Vict. c. 49). The former consolidated the law up to that time of a large number
                    of Acts, but only to a certain extent, for a considerable number of previous
                    enactments dealing in a greater or less degree with this subject are still law,
                    the earliest being 5 Hen. IV. c. 10. It also amended the law in several
                    important particulars. The amendment was in the direction of greater simplicity
                    of procedure, and related to both criminal and only quasicriminal matters. The
                    procedure under the Act is shortly this. In all cases where an information is
                    laid or complaint made the justices are, on proof of a <hi rend="italic">prima
                    facie</hi> case, to issue a <hi rend="smallcaps">Summons</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                    >q.v.</hi>). An information is laid in criminal matters in which the decision of
                    the justices, if adverse to the defendant, would be a conviction. A complaint is
                    made where the decision of the justices in such an event would be an order for
                    the payment of money or otherwise in what may be called only quasi-criminal
                    matters, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> claims under the Employers and Workmen
                    Act. If the summons is disobeyed, a warrant may (in criminal charges only) issue
                    in the first instance at the discretion of a justice. The warrant is good only
                    within the local jurisdiction of the justice issuing it; and, if it is required
                    to be executed in another jurisdiction, it must be backed, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e</hi>., endorsed, by a justice of that jurisdiction (unless in case of a
                    fresh pursuit, when it is good for 7 miles beyond the bounds of the jurisdiction
                    in which it was issued). Complaints need not be in writing; informations usually
                    are, though the Act does not make writing necessary. Where a warrant issues in
                    the first instance, the information must be upon oath. In all cases not
                    otherwise provided for, the information must be laid or complaint made within
                    six calendar months from the time at which the matter of the information or
                    complaint arose. The hearing is in open court, and parties may appear by counsel
                    or solicitor. If both parties appear, the justices must hear and determine the
                    case. If the defendant does not appear, the justices may hear and<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n669/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0669-0642"/> determine in his absence, or may issue a warrant
                    and adjourn the hearing until his apprehension. If the complainant does not
                    appear, the justices may dismiss the complaint or adjourn the hearing. The
                    punishment inflicted may be fine or imprisonment, or both. Imprisonment as a
                    rule cannot exceed six mouths. The regular mode of proceeding where a conviction
                    adjudges a pecuniary penalty, or an order requires payment of a sum of money, is
                    by issue of a warrant of distress to be levied on the goods of the defendant.
                    The court usually consists of two or more justices, but the lord mayor or an
                    alderman of the City of London, a metropolitan police magistrate, and a
                    stipendiary magistrate have each the authority of two justices. The Act further
                    makes provision for curing defects in form in the proceedings for the payment of
                    costs, for removing difficulties as to the boundaries of jurisdiction, and for
                    various other matters. The schedule gives forms of proceedings, which are as far
                    as possible to be followed. The Act of 1879 amended the Act of 1848 in several
                    important particulars, chiefly in the direction of greater leniency and enlarged
                    jurisdiction and power of appeal. A greater discretion in the infliction of
                    punishment is conferred on the court. A scale of imprisonment in respect of
                    non-payment of a fine or default of distress is fixed at periods varying
                    according to the amount of the fine unpaid, but in no case exceeding three
                    months (except in certain revenue offences, where the limit is six months), and
                    without hard labour, unless hard labour is specially authorized by the Act on
                    which the conviction is founded. Time may be given for payment of money, or it
                    may be ordered to be paid by instalments, or security may be taken. Summary
                    trial of children under twelve is allowed at the discretion of the court in case
                    of any indictable offence other than homicide, unless objection is made by the
                    parent or guardian. A child cannot on summary conviction be imprisoned for more
                    than a month or fined more than 40s. Summary trial of juvenile offenders between
                    twelve and sixteen and of adults is allowed in certain crimes mentioned in the
                    Act, if the accused assents and foregoes his right to trial by jury. There are
                    cases in which the court can deal summarily with an adult pleading guilty where
                    it would have been necessary to commit him for trial had he pleaded not guilty.
                    The court may in trivial cases discharge the accused without punishment or with
                    only a nominal punishment. Improvements are made in the practice as to sureties,
                    recognizances (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Surety, Recognizance),</hi> and the
                    issue and execution of warrants of commitment and distress. The issue of such a
                    warrant may be postponed if the court thinks fit. The wearing apparel and
                    bedding of a person and his family, and the tools and implements of his trade to
                    the value of £5, are exempt from distress. Imprisonment may in certain cases be
                    ordered instead of distress. The right of appeal is much extended. An appeal now
                    lies from every conviction or order adjudging imprisonment without the option of
                    a fine where the accused did not plead guilty. The appeal by the Act of 1884
                    must be in accordance with the procedure of the Act of 1879, or of any
                    subsequent Act giving a right of appeal in the particular case. The appeal is to
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Quarter Sessions (</hi><hi rend="italic">q.v.).</hi> A
                    summons or warrant is not avoided by the death or cesser of office of the
                    justice issuing it. Under the powers of the Act rules and forms were framed
                    which came into effect on 1st January 1880. The Summary Jurisdiction (Process)
                    Act, 1881 (44 and 45 Vict. c. 24, applying to Great Britain, but not to
                    Ireland), gave additional facilities for serving and executing the process of an
                    English court of summary jurisdiction in Scotland or of a Scotch court in
                    England, on endorsement in the country where it is executed. The Summary
                    Jurisdiction Act, 1884 (47 and 48 Vict. c. 43), repealed a number of enactments
                    rendered obsolete by the Acts of 1848 and 1879 and explained certain sections of
                    those Acts as to which doubts had arisen. There are numerous other enactments
                    dealing less directly with the powers of courts of summary jurisdiction. For
                    instance, the Merchant Shipping Acts give justices large powers in case of
                    salvage claims and of offences by seamen. The Criminal Law Consolidation Acts of
                    1861 give them limited jurisdiction in larceny, coining, malicious injuries to
                    property, and offences against the person. Among many other Acts conferring
                    summary jurisdiction are the Army, Bastardy, Customs, Employers and Workmen,
                    Game, Highway, Licensing, Post Office, and Vagrant Acts. Some of the later Acts,
                    such as the Customs and Army Acts, apply to the United Kingdom. The decision of
                    a court of summary jurisdiction may be reviewed by, besides appeal, a writ of
                    certiorari, mandamus, or habeas corpus, or by statement of a special case.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Scotland.—</hi> Summary jurisdiction in Scotland depends
                    chiefly upon the Summary Jurisdiction Acts, 1864 and 1881. A court of summary
                    jurisdiction includes the sherifi' court. The Acts follow, <hi rend="italic"
                    >mutatis mutandis,</hi> the lines of English legislation. All proceedings for
                    summary conviction or for recovery of a penalty must be by way of complaint
                    according to one of the forms in the schedule to the Act of 1864. The English
                    summons and warrant are represented in Scotland by the warrant of citation and
                    the warrant of apprehension. Where no punishment is fixed for a statutory
                    offence, the court cannot sentence to more than a fine of £5 or sixty days’
                    imprisonment, in addition to ordering caution to keep the peace. The Act of 1881
                    adopts many of the provisions of the English Act of 1879. In addition, it
                    confers the discretion as to punishment to a sheriff trying by jury in cases
                    where the prosecution might have been by complaint under the Acts. Appeals from
                    courts of summary jurisdiction are now mainly regulated by 38 and 39 Vict. c.
                    62, and proceed on case stated by the inferior judge.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ireland.—</hi> The principal Acts dealing with the subject are
                    the Summary Jurisdiction and Petty Sessions Acts, 1851 (14 and 15 Vict. cc. 92,
                    93). These Acts are more extensive in their purview than the English Acts, as
                    they form in a great degree a code of substantive law as well as of procedure.
                    The exceptional political circumstances of Ireland have led to the appointment
                    of resident magistrates under 6 and 7 Will. IV. c. 13, and to the conferring at
                    different times on courts of summary jurisdiction of an authority, generally
                    temporary, greater than that which they can exercise in Great Britain. Recent
                    instances are the Peace Preservation Act, 1881, and the Prevention of Crime Act,
                    1882. The provisions of the English Act of 1879 as to children were extended to
                    Ireland by 47 and 48 Vict. c. 19.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States.—</hi> By Art. III. s. 2 of the constitution the
                    trial of all crimes, except in cases of impeachment, is to be by jury. By Art.
                    V. of the amendments no person can be held to answer for a capital or otherwise
                    infamous crime unless on a presentment or indictment of a grand jury.
                    Considerable changes have been made by State legislation in the direction of
                    enlarging the powers of courts of summary jurisdiction. (J. W+.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
