<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0175-0160-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SLOANE, Sir Hans (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    160)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4cr0j">Bequests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n175/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SLOANE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Hans</hi></label>
                    (1660-1753), a celebrated collector and successful physician, was born on 16th
                    April 1660 at Killileagh in county Down, Ireland, where his father had settled
                    at the head of a Scotch colony sent over by James I. He had as a youth a strong
                    turn for collecting objects of natural history and other curiosities. This led
                    him to the study of medicine, which he went to London to pursue, directing his
                    attention assiduously to botany, materia medica, and pharmacy. His collecting
                    propensities made him useful to the more philosophically minded Ray and Boyle,
                    and procured him their patronage. After four years in London he travelled
                    through France, spending some time at Paris and Montpellier, and taking his M.D.
                    degree at the university of Orange. He returned to London with a considerable
                    collection of plants and other curiosities, of which the former were sent to Ray
                    and utilized by him for his <hi rend="italic">History of Plants.</hi> Sloane was
                    quickly elected into the Royal Society, and at the same time he had the good
                    fortune to attract the notice of Sydenham, who took a fancy to him and gave him
                    valuable introductions to practice. In 1687 he became fellow of the College of
                    Physicians, and took the opportunity of proceeding to Jamaica the same year as
                    physician in the suite of the duke of Albemarle. The duke died soon after
                    landing, and Sloane’s visit lasted only fifteen months; but during that time he
                    got together about 800 new species of plants, the island being at the time
                    virgin ground to the botanist. Of these he published an elaborate catalogue in
                    Latin; and at a later date (1707-25) he made the experiences of his visit the
                    subject of two sumptuous folio volumes. His merits as a collector were
                    sufficient to give him a high place in the scientific circles of the time. He
                    became secretary to the Royal Society in 1693, and edited its <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transactions</hi> for twenty years. His practice as a physician among the upper
                    classes was large and lucrative; he is said to have inspired the members of the
                    court and aristocracy with the “greatest confidence in his prescriptions.” In
                    the pamphlets written concerning Dr Cockburn’s sale of a secret remedy for
                    dysentery and other fluxes, it was stated for the defence that Sloane himself
                    did not disdain the same kind of professional conduct; and there is some colour
                    given to that charge by the fact that his only medical piece, an <hi
                    rend="italic">Account of a Medicine for Soreness, Weakness, and other Distempers
                    of the Eyes</hi> (London, 1745) was not given to the world until its author was
                    in his eighty-fifth year, and had retired from practice.</p>
                <p>On the accession of George I. Sloane was made physician-general to the army, and
                    in 1716 was created a baronet, being the first medical practitioner to receive
                    an hereditary title. In 1719 he became president of the College of Physicians,
                    and held the office sixteen years. In 1727 he succeeded Sir Isaac Newton in the
                    presidential chair of the Royal Society; he retired from it at the age of
                    eighty, “much against the inclination of that respectable body, who chose Martin
                    Folkes to succeed him, and in a public assembly thanked him for the great and
                    eminent services which he had rendered them.” Sloane’s memory survives more by
                    his judicious investments than by anything that he contributed to the
                    subject-matter of natural science or even of his own profession; his name is
                    absolutely unknown in the history of medicine, and his services to botany were
                    such as, in the nature of things, would be soon forgotten. But his purchase of
                    the manor of Chelsea has perpetuated his memory in the name of a “place,” a
                    street, and a square. His great stroke as a collector was to acquire (by
                    bequest, conditional on paying off certain debts) in 1701 the cabinet of William
                    Courten, who had made collecting the business of his life. When Sloane retired
                    from active work in 1741 his library and cabinet of curiosities, which he took
                    with him from Bloomsbury to his house in Chelsea, had grown to be very extensive
                    and of unique value. On his death on 11th January 1753 he bequeathed his books,
                    manuscripts, prints, drawings, pictures, medals, coins, seals, cameos, and other
                    curiosities to the nation, on condition that parliament should pay to his
                    executors &lt;£20,000, which was a good deal less than the value of the
                    collection. The bequest was accepted on those terms by an Act passed the same
                    year, and the collection, together with George II.’s royal library, &amp;c., was
                    opened to the public at Bloomsbury as the British Museum in 1759. Among his
                    other acts of benevolence or munificence may be mentioned his gift to the
                    Apothecaries’ Company of the freehold of the botanical or physic garden, which
                    they had rented from the Chelsea estate since 1673, also his help in starting
                    the foundling hospital. Sloane is described as having been a man of considerable
                    presence and of courtly address.</p>
                <p>See Weld, <hi rend="italic">History of the Royal Society,</hi> i. 450 (London,
                    1848); and Munk, <hi rend="italic">Roll of the College of Physicians,</hi> 2d
                    ed., i. 466 (London, 1878).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
