<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0082-0067-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SILURIDAe (9th edition, volume 22, page 67)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xg7p">Gills</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942722">Gills</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980379">Isthmuses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207034">Mississippi</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n82/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SILURIDAe</label>, a large family of freshwater Fishes,
                    flourishing in the present epoch, and represented by a great variety of forms in
                    all the tropical and temperate regions, many of them reaching back into the
                    Tertiary age. The principal characters of this family (termed a “suborder” by
                    some), its position in the system, its geographical distribution, and some of
                    the most remarkable points in the structure and life-history of its members have
                    been already sufficiently noticed under <hi rend="smallcaps">Ichthyology,</hi>
                    but we have here to notice more fully the sections into which it has been
                    divided, and certain remarkable forms which were referred to nominally only in
                    that article.</p>
                <p>The modifications of the vertical fins, or rather the specialization of certain
                    portions at the expense of others, and the greater or less extent of the
                    branchial aperture form excellent characters for subdividing the Siluroids.</p>
                <p>I. In the <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Homalopterae</hi> the vertical fins are
                    exceedingly long, occupying nearly the whole extent of the embryonal fin, and in
                    one genus <hi rend="italic">(Heterobranchus)</hi> a great part of the dorsal
                    portion retains its embryonic character, being a rayless adipose fin. All the
                    Siluroids of this section belong to the fauna of the Old World and Australia.
                    The rivers and lakes of tropical Africa harbour many species of the genera <hi
                    rend="italic">Clarias</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Heterobranchus,—</hi> those of
                    the Nile being known under the name of “Carmoot.” One of the Nilotic species,
                    <hi rend="italic">Clarias macracanthus,</hi> occurs abundantly in the Lake of
                    Galilee, and, being a long, scaleless, eel-like fish of black colour, with eight
                    long barbels round its broad mouth, was certainly included among those which the
                    Jews were forbidden to eat by the Mosaic law. These fish grow to a length of
                    from 4 to 6 feet, and are eaten by the natives of tropical Africa.</p>
                <p>II. In the <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Heteropterae</hi> the dorsal fin has
                    almost or entirely disappeared; only its foremost portion and a small adipose
                    remnant may be preserved; on the other hand the anal portion is retained in its
                    whole extent. The gill-membranes remain separate and overlap the isthmus. This
                    section likewise belongs to the fauna of the Old World, and includes, among many
                    others, the species which has given the name to the whole family, <hi
                    rend="italic">Silurus glanis,</hi> the “Wels”</p>
                <p>of the Germans. It is the only representative of the family in Europe, and with
                    the exception of the sturgeon, is the largest freshwater fish of the Continent.
                    It was known to Aristotle, who described it under the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Glanis.</hi> It inhabits more the central and eastern portions of Europe than
                    the western, being absent in Italy, Greece, southern Switzerland, France, and
                    those parts of Germany which are drained by the Rhine and its affluents. In
                    general appearance it somewhat resembles the burbot. Its head is large<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n83/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0083-0068"/> and broad, its mouth wide, furnished with six
                    barbels, of which those of the upper jaw are very long. Both jaws and the palate
                    are armed with broad bands of small closely-set teeth, which give the bones a
                    rasp-like appearance. The eyes are exceedingly small. The short body terminates
                    in a long, compressed, muscular tail, and the whole fish is covered with a
                    smooth, scaleless, slippery skin. Specimens of 4 and 5 feet in length, and of 50
                    to 80 lb in weight, are of common occurrence. Its food consists chiefly of other
                    bottom-feeding fishes, and in inland countries it is considered one of the
                    better class of food fishes. Stories about children having been found in the
                    stomach of very large individuals are probably inventions.</p>
                <p>III. The <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Anomalopterae</hi> are a small section from
                    tropical America, in which the dorsal and adipose fins are very short and belong
                    to the caudal vertebral column, while the anal is very long, and the
                    gill-membranes are entirely separate, overlapping the isthmus.</p>
                <p>IV. The <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Proteropterae</hi> are a section extremely
                    numerous in species, and represented throughout the tropics. The dorsal fin
                    consists of a short-rayed and an adipose portion, the former belonging to the
                    abdominal vertebral column; the anal is always much shorter than the tail. The
                    gill-membranes are not confluent with the skin of the isthmus; they have a free
                    posterior margin. When a nasal barbel is present, it belongs to the posterior
                    nostril. This section includes among many others the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bagrus,</hi> of which the “Bayad” <hi rend="italic">(B. bayad)</hi> and
                    “Docmac” <hi rend="italic">(B. docmac)</hi> frequently come under the notice of
                    travellers on the Nile; they grow to a length of 5 feet, and are eaten. Of the
                    “Cat-Fishes” of North America <hi rend="italic">(Amiurus),</hi> locally called
                    “bull-heads” or “horned-pouts,” with eight barbels, some twenty species are
                    known. Some of them are valued as food, especially one which is abundant in the
                    ponds of New England, and capable of easy introduction into other localities (A.
                    <hi rend="italic">nebulosus).</hi> Others which inhabit the great lakes <hi
                    rend="italic">(A. nigricans)</hi> and the Mississippi <hi rend="italic">(A.
                    ponderosus)</hi> often exceed the weight of 100 lb. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Platystoma</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pimelodus</hi> people the rivers and
                    lakes of tropical America, and many of them are conspicuous in this fauna by the
                    ornamentation of their body, by long spatulate snouts, and by their great size.
                    The genus <hi rend="italic">Arius</hi> is composed of the greatest number of
                    species (about seventy), and has the widest distribution of all Siluroids, being
                    represented in almost all tropical countries which are drained by large rivers.
                    Some of the species enter salt water. They possess six barbels, and their head
                    is extensively osseous on its upper surface; their dorsal and pectoral spines
                    are generally developed into powerful weapons. <hi rend="italic">Bagarius,</hi>
                    one of the largest Siluroids of the rivers of India and Java, exceeding a length
                    of 6 feet, differs from <hi rend="italic">Arius</hi> in having eight barbels,
                    and the head covered with skin.</p>
                <p>V. In the <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Stenobranchiae</hi> the dorsal fin consists
                    of an adipose portion and a short-rayed fin which belongs to the abdominal
                    vertebral column, and, like the adipose fin, may be sometimes absent. The
                    gill-membranes are ∞nfluent with the skin of the isthmus. The Siluroids
                    belonging to this section are either South-American or African. Among the former
                    we notice specially the genus <hi rend="italic">Doras,</hi> which is
                    distinguished by having a series of bony scutes along the middle of the side.
                    The narrowness of their gill-openings appears to have developed in them a habit
                    which has excited the attention of all naturalists who have visited the
                    countries bordering upon the Atlantic rivers of tropical America, viz., the
                    habit of travelling during seasons of drought from a piece of water about to dry
                    up to ponds of greater capacity. These journeys are occasionally of such a
                    length that the fish have to travel all night; they are so numerous that the
                    Indians fill many baskets of them. Hancock supposes that the fish carry a small
                    supply of water with them in their gill-cavity, which they can easily retain by
                    closing their branchial apertures. The same naturalist adds that they make
                    regular nests, in which they cover up their eggs with care and defend them,—male
                    and female uniting in this parental duty until the eggs are hatched. <hi
                    rend="italic">Syngdontis</hi> is an African genus and common in the Nile, where
                    the various species are known by the name of “Shal.” They frequently occur among
                    the representations of animals left by the ancient Egyptians. The upper part of
                    their head is protected by strong osseous scutes, and both the dorsal and
                    pectoral fins are armed with powerful spines. Their mouth is small, surrounded
                    by six barbels, which are more or less fringed with a membrane or with branched
                    tentacles. Finally, the Electric Cator Sheath-Fishes (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Malapterurus)</hi> also belong to this section. Externally they are at once
                    recognized by the absence of a rayed dorsal fin, of which only a rudiment
                    remains as a small interneural spine concealed below the skin. The entire fish
                    is covered with soft skin, an osseous defensive armour having become unnecessary
                    in consequence of the development of a powerful electric apparatus, the strength
                    of which, however, is exceeded by that of the electric eel and the large species
                    of <hi rend="italic">Torpedo.</hi> It has been noticed in vol. xii. p. 650.
                    Three species have been described from rivers of tropical Africa, of which one
                    (<hi rend="italic">M</hi>. <hi rend="italic">electricus)</hi> occurs in the
                    Nile; it rarely reaches a length of 4 feet.</p>
                <p>VI. The section of <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Proteropodes</hi> contains small
                    forms, some of which are of interest by the degree of specialization to which
                    they have attained in one or the other direction. Many of them are completely
                    mailed; but all have in common a short-rayed dorsal fin, with the ventrals below
                    or rarely in front of it. Their gill-openings are reduced to a short slit; their
                    pectorals and ventrals have assumed a horizontal position; and their vent is
                    before, or not much behind, the middle of the length of the body. The first
                    group of this section comprises alpine forms of the Andes, without any armature,
                    and with a very broad and pendent lower lip. They have been referred to several
                    genera (<hi rend="italic">Stygogenes, Arges, Brontes, Astroplebus),</hi> but are
                    collectively called “preñadillas” by the natives, who state that they live in
                    subterranean craters within the bowels of the volcanoes of the Andes, and are
                    ejected with streams of mud and water during eruptions. These fishes may,
                    however, be found in surface waters at all times, and their appearance in great
                    quantities in the low country during volcanic eruptions can be accounted for by
                    numbers being killed by the sulphuretted gases which escape during an eruption
                    and<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n84/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0084-0069"/> by their being swept down with the torrents of
                    water issuing from the volcano. The lowland forms have their body encased in
                    large scutes, either rough, scale-like, and arranged in four or five series <hi
                    rend="italic">(Chaetostomus),</hi> or polished, forming broad rings round the
                    slender and depressed tail (<hi rend="italic">Loricaria,</hi> fig. 4), or
                    polished and large, so as to form two series only along the body and short tail
                    <hi rend="italic">(Callichthys,</hi> fig. 5). In India this sec tion is but
                    sparsely represented, chiefly in mountainstreams, by small loach-like Siluroids,
                    in which various kinds of peculiar apparatus are developed to enable them to
                    hold on to stones, this preventing their being swept away by the current; in <hi
                    rend="italic">Pseudecheneis</hi> the adhesive apparatus consists of transverse
                    plaits of the skin on the thorax between the pectoral fins; in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ex</hi><hi rend="italic">ostoma</hi> the mouth is modified in to a sucto rial
                    organ, probably with the same func tion. Finally, the South-American genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Aspredo,</hi> which is remarkable for the peculiar mode of
                    protecting its eggs, as mentioned in vol. xii. p. 660, belongs also to this
                    section.</p>
                <p>VII. The small section of <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Opisthopterae</hi>
                    comprises South-American forms, the majority of which inhabit waters at high
                    altitudes up to 14,000 feet above the level of the sea. All have a short-rayed
                    dorsal fin, placed above or behind the middle of the length of the body, above
                    or behind the ventrals, which may be absent. Also the anal is short. The
                    nostrils are remote from each other, and the gill-membranes are not confluent
                    with the skin of the isthmus. These little fishes, of which <hi rend="italic"
                    >Trichomycterus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nematogenys</hi> are the principal
                    genera, replace in the Andes the loaches of the northern hemisphere; they
                    resemble them in appearance and habits, and even in coloration, offering a
                    striking illustration of the fact that similar forms of animals are produced
                    under similar external physical conditions.</p>
                <p>VIII. Finally, the <hi rend="italic">Siluridae Branchicolae</hi> comprise the
                    smallest and least developed members of the family; they are referred to two
                    genera only from South America, <hi rend="italic">Stegophilus</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Vandellia,</hi> the smallest of which does not exceed the length
                    of 2 inches. Their body is soft, narrow, cylindrical, and elongate; the dorsal
                    and anal fins short; the vent far behind the middle of the length of the body;
                    gill-membranes confluent with the skin of the isthmus. Each maxillary is
                    provided with a small barbel; and the gill-covers are armed with short stiff
                    spines. Their small size notwithstanding, these Siluroids are well known to the
                    Brazilians, who accuse them of entering and ascending the urethra of persons
                    while bathing, causing inflammation and sometimes death. They certainly live
                    parasitically in the gill-cavity of large Siluroids, probably entering those
                    cavities for places of safety, but without drawing any nourishment from their
                    hosts. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. c. g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
