<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0601-0578-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">STOTHARD, Thomas (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    578)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23k3t">Novelists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0671r">Heaths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1039684">Novelists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1089970">Rape</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891253">Design</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n601/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">STOTHARD, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>
                    (1755-1834), subject painter, was born in London on August 17, 1755, the son of
                    a well-to-do innkeeper in Long Acre. Being a delicate child, he was sent at the
                    age of five to a relative in Yorkshire, and attended school at Acomb, and
                    afterwards at Tadcastle and at Ilford in Essex. Showing a turn for drawing he
                    was apprenticed to a draughtsman of patterns for brocaded silks in Spitalfields,
                    and during his leisure hours he attempted illustrations to the works of his
                    favourite poets. Some of these drawings were praised by Harrison, the editor of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Novelist’s Library,</hi> and, Stothard’s master having
                    died, he resolved to devote himself to art. In 1778 he became a student of the
                    Royal Academy, of which he was elected associate in 1791, full academician in
                    1794, and librarian in 1817. He married before he was thirty; and it is recorded
                    that, after attending the wedding ceremony, he spent the afternoon in quietly
                    drawing in the schools, and, on leaving, requested a fellow student to accompany
                    him “to a family party.” “Do come,” he said, “for I have this day taken unto
                    myself a wife.” He died in London on the 27th of April 1834.</p>
                <p>Among his earliest book illustrations are plates engraved for <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ossian</hi> and for <hi rend="italic">Bell's Poets·,</hi> and in 1780 he became
                    a regular contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Novelist's Library,</hi> for
                    which he executed one hundred and forty-eight designs, including his eleven
                    admirable illustrations to <hi rend="italic">Peregrine Pickle</hi> and his
                    graceful subjects from <hi rend="italic">Clarissa</hi> and Sir <hi rend="italic"
                    >Charles Grandison.</hi> Soon his hands were full of work, for all commissions
                    were welcome to him. He contentedly designed plates for pocket-books, tickets
                    for concerts, illustrations to almanacs, portraits of popular players,—and into
                    even the slightest and most trivial sketches he infused a grace and distinction
                    which render them of value to the collectors of the present time. Among his more
                    important series are the two sets of illustrations to <hi rend="italic">Robinson
                    Crusoe,</hi> and the plates to <hi rend="italic">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>
                    (1788), to <hi rend="italic">The Rape of the Lock</hi> (1798), to the works of
                    Gessner (1802), to Cowper’s <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1825), and to <hi
                    rend="italic">The Decameron·,</hi> while his figure-subjects in the superb
                    editions of Roger’s <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi> (1830) and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poems</hi> (1834) prove that even in latest age his fancy was still unexhausted
                    and his hand hardly at all enfeebled. He is at his best in subjects of a
                    domestic or a gracefully ideal sort; the heroic and the tragic were beyond his
                    powers. The designs by Stothard have been estimated by Mr Wornum to number five
                    thousand, and of these about three thousand have been engraved. His oil pictures
                    are usually small in size, and rather sketchy in handling. Their colouring is
                    often rich and glowing, being founded upon the practice of Rubens, of whom
                    Stothard was a great admirer. He was a contributor to Boydell's <hi
                    rend="italic">Shakespeare Gallery,</hi> but his best-known painting is the
                    Procession of the Canterbury Pilgrims, the engraving from which, begun by
                    Schiavonetti and finished by Heath, attained an immense popularity. It was
                    followed by a companion work, the Flitch of Bacon, which was drawn in sepia for
                    the engraver, but was never carried out in colour.</p>
                <p>In addition to his easel pictures. Stothard adorned the grand<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n602/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0602-0579"/> staircase of Burleigh House with subjects of War,
                    Intemperance, and the Descent of Orpheus in Hell (1799-1803); the mansion of
                    Hafod, North Wales, with a series of scenes from Froissart and Monstrelet
                    (1810); the cupola of the upper hall of the Advocates’ Library, Edinburgh (now
                    occupied by the Signet Library), with Apollo and the Muses, and figures of
                    poets, orators, &amp;c. (1822); and he prepared designs for a frieze and other
                    decorations for St James’s Palace. He also designed the magnificent shield
                    presented to the duke of Wellington by the merchants of London, and executed
                    with his own hand a series of eight etchings from the various subjects which
                    adorned it.</p>
                <p>An interesting, but most indiscriminately eulogistic biography of Stothard, by
                    his daughter-in-law Mrs Bray, was published in 1851.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
