<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0312-0291-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SOZOMEN (9th edition, volume 22, page 291)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m3m">Caves</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957686">Historians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814376">Arianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n312/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SOZOMEN</label>, church historian. Hermias Salamanes
                    (Salaminius) Sozomenus came of a wealthy family of Palestine, and it is
                    exceedingly probable that he himself was born (not later than 400 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> and brought up there, —in Gaza or the neighbourhood.
                    What he has to tell us of the history of South Palestine was derived from oral
                    tradition. His grandfather, as he himself tells us, lived at Bethel near Gaza,
                    and became a Christian, probably under Constantius, through the influence of
                    Hilarion, who among his other miracles had miraculously healed an acquaintance
                    of the grandfather, one Alaphion. Both men with their families became zealous
                    Christians and conspicuous for their virtues. The historian’s grandfather became
                    within his own circle a highly esteemed interpreter of Scripture, and held fast
                    his profession even in the time of Julian. The descendants of the wealthy
                    Alaphion founded churches and convents in the district, and were particularly
                    active in promoting monasticism. Sozomen himself had conversed with one of
                    these, a very old man. He was brought up under monkish influences; so he
                    expressly states, and his history bears him out. As a man he retained the
                    impressions of his youth, and his great work was to be also a monument of his
                    reverence for the monks in general and for the disciples of Hilarion in
                    particular. He became a lawyer and advocate in Constantinople, where as such he
                    wrote his Έ <hi rend="italic">κκλησιαστικὴ</hi> 'I <hi rend="italic">στωρία</hi>
                    about the year 440. The nine books of which it is composed begin with
                    Constantine and come down to the death of Honorius (423); but according to his
                    own statement the author intended to continue it as far as the year 439. From
                    Sozomen himself (iv. 17), and statements of his excerptors Nicephorus and
                    Theophanes, it can be made out that the work did actually come down to that
                    year, and that consequently it has reached us only in a somewhat mutilated
                    condition, at least half a book being wanting. A flattering and bombastic
                    dedication to Theodosius II. is prefixed. When compared with the history of <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Socrates</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v)</hi> it is plainly seen to
                    be a plagiarism from that work, and that on a large scale. Some three-fourths of
                    the<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n313/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0922-0313-0292"/> materials, essentially in the same arrangement,
                    have simply been appropriated from his predecessor without his being so much as
                    named even once, the other sources to which Sozomen was indebted being, however,
                    expressly cited. All that can be said to the credit of Sozomen is that he has
                    been himself at the trouble to refer to the principal sources used by Socrates
                    (Rufinus, Eusebius, Athanasius, Sabinus, the collections of epistles,
                    Palladius), and has not unfrequently supplemented Socrates from them, and also
                    that he has adduced some new authorities, in particular sources relating to
                    Christianity in Persia, Arian history, monkish histories, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vita Martini</hi> of Sulpicius, books of Hilarius; the whole of the ninth book
                    is entirely drawn from Olympiodorus.</p>
                <p>It is difficult to discern the motive for a work which was merely an enlarged
                    edition of Socrates. But it is probable that Sozomen did not approve of
                    Socrates’s freer attitude towards Greek science, and that he wished to present a
                    picture in which the clergy should be still further glorified, and, above all,
                    monasticism brought into still stronger prominence. In Sozomen everything is a
                    shade more ecclesiastical—but only a shade—than in Socrates. Perhaps also he
                    wrote for a different circle,— say, the monks in Palestine,—and could be sure
                    that in it the work of his predecessor would not be known.</p>
                <p>Sozomen is everywhere an inferior Socrates. What in Socrates still betrays some
                    vestiges of historical sense, his moderation, his reserve in questions of dogma,
                    his impartiality,—all this is wanting in Sozomen. In many cases he has repeated
                    the exact words of Socrates, but with him they have passed almost into mere
                    phrases. The inferiority of Sozomen to Socrates as an historian appears as much
                    in the manner in which he transcribed him as in those passages where he
                    introduces something new. The chronological scrupulosity of the earlier writer
                    has made no impression on his follower; he has either wholly omitted or
                    inaccurately repeated the chronological data. He writes more wordily and
                    diffusely. In his characterizations of persons, borrowed from Socrates, he is
                    more dull and colourless. After Socrates he has indeed repeated the caution not
                    to be too rash in discerning the linger of God; but his way of looking at things
                    is throughout mean and rustic. Two souls inhabit his book: one, the better, is
                    borrowed from Socrates; another, the worse, is his own. Wherever he abandons his
                    leader he frequently falls into mere retailing of stories, and prostrates
                    himself in reverence before the poorest products of the religious fantasy of a
                    degenerating age. Evidence of a boundless credulity with regard to all sorts of
                    monkish fables is to be met with everywhere. Raisings of the dead are quite
                    common occurrences with him, and he repeatedly gives accounts of enormous
                    dragons. In the finding of the bones of saints he takes the highest interest,
                    and even believes in the rediscovery of the tombs of the Old Testament
                    prophets.</p>
                <p>Where we still possess Socrates’s account that of Sozomen very seldom has any
                    consequence, but some of the additions he has made are instructive and
                    important. The number of new acts of councils introduced by him is small. His
                    monkish histories are as sources almost utterly valueless; his account of the
                    Christians in Persia absolutely swarms with mistakes. It must, however, be noted
                    that for the period from Theodosius I. onward he has emancipated himself more
                    fully from Socrates and has followed Olympiodorus in part, partly also oral
                    tradition; here accordingly his statements possess greater value.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Editions and Literature.—</hi> Socrates and Sozomen have been
                    edited by Stephanus (Paris, 1544; Geneva, 1612), Valesius (Paris, 1659-73),
                    Reading (Cambridge, 1720), Hussey (Oxford, 1853, 1860). They are also to be
                    found in vol. lxvii. of Migne’s <hi rend="italic">Patrologia,</hi> and there is
                    an Oxford school edition (1844) after Reading. Bright edited Socrates according
                    to the text of Hussey in 1878. There are “Testimonia Veterum” in Valesius; and
                    Nolte’s papers in <hi rend="italic">Tubing. Quartalschr.,</hi> (1859) p. 518 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.,</hi> (1861) p. 417 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> contain
                    emendations in Hussey’s text, and notes towards the history of the text and
                    editions; see also Overbeck, in <hi rend="italic">Theol. Lit. Ztung.</hi>
                    (1879), No. 20.</p>
                <p>Special studies have been made by Baronius, Miraeus, Labbé, Valesius, Halloix,
                    Scaliger, Ceillier, Cave, Dupin, Pagi, Ittig, Tillemont, Walch, Gibbon,
                    Schroeckh, Lardner. See also Voss, <hi rend="italic">De Histor. Graecis·,</hi>
                    Fabricius-Harless, <hi rend="italic">Biblioth. Gr.,</hi> vol. vii.; Rössler, <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliothek d. Kirchenväter;</hi> Holzhausen, <hi rend="italic">De
                    Fontibus quibus Socr., Soz., ac Theod. in scribenda Historia Sacra usi
                    sunt,</hi> (Göttingen, 1825; Stäudlin, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. u. Lit. d.
                    K.-G.,</hi> Hanover, 1827; Baur, <hi rend="italic">Epochen</hi> (1825); Hamack,
                    “Socr. u. Soz.,” in Herzog-Plitt's <hi rend="italic">Theol. Encykl.</hi>
                    Detached details are given also in works upon Constantine (Manso), Julian
                    (Mücke, Rode, Neumann, Rendall), Damasus (Rade), Arianism (Gwatkin’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Studies of Arianism,</hi> 1882, gives a severe but trustworthy
                    criticism of Rufinus and discusses the manner in which Socrates was related to
                    him), the emperors after Julian (De Broglie, Richter, Clinton, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Weltgeschichte</hi> of Ranke, the <hi rend="italic">Gesch. d.
                    Kaiser Arcadius u. Theod. II.,</hi> 1885, of Güldenpenning, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Kaiser Theodosius d. Gr.,</hi> Halle, 1878, of Iffland, the
                    last-named work discussing the relation of Socrates to Sozomen), the barbarian
                    migrations (Wietersheim, Dahn), the Goths (Waitz, Bessel, Kauffmann, and Scott’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Ulfilas,</hi> 1885). Lastly, reference may be made to
                    Rosenstein, <hi rend="italic">Forsch.</hi> z. <hi rend="italic">deutsch.
                    Gesch.,</hi> vol. i.,— <hi rend="italic">Krit.</hi></p>
                <p>Untersuch. üb. d. Verhältnis* zu Olympiodor, Zosimus, u. Soz.; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sarrazin,</hi> De Theodoro Lectore, Theophanis Fonte Praecipuo, <hi
                    rend="italic">1881 (treats of the relation bet ween Socrates and Sozomen, and of
                    the completeness of the former’s work); Jeep,</hi> Quellenuntersuch. z. d.
                    griech. Kirchenhistorikern, <hi rend="italic">Leipsic, 1884. (A HA.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
