<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0922-0246-0231-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SOCOTRA, or Socotora (9th edition, volume 22, page
                    231)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4td9ng4n">Polo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit22newyrich/page/n246/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SOCOTRA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Socotora</hi></label>
                    (Arabic <hi rend="italic">Sokotrá),</hi> an island of the Indian Ocean, 150
                    miles from Cape Gardafιιi and about 220 from the Arabian coast. Its length from
                    east to west is 71 miles, its greatest breadth 22. A plain 2 to 4 miles wide
                    skirts the greater part of the coast, while the interior is mountainous. The
                    granite peaks behind Tamarída (a village on the north coast and the chief place
                    in the island, but now much decayed) rise to a height of 4000 feet, and a
                    limestone chain connected with these runs north and south with an average height
                    of about 1900 feet. The climate is moist, but not unhealthy, with much rain,
                    especially during the south-west monsoon. At this season the temperature rises
                    to 80° or even 95°, but on the whole the heat is not excessive. The scenery of
                    the island is very striking, with bare rocky heights and fertile valleys; but
                    there is little cultivation, the inhabitants living mainly by their vast flocks
                    of sheep and goats, or on dates, homegrown and imported. Milch cows are numerous
                    near Tamarída. The population is about 5000, of two distinct types. The nomad
                    inhabitants of the uplands are a peculiar race, well built, with good features
                    and long curling but not woolly hair; they resemble neither the Arabs nor the
                    Somál. In Tamarída and other villages and towards the eastern end of the island
                    the population is a mixture of Arab, African, and other elements, even including
                    Portuguese. The native speech is not intelligible to ordinary Arabs, but
                    Wellsted says that it can sometimes be made out by Arabs from the opposite
                    (Mahra) coast. In fact, according to Ibn Mojáwir and Hamdání, the Socotrans in
                    the Middle Ages were regarded as Mahra and spoke the Mahra dialect. Their way of
                    life is rude and simple in the extreme, but they are hospitable and generally
                    well-behaved, though they have almost no government; they are nominally
                    dependent on the sultan of Keshin. A certain dependence (at least of places on
                    the coast) on some sovereign of the Arabian coast has endured for many
                    centuries, except during the short Portuguese occupation of Tamarída by
                    Albuquerque. From 1876 to 1886 the sultan of Keshin was bound by treaty not to
                    cede the island to a foreign power or allow settlements on it without the
                    consent of England. In 1886 it was formally annexed by Great Britain.</p>
                <p>The fauna and flora of Socotra are peculiar. As regards mammalia the civet cat is
                    found, but the ordinary wild beasts of Arabia are unknown. The flora was studied
                    by Professor Bailey Balfour in 1880, and his account of it is about to be
                    published by the Royal Society of Edinburgh. The most valuable vegetable
                    products are now, as in the Middle Ages, aloes and dragon’s-blood. The Socotran
                    aloes (the French <hi rend="italic">chicotin)</hi> is esteemed the best in the
                    world when unadulterated. In old times the ambergris of Socotra was also
                    famous.</p>
                <p>Socotra was known to the ancients as the isle of Dioscorides; this name, and that
                    by which the island is now known, are usually traced back to a Sanscrit form,
                    Dvípa-Sakhádhára, “the island abode of bliss,” which again suggests an
                    identification with the <hi rend="italic">vησoι εὐδαίµovες</hi> of Agatharchides
                    (§ 103). The <hi rend="italic">Periplus</hi> of the Erythraean Sea speaks of the
                    island as peopled only in one part by a mixed race of Arab, Indian, and Greek
                    traders. It was subject to the king of the Incense Country, and was a
                    meeting-place of Arabian and Indian ships. Cosmas in the 6th century says that
                    the people spoke Greek and were largely Christian, with a bishop sent from
                    Persia. The Arab geographers also had a tradition of an early Greek settlement
                    (which they naturally ascribe to Alexander), but also of later Persian
                    influence, followed by a settlement of Mahra tribes, who partly adopted
                    Christianity. The Socotrans remained Nestorian Christians, with a bishop under
                    the metropolitan of Persia, through the Middle Ages (Assemani, <hi rend="italic"
                    >B. O.,</hi> ii. 459; comp. Mohallebí, in Abulfeda, p. 371); but in their
                    isolated position they have gradually lost all trace of Christianity except
                    reverence for the cross, and practise the old South Arabian moon worship. There
                    was much more at least of the forms of Christianity when Europeans first visited
                    the island in the 16th century. In the Middle Ages Socotra was a station of the
                    Indian corsairs who harassed the Arab trade with the far East. The population
                    seems then to have been much larger; Arabian writers estimate the fighting men
                    at 10,000.</p>
                <p>See, for the history of Socotra, Yule, <hi rend="italic">Marco Polo,</hi> ii. 400
                    <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> and, besides the authorities there cited, Yakut, <hi
                    rend="italic">s.v.</hi>; Hamdání, p. 52; Kazwíní, ii. 54. For the state of the
                    island at the beginning of the 18th century, see the account of the French
                    expedition to Yemen in 1708 (V <hi rend="italic">iaggio nell' Arabia
                    Felice,</hi> Venice, 1721); and, for the present century, Wellsted, <hi
                    rend="italic">City of the Caliphs,</hi> vol. ii. (1840). For the topography,
                    &amp;c., see <hi rend="italic">Red Sea Pilot,</hi> 2d ed., 1882.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
