<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0035-0026-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRACES (9th edition, volume 11, page 26)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g601">Myths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j62t">Legends</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944180">Goddesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1031678">Myth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995592">Legends</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970716">Indos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1919441">Ostara</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151519">Titanates</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n35/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRACES</label> is the name generally given to the Greek
                    goddesses Charites. The chief seat of their worship was the ancient Boeotian
                    city Orchomenus. They were three in number, but their names were not known; and
                    stones fallen from heaven stood in their temple as symbols of the goddesses
                    (Paus., ix. 35). Their worship was instituted by a king Eteocles, whose three
                    daughters fell into a well while dancing in honour of the Charites (Westermann,
                    <hi rend="italic">Myth. Gr.,</hi> p. 387). In no Greek legend is the pre-Greek
                    Indo-Germanic character more strongly marked. Eteocles, he whose glory is real,
                    is the Vedic Satyaçravas, the sun; and his genealogy consists of a string of
                    epithets for sun anl dawn. Charis (Skt. <hi rend="italic">han,</hi> bright), is
                    an old adjective, originally an epithet of the light-illumined clouds which seem
                    to escort the dawn, often applied in the Rig-Veda to the horses of the dawn or
                    of the sun, and at last growing into a distinct deity who preserves the
                    character of the ancient dawn-goddess (see Müller, <hi rend="italic">Led.
                    Laug.,</hi> ii.; Sonne in Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">Zft.,</hi> x.). The burning
                    bright <hi rend="italic">vasas</hi> (Ushas, τ)ως, Aurora, with a different
                    suffix Ostara, Easter) —who restores the blessings lost during the night, who
                    lights up what was dark and reveals the hidden wrong, who give3 active labour
                    and wealth to men, growth and fertility to plants—had been from the earliest
                    time the centre of a great worship To appearance these religious ceremonies have
                    been lost in Greece; and in a people so retentive of all that relates to
                    religion, this implies merely that the worship of the dawn has been changed in
                    outward form. Eos is of slight importance; but Charis, Hebe, Aphrodite (in so
                    far as the genuine Greek goddess has not given way to the Oriental deity)
                    preserve and develop the original idea. Charis then was the goddess of the
                    freshness and vigour of life, of fertility and growth; like Aphrodite, she
                    closely resembles Persephone (see Gerhard, <hi rend="italic">Venus
                    Proserpina'),</hi> and in later art the Graces often hold corn eιrs in their
                    hands; like Hebe, she is often associated with Hera (see Welcker, <hi
                    rend="italic">Gr. Gott.,</hi> iii. 174). The single goddess grew into a triad,
                    as occurs often in Greek mythology; in Sparta, however, and in Athens only two
                    Charites were known. Rites of peculiar antique character belong to the worship
                    of the Charites: in Orchomenus nightly dances took place in their honour
                    (compare the legend of Eteocles’s daughters, who obviously are bye forms of the
                    goddesses); in Paros their worship was celebrated without music or garlands; in
                    Messene they were worshipped along with the Eumenides; in Athens their rites
                    secret from the vulgar were held at the entrance of the Acropolis; one swore by
                    the Charites as one did by the deities of the lower world (Pollux, viii. 106).
                    Far as these characteristics seem removed from the nature of a dawn-goddess we
                    find a similar double character in many other cases, such as Artemis-Hecate.
                    They are thus brought into the cycle of older more purely nature worship, which
                    we find in Greece alongside of the more moral religion of the Olympian deities,
                    and which has in mythology its counterpart in the older generation of Titans
                    destroyed by the younger gods. The Charites were received into the Olympian
                    Pantheon only in a subordinate character. In Homer we have a transitional stage;
                    they appear sometimes as distinct independent beings, one being wife of
                    Hephaestus, another of Sleep (7Z., xviii. 382, xiv. 231); often they are a set
                    of nymphs attending on Aphrodite, herself then wife of Hepliaestus <hi
                    rend="italic">(Od.,</hi> viii. 364, &amp;c ). The dawn is naturally the wife of
                    Hephaestus, the fire of the sun in heaven and of the morning sacrifice on earth.
                    In later literature this second form prevails. Obviously the noun <hi
                    rend="italic">charis</hi> and the connected verbs and substantives, which
                    existed alongside of the mythological name, exercised a continually growing
                    influence on it. The Charites become then the impersonation of the bloom of all
                    sensuous appearance, of grace and cheerfulness, both in nature and in moral
                    action. They form part of the train attendant on the greater gods, especially
                    Aphrodite and Apollo. Their names, Aglaia, Euphrosyne, and Thalia, occur first
                    in Hesiod <hi rend="italic">(Theog.,</hi> 907). Pindar, however, following the
                    Boeotian belief, celebrates them <hi rend="italic">(Ol.,</hi> xiv.) as the
                    queens of glittering Orchomenus and as the guardian goddesses of the ancient
                    Minyae. In art they were represented in earlier time as draped goddesses with
                    varying attributes; gradually the one well-known conception predominated of the
                    three beautiful nude figures gracefully intertwined. Jacobi <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Wörter!).</hi><hi rend="italic">d. Myth.)</hi> gives a very complete list of
                    ancient authorities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
