<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0286-0273-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUJRÂNWÂLA (9th edition, volume 11, page 273)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1118436">Sikhs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n286/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUJRÂNWÂLA</label>, a British district in the Punjab, lying
                    between 31° 32' and 32° 33' N. lat., and between 73° 11' 30" and 74° 28' 15" E.
                    long., with an area (1877) of 2563 square miles, and population (1868) of
                    550,576. It is bounded on the N.W. by the river Chenâb, on the S. and S.E. by
                    the districts of Jhang and Lahore, and on the E. by the district of Siâlkot.
                    This district forms the central portion of the Rechna Doâb, intermediate between
                    the fertile submontane plains of Siâlkot and the desert expanses of Jhang. On
                    the northern frontier, a belt of alluvial land, some 2 to 6 miles in breadth,
                    fringes the Chenâb throughout its course.. The southern portion of the plateau
                    has a rich soil, with accessible water; the villages here lie close together,
                    while the people are careful and industrious cultivators. But further south the
                    ground becomes harder and drier until in the extreme south the <hi rend="italic"
                    >bar,</hi> a flat expanse of barren land, passes slowly into the desert of
                    Jhang. In the south-east corner of the district, the little river Degh irrigates
                    and fertilizes a tiny valley of its own. Two or three minor watercourses are
                    used for the purposes of irrigation in the villages through which they pass. The
                    country is very bare of trees, and the scenery throughout is tame and in the
                    central plateau becomes very monotonous.</p>
                <p>The district of Gujrânwâla is essentially a modern one; yet it can claim
                    considerable relics of the past, constructed during an early period of
                    prosperity. It seems likely that the district once contained the capital of the
                    Punjab, at an epoch when Lahore had not begun to exist. We learn from the
                    Chinese Buddhist pilgrim, Hiouen Thsang, that about the year 630 he visited a
                    town known as Tse-kia (or Tâki), the metropolis of the whole country of the five
                    rivers. A mound near the modern village of Asazur has been identified as the
                    site of the ancient capital. Until the Mahometan invasions little is known of
                    Gujrânwâla except that Tâki had fallen into oblivion and Lahore had become the
                    chief city. Under Mahometan rule the district flourished for a time; but a
                    mysterious depopulation fell upon the tract, and the whole region seems to have
                    been almost entirely abandoned. At the first beginning of the Sikh war, the
                    waste plains of Gujrânwâla were seized by various military adventurers. Charat
                    Sinh took possession of the village of Gujrânwâla, and here his grandson the
                    great mahârâjâ Ranjit Sinh was born. The Sikh rule, which was elsewhere so
                    disastrous, appears to have been an unmitigated benefit to this district. Ranjit
                    Sinh settled large colonies in the various villages, and encouraged cultivation
                    throughout the depopulated plain. In 1847 the district came under British
                    influence, in connexion with the regency at Lahore; and in 1849 it was included
                    in the territory annexed after the second Sikh war. Since that time Gujrânwâla
                    has enjoyed an immunity from the catastrophes of history, with the exception of
                    the events of 1857, which belong to the general annals of India.</p>
                <p>The population in 1868 numbered550,576 persons,—306,296males and 244,280 females.
                    In religion, the district is mainly Mahometan. There were five towns, namely,
                    Gujrânwâla, Wazirâbad, Râmnagar, Eminâbâd, and Akalgarh, with a population
                    aggregating 54,458 persons. The total cultivated area of the district amounts to
                    567,849 acres, while the cultivable margin reaches the high figure of 7θl,761
                    acres. The staple crop is wheat, which occupies one-third of the cultivated
                    area. The other products are—barley, gram, tobacco, oil-seeds, vegetables, rice,
                    Indian corn, pulses, cotton, and sugarcane. Irrigation is very general, 327,832
                    acres being artificially watered. The trade of the district is unimportant. The
                    chief exports are agricultural produce, brass vessels, leathern bottles, and
                    timber. The imports consist of salt, iron, cattle, spices, and English
                    piece-goods. A great religious fair is held at Dhonkal. The principal channel of
                    communication is the Northern State Railway from Lahore to Peshawar. The Grand
                    Trunk road, connecting the same two places, traverses the district for 42 miles.
                    There are 1055 miles of unmetalled road in Gujrânwâla, besides a number of local
                    by-ways. The Chenâb is navigable throughout for the boats of the country. The
                    revenue in 1871 was £53,560. In 1872-73 the district contained 12 civil and 19
                    magisterial courts. The total police force numbered 523 men, supplemented by
                    1092 village watchmen. Education is still very backward; the pupils in 1873
                    numbered in all 5818, maintained at a cost of £2469. The mean monthly
                    temperature in 1867 ranged from 53° in January to 95° in June. The average
                    rainfall for the eleven years ending 1867 was 24 inches. The prevalent diseases
                    are intermittent fever and small-pox. The death-rate in 1872 amounted to 12,592,
                    or 23 per thousand of the population.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gujranwala,</hi> the chief town and administrative
                    headquarters of the above district, in 32° 9' 30" N. 1at. and 74° 14' E. long.,
                    with a population in 1868 of 19,381. The town is situated on the Grand Trunk
                    road and Northern State Railway, 40 miles north of Lahore. It is of modern
                    creation, and owes its importance to the father and grandfather of Mahârâjâ
                    Ranjit Sinh, whose capital it formed during the early period of the Sikh power.
                    There is a mausoleum to Mâhan Sinh, father of Ranjit Sinh, and a lofty cupola
                    covers a portion of the ashes of the mahârâjâ himself. The civil station lies a
                    mile south-east of the native town. It contains the court-house, treasury, jail,
                    dispensary, post-office, staging bungalow, and church.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
