<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0358-0339-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUTZKOW, Karl (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    339)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:949496">Gurus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955408">Herding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841601">Bunding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mg3z">Socialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n358/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUTZKOW, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karl</hi></label> (1811-1878),
                    one of the most distinguished of modern German novelists and dramatists, was
                    born 17th March 1811 at Berlin, where his father held a clerkship in the war
                    office. After completing his education at the Friedrichswerder gymnasium, he
                    entered upon the study of theology and philosophy at the university of his
                    native town, where, having had his interest awakened by the political and social
                    questions of the time by the Paris revolution of July 1830, he, while still a
                    student, began his chequered literary career by the publication in 1831 of a
                    periodical entitled <hi rend="italic">Forum der Journalliteratur.</hi> Although,
                    as was to be expected, the serial was a failure and was soon discontinued, it
                    procured for him the notice of Wolfgang Menzel, who invited him to Stuttgart to
                    assist him in the editorship of the <hi rend="italic">Literaturblatt.</hi> At
                    the same time he continued his university studies, first at Jena, then at
                    Heidelberg, and latterly at Munich. In 1832 he published anonymously at Hamburg
                    <hi rend="italic">Briefe eines Narren an eine</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n359/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0359-0340"/><hi rend="italic">Hämin,</hi> and in 1833 appeared
                    at Stuttgart <hi rend="italic">Hαha-Guru,Geschichte eines Gottes,</hi> a
                    fantastic and satirical romance intended to ridicule the current conceptions of
                    the divine. In 1835, on account of a difference with Menzel, he discontinued his
                    contributions to the <hi rend="italic">Literaturblatt,</hi> and went to
                    Frankfort, where he became collaborateur with Duller on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phönix,</hi> and also founded the <hi rend="italic">Deutsche Revue.</hi> In the
                    same year appeared <hi rend="italic">Wally, die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Zweiflerin,</hi> from the publication of which may be said to date the school
                    of writers who, from their opposition not only to Romanticism but to all the
                    time-honoured literary, social, and religious traditions, have received the name
                    of “Young Germany.” The work was directed specially against the institution of
                    marriage and the belief in revelation; and whatever attention it might have
                    attracted from its own merits was tenfold increased by the action of the
                    Government, which, besides condemning its author to three months’ imprisonment,
                    decreed the suppression of all he had written or might yet write, and prohibited
                    him from exercising the functions of editor within the states of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bund.</hi> During his term of imprisonment Gutzkow employed
                    himself in the composition of his treatise <hi rend="italic">Zur</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">philosophie</hi><hi rend="italic">der Geschichte,</hi> published
                    at Hamburg in 1836, in which he opposed the Hegelian theory as to the nature and
                    ends of history. On obtaining his freedom he went to Frankfort, where, shortly
                    afterwards, he was married, and where he wrote several volumes on various
                    subjects which he published at Hamburg and Stuttgart ;' but finding himself
                    hampered in his literary undertakings by the prohibitions of the Prussian
                    Government, he removed in 1837 to Hamburg. Here he inaugurated a new epoch of
                    his literary activity by bringing out his tragedy <hi rend="italic">Richard
                    Savage,</hi> which immediately made the round of all the German theatres, and
                    first decidedly won the ear of Germany for the modern drama. Of his numern-ous
                    other plays the majority are now neglected; but a few have obtained an
                    established place in the repertory of the German theatre,—especially the
                    comedies <hi rend="italic">Zopf und Schwert</hi> (1844) and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Das Urbild des</hi><hi rend="italic">Tartuffe</hi> (1847), and the tragedy <hi
                    rend="italic">Uriel Acosta</hi> (1847); the deep tragic interest, fine dramatic
                    situations, and terse and pregnant diction of the last entitle it to rank among
                    the best dramas of modem times. In 1842 Gutzkow paid a visit to Paris, of which
                    he gave an account in <hi rend="italic">Briefe aus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Paris</hi> (Leipsic, 1842). After his return to Germany he resumed his stay at
                    Frankfort, where he was chiefly occupied in preparing for the press an edition
                    of his collected works, published in 12 volumes, 1845-46; but in 1847 he went to
                    Dresden, where he succeeded Tieck as director of the court theatre. About the
                    same time began that period of his literary activity to which belongs the series
                    of remarkable works of fiction intended to depict the action and tendency of the
                    principal intellectual, social, and religious forces in modern society. The
                    chief of these novels are <hi rend="italic">Die Ritter</hi><hi rend="italic">vom
                    Geiste</hi><hi rend="italic">(f)</hi> vols., Leipsic, 1850-52) and <hi
                    rend="italic">Der Zauberer von Rom</hi> (9 vols., Leipsic, 1859-61). The latter,
                    a study of Roman Catholic life in southern Germany, is generally regarded as his
                    masterpiece; and its vigorous and trenchant delineations of character are not
                    more notable than its keen analysis of the motives underlying religious
                    professions, and its subtle penetration into the characteristics and tendencies
                    of the various forms of religious opinion. In regard, however, to both works, it
                    may be objected that their great length, their somewhat tedious dallying over
                    unimportant details, the intricate nature of their plots, and the hampering
                    influence of their controversial purpose, lessen considerably the legitimate
                    effect of their many striking and original character portraits, their skilfully
                    arranged dialogues and frequently powerfully dramatic scenes, and the cunning
                    manner in which their incidents are blended into one whole. The success of <hi
                    rend="italic">Die Ritter</hi><hi rend="italic">vom Geiste</hi> suggested to
                    Gutzkow the establishment of a journal on the model of Dickens’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Household Words,</hi> entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Unterhaltungen</hi><hi rend="italic">am</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >häuslichen</hi><hi rend="italic">Herd,</hi> which first appeared in 1852, and
                    was continued till 1862. In 1864 he had an attack of insanity, during which he
                    made an attempt upon his life; and although after his recovery he continued to
                    write as voluminously as formerly, his productions show henceforth decided
                    traces of failing powers. To this period belong the historical novels <hi
                    rend="italic">Hohenschwangau</hi><hi rend="italic">(f&gt;</hi> vols. 1868) and
                    <hi rend="italic">Frits Ellrodt</hi> (3 vols. 1872); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lebenbilder</hi> (3 vols. 1870-72), consisting of autobiographic sketches; and
                    <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Sohne Pestalozzis</hi> (3 vols.
                    1870), the plot of which is founded on the story of Kaspar Hauser. On account of
                    a return of his nervous malady, Gutzkow in 1873 made a journey to Italy, and on
                    his return took up his residence in the country near Heidelberg. Although some
                    time before his death he had been confined to his sick chamber at Frankfort, its
                    occurrence, 16th December 1878, was due to accidental suffocation from
                    smoke.</p>
                <p>The writings of .Gutzkow suffer in character from the controversy which
                    embittered his life. His didactic purpose was too strong to allow his fine
                    artistic faculty full freedom of action, and notwithstanding his true dramatic
                    insight, firm grasp of character, rich vein of original thought, and wonderful
                    comprehension of the principles at work in modern society, he did not possess
                    that command of his materials which is necessary to mould them into poetic
                    completeness. But although his popularity has not been commensurate even with
                    his merits, no recent writer has exerted a more powerful influence on the
                    opinions of modern Germany; and if his works are not destined to live by virtue
                    of their inherent value, many of them will always be of interest as the mirror
                    in which the intellectual and social struggles of his time are best
                    reflected.</p>
                <p>An edition of Gutzkow’s collected works appeared at Jena, 1873— 76. Since his
                    death the issue of a popular edition has been undertaken, the first volume of
                    which, containing the autobiography of his boyhood and his miscellaneous poems,
                    has already appeared. His <hi rend="italic">Rückblicke auf mein Leben,</hi>
                    published in 1875, deals specially with that period of his life when he was
                    director of the Dresden theatre. A complete biography by Johannes Proelss is now
                    in process of preparation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
