<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0183-0172-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GREENOCK (9th edition, volume 11, page 172)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896024">Docks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dr26">Sketching</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25f3j">Docks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n183/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GREENOCK</label>, a seaport town of Renfrewshire, Scotland,
                    on the south bank of the Firth of Clyde, 22 miles below Glasgow, in <hi
                    rend="italic">55°</hi> 57' 2" N. lat. and 4° 45' 30" W. long. In front of the
                    town there is a fine and extensive bay, formerly known by the name of the Bay of
                    St Lawrence, from a religious house that anciently stood there. Behind the town
                    the land rises into a picturesque ridge of hills, about 800 feet high, between
                    which and the bay Greenock stretches for upwards of two miles and a half along
                    the shore.</p>
                <p>Greenock is an irregularly built town. The western part is occupied by spacious
                    streets and numerous fine villas, but the central and busier part is composed of
                    narrow and rather mean and overcrowded streets and lanes. The board of police
                    are taking measures, however, to have some of these opened up and occupied with
                    an improved class of buildings. The view from the heights behind the town is
                    exceedingly striking and picturesque; and notwithstanding the steep slopes
                    towards the south, the town is steadily progressing in that direction, as well
                    as along the shore, where premises for shipbuilding and various public works,
                    and also dwelling-houses, are extending the town both east and west. Amongst
                    noticeable structures may be enumerated the custom-house, a handsome Doric
                    edifice, and the Watt Monument, a building erected to the memory Of the
                    celebrated James Watt, whom with just pride the town claims as a native. The
                    latter contains an exquisite statue of the philosopher by Chantrey, and
                    accommodates a public library founded in 1783, having now upwards of 15,000
                    volumes. Associated with it is also a museum and lecture hall, built at the
                    expense of the late Mr James M‘Lean, and opened in 1876. The town also contains
                    several elegant churches, a spacious academy, and various other educational and
                    charitable institutions, the chief of the latter being the public hospital and
                    infirmary, and the Wood mariners’ asylum, an institution founded by Sir Gabriel
                    Wood for the benefit of decayed seamen belonging to Clyde ports. The corporation
                    is about to erect a suite of municipal buildings fronting the principal street
                    of the town, on which it is proposed to expend not less than £80,000. Greenock
                    possesses two public parks; and in 1866 a magnificent esplanade, a mile and a
                    quarter in length, skirting the shore, was laid off at an expense of £20,000,
                    and is now a favourite promenade and recreation ground. A new carriage-drive is
                    being constructed, at a cost of about £10,000, across the heights to the
                    south-west of the town.</p>
                <p>The water supply is derived from two enormous reservoirs in the high lands behind
                    the town called Loch Thom and Loch Gryfe. The Loch Thom works were completed in
                    1828, and the Gryfe works were added in 1873. The Loch Thom works are so
                    constructed that they not only supply water to the town, but provide also in
                    their course power to drive the machinery of a number of mills of great size,
                    the water descending from mill to mill till it reaches the level of ordinary
                    supply. Street tramways were introduced in 1873, and connect the town with
                    Gourock. The gasworks of the town, which were originally situated in a populous
                    district, have recently been removed to a small island, Inchgreen, on which a
                    commodious establishment has been erected. The principal industries are
                    shipbuilding and sugar-refining. Many of the steamers of the Cunard Company, the
                    Peninsular and Oriental Company, and the Allan Line have been built at Greenock,
                    and the excellence of the iron sailing ships of Greenock yards has become almost
                    proverbial. There are eighteen large sugar refineries in the town, some of which
                    turn out 1000 tons of refined sugar per week. Greenock is connected <hi
                    rend="italic">via</hi> Paisley with Glasgow by two competing lines of railway,
                    by one of which there is also direct communication with Ayrshire and the
                    south-west. All the important Clyde passenger steamers call at or sail from
                    Greenock; indeed for passenger traffic by steamer it is a more important town
                    than Glasgow, as the greater portion of the travelling public, to save time and
                    avoid the unsavoury odour of the upper reaches of the river, make the journey
                    between Glasgow and Greenock by rail. A large amount of passenger and goods
                    traffic is also carried on between Greenock and Belfast, Londonderry, Dublin,
                    Liverpool, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>In the earlier part of the 17th century Greenock was an obscure fishing village,
                    consisting of one row of thatched cottages; and in 1716 there were only six
                    slated houses in the place. In 1741 the population of Greenock was 4100; a
                    century later it was 38,846; in 1851, 39,391; in 1861, 42,785; in 1871, 57,825;
                    and in the middle of 1879 it was estimated in the Registrar-General’s reports at
                    76,955. In 1635 “the town or village of Greenock” was erected by Charles I. into
                    a burgh of barony under a charter granted in favour of John Schaw and Helen
                    Houston, his spouse, and down to 1741 the government of the burgh was
                    administered by the baron-bailie appointed by the superior. In 1741 and 1751
                    charters were granted by Sir John Schaw, under which feuars and sub-feuars were
                    empowered to elect a town council of nine members— two bailies, a treasurer, and
                    six councillors—for the good government of the town. Under these charters
                    Greenock possessed the most liberal burghal constitution enjoyed by any Scotch
                    burgh till the passing of the Reform Act—the first municipal election under the
                    provisions of which took place in 1833. Greenock was then advanced to the
                    position of a parliamentary burgh, with the right to return one representative
                    to parliament.. Municipally the town is divided into five wards, and the town
                    council consists of a provost, six bailies, a treasurer, and eight
                    councillors.</p>
                <p>The beginning of the harbour of Greenock was made by John Schaw, already
                    mentioned as the first superior of the burgh. Till the commencement of the 18th
                    century, however, it was little more than an insecure landing-place; but in 1703
                    an agreement was entered into between the superior and feuars of the town,
                    whereby he advanced money and they submitted to a voluntary assessment for the
                    extension and improvement of harbour accommodation.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n184/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0184-0173"/>
                <p>The harbour constructed under this agreement was not finished till 1710, in which
                    year Greenock was established as a customhouse port. In 1751 an Act of
                    Parliament was obtained whereby a duty of 2d Scots was imposed on every Scots
                    pint of ale or beer “brewed, brought in, tapped, or sold” within the town “for
                    cleaning, deepening, building, and repairing” the harbour and piers. Till the
                    year 1772 the harbour was simply leased to the town by the superior, but in that
                    year and in 1773 the magistrates and town council received a feu-right to it
                    from John Shaw Stewart the owner of the Greenock estate. From that date down to
                    the present time the additions made to the harbour by parliamentary authority
                    have been very numerous. The dock and quay accommodation now amounts to eighty
                    acres. In addition there is in course of construction an immense dock to be
                    named the “James Watt Dock,” which is intended to afford accommodation to
                    vessels of the largest tonnage, and maintain them water-borne in·all states of
                    the tide. The estimated cost of this dock, with warehouses and sheds, is
                    £250,000. The harbour trustees who now have the management of the docks consist
                    of the town council and nine elective members chosen by the local shipowners and
                    harbour ratepayers.</p>
                <p>Th'e commercial prosperity of Greenock received its first great impetus from the
                    Treaty of Union in 1707. The earliest trade seems to have been in herrings, a
                    trade which, however, has long been extinct. Trading in tobacco was also carried
                    on at a very early period. It was first brought from the colonies, and then
                    exported to the Continent. The Greenland whale-fishing commenced as far back as
                    1762, but it never rose to be of any importance, and is now discontinued. The
                    American war greatly interrupted the progress of Greenock, as the principal
                    trade of the port was then with that country; but after the peace in 1783 it
                    speedily revived, and within the seven following years the shipping trade was
                    trebled in amount. At present the principal intercourse is with the East and
                    West Indies, Australia, and the United States and Canada. Newfoundland and South
                    America have also employed a considerable quantity of shipping. The gradual
                    increase of trade is shown by the following table of the number and tonnage of
                    vessels that entered and cleared from and to foreign ports in various years
                    since 1784 :—·</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="4"><p>INWARDS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4"><p>OUTWARDS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>British.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Foreign.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>British.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Foreign.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tons.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tons.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tons.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1784</p><p>1804</p><p>1824</p><p>1853</p><p>1878</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52</p><p>165</p><p>188</p><p>274</p><p>428</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6,569</p><p>30,802</p><p>46,162</p><p>94,575</p><p>219,521</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p><p>25</p><p>11</p><p>44</p><p>178</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>530</p><p>5,120</p><p>3,054</p><p>13,764</p><p>64,918</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>63</p><p>155</p><p>188</p><p>153</p><p>419</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7,297</p><p>31,896</p><p>46,857</p><p>55,630</p><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p><p>20</p><p>9</p><p>45</p><p>98,26</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>520</p><p>5,965</p><p>2,699</p><p>111,975 &gt;7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Interesting historical details will be found in <hi rend="italic">Memorials of
                    James Watt,</hi> by G. Williamson, 1856. The first volume of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historical Sketches of the Town and Harbours of Greenock,</hi> by Dugald
                    Campbell, appeared in 1879. (J. PA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
