<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0228-0217-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GROTIUS, Hugo (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    217)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh7s">Arminianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80q31">Arminians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x66s">Classicism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814833">Arminians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863557">Classicism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n228/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GROTIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugo</hi></label> (1583-1645),
                    in his native country Huig van Groot, but known to the rest of Europe by the
                    Latinized form of the name, was one of the famous men of the 17th century,
                    almost equally eminent for public services and as a writer. He was born at Delft
                    on Easter day, 10th April 1583. The Groots were a branch of a family of
                    distinction, which had been noble in France, but had removed to the Low
                    Countries more than a century before. Their French name was De Cornets, and this
                    cadet branch had taken the name of Groot on the marriage of Hugo’s
                    great-grandfather with a Dutch heiress. The father of Hugo was a lawyer in
                    considerable practice, who had four times served the office of burgomaster of
                    Leyden, and was one of the three curators of the university of that place.</p>
                <p>In the annals of precocious genius there is no greater prodigy on record than
                    Hugo Grotius, who was able to make good Latin verses at nine, was ripe for the
                    university at twelve, and at fifteen edited the encyclopaedic work of Marcianus
                    Capella. At Leyden he was much noticed by J. J. Scaliger, whose habit it was to
                    engage his young friends in the editing of some classical text, less for the
                    sake of the book so produced than as a valuable education for themselves. At
                    fifteen Grotius accompanied Count Justin of Nassau, and the grand pensionary
                    Oldenbarnevelt on their special embassy to the court of France. After a year
                    profitably spent in that country in acquiring the language and making
                    acquaintance with the leading <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n229/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0229-0218"/> men, Grotius returned home. He took the degree of
                    doctor of law at Leyden, and entered on practice as an advocate.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding his successes in his profession, which seemed to open the most
                    brilliant career to his ambition, he was in secret hankering after the pleasures
                    of literature. In 1600 he edited the remains of Aratus, with the versions of
                    Cicero, Germanicus, and Avienus. Of the <hi rend="italic">Germanicus</hi>
                    Scaliger says—“A better text than that which Grotius has given, it iβ impossible
                    to give ;” but it is probable that Scaliger had himself been the reviser.
                    Grotius vied with the Latinists of his day in the composition of Latin verses.
                    Some lines on the siege of Ostend were greatly admired, and-spread his fame
                    beyond the circle of the learned. He wrote three dramas in Latin :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Christus Patiens</hi><hi rend="italic">; Sophom-phaneas,</hi> on
                    the story of Joseph and his brethren; and <hi rend="italic">Adamus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Exul,</hi> a production which is still remembered as having given
                    hints to Milton. The <hi rend="italic">Sορhomphaneas</hi> was translated into
                    Dutch by Vondel, and into English by Francis Goldsmith (1652); the <hi
                    rend="italic">Christus</hi><hi rend="italic">Patiens</hi> into English by George
                    Sandys (1640).</p>
                <p>In 1603 the United Provinces, desiring to transmit to posterity some account of
                    their struggle with Spain, determined to appoint a historiographer. Several
                    candidates appeared, Dominicus Bandius of course among them. But the choice of
                    the states fell upon Grotius, though only twenty years of age, and not having
                    offered himself for the post.</p>
                <p>There was some talk at this time in Paris of calling Grotius to be librarian of
                    the royal library. But it was never meant seriously. It was a ruse of the Jesuit
                    party, who wiβhed to persuade the public that the opposition to the appointment
                    of Isaac Casaubon did not proceed from theological motives, since they were
                    ready to appoint a Protestant in the person of Grotius.</p>
                <p>His next preferment was that of advocate-general of the fisc for the provinces of
                    Holland and Zeeland. This was followed by his marriage, in 1608, to Mary van
                    Reigesberg, a lady of family in Zeeland, a woman of great capacity and noble
                    disposition, who proved every way worthy to be the wife of Grotius.</p>
                <p>He had already passed from occupation with the classics to studies more
                    immediately connected with his profession. In the winter of 1604 he composed a
                    treatise entitled <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi rend="italic">proedoe.</hi>
                    This treatise he did not publish, and the MS. of it remained unknown to all the
                    biographers of Grotius till 1868, when it was brought to light, and printed at
                    the Hague under the auspices of Professor Fruin, It discovers to us that the
                    principles and the plan of the celebrated <hi rend="italic">De jure belli,</hi>
                    which was not composed till 1625, more than twenty years after, had already been
                    conceived by a youth of twenty-one. It has always been a question among the
                    biographers what it was that determined Grotius, when an exile in Paris in 1625,
                    to that particular subject, and various explanations have been offered; among
                    others we have been referred to a casual suggestion of Peiresc in a letter of
                    early date. The discovery of the MS. of the <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">proedoe</hi> discloses to us the whole history of Grotius’s ideas,
                    and shows us that from youth upwards he had steadily read and meditated in one
                    direction, that, namely, of which the famous <hi rend="italic">De jure
                    belli</hi> was the mature product. In the <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">proedoe</hi> of 1604 we have much more than the germ of the later
                    treatise <hi rend="italic">De jure belli.</hi> Its main principles, and the
                    whole system of thought implied in the later, are anticipated in the earlier
                    work. The arrangement even is the same. The chief difference between the two
                    treatises is one which twenty years’ experience in affairs could not but
                    bring,—the substitution of more cautious and guarded language, less dogmatic
                    affirmation, more allowance for exceptions and deviations. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Jus</hi><hi rend="italic">pacis</hi> was an addition introduced first in the
                    later work, an insertion which is the cause of not a little of the confused
                    arrangement which has been found fault with in the <hi rend="italic">De jure
                    belli.</hi></p>
                <p>We learn further from the <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >proedoe</hi> that Grotius was originally determined to this subject, not by any
                    speculative intellectual interest, but by a special occasion presented by his
                    professional engagements. He was retained by the Dutch East India Company as
                    their advocate. The company had been formed for the peaceful purposes of
                    commerce, but had found itself compelled by the aggressions of the Portuguese to
                    repel force by force. One of their captains, Heemskirk, had captured a rich
                    Portuguese galleon in the Straits of Malacca. The right of a private company to
                    make prizes was hotly contested in Holland, and denied by the stricter
                    religionists, especially the Mennonites, who considered all war unlawful.
                    Grotius undertook to prove that Heemskirk’s prize had been lawfully captured. In
                    doing this he was led to investigate the grounds of the lawfulness of war in
                    general. Such was the casual origin of a book which long enjoyed such celebrity
                    that it used to be said, with some exaggeration indeed, that it had founded a
                    new science.</p>
                <p>A short treatise which was printed in 1609, Grotius says without his permission,
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Mare Liberum,</hi> is nothing more than a
                    chapter—the 12th—of the <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >proedoe.</hi> It was necessary to Grotius’s defence of Heemskirk that he should
                    show that the Portuguese pretence that Eastern waters were their private
                    property was untenable. Grotius maintains that the ocean is free to all, and
                    cannot be appropriated by any one nation. The occasional character of this piece
                    explains the fact that at the time of its appearance it made no sensation. It
                    was not till many years afterwards that the jealousies between England and
                    Holland gave importance to the novel doctrine broached in the tract by Grotius,
                    a doctrine which Selden set himself to refute in his'3∕cπ <hi rend="superscript"
                    > ,</hi> e <hi rend="italic">clausum,</hi> 1632.</p>
                <p>Equally due to the circumstances of the time was his small contribution to
                    constitutional history entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >antiquitate</hi><hi rend="italic">reipublicoe Batavoe</hi> (1610). In this he
                    vindicates, on grounds of right, prescriptive and natural, the revolt of the
                    United Provinces against the sovereignty of Spain.</p>
                <p>On the death of Elias Oldenbarnevelt, Grotius, though only thirty, succeeded him
                    as pensionary of the city of Rotterdam. Foreseeing the troubles impending from
                    the growing theological fermentation, he made the stipulation that he should be
                    irremovable by the municipal authorities —a stipulation certain not to be
                    respected should it ever be wanted for his protection.</p>
                <p>In 1613 he formed one of a deputation to the court of England, for the purpose of
                    adjusting those differences which were already beginning to arise between the
                    two young maritime powers, and which gave rise afterwards to a naval struggle
                    disastrous to Holland. He was received by James with every mark of distinction
                    due to his rising reputation. He also cultivated the acquaintance of the
                    Anglican ecclesiastics Overal and Andrewes, and was much in the society of the
                    celebrated scholar Isaac Casaubon, with whom he had been in correspondence by
                    letter for many yeara. Though the mediating views in the great religious
                    conflict between Catholic and Protestant, by which Grotius was afterwards known,
                    had been arrived at by him by independent reflexion, yet it could not but be
                    that he would be confirmed in them by finding in England a developed school of
                    thought of the same character already in existence. How highly Casaubon esteemed
                    Grotius appears from a letter of his to Daniel Heinsius, dated London, 13th
                    April 1613. “I cannot say how happy I esteem myself in having seen so much of
                    one so truly great <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n230/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0230-0219"/> as Grotius. A wonderful man! This I knew him to
                    be before I had seen him; but the rare excellence of that divine genius no one
                    can sufficiently feel who does not see his face, and hear him speak. Probity is
                    stamped on his features; his conversation savours of true piety and profound
                    learning. It is not only upon me that he has made this impression; all the pious
                    and learned to whom he has been here introduced have felt the same towards him;
                    the king especially so!”</p>
                <p>After Grotius’s return from England the exasperation of theological parties in
                    Holland gradually rose to such a pitch that it became clear that an appeal to
                    force would sooner or later be made. This Grotius must have foreseen, but he
                    could hardly have anticipated that he himself would be one of the first and
                    principal victims. Grotius was not sufficient of a philosopher to rise above the
                    level of a mere theological wrangle. But from a natural moderation of temper he
                    sought to find some mean term in which the two hostile parties of Remonstrants
                    and Anti-remonstrants, or as they were subsequently called Arminians and
                    Gomarists (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Remonstrants),</hi> might agree. A form of
                    edict drawn by Grotius was published by the states, recommending mutual
                    toleration, and forbidding ministers in the pulpit from handling the disputed
                    dogmas. To the orthodox Calvinists the word toleration was insupportable. They
                    had the populace on their side. This fact determined the stadtholder, Maurice of
                    Nassau, to support the orthodox party— a party to which he inclined the more
                    readily that Oldenbarnevelt, the grand pensionary, the man whose uprightness
                    p,nd abilities he most dreaded, sided with the Remonstrants.</p>
                <p>In 1618 Prince Maurice set out on a sort of pacific campaign, disbanding the
                    civic guards in the various cities of Guelders, Holland, and Zeeland, and
                    occupying the places with troops on whom he could rely. The states of Holland
                    sent a commission, of which Grotius was chairman, to Utrecht, with the view of
                    strengthening the hands of their friends, the Remonstrant party, in that city.
                    Feeble plans were formed, but not carried into effect, for shutting the gates
                    upon the stadtholder, who entered the city with troops on the night of 26th July
                    1618. There were conferences in which Grotius met Prince Maurice face to face,
                    and taught him that Oldenbarnevelt was not the only man of capacity in the ranks
                    of the Remonstrants whom he had to fear. On the early morning of 31st July the
                    prince’s <hi rend="italic">coup d'etat</hi> against the liberties of Utrecht and
                    of Holland was carried out; the civic guard was disarmed,—Grotius and his
                    colleagues saving themselves by a precipitate flight. But it was only a
                    reprieve. The grand pensionary, Oldenbarnevelt, the leader of the Remonstrant
                    party, Grotius, and Hoogeoberz were arrested by order of the stadtholder,
                    brought to trial, and condemned,—Oldenbarnevelt to death, and Grotius to
                    imprisonment for life and confiscation of his property. In June 1619 he was
                    immured in the fortress of Lovestein near Gorcum. His confinement was rigorous,
                    but after a time his wife obtained permission to share his captivity, on the
                    condition that if she came out, she should not be suffered to return</p>
                <p>Grotius had now before him, at thirty-six, no prospect but that of a lifelong
                    captivity. He did not abandon himself to despair, but sought refuge in returning
                    to the classical pursuits of his youth. Several of his translations (into Latin)
                    from the Greek tragedians and other writers, made at this time, have been
                    printed. They are without any philological value, and only prove his taste and
                    facility in the classical languages. “The Muses,” he writes to Voss, “were now
                    his consolation, and appeared more amiable than ever.”</p>
                <p>The address and ingenuity of Madame Grotius at length devised a mode of escape.
                    It had grown into a custom to send, at stated intervals, the books which he had
                    done with. in a chest, along with his linen to be washed at Gorcum. For many
                    months the warders of the fortress were very exact in searching the chest. But
                    never finding anything but books and linen they grew careless, and began to let
                    the chest pass without opening it. Madame Grotius, perceiving this, prevailed on
                    her husband to allow himself to be shut up in it at the usual time. The two
                    soldiers who carried the chest out complained that it was so heavy “there must
                    be an Arminian in it.” “There are indeed,” said Madame Grotius, “Arminian books
                    in it.” The chest was carried by canal to Gorcum. When it came there they wanted
                    to put it on a sledge; but the maid telling the boatmen there were some brittle
                    things in it, it was put on a horse, and so carried to the house of a friend,
                    where it was opened, and Grotius released. He was then dressed up like a mason
                    with hod and trowel, and so conveyed in disguise over the frontier. His first
                    place of refuge was Antwerp, from which he proceeded to Paris, where he arrived
                    in April 1621. In October he was joined by his wife. There he was presented to
                    the king, Louis XIII., and a pension of 3000 livres conferred upon him. French
                    pensions were easily granted, all the more so as they were never paid. Grotius
                    was now reduced to great straits. •He had not the means of procuring the bare
                    necessaries of life. His family was a growing one, and it was with difficulty
                    that he procured them clothes. His relations in Holland sent him occasionally
                    small remittances in money, clothes, or Dutch butter. He looked about for any
                    opening through which he might earn a living. There was talk of something in
                    Denmark; or he w’ould settle in Spire, and practise in the court there. Some
                    little relief he got through the intervention of D’Aligre, the new chancellor,
                    who procured a royal mandate which enabled Grotius to draw, not all, but a large
                    part of his pension. In 1623 the president Henri de Même lent him his chateau of
                    Balagni near Senlis (dep. Oise), and there Grotius passed the spring and summer
                    of that year. De Thou gave him facilities to borrow books from the superb
                    library formed by his father.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances the <hi rend="italic">De jure belli</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et pacis</hi> was composed. The biographers are naturally
                    astonished by the fact that a work of such immense reading, consisting in great
                    part of quotation, could have been written in little more than a year. The
                    achievement would have been, not wonderful, but impossible, but for the fact
                    above mentioned that Grotius bad with him the first draft of the work made in
                    1604. He had also got his brother William, when he was reading his classics, to
                    mark down all the passages which touched upon law, public or private. In March
                    1625 the printing of the <hi rend="italic">De jure belli,</hi> which had taken
                    four months, was completed, and the edition despatched to the fair at Frankfort.
                    His own honorarium as author consisted of 200 copies, of which, however, he had
                    to give away many to friends, to the king, the principal courtiers, the papal
                    nuncio, &amp;c. What remained he sold for his own profit, at the price of a
                    crown each, but the sale did not recoup him his outlay. But though his book
                    brought him no profit it brought him reputation, so widely spread, and of such
                    long endurance, as no other legal treatise has ever enjoyed.</p>
                <p>Grotius naturally hoped that his fame would soften the hostility of his foes, and
                    that his country would recall him to her service. In this he was disappointed.
                    Theological rancour prevailed over all other sentiments. After some fruitless
                    attempts to re-establish himself in Holland, Grotius was fain to accept service
                    under the crown of Sweden, in the capacity of ambassador to the court of France.
                    He was not very successful in negotiating the treaty on behalf of the Protestant
                    interest in Germany, Richelieu having a special dislike to him. He never enjoyed
                    the confidence <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n231/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0231-0220"/> of the court to which he was accredited, and
                    frittered away his influence in disputes about precedence, which seem little
                    worthy of his reputation.</p>
                <p>In 1645 he demanded and obtained his recall. He was received at Stockholm with
                    all the honours due to him. But neither the climate nor the tone of the court
                    suited him, and he demanded permission to leave. He was driven by a storm on the
                    coast near Dantzic. He got as far as Rostock, where he found himself very ill.
                    Stockman, a Scotch physician who was sent for, thought it was only weakness, and
                    that rest would restore the patient. But Grotius sank rapidly, and died on 29th
                    August 1645.</p>
                <p>Grotius was a man of varied interests and accomplishments, combining a wide
                    circle of general knowledge with a profound study of one branch of law, History,
                    theology, jurisprudence, politics, classics, poetry,—all these fields he
                    cultivated, and has left numerous works in each kind.</p>
                <p>His commentaries on the Scriptures were the first application on an extensive
                    scale of the principle affirmed by Scaliger, that, namely, of interpretation by
                    the rules of grammar without dogmatic assumptions. Grotius’s philological skill,
                    however, was not sufficient to enable him to work up to this ideal.</p>
                <p>As in many other points Grotius inevitably recalls to us Erasmus, so he does in
                    his attitude towards the great schism. Grotius was indeed a man of profound
                    religious sentiment, which Erasmus was not; but he had an indifference to dogma
                    equal to that of Erasmus, although his disregard sprang from another source.
                    Erasmus felt the contempt of a man of lettera for the barbarous dissonance of
                    the monkish wrangle. Grotius was animated by an ardent desire for peace and
                    concord. He thought that a basis for reconciliation of Protestant and Catholic
                    might be found in a common piety, combined with reticence upon discrepancies of
                    doctrinal statement. His <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">veritate
                    religionis</hi><hi rend="italic">Christianae</hi> (1627), a presentment of the
                    evidences, is so written as to form a code of common Christianity, irrespective
                    of sect. The little treatise diffused itself rapidly over Christendom, gaining
                    rather than losing popularity in the 18th century. It became the classical
                    manual of apologetics in Protestant colleges, and was translated for missionary
                    purposes into Arabic (by Pococke, 1660), Persian, Chinese, &lt;fcc. His <hi
                    rend="italic">Via</hi><hi rend="italic">et votum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ad</hi><hi rend="italic">pacem ecclesiasticam</hi> (1642) was a detailed
                    proposal of a scheme of accommodation. Of course, like all men of moderate and
                    mediating views, he was charged by both sides with vacillation. An Amsterdam
                    minister, James Laurent, published his <hi rend="italic">Grotius</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">papizans</hi> (1642), and it was continually being announced from
                    Paris that Grotius had “gone over.” Hallam, who has collected all the passages
                    from Grotius’s letters in which the prejudices and narrow tenets of the Reformed
                    clergy are condemned, thought he had a “bias towards popery” (Z⅛. <hi
                    rend="italic">of Europe,</hi> ii. 312). The true interpretation of Grotius’s
                    mind appears to be an indifference to dogmatic propositions, produced by a
                    profound sentiment of piety. He rose above the separatist bigotry of the vulgar
                    theologian, but did not ascend into that philosophical region in which dogma is
                    transcended and dissolved. He approached parties as a statesman approaches them,
                    as facts which have to be dealt with, and governed, not suppressed in the
                    interests of some one of their number.</p>
                <p>His editions and translations of the classics were either juvenile exercises
                    prescribed by Scaliger, or “lusus poetici,” the amusement of vacant hours.
                    Grotius read the classics as a humanist, for the sake of their contents, not as
                    a professional scholar.</p>
                <p>His <hi rend="italic">Annals of the Low Countries</hi> was begun as an official
                    duty while he held the appointment of historiographer, and was being continued
                    and retouched by him to the last. It was not published till 1657, by his sons
                    Peter and Cornelius.</p>
                <p>But the high reputation which Grotius attained in his lifetime, though it rests
                    in part, like that of Erasmus, on the diversity of his accomplishments and the
                    comprehensiveness of his literary view, had also a scientific basis in a
                    professional specialty. Grotius was a great jurist, and his <hi rend="italic">De
                    jure belli</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">ρacis</hi> (Paris,
                    1625), though not by any means the first attempt in modern times to ascertain
                    the principles of jurisprudence, went far more fundamentally into the discussion
                    than anyone had done before him. The title of the work was so far misleading
                    that the <hi rend="italic">jus belli</hi> was a very small part of his
                    comprehensive scheme. In his treatment of this narrower question he had the
                    works of Albericus Gentilis (1588) and Ayala (1597) before him, and has
                    acknowledged his obligations to them. But it is in the larger questions to which
                    he opened the way that the merit of Grotius consists. His was the first attempt
                    to obtain a principle of right, and a basis for society and government, outside
                    the church or the Bible. The distinction between religion on the one hand and
                    law and morality on the other is not indeed clearly conceived by Grotius, but he
                    wrestles with it in such a way as to make it easy for those who followed him to
                    seize it. The law of nature is unalterable; God Himself cannot alter it any more
                    than He can alter a mathematical axiom. This law has its source in the nature of
                    man as a social being; it would be valid even were there no God, or if God did
                    not interfere in the government of the world. These positions, though Grotius’s
                    religious temper did not allow him to rely unreservedly upon them, yet, even in
                    the partial application they find in his book, entitle him to the honour of
                    being held the founder of the modern science of the law of nature and nations.
                    The <hi rend="italic">De jure</hi> exerted little influence on the practice of
                    belligerents, yet its publication was an epoch in the science. “The elegance of
                    his diction,” says Bluntschli, “the pearls from classical antiquity with which
                    he adorned his pages, the temper of humanity which pervaded his argument, his
                    effort to mitigate the horrors of the Thirty Years’ War in the midst of which he
                    wrote, and the warmth of his general sympathy for a moral as opposed to a
                    material order, enlisted men’s hearts on the side of his reasoning, while the
                    deficiencies of his doctrine were not as yet detected.” These defects are
                    probably now, at 250 years’ distance of time, more palpable than the merits of
                    the work. But only in the heat and impertinence of irresponsible periodical
                    criticism could it be said, as De Quincey has said, that the book is equally
                    divided between “empty truisms and time-serving Dutch falsehoods.” For a saner
                    judgment and a brief abstract of the contents of the <hi rend="italic">De
                    jure,</hi> the reader is referred to Bluntschli, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                    des allgemeinen Staatsrechts</hi> (Munich, 1864). A fuller analysis, and some
                    notice of the predecessors of Grotius, will be found in Hély, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Etude sur le</hi><hi rend="italic">droit de la guerre</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Grotius</hi> (Paris, 1875). The writer, however, with the usual unacquaintance
                    of Frenchmen with everything which goes on outside France, has never heard of
                    the <hi rend="italic">De jure prcedοe,</hi> published in 1868. Hallam, <hi
                    rend="italic">Lit. of Europe,</hi> ii. p. 543, has an abstract done with his
                    usual conscientious pains. Dugald Stewart <hi rend="italic">{Collected
                    Works,</hi> i. 370) has dwelt upon the confusion and defects of Grotius’s
                    theory. Mackintosh <hi rend="italic">(Miscell. Works,</hi> p. 166) has defended
                    Grotius, affirming that his work “is perhaps the most complete that the world
                    has yet owed, at so early a stage in the progress of any science, to the genius
                    and learning of one man.”</p>
                <p>The chief writings of Grotius have been named in the course of our article. For a
                    complete bibliography of his works, published and unpublished, the reader is
                    referred to Lehmann, <hi rend="italic">Hugοηis Grοtii manes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vindicati,</hi> Delft, 1727, which also contains a full biography.
                    Of this Latin life De Burigny published a réchauffée in French, 2 vols. 8vo,
                    Paris, 1752. Other lives are :—Van Brandt, <hi rend="italic">Historie</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">van het</hi><hi rend="italic">Leven</hi><hi rend="italic">H. de
                    Groot,</hi> 2 vols. 8vo, Dordrecht, 1727; V on Lu I en, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hugo</hi><hi rend="italic">Grotius</hi><hi rend="italic">nach seinen
                    Schicksalen und</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n232/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0232-0221"/><hi rend="italic">Schriften dargestellt,</hi> 8vo,
                    Berlin, 1806; <hi rend="italic">Life of</hi><hi rend="italic">Hugo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Grotius,</hi> by Charles Butler of Lincoln’s Inn, 8vo, London,
                    1826. The work of the Abbé Hély already mentioned contains a life of Grotius.
                    Grotius’s theological works were collected in 3 vols. fol. at Amsterdam, 1644—46
                    (reprinted London, 1660; Amsterdam, 1679; and again Amsterdam, 1698). His
                    letters were printed first in a selection, <hi rend="italic">Epistolae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ad Gallos,</hi> 12mo, Leyden, 1648, abounding, though an Elzevir,
                    in errors of press. They were collected in <hi rend="italic">H. Grotii</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Epislolae</hi><hi rend="italic">quotquot</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >reperiri</hi><hi rend="italic">potuerunt,</hi> fol., Amsterdam, 1687. A few may
                    be found scattered in other collections of <hi rend="italic">Epistoloe.</hi>
                    Supplements to the large collection of 1687 were published at Haarlem, 1806;
                    Leyden, 1809; and Haarlem, 1829. The <hi rend="italic">De jure belli</hi> was
                    translated into English by Whewell, 3 vols. 8vo, Camb., 1853; into French by
                    Barbeyrac, 2 vols. 4to, Amst., 1724; into German in Kirchmann’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophische Bibliothek,</hi> 3 vols. 12mo, Leipsic, 1879. (Μ.
                    P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
