<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0268-0255-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUICCIARDINI, Francesco (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    255)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n268/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUICCIARDINI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Francesco</hi></label>
                    (1483-1540), the celebrated Italian historian and statesman, was bora at
                    Florence in the year 1483, when Marsilio Ficino held him at the font of baptism.
                    His family was illustrious and noble; and his ancestors for many generations had
                    held the highest posts of honour in the state, as may be seen in his own
                    genealogical <hi rend="italic">Ricordi (Op. Ined.,</hi> vol. x.). After the
                    usual education of a boy in grammar and elementary classical studies, his
                    father, Piero, sent him to the universities of Ferrara and Padua, where he
                    stayed until the year 1505. The death of an uncle, who had occupied the see of
                    Cortona with great pomp, induced the young Guicciardini to hanker after an
                    ecclesiastical career. He already saw the scarlet of a cardinal awaiting him,
                    and to this eminence he would assuredly have risen. His father, however, checked
                    this ambition, declaring that, though he had five sons, he would not suffer one
                    of them to enter the church in its then state of corruption and debasement.
                    Guicciardini, whose motives were confessedly ambitious (see <hi rend="italic"
                    >Autobiogr. Picordi, Op. Ined.,</hi> x. p. 68), turned his attention to law, and
                    at the age of twenty-three was appointed by the signoria of Florence to read the
                    <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi> in public. Shortly afterwards he engaged
                    himself in marriage to Maria, daughter of Alamanno de’ Salviati, prompted, as he
                    frankly tells us, by the political support which an alliance with that great
                    family would bring him <hi rend="italic">(ib.,</hi> x. 71). He was then
                    practising at the bar, where he won so much distinction that the signoria, in
                    1512, entrusted him with an embassy to the court of Ferdinand the Catholic. Thus
                    he entered on the real work of his lifo as a diplomatist and statesman. His
                    conduct upon that legation was afterwards severely criticized; for his political
                    antagonists accused him of betraying the true interests of the commonwealth, and
                    using his influence for the restoration of the exiled Casa Medici to power. His
                    Spanish correspondence with the signoria <hi rend="italic">(Op. Ined.,</hi> vol.
                    vi.) reveals the extraordinary power of observation and analysis which was a
                    chief quality of his mind; and in Ferdinand, hypocritical and profoundly
                    dissimulative, he found a proper object for his scientific study. To suppose
                    that the young statesman learned his frigid statecraft in Spain would be perhaps
                    too simple a solution of the problem offered by his character, and scarcely fair
                    to the Italian proficients in perfidy. It is clear from Guicciardini’s
                    autobiographical memoirs that he was ambitious, calculating, avaricious, and
                    power-loving from his earliest years; and in Spain he had no more than an
                    opportunity of studying on a large scale those political vices which already
                    ruled the minor potentates of Italy. Still the school was pregnant with
                    instructions for so apt a pupil. Guicciardini issued from this first trial of
                    his skill with an assured reputation for diplomatic ability, as that was
                    understood in Italy. To unravel plots and weave counterplots; to meet treachery
                    with fraud; to parry force with sleights of hand; to credit human nature with
                    the basest motives, while the blackest crimes were contemplated with cold
                    enthusiasm for their cleverness, was reckoned then the height of political
                    sagacity. Guicciardini could play the game to perfection. In 1515 Leo X. took
                    him into service, and made him governor of Reggio and Modena. In 1521 Parma was
                    added to his rule, and in 1523 he was appointed viceregent of Romagna by Clement
                    VII. These high offices rendered Guicciardini the virtual master of the papal
                    states beyond the Apennines, during a period of great bewilderment<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n269/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0269-0256"/> and difficulty. The copious correspondence
                    relating to his administration has recently been published <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Op. Ined.,</hi> vols, vii., viii.). In 1526 Clement gave him still higher rank
                    as lieutenant-general of the papal army. While holding this commission, he had
                    the humiliation of witnessing from a distance the sack of Rome and the
                    imprisonment of Clement, without being able to rouse the perfidious duke of
                    Urbino into activity. The blame of Clement’s downfall did not rest with him; for
                    it was merely his duty to attend the camp, and keep his master informed of the
                    proceedings of the generals (see the Correspondence, <hi rend="italic">Op.
                    Ined.,</hi> vols, iv., v.). Yet Guicciardini’s conscience accused him, for he
                    had previously counselled the pope to declare war, as he notes in a curious
                    letter to himself written in 1527 <hi rend="italic">(Op. Ined., x.</hi> 104).
                    Clement did not, however, withdraw his confidence, and in 1531 Guicciardini was
                    advanced to the governorship of Bologna, the most important of all the papal
                    lordlieutenancies (Correspondence, <hi rend="italic">Op. Iηed.,</hi> vol. ix.).
                    This post he resigned in 1534 on the election of Paul III., preferring to follow
                    the fortunes of the Medicean princes. It may here be noticed that though
                    Guicciardini served three popes through a period of twenty years, or perhaps
                    because of this, he hated the papacy with a deep and frozen bitterness,
                    attributing the woes of Italy to the ambition of the church, and declaring he
                    had seen enough of sacerdotal abominations to make him a Lutheran (see <hi
                    rend="italic">Op. Ined.,</hi> vol. i. 27, 104, 96, and <hi rend="italic">1st.
                    &lt;T It.,</hi> ed. Ros., ii. 218). The same discord between his private
                    opinions and his public actions may be traced in his conduct subsequent to 1534.
                    As a political theorist, Guicciardini believed that the best form of government
                    was a commonwealth administered upon the type of the Venetian constitution <hi
                    rend="italic">(Op. Ined.</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> y</hi> i. 6; ii. 130
                    «?.); and we have ample evidence to prove that he had judged the tyranny of the
                    Medici at its true worth <hi rend="italic">(Op. Iηed.,</hi> vol. i. 171, on the
                    tyrant; the whole <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">Fiorentina</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Reggimento di Firenze, ib.</hi> i. andiii., on the
                    Medici). Yet he did not hesitate to place his powers at the disposal of the most
                    vicious members of that house for the enslavement of Florence. In 1527 he had
                    been declared a rebel by the signoria on account of his well-known Medicean
                    prejudices; and in 1530, deputed by Clement to punish the citizens after their
                    revolt, he revenged himself with a cruelty and an avarice that were long and
                    bitterly remembered. When, therefore, he returned to inhabit Florence in 1534,
                    he did so as the creature of the dissolute Alessandro de’ Medici. Guicciardini
                    pushed his servility so far as to defend this infamous despot at Naples in 1535,
                    before the bar of Charles V., from the accusations brought against him by the
                    Florentine exiles <hi rend="italic">(Op. Tned.,</hi> vol. ix.). He won his
                    cause; but in the eyes of all posterity he justified the reproaches of his
                    contemporaries, who describe him as a cruel, venal, grasping seeker after power,
                    eager to support a despotism for the sake of honours, offices, and emoluments
                    secured for himself by a bargain with the oppressors of his country. Varchi,
                    Pitti, Segni, and Nardi are unanimous upon this point; but it is only the recent
                    publication of Guicciardini’s private MSS. that has made us understand the force
                    of their invectives. To plead loyalty or honest political conviction in defence
                    of his Medicean partisanship is now impossible, face to face with the opinions
                    expressed in the <hi rend="italic">Ricordi</hi><hi rend="italic">Politici</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">Fiorentina.</hi> Like
                    Macchiavelli, but on a lower level, Guicciardini was willing to “roll stones,”
                    or to do any dirty work for masters whom, in the depth of his soul, he detested
                    and despised. After the murder of Duke Alessandro in 1537, Guicciardini espoused
                    the cause of Cosimo de’ Medici, a boy addicted to field sports, and unused to
                    the game of statecraft. The wily old diplomatist hoped to rule Florence as grand
                    vizier under this inexperienced princeling. He was mistaken, however, in his
                    schemes, for Cosimo displayed the genius of his family for politics, and coldly
                    dismissed his would-be lord-protector. Guicciardini retired in disgrace to his
                    villa, where he spent his last years in the composition of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Istoria d'Italia.</hi> He died in 1540 without male heirs.</p>
                <p>Guicciardini was the product of a cynical and selfish age, and his life
                    illustrated its sordid influences. Of a cold and worldly temperament, devoid of
                    passion, blameless in his conduct as the father of a family, faithful as the
                    servant of his papal patrons, severe in the administration of the provinces
                    committed to his charge, and indisputably able in his conduct of affairs, he was
                    at the same time, and in spite of these qualities, a man whose moral nature
                    inspires a sentiment of liveliest repugnance. It is not merely that he was
                    ambitious, cruel, revengeful, and avaricious, for these vices have existed in
                    men far less antipathetic than Guicciardini. Over and above those faults, which
                    made him odious to his fellow-citizens, we trace in him a meanness that our
                    century is less willing to condone. His phlegmatic and persistent egotism, his
                    sacrifice of truth and honour to self-interest, his acquiescence in the worst
                    conditions of the world, if only he could use them for his own advantage,
                    combined with the glaring discord between his opinions and his practice, form a
                    character which would be contemptible in our eyes were it not so sinister. The
                    social and political decrepitude of Italy, where patriotism was unknown, and
                    only selfishness survived of all the motives that rouse men to action, found its
                    representative and exponent in Guicciardini. When we turn from the man to the
                    author, the decadencé of the age and race that could develop a political
                    philosophy so arid in its cynical despair of any good in human nature forces
                    itself vividly upon our notice. Guicciardini seems to glory in his
                    disillusionment, and uses his vast intellectual ability for the analysis of the
                    corruption he had helped to make incurable. If one single treatise of that
                    century should be chosen to represent the spirit of the Italian people in the
                    last phase of the Renaissance, the historian might hesitate between the <hi
                    rend="italic">Principe</hi> of Macchiavelli and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ricordi</hi><hi rend="italic">Politici</hi> of Guicciardini. The latter is
                    perhaps preferable to the former on the score of comprehensiveness. It is,
                    moreover, more exactly adequate to the actual situation, for the <hi
                    rend="italic">Principe</hi> has a divine spark of patriotism yet lingering in
                    the cinders of its frigid science, an idealistic enthusiasm surviving in its
                    moral aberrations; whereas a great Italian critic of this decade has justly
                    described the <hi rend="italic">Ricordi</hi> as “Italian corruption codified and
                    elevated to a rule of life.” Guicciardini is, however, better known as the
                    author of the <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Italia,</hi> that vast and
                    detailed picture of his country’s sufferings between the years 1494 and 1532.
                    Judging him by this masterpiece of scientific history, he deserves less
                    commendation as a writer than as a thinker and an analyst. The style is
                    wearisome and prolix, attaining to precision at the expense of circumlocution,
                    and setting forth the smallest particulars with the same distinctness as the
                    main features of the narrative. The whole tangled skein of Italian politics, in
                    that involved and stormy period, is unravelled with a patience and an insight
                    that are above praise. It is the crowning merit of the author that he never
                    ceases to be an impartial spectator,—a cold and curious critic. We might compare
                    him to an anatomist, with knife and scalpel dissecting the dead body of Italy,
                    and pointing out the symptoms of her manifold diseases with the indifferent
                    analysis of one who has no moral sensibility. This want of feeling, while it
                    renders Guicciardini a model for the scientific student, has impaired the
                    interest of his history. Though he lived through that agony of the Italian
                    people, he does not seem to be aware that he is writing a great historical
                    tragedy. He takes as much pains in laying bare the trifling causes of a petty
                    war with Pisa as in probing the deep-seated ulcer of the papacy. Nor is he
                    capable of painting <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n270/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0270-0257"/> the events in which he took a part, in their
                    totality as a drama. Whatever he touches, lies already dead on the dissecting
                    table, and his skill is that of the analytical pathologist. Consequently, he
                    fails to understand the essential magnitude of the task, or to appreciate the
                    vital vigour of the forces contending in Europe for mastery. This is very
                    noticeable in what he writes about the Reformation. Notwithstanding these
                    defects, inevitable in a writer of Guicciardini’s temperament, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >Italia</hi> was undoubtedly the greatest historical work that had appeared
                    since the beginning of the modern era. It remains the most solid monument of the
                    Italian reason in the 16th century, the final triumph of that Florentine school
                    of philosophical historians which numbered Macchiavelli and Vettori, Segni,
                    Pitti, Nardi, Nerli, Varchi, and Giannotti. Up to the year 1857 the fame of
                    Guicciardini as a writer, and the estimation of him as a man, depended almost
                    entirely upon the <hi rend="italic">History of Italy,</hi> and on a few
                    ill-edited extracts from his aphorisms. At that date his representatives, the
                    Counts Piero and Luigi Guicciardini, opened their family archives, and committed
                    to Signor Giuseppe Canestrini the publication of his hitherto inedited MSS. in
                    ten important volumes. The vast mass of documents and finished literary work
                    thus given to the world has thrown a flood of light upon Guicciardini, whether
                    we consider him as author or as citizen. It has raised his reputation as a
                    political philosopher into the first rank, where he now disputes the place of
                    intellectual supremacy with his friend Macchiavelli; but it has coloured our
                    moral judgment of his character and conduct with darker dyes. From the stores of
                    valuable materials contained in those ten volumes, it will be enough here to
                    cite (1) the <hi rend="italic">Ricordi</hi><hi rend="italic">Politici,</hi>
                    already noticed, consisting of about 400 aphorisms on political and social
                    topics; (2) the observations on Macchiavelli’s <hi rend="italic">Discorsi,</hi>
                    which bring into remarkable relief the views of Italy’s two great theorists on
                    statecraft in the 16th century, and show that Guicciardini regarded Macchiavelli
                    somewhat as an amiable visionary or political enthusiast; (3) the <hi
                    rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">Fiorentina,</hi> an early work of the
                    author, distinguished by its animation of style, brilliancy of portraiture, and
                    liberality of judgment; and (4) the <hi rend="italic">Dialogo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">del Reggimento di Firenze,</hi> also in all probability an early
                    work, in which the various forms of government suited to an Italian commonwealth
                    are discussed with infinite subtlety, contrasted, and illustrated from the
                    vicissitudes of Florence up to the year 1494. To these may be added a serie3 of
                    short essays, entitled <hi rend="italic">Discorsi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Politici,</hi> composed during Guicciardini’s Spanish legation. It is only
                    after a careful perusal of these minor works that the student of history may
                    claim to have comprehended Guicciardini, and may feel that he bring3 with him to
                    the consideration of the <hi rend="italic">Stoma (I Italia</hi> the requisite
                    knowledge of the author’s private thoughts and jealously guarded opinions.
                    Indeed, it may be confidently affirmed that those who desire to gain an insight
                    into the true principles and feelings of the men who made and wrote history in
                    the 16th century will find it here far more than in the work designed for
                    publication by the writer. Taken in combination with Macchiavelli’s treatises,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Opere Inedite</hi> furnish a comprehensive body of Italian
                    political philosophy anterior to the date of Fra Paolo Sarpi.</p>
                <p>The student may be referred to Rosini’s edition of the <hi rend="italic">Stοriα
                    d'Italla,</hi> Pisa, 1819, 10 vols., and to the <hi rend="italic">Opere
                    Inedite,</hi> in 10 vols., published at Florence, 1857. These two books place
                    him in possession of all that is extant of Guicciardini. (J. <hi rend="italic"
                    >A.</hi> S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
