<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0278-0265-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUISE, House of (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    265)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n278/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GUISE, <hi rend="smallcaps">House of</hi></label>. The House
                    of Guise, which in the 16th century suddenly rose to an eminence unrivalled in
                    Europe, takes title from the place noticed above. The countship of Guise, a fief
                    under the French crown, was carried in 1333 by its holder, Marie of Blois, as
                    her dower to Rodolf, duke of Lorraine. In 1508 René II., the conqueror of
                    Charles the Bold, divided bis territories between his sons Antony, who became
                    duke of Lorraine, and received the Germanic part, and Claude, who had the French
                    fief, including Guise.</p>
                <p>Claude of Lorraine thus became founder of a great and well-marked family, which
                    occupied the place that had in the fifteenth century been held by the princes of
                    the lilies. Generation after generation we have a duke and a cardinal side by
                    side: they illustrate with singular <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n279/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0279-0266"/> fidelity the movements of the period from its
                    Catholic side: the first duke and cardinal belonged to the Renaissance; the
                    second pair threw themselves into the Catholic reaction, and led the resistance
                    to the Reformation in France; the third pair showed the decay of the religious
                    movement, and its transit into political activities, being among the most
                    ambitious statesmen of the later years of the century; while the fourth and last
                    pair feel the breath of Richelieu’s absolutism. The family has throughout
                    characteristic qualities,—bravery, ambition, a certain nobleness of sentiment,
                    an imposing presence, and winning manners; they stand between nobility and
                    royalty,—always greater than the one, sometimes even overtopping the other. They
                    seem never to forget that in their veins runs the blood of those who wore or
                    claimed the crowns of Jerusalem and Naples, of Sicily and Hungary. Claude of
                    Lorraine, born in 1496, succeeded in 1508 to a group of lordships, which by
                    their names testify to the high fortunes of the house: besides Guise itself, he
                    had Elbeuf, Aumale, Mayenne, Joinville, Harcourt, Longjumeau, Boves, Sablé,
                    Lambesc, and others. In addition to these, the family gathered to itself
                    relations with Eu, Sully, Ventadour, Aiguillon, Mercoeur, Joyeuse, and Nevers; a
                    cardinal’s hat, together with a group of splendid church dignities, also went
                    with the house of Guise; the archbishopric of Rheims, the bishopric of Metz, and
                    several other bishoprics were family benefices, which enabled younger members to
                    take an important share in the fortunes of the family. The shield of Claude
                    expresses the pride of the race: we find there not only the Lorraine
                    spread-eagle, the German bird, but also the quarterings of eight sovereign
                    houses, those of the kings of Hungary, Naples, Jerusalem, and Aragon, and of the
                    sovereign lords of Anjou, Guelderland, Flanders, and Bar. This young prince, who
                    claimed so much, and did so much, who both exercised his rights as a foreign
                    prince and took precedence of the proudest in France, attached himself closely
                    to Francis I. He was the most brilliant among the “young men” who displaced the
                    older wisdom of the court of Louis XII. In 1513 he married Antoinette of
                    Bourbon, the duke of Vendome’s daughter and great-aunt of Henry IV.; in 1515 he
                    accompanied Francis to Italy, and showed the mettle of his race at Marignano,
                    where his brother Ferry was killed. From that time he sagaciously avoided the
                    Italian expeditions, and stayed in France, winning popularity as protector of
                    the realm. Thus in 1521 he was on the Spanish frontier, and helped to take
                    Fuenterrabia; in 1522 he opposed the English in the north, covering Paris; next,
                    he defended Champagne from the Germans, clearing that rich district with equal
                    glory and gain. In 1525 he avoided the expedition which ended in the disaster of
                    Pavia, wherein another of his brothers, Francis, was slain; and during the
                    captivity of Francis I. at Madrid, he became virtual head of the regency under
                    the queen, Louise of Savoy. In these dark days he crushed the rising of the
                    peasants of Lorraine and Swabia, which threatened all the east of France. After
                    the king’s return, Claude was made (in 1527) duke of Guise, and peer, and
                    governor of Champagne; fresh territory and wealth were added to these honours.
                    He had now reached his highest point; henceforth it is clear that Francis I.
                    regarded him with more jealousy than favour: hie ambitious views as to the crown
                    of the “good king René,” and hopes of a revived Angevin dynasty, offended the
                    French king, though they were only dreams of the past; for the new spirit of
                    monarchy and national life in the 16th century made any creation of lesser
                    kingdoms on the borderlands of France and Germany impossible. Claude was a man
                    of harsh and narrow character: cautious and persistent, he saw his way, .and
                    walked carefully along it all his days. In an age in which wealth was becoming
                    the most effective of all means of power, he gathered riches in all ways, fair
                    or foul; and though willing to spend for his own advancement, he won and
                    deserved the character of a grasping and greedy prince. His brother John, first
                    cardinal of Lorraine, seconded him in every way; he was as greedy as the duke,
                    though much more open-handed. Accepting the new ideas of the time, he became a
                    splendid Renaissance prelate, the friend of Erasmus and Rabelais, and even of
                    Marot, while, at the same time, he only too faithfully reflected the worst vices
                    of the movement. His church preferment was enormous; he shamelessly took all he
                    could get. He and his brother have the distinction of giving a bad name to a
                    whole country; for, thanks to their rapacity, the Lorrainers got that reputation
                    for avarice and greediness which has unjustly clung to them even to our days.
                    After 1527 the cleverness of the cardinal rather than the prudence of the duke
                    advanced the family. Claude had twelve children, a splendid group of princely
                    youths, who inherited the handsome features and figure of their father, with
                    even greater abilities and a more effective ambition. Francis, the eldest of
                    those who grew up, was born in 1519, and became the second duke; Charles, born
                    in 1524, was the second cardinal of Lorraine, a man as intelligent and depraved
                    as his uncle, and more vigorous and ambitious; Claude, the next, was created
                    duke of Aumale; Louis, archbishop of Sens and cardinal of Guise; René, marquis
                    of Elbeuf. The daughters made brilliant matches: above all, the eldest, Marie,
                    widow of the duke of Longueville, was married in 1538 to James V. of Scotland,
                    and had a stormy career as regent to her daughter, Mary Stuart, queen of
                    Scots.</p>
                <p>In his later days Claude of Guise withdrew somewhat from public life; he stood
                    aloof from the intrigues of the reign, while the cardinal attached himself to
                    the “black court,” the court of Diana of Poitiers, and promoted the interests of
                    his nephews without stint. From this time all leanings towards either
                    Renaissance or reform were at an end: henceforth the Guises became the heads of
                    the opposition to the Huguenots, the strength and support of the new Jesuit
                    movement, and, later, the leaders of the League. Claude of Guise died in 1550,
                    leaving his dignities to his son Francis, “le grand Guise,” who had already won
                    great credit for bravery, and had shown that dashing contempt for all rules of
                    military prudence which gives a captain undying popularity. The ghastly wound in
                    the face, which his rashness won for him in 1545 at the hands of the English
                    near Boulogne, got him the name of the first “Balafré;” it was the outward
                    symbol of his devotion to his country, and greatly raised his repute among the
                    people. He had too the essential qualities of popularity, a majestic presence,
                    and friendly manners in camp; he was chivalrous, liberal, humane, discerning. In
                    1552, as lieutenant-general in the three bishoprics, he withstood at the siege
                    of Metz the last efforts of Charles V., and saved France from a terrible
                    invasion. Thanks to the jealousy of the Montmorencies, he was sent in 1557 to
                    conquer Naples, and would have added another to the long roll of reputations
                    ruined by Italy, had he not been suddenly recalled to protect his country after
                    the disaster of St Quentin. With happy boldness, instead of watching the
                    victorious allies, he suddenly attacked and took Calais, ending the English
                    occupation of French soil, and raising his own renown to the highest point.
                    Then, with his brother Charles, second cardinal of Lorraine, he wielded
                    unlimited power throughout the reign of Francis II. Under Charles IX. his
                    influence abated, and he withdrew into Alsace. On his return thence in 1562, he
                    was, however unwillingly, for he was not inhumane, the cause of the massacre of
                    Vassy, which began the civil wars. In the first war he won the battle of Dreux
                    (1562), and thence passing southward besieged <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n280/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0280-0267"/> the Huguenots in Orleans. There, early in 1563,
                    he was assassinated. If he was the noblest of the Guises, his brother Charles,
                    second cardinal of Lorraine, was the ablest. In his earlier days the cardinal
                    had shown some sympathy with the Reformers; in later life he vigorously
                    repressed them, and took a leading part in the council of Trent, where he is
                    said to have sketched the first lines of the famous League. Like all early
                    friends of the Jesuits, he did his best for education, and patronized men of
                    letters, while he coerced independence of thought and aimed at introducing the
                    Inquisition. He died in 1574. His younger brother Louis, first cardinal of
                    Guise, “le cardinal des bouteilles,” was a grand pluralist, an easy-going
                    personage, whose quiet life was in striking contrast to the feverish energy of
                    his brothers. René, marquis of Elbeuf, another brother, is the stem of the great
                    houses of Elbeuf. Harcourt, and Lislebonne.</p>
                <p>Henry of Guise, eldest son of Duke Francis, born in 1550, was with his father at
                    Orleans, and saw his death. The boy therefore began his public life with an
                    inextinguishable hatred against Huguenots, eager to distinguish himself in civil
                    war. With his brother Louis, second cardinal of Guise, he entered into all the
                    intrigues of the succession question, and bitterly opposed Henry of Navarre. He
                    was at Jarnac,and, in the victory of Dormans (1575) over the German invaders, he
                    too won the title of “le Balafré.” He soon became the idol of Paris: manly,
                    handsome, and decide!, he won all hearts, and was at once a popular hero.
                    Fortune too favoured him by bringing him into contrast with the wretched Henry
                    III., and with his portly cautious brother the duke of Mayenne. In 1576 he was
                    recognized as head of the League, supported by Philip II. and the papacy.
                    Ambitious of the crown of France, he worked subtly for it behind the screen of
                    old Cardinal Bourbon’s name. In the war of the three Henries (Henry III., Henry
                    of Navarre, Henry of Guise) he again drove the Germans out of France; and, when
                    invited to the capital by the <hi rend="superscript"> ,t</hi> Sixteen,” ruled
                    there unopposed, the “King of Paris.” Henry IIL, whom he had compelled to sign
                    the Edict of Union, found his supremacy intolerable; and just before Christmas
                    (1588), the duke and the cardinal his brother were assassinated by the royal
                    orders.</p>
                <p>His eldest son Charles, born in 1571, wa3 arrested at the time of the double
                    murder, but escaped in 1591, and was welcomed with enthusiasm by the Paris mob,
                    which hoped he would wed the infanta of Spain, and with the help of Philip II.
                    secure for himself the throne of France. But the opposition of his uncle Mayenne
                    proved fatal to the scheme. At the end of the struggle, both he and Mayenne
                    submitted to Henry IV., helped him to reduce the npbles in Languedoc, and
                    received the government of Provence. In Richelieu’s days he sided with the queen
                    mother, and was compelled to withdraw in 1631 to Italy, where he died in 1640.
                    By his side also was a cardinal brother, the third of Guise, who ended by
                    abandoning the ecclesiastical state, and marrying one of the mistresses of Henry
                    IV.</p>
                <p>Henry, fourth son of Charles, born in 1614, had already succeeded to that family
                    benefice, the archbishopric of Rheims, when the death of his elder brother made
                    him head of the family, and in 1640 fifth duke. He too went against the
                    absolutism of the age, and joined the count of Soissons. Condemned to lose his
                    head he fled to Brussels, and took command of the Austrian troops against
                    France,— noble traitors to their country being then not uncommon. In 1613,
                    however, after Richelieu’s death, he returned to France; but being chosen their
                    chief by the Neapolitans, at the time of Masaniello’s revolt, and dazzled by
                    this opening for his ambition, he betook himself to Naples. There his failure
                    was complete; he was defeated and carried prisoner to Madrid. Delivered thence
                    by the intercession of the Great Condé, he again attempted Naples, and failed
                    again. After this he spent the rest of his romantic ill-ordered life at the
                    French court, and died in 1664 leaving no issue; his sisters never married, and
                    of all his brothers, one only, Louis, duke of Joyeuse, left a son, born in 1650,
                    who became sixth duke of Guise. He died of small-pox in 1671, leaving an infant
                    son, Francis Joseph, seventh duke, a sickly babe, with whom, four years later,
                    the direct line of the house of Guise expired. The other branches had early died
                    out, saving the family of the seventh son of Claude first duke, René, marquis of
                    Elbeuf; the marquis of Lambesc, who died in 1826, was the last descendant of
                    this branch, and with him the family finally became extinct.</p>
                <p>The authorities for the house of Guise are René de Bouille, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">des Dues de Guise,</hi> 4 vols., 1853, the most
                    complete account of the family; Valincour, <hi rend="italic">Vie</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de François</hi><hi rend="italic">de Lorraine, Due de Guise,</hi>
                    1664; Guiilemin, <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">du Cardinal de
                    Lorraine;</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Biographie Universelle,</hi> art. “Guise;”
                    and Forneron’s <hi rend="italic">Dues de Guise</hi><hi rend="italic">et leur
                    époque,</hi> 2 vols.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Genealogical</hi><hi rend="italic">Table</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of the House of Guise.</hi></p>
                <p>René TI. (who united the two brandie? of the house of Lorraine), duke of
                    Lorraine, and Philippa of Guelders, had (besides two older boys who died in
                    childhood, and four unmarried daughters)—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>1 1 1 Antoine, Claude, 1st John, 1st duke of duke of Guise
                            cardinalof 1 Lorraine. ^Antoinette Lorraine. 3J of Bourbon,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Feιτy, killed at iarignano.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Louis, killed at Naples.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Francis, killed at Pavia.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>fl550.</p><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Francis, 2d</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Charles, 2d Claude, Loιιis,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Rene',</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Marie=</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p><p>And</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>duke of</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>card, of marquis of 1st</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>marquis</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>James V.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>six</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Guise=</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Lorraine. Mayenne, cardinal</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>others.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Anne of</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>and duke of Guise.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Elbeuf.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Scotland.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Este,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of Aumale.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>11563.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Mary</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Stuart,</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1 1 1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Q. of Scots.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Henry, 3d</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Charles, Louis, 2d And</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Charles,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>duke—</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>duke of cardinal five</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>duke of</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Catherine</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Mayenne, of Guise, others.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Elbeuf.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>of Cleves</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>tl611. fl5S8.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>(and had</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>14 children),</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Henry,</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>11588.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>duke of</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Mayenne,</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>+ 1621.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Charles,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Louis, 3d And</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>4th duke</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>cardinal of twelve</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>of Guise,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Guise= more</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>fl640.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Charlotte</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>des Essarts.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Henry, archb. Louis, duke And</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>of Rheims,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of Joyeuse, eight</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>and 5th duke</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>, 11654. ' more.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>11664.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Louis-Joseph,</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>6th duke of Guise, 11671.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Francis-Joseph,</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>7th (and last) duke of Guise, f 1675.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>(G. W. K.)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
