<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0367-0348-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GYMNASTICS (9th edition, volume 11, page 348)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1144248">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937529">Games</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n367/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GYMNASTICS</label>, in the general acceptation of the term,
                    denotes every exercise which tends to develop and invigorate the bodily powers,
                    such as walking, running, riding, fencing, rowing, skating, dancing, and many
                    others. In another sense gymnastics includes those manly and healthful games
                    which have been encouraged by all high-minded nations as calculated to improve
                    the physical strength and keep alive the martial spirit of their people. In a
                    more limited sense, the term has been employed to denote the modern system of
                    bodily exercises. Physical strength was the veritable god of antiquity, and we
                    therefore find the elements of a system of gymnastics in most nations from the
                    earliest times. In the infancy of society, when the individual was valued
                    according to his personal strength and prowess, it was only natural that the
                    utmost care should be bestowed on those arts which most surely led to
                    distinction. All education then consisted chiefly in the practice of such
                    exercises as were best calculated to develop muscular strength and make the
                    tenure of life as secure as possible. The first gymnastic exercises, both of
                    those nations that reached the highest civilization and of barbarians, were the
                    same, viz., running, leaping, swimming, and the throwing of missiles. These
                    exercises were at a very remote period systematized and reduced to a science by
                    the Greeks (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Gymnasium).</hi> Among the Romans of the
                    republic, the games in the Campus Martius, the duties of camp life, and the
                    preliminary military exercises to which the soldier devoted himself, besides the
                    enforced marches which were imposed upon him, and the part he took in the
                    erection of public edifices, served to take the place of the gymnastic exercises
                    required by the Greeks. In the Middle Ages, chivalry with its jousts, its feats
                    of horsemanship, and encouragement to the arts of fencing, single stick,
                    &lt;fcc., took the place of the ancient gymnastic exercises. The invention of
                    gunpowder, which modified the system of warfare, and the increasing value of
                    individual life,—in a word, the progress of civilization— closed the career of
                    the champions and votaries of physical strength, and gymnastic exercises in the
                    course of time were neglected. Rousseau, in his <hi rend="italic">Émile,</hi>
                    was the first to call attention to the injurious consequences of such
                    indifference; and it is in a large measure to his eloquent appeals that
                    gymnastics have in recent times been held to constitute an integral part of
                    school education, although it cannot be said that in every country the practical
                    application of his views has met with much success. The good effects of the
                    innovation which he advocated have nowhere been more strikingly exemplified than
                    in Germany. When many parts of that country groaned under the iron yoke of
                    Napoleon, Jahn and his followers, encouraged by the Prussian minister Stein,
                    were establishing <hi rend="italic">Turnplätze</hi> or gymnastic schools, from
                    which issued the well-trained youth who in due time drove the French legions
                    across the Rhine.</p>
                <p>Of late years public attention has been drawn to the increasing deterioration in
                    the physique of the population of England, and several proposals have been put
                    forward to check an evil which can no longer be concealed. These proposals may
                    be arranged under the banners of two rival camps. The one maintains the opinion
                    put forward in a work just published on exercise and training, in the following
                    words <hi rend="italic">(Exercise and Training,</hi> 1878) :—</p>
                <p>“In our opinion the natural varieties of exercise of cricket, football, anil
                    rowing for boys, hunting, shooting, &amp;c., formen, pursued at the different
                    seasons of the year, are quite sufficient for a proper development of all parts
                    of the body, in accordance with the uses of the different limbs, for the
                    development of special muscles; or, where a great varie’ty of exercise cannot be
                    procured, a system of gymnastics may be pursued. To the advocates for the
                    adoption of systematic physical education by means of gymnasia at our schools,
                    whilst we concede the immense value of such establishments in our large towns,
                    where outdoor exercise and field sports are difficult of attainment, or in cases
                    where from the physical debility the muscles have to be gradually developed,
                    still we maintain that the national games played by the English schoolboy are
                    infinitely superior to any system of artificial exercise ever devised.”</p>
                <p>On the other aide we have the advocates of physical education by means of regular
                    gymnastic exercises superintended by trained and educated teachers, the whole
                    placed <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n368/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0368-0349"/> under competent medical supervision. Among the
                    staunch supporters of the latter view may be named Dr Roth, and Mrs Westlake, a
                    member of the London School Board. The following considerations appear to be of
                    great weight as supporting the views put forward by the advocates of physical
                    education. While the national games may seem to some sufficient for the physical
                    development of the ordinary youth and manhood of a country, it must not be
                    forgotten that there is a vast and rapidly increasing portion of the population,
                    especially in large cities, to whom the “national games” are quite unknown
                    diversions, and that it is among this class that the most marked deterioration
                    in physical development is only too apparent. The children of this class dwell
                    cooped up in narrow, ill-lighted, and worse-ventilated courts, from which they
                    are often dragged to undergo a certain amount of mental training, in many cases
                    perhaps too severe to be sustained by their debilitated and enfeebled bodies.
                    Whilst so much is being done for the mental culture of the rising generation,
                    their physical culture is left very much to inclination or chance. But there is
                    another source of danger put forward by those who advocate the sufficiency of
                    the national games, viz., “the neglect of any classification of games at school,
                    and allowing the weak and strong to engage in them indiscriminately, to the
                    detriment of the physical wellbeing of the more delicate;” and they proceed to
                    show the injury that may be done by the present system of competitive outdoor
                    sports unregulated by judicious restraint. Important information on this subject
                    will be found in two papers published in the <hi rend="italic">St George's
                    Hospital</hi><hi rend="italic">Deports</hi> for 1874-76, by Mr C. Roberts,
                    F.R.C.S., and by Mr Street, and another in the <hi rend="italic">Tenth Annual
                    Report of the State Board of Health of Massachusetts,</hi> by Professor Edward
                    Hitchcock. Mr Roberts points out that between the ages of fifteen and seventeen
                    the greatest amount of physical development takes place, and that if at this
                    period a boy is subjected to a great strain upon his strength his future growth
                    may be interfered with, or the foundation laid of constitutional disease. Prof.
                    Hitchcock’s paper embodies the experience of seventeen years of careful
                    observation. Acting upon the well-grounded opinion that neither mental serenity
                    nor mental development can exist with an unhealthy animal organization, and
                    admonished by “the sad deaths of two promising young men, and the breaking down
                    in health of others just at the end of their college courses,” the authorities
                    of Amherst College were impelled to demand that the college officials should
                    give a proper attention to physical health as well as to the culture of those
                    powers for which departments were ordinarily created and endowments made. In
                    1859 a department of physical education and hygiene was created, concerning
                    which we read in the catalogue of 1861-62 that—</p>
                <p>“Its design is to secure healthful daily exercise and recreation to all students;
                    to instruct them in the use of the vocal organs, movements of the body, and
                    manners, as connected with oratory; and to teach them, both theoretically and
                    practically, the laws of health. This daily physical training is a part of the
                    regular college course. The professor is an educated physician, and has not only
                    a general oversight of the health of the college, but students have the
                    privilege of consulting him without charge. While the gymnasium will furnish
                    opportunities for the highest physical training, the required exercises will be
                    such as can be performed without undue effort or risk of injury.”</p>
                <p>Each class, at a stated hour on four days of the week appears at the gymnasium,
                    and all perform their part in systematic and methodical exercises timed to
                    music. The statistics of this department show some interesting facts in
                    reference to the duration of sickness among students. While the average amount
                    of time lost on account of sickness by each labourer in Europe is found to be 19
                    or 20 days each year, the returns of Amherst College sick-list for term time
                    give 2 ’ 64 days as an annual average of time lost to every student, and 11*36
                    days to each sick student for 17 years. A decrease in the amount of sickness
                    during the course is also an important feature in the health of the college.</p>
                <p>From replies to questions put by Dr Roth to the heads of the educational bodies,
                    and also from the recorded personal experience of his son, Mr B. Roth, F.R.C.S.,
                    it appears that considerable attention is now being paid to the best methods for
                    improving the physical education of the people in nearly all the Continental
                    states. The greatest activity is perhaps shown by Sweden, Germany, France,
                    Belgium, and Italy; and even in Russia the question is attracting much public
                    attention, Dr Berglind having been ordered to write a special book on the
                    subject. In Hungary also the Government has made physical education an
                    obligatory part of the school curriculum. In Prussia gymnastic instruction was
                    formally recognized by a cabinet order of June 1842, and by a royal order of
                    1862 a guidebook of gymnastic instruction was introduced into the primary
                    schools and into the training colleges for teachers. In Sweden this subject
                    appears to have earlier attracted attention, for in 1813 the Government, under
                    the direction of P. H. Ling, founded the Royal Central Gymnastic Institute at
                    Stockholm, where teachers of both sexes are gratuitously trained for two years,
                    and receive a diploma after undergoing a theoretical and practical examination.
                    In Belgium, under the united efforts of MM. Delcour and Émile Greyson,
                    considerable progress has been made, although much has still to be done, owing
                    to the opposition raised by the municipality of Brussels to the views put
                    forward by the Government. In the girls’ schools the exercises are accompanied
                    by music, after the example set by Colonel Ameros, who about the beginning of
                    this century introduced into France a series of gymnastic exercises adapted to a
                    jingling rhyme and to music. The chanting governed the movements, marked the
                    intervals of repose, and helped to strengthen the organs of the voice and
                    respiration. In France the necessity for the physical education of the people
                    began to attract attention about the year 1845, owing probably to the energy
                    displayed by Jahn in Prussia. M. de Salvandy proposed to introduce the teaching
                    of gymnastics into the Lycées of Paris and Versailles, and a commission was
                    appointed by him, which, however, never presented a report. In 1850, 1851, 1855,
                    and 1856 several attempts were made to enforce compulsory gymnastic training,
                    but the principle was not accepted till 1869, when Μ. V. Duruy took for his
                    basis of action the labours of the commission presided over by Dr Hillairet.
                    After the fall of the empire, M. Jules Simon addressed the head masters of the
                    colleges and schools in France as follows:—</p>
                <p>“I beg you to assist me in introducing gymnastics into our habits in a profitable
                    and earnest manner. This is not only in the interest of public health; a healthy
                    child is better prepared for study, and especially for the battle of life.
                    Morality gains by this education of the body; much money is not wanted for the
                    purpose; and in case of need, exercises can be performed without a trapeze or
                    dumb-bells. Our medical men will help us to do our task; if the children are
                    once accustomed to, and take pleasure in, these healthy exercises, we may be
                    sure of a prompt amelioration of the race.”</p>
                <p>In England we find that the first attempt to introduce scientific physical
                    education among the people was made in parliament in 1862 by Lord Elcho. This
                    attempt failed, as also did another made in 1875 by P. A. Taylor, M.P. for
                    Leicester, although supported in an able speech by Mr Butler Johnstone. Lord
                    Sandon, then vice-president of the committee of council on education, told
                    Parliament that “the Government has done all that could be expected of them for
                    physical education by taking steps to substitute military drill for ordinary
                    drill.” The substitution, it may be remarked, does not appear to have any
                    advantage over the drill it displaced, as the military authorities declared the
                    ordinary military drill to be insufficient for the requirements<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n369/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0369-0350"/> of the soldier, and have during the last sixteen
                    years instituted gymnasiums at Aldershott, Gibraltar, Malta, and elsewhere, the
                    teachers in which have, for the most part, passed under the care of Mr Maclaren
                    of Oxford, one of the principal authorities on the subject in England. Without
                    entering into details, it may be admitted that the physical condition of the
                    people, if not actually deteriorating, 13 not improving, and it is a significant
                    fact that within the last year or two it has been found necessary to lower the
                    standard in the British army, and that Dr Ord, in his report for 1869, states
                    that out of 5567 boys 4410 were rejected a3 under the standard of width of chest
                    and height. We have already referred to the tendency to rely on the casual
                    outdoor sports for maintaining the physique of the population, and to a great
                    extent to depreciate systematic gymnastic exercises and physical education. That
                    in some quarters, however, this opinion is not entertained is shown from the
                    fact that the London School Board has appointed Miss Löfving of the Stockholm
                    Training College to instruct certain of their teachers so as to fit them for
                    teaching the girls in the schools. It Î3 to be regretted that in the blind
                    asylums so little iβ done for the physical education of the inmates. An
                    institution in Milan provides for the training of ricketty children by carefully
                    regulated gymnastic exercises; but this institution seems to be the only one of
                    its kind in Europe.</p>
                <p>To show that the importance of gymnastics has not been overstated, we may
                    describe the effects produced on twelve non-commissioned officers sent by the
                    military authorities to be trained as teachers for the British army by Mr
                    Maclaren. The men ranged from nineteen to twenty-nine year3 of age, and in
                    height from 5 feet 5 inches to 6 feet. In Mr Maclaren’s own words, “the muscular
                    additions to the arms and shoulders and the expansion of the chest were so great
                    as to have absolutely a ludicrous and embarrassing result, for before the fourth
                    month several of the men could not get into their jackets and tunics without
                    assistance, and when they had got them on they could not get them to meet down
                    the middle by a hand’s breadth.” In a month more they could not get into them at
                    all, and new clothing had to be procured, pending the arrival of which the men
                    hid to go to and from the gymnasium in their greatcoats.</p>
                <p>Although, there is some diversity of opinion among teachers of gymnastics as to
                    the relative value of the different exercises, some holding that “free
                    exercises” are sufficient, others that certain mechanical appliances are
                    necessary, yet all agree that, to ensure healthy and perfect development of the
                    organs of the body, a course of gymnastics must commence with such simple
                    exercises as walking, running, jumping, &amp;c. The introductory course
                    ordinarily consists of “movements and positions” and the use of dumb-bells and
                    bar-bells. In some French gymnasiums, especially those presided over by Μ.
                    Laisné of Paris, an instrument invented and called by him a “xy lofer” is in
                    use, consisting of a wooden stick strengthened and weighted with a rod of iron,
                    and corresponding apparently to the bar-bell of English teachers. Another form
                    of movable apparatus, also in use in some Continental schools, consists of
                    sticks on which slide wooden spheres of from 6 to 7 inches diameter, prevented
                    from slipping off by india-rubber rims at each end. The movements which
                    accompany the use of the stick are intended to expand the chest and increase the
                    power of the muscles of the back. In stretching the arms outwards from the bent
                    position, the spheres fly outwards and very much increase the energy of the
                    movement.</p>
                <p>For the preliminary exercises with movable apparatus, the dumbbell is that
                    usually selected. It was in use in England in the time of Elizabeth. It has many
                    advantages over the Indian club, the practice of the dumb-bell requiring a less
                    amount of room, and not presenting the risk the club does of overstraining the
                    body by its unskilful use.</p>
                <p>The dumb-bell admits of being exactly proportioned to the individual strength of
                    each learner, and can be adjusted in weight as his strength increases. The
                    exercises also that may be performed with it give employment to all parts of the
                    body and to both sides equally. The <hi rend="italic">bar</hi> is simply a
                    two-handed dumb-bell. Next in order oome walking, running, and leaping, the
                    exercises being so regulated that both the distance and speed are gradually
                    increased. The <hi rend="italic">leaping rape</hi> is suspended from a beam, and
                    enables the leaper to clear a barrier at the same time that it gives employment
                    to both the upper and lower limbs. The <hi rend="italic">leaping pole</hi> is
                    usually made of ash, and varies from 8 to 10 feet in length. Its use may be left
                    to the pleasure of the pupil after he has acquired some dexterity with the
                    leaping rope.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">horizontal beam</hi> is a round wooden beam so mounted that
                    it may be moved up and down. The exercises on this are chiefly balancing the
                    body in the sitting and erect posture, and when <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                    moving along it.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">vaulting bar</hi> differs from the preceding in being
                    somewhat thinner, so as to be easily grasped by the hand. The appropriate
                    exercises on it have for their object the strengthening of the muscles of the
                    upper extremity and loins. The <hi rend="italic">vaulting horse</hi> allows of a
                    wider range of exercises, and requires a greater amount of strength and
                    dexterity. The muscles of the upper and lower limbs and trank are all benefited
                    by its use. The <hi rend="italic">fixed parallel bars</hi> are used to develop
                    the muscles of the trunk and upper limbs, but chiefly the former. The <hi
                    rend="italic">movable parallel bars</hi> may be used for the same exercises as
                    the preceding. The <hi rend="italic">trapeze</hi> consists of a horizontal bar
                    suspended by ropes at a height of 4 or 5 feet from the floor. Considerable
                    practice is required to perform the exercises on this machine with dexterity and
                    neatness. The <hi rend="italic">horizontal bar,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >bridge ladder,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">plank,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >inclined plane,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">prepared wall,</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">mast,</hi> and several modifications of these that are used,
                    permit of a great variety of exercises.</p>
                <p>In “calisthenics” the exercises are more directed to ensure grace and ease in the
                    several movements of the body than muscular development, and are, therefore,
                    closely allied to the <hi rend="superscript"> ,,</hi> movements and positions”
                    or “free exercises” of the gymnast. Among these exercises dancing takes a
                    prominent part, being at once healthful and graceful.</p>
                <p>See Combe’s <hi rend="italic">Edïication,</hi><hi rend="italic">its Principles
                    and Practice,</hi> edited by Jolly; Maclaren’s <hi rend="italic">Physical
                    Education</hi>; the various works (in French) of Prof. N. Laisné, Capt. Docx,
                    and Dr Le Blond; and numerous pamphlets by Dr Roth. (H. A. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
