<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0186-0175-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GREGORY, St (9th edition, volume 11, page 175)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n186/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GREGORY, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>, surnamed <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">the Great</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(c.</hi> 540-604), the first
                    pope of that name, and one of the four doctors of the Latin Church (Ambrose,
                    Augustine, and Jerome being the other three), wa3 born at Rome about the year
                    540. His father Gordianus possessed senatorial rank, and his mother Sylvia is
                    said to have been remarkable for her mental endowments. Educated for the legal
                    profession, Gregory about his thirtieth year was chosen by the citizens to the
                    high position of praetor urbanus; this post he is said to have occupied for
                    three years (571-574), discharging its duties with great pomp and magnificence;
                    but on the death of his father, having become deeply impressed with a sense of
                    the transitoriness and vanity of all earthly things, he retired from public life
                    and gave up his whole fortune to pious uses, building six monasteries in Sicily
                    and one in Rome; in this last, which was dedicated by him to St Andrew, he
                    embraced the Benedictine rule, and divided his whole time between works of
                    charity and the exercises of fasting, meditation, and prayer. It was while he
                    was still a simple monk of St Andrew that the often repeated incident related by
                    Bede is believed to have occurred. Having seen some English slaves of striking
                    beauty exposed for sale in the public market, “non Angli sed Angeli,” he set his
                    heart upon the evangelization of Britain, and was only prevented by the command
                    of his ecclesiastical superiors from setting out in person to seek the
                    realization of his pious wish. About 578 or 579 he was appointed abbot of his
                    monastery, and likewise one of the seven deacons (regionarii) of the Roman
                    Church; and in 582 he was sent by Pelagius II. to Constantinople as papal
                    apocrisiarius or responsatis at the imperial court. There he remained for
                    upwards of three years, during which he negotiated several matters of importance
                    and delicacy; but amid his diplo matic and other engagements he found time to
                    begin, if not even to complete, one of his largest works, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Moralia,</hi> or exposition of the book of Job. A few years after his return
                    from the Eastern capital, the death of Pelagius (590) caused a vacancy in the
                    papal chair, and the choice of. the clergy, senate, and people unanimously fell
                    upon Gregory. He strongly deprecated the bestowal of this honour, and wrote to
                    the emperor (Maurice) imploring him not to confirm the nomination. A pious
                    fraud, committed by the city praetor then in office, prevented the letter from
                    reaching its destination; and though Gregory hid himself for a time, he was at
                    length obliged to yield to the urgency of his friends by accepting the papal
                    crown (September 590). The pontificate of fourteen years which followed was
                    marked by extraordinary vigour and activity, which made themselves felt
                    throughout almost every department of the doctrine, discipline, and worship of
                    the entire Western Church. By means of earnest prayer and wisely expended pains
                    the aggressions of the Lombards were checked, and order and tranquillity were
                    speedily restored to Rome; in Italy and France he tightened the too long relaxed
                    reins of ecclesiastical discipline; in England, Spain, and Africa the powers of
                    Paganism, Arianism, and Donatism were perceptibly weakened; as against the
                    Eastern emperor and the patriarch of Constantinople the prerogatives of the
                    bishop of Rome were asserted with a vigour previously unwitnessed; the
                    ceremonies of the church were regulated and extended, the liturgy further
                    developed. The anniversary of Gregory’s death, which took place at Rome on the
                    12th of March 604, is observed as a duplex by the Latin Church, and even in the
                    Greek Church his wisdom and sanctity continue to be commemorated. The
                    hyperbolical panegyrics of those ecclesiastical writers who lived nearest his
                    time (such as Gregory of Tours and Isidore of Seville) must of course be taken
                    with considerable reservation; but they are interesting as showing how powerful
                    and profound was the impression he left upon his contemporaries and immediate
                    successors—an impression and an influence well entitling him to the epithet of
                    “great.” Of the personal qualities of Gregory, the most obtrusive are beyond all
                    question the singular strength and energy of his character. Firmly and intensely
                    convinced of the divineness of the Christian doctrine and life as these had
                    presented themselves to his mind and heart, he suffered no obstacle and no
                    discouragement to triumph over his determination to give them all the currency
                    and prevalence that were possible in his day. Having clearly seen the end he had
                    in view, he with equal discernment made choice of his measures for its
                    attainment. The refinements alike of literature and of art had for him no place
                    in the Christian scheme; it is needless to say that he therefore despised them
                    both for himself and for others. There is some room for hoping indeed that the
                    burning of the books of the Palatine library was due to some ruder pontiff; but
                    there is no possibility of mistake as to the literary taste of the man who could
                    write (pref, to <hi rend="italic">Moralia)</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> “non
                    metacismi collisionem fugio, non barbarismi confusionem devito, situs motusque
                    etiam et praepositionum casus servare contemno, quia indignum vehementer
                    existimo utverba coelestis oraculi restringam sub regulis Donati.” The
                    uniformity of the Roman ritual, the ascendency of the Roman hierarchy, the
                    prevalency of the Catholic dogma,—these were not merely the highest, they were
                    the only, ideals he had ever caught sight of. It ought not therefore to surprise
                    us if in striving towards them he sometimes was tempted, and yielded to the
                    temptation, to sacrifice truthfulness to what he conceived to be the truth, and
                    the mere claims of humanity to the demands of what he regarded as a higher love.
                    Never purely selfish, he was, apart from the exigencies of his ecclesiastical
                    position, singularly tolerant, liberal, and kindly.</p>
                <p>Of the numerous extant works attributed to Gregory the Great the following are
                    undisputed:—the <hi rend="italic">Moralia,</hi> in thirty-five books, being an
                    exposition of the book of Job, composed between 580 and 590; the twenty-two <hi
                    rend="italic">Homilies on Ezekiel</hi> (about 595), and the forty <hi
                    rend="italic">Homilies on the Gospels</hi> (about 592); the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Regula</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Cura)</hi><hi rend="italic">Pastoralis,</hi>
                    dedicated to John, archbishop of Ravenna (about 590); the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dialogues</hi> with Peter the deacon, in four books, on the lives and miracles
                    of the Italian saints (593 or 594); and the <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> in
                    fourteen “registers,” aιτanged according to the years of his pontificate. He was
                    also the author of various rhymed hymns, nine of which are still extant and
                    appear in the collected editions of his works. They are characterized more by
                    simplicity of language than by depth of feeling. The <hi rend="italic">Concordia
                    quorundam</hi><hi rend="italic">testimoniorum sacrarum scripturarum,</hi> and
                    also the <hi rend="italic">Commentaries</hi> on 1 Kings, Canticles, and the
                    seven penitential psalms usually ascribed to him, are spurious. His liturgical
                    works, the <hi rend="italic">Sacramentarium</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Λntiphon-arium,</hi> have been considerably tampered with by mediaeval
                    collectors and revisers; and even the <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> are not
                    wholly free from interpolations. Of Gregory’s merits as an expositor little need
                    be said; he avowedly adopts in all cases the allegorical method, which in his
                    hands is unflinchingly carried out, with, in many cases, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n187/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0187-0176"/> sufficiently astounding results. As Milman has
                    remarked, “It may safely be said that, according to Gregory’s licence of
                    interpretation, there is nothing which might not be found in any book ever
                    written.” In practical homiletics, however, he is very often just and profound
                    as well as high-toned; but it would be too much to say that he was superior to
                    the prejudices of his time; in particular his preference for the monastic and
                    ascetic forms of the Christian life is carried to a height which a wider
                    observation of the conditions of human usefulness and happiness will never cease
                    to regaι ’ d as excessive. His <hi rend="italic">Dialogues,</hi> which have been
                    translated into Anglo-Saxon, Greek, and even Arabic, describe the most
                    astonishing miracles with an artless simplicity which, as suggestive of entire
                    belief, is certainly interesting to the student; yet it is difficult (as Gibbon
                    has pointed out) to free the lavish dispenser of miraculous filings from the
                    chains of St Peter from the suspicion of some degree of pious insincerity. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> are, as might be expected, of great importance
                    from the light they throw upon the history of those times.</p>
                <p>The complete editions of the works of this great father of the Latin Church have
                    been, as was to be expected, numerous. The earliest was that of Lyons (1516),
                    which was rapidly followed by those of Paris (1518-39), Basel (1551), and Rome
                    (1588). The best edition is the Benedictine (Paris, 1705), in 4 vols, fol.,
                    reprinted at Venice (1768-76), in 17 vols. 4to, and in Migne’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Patrology,</hi> vol. lxxv.-lxxix. See Wiggers, <hi rend="italic">De Gregorio
                    Magno</hi> (1838-40); Marggraf, <hi rend="italic">De Greg. Μ. Vita</hi> (1844);
                    Lau, <hi rend="italic">Gregor, d. Grosse</hi><hi rend="italic">nach</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">s.</hi><hi rend="italic">Leben</hi><hi rend="italic">u.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lehre dargestellt</hi> (1845); Pfähler, <hi rend="italic">Gregor
                    der Grosse u. seine Zeit</hi> (1852); and Baxmann, <hi rend="italic">Politik der
                    Päpste von Gregor I. bis Gregor VII.</hi> (1868-69). There is a convenient
                    edition of the <hi rend="italic">Cura</hi><hi rend="italic">Pastoralis</hi> by
                    Westhoff (1860).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
