<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0011-0002-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOUGH, Hugh Gough, Viscount (9th edition, volume 11,
                    page 2)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62g2p">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204607">Suriname</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1118436">Sikhs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOUGH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh Gough, Viscount</hi></label>
                    (1779-1869), British field-marshal, was of Irish origin, and was a descendant of
                    Francis Gough, who was made bishop of Limerick in 1626. He was born at
                    Woodstown, Limerick, November 3, 1779. After holding for a short time a
                    commission in his father’s regiment of militia, he was transferred to the line
                    as ensign in August 1794, and was very soon after promoted lieutenant. In the
                    following year he served with the 78th Highlanders at the Cape of Good Hope,
                    taking part in the capture of Cape Town and of the Dutch fleet in Saldanha Bay.
                    His next service was in the West Indies, where, with the 87th (Royal Irish
                    Fusiliers), he shared in the attack on Porto Rico, the capture of Surinam, and
                    the brigand war in St Lucia. In 1809 he was called to take part in the
                    Peninsular War, and, joining the army under Wellington, commanded his regiment
                    as major in the operations before Oporto, by which the town was taken from the
                    French. At Talavera he was severely wounded, and had his horse shot under him.
                    For his conduct on this occasion he was afterwards promoted lieutenant-colonel,
                    his commission, on the recommendation of Wellington, being antedated from the
                    day of the duke’s despatch. He was thus, as pointed out in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hares Army List,</hi> the first officer who ever received brevet rank for
                    services performed in the field at the head of a regiment. He was next engaged
                    at the battle of Barossa, at which his regiment captured a French eagle. At the
                    defence of Tarifa the post of danger was assigned to him, and he compelled the
                    enemy to raise the siege. At Vittoria, where Gough again distinguished himself,
                    his regiment captured the baton of Marshal Jourdan. He was again severely
                    wounded at Nivelle, and was soon after created a knight of St Charles by the
                    king of Spain. In recognition of his services the citizens of Dublin presented
                    him with the freedom of the city and with a costly sword. At the close of the
                    war he returned home and enjoyed a respite of some years from active service. He
                    next took command of a regiment stationed in the south of Ireland, discharging
                    at the same time the duties of a magistrate during a period of agitation. Gough
                    did not attain the rank of general officer till 1830, when he was promoted
                    major-general. Seven years later a new epoch opened for him; he was sent to
                    India to take command of the Mysore division of the army. But not long after his
                    arrival in India, the difficulties which had arisen between the Chinese and
                    British Governments, and which led to the first Chinese war, made the presence
                    of an energetic general on the scene indispensable, and Gough was appointed
                    commander-in-chief of the British forces in China. This post he held during all
                    the operations of the war; and by his great achievements and numerous victories
                    in the face of immense difficulties, he at length enabled the English
                    plenipotentiary, Sir H. Pöttinger, to dictate peace on his own terms, and on
                    terms of perfect equality with the emperor. After the conclusion of the treaty
                    of Nanking in August 1842 the British forces were withdrawn; and before the
                    close of the year Gough was created a baronet, and was invested with the grand
                    cross of the Bath. He also received the thanks of both Houses of Parliament.
                    Returning to India, he was appointed (August 1843) commander-inchief of the
                    British forces in India. In December 1843 he took the command in person against
                    the Mahrattas, and defeated them at Maharajpore, capturing more than fifty guns.
                    He defeated them again at Punniar, and peace was then concluded at Gwalior. In
                    1845 occurred the rupture with the Sikhs, who crossed the Sutlej in large
                    numbers, and Sir Hugh Gough conducted the operations against them. In this
                    campaign he was well supported by Lord Hardinge, the governor-general, who had
                    been his comrade in the Peninsula, and now volunteered to serve under him. The
                    Sikhs were defeated in three great battles in rapid succession—at Moodkee,
                    Ferozeshah, and Sobraon,—and submitted to make peace soon after at Lahore. The
                    services of Sir Hugh Gough on these occasions were rewarded by a vote of thanks
                    from both Houses of Parliament, and by his elevation to the peerage of the
                    United Kingdom as Baron Gough (April 1846). The war broke out again in 1848, and
                    again Lord Gough took the field. With unabated energy he defeated the Sikhs at
                    Ramnuggar, and at Chillianwallah, and finally broke their power by his decisive
                    victory at Gujrat (February 1849). He was now succeeded as commander-in-chief by
                    Sir Charles Napier, and, returning to England, was raised to a viscountcy, and
                    for the third time received the thanks of both Houses of Parliament. A pension
                    of £2000 per annum was granted to him by parliament, and an equal pension by the
                    East India Company. He did not again see active service. In 1854 he was
                    appointed colonel of the Royal Horse Guards, and two years later he was sent to
                    the Crimea to invest Marshal Pelissier and other officers with the insignia of
                    the Bath. Honours were multiplied upon him during his latter years. He was made
                    a knight of St Patrick, being the first knight of the order who did not hold an
                    Irish peerage, was sworn a privy councillor, was named a knight grand commander
                    of the Star of India, and in November 1862 was made field-marshal. He was twice
                    married, and left children by both his wives. He died at his seat near Dublin,
                    March 2, 1869.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
