<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0057-0048-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRANITE (9th edition, volume 11, page 48)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1085454">Quartz</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1019324">Mica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884667">Crystals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884644">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:879476">Cornish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80x9m">Quartz</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28m5p">Mica</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s42j">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wc2h">Fusion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n57/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GRANITE</label>, a rock so named from the Latin granum, a
                    grain, in allusion to the granular texture of many of its varieties. The term
                    appears to have been introduced by the early Italian antiquaries, and it is
                    believed that the first recorded use of the word occurs in a description of Rome
                    by Flaininiue Vacca, an Italian sculptor of the 16th century. This description
                    was published by Montfaucon in his <hi rend="italic">Diarium Italicum,</hi>
                    where we read of certain columns “ex marmore granito Aegyptio” (cap. xvii.), and
                    of others “ex marmore granito Aethaliae insulae” (cap. xviii.), showing that the
                    Romans of Vacca’s day were acquainted with granite from Egypt and from Elba.
                    Granite is also referred to by Caesalpinus in his treatise <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Metallicis</hi> (1596), and by Tournefort in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Relation Tun Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic">au</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Levant</hi> (1698); indeed the latter has been cited by Emmerling <hi
                    rend="italic">(Lehrb. d. Mineral.}</hi> as the first author who uses the term.
                    By these early writers, however, the name was loosely applied to several
                    distinct kinds of granular rock, and it remained for Werner to give it that
                    precise meaning which it at present possesses as the specific designation of a
                    rock.</p>
                <p>Granite is a crystalline-granular rock consisting, in its typical varieties, of
                    orthoclase, quartz, and mica, to which a plagioclastic felspar is usually added.
                    These minerals are aggregated together without the presence of any matrix or
                    connecting medium. Thin sections of a true granite, examined under the
                    microscope by transmitted light, show no trace of any amorphous or
                    crypto-crystalline groundmass. The chemical composition of the rock will, of
                    course, vary with its mineralogical constitution. For an average analysis see
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Geology,</hi> vol. x. p. 233. The proportion of silica
                    varies fιδm 62 to 81 per cent. Granite belongs therefore to Bunsen’s class of
                    <hi rend="italic">acid</hi> rocks, or those which contain more than 60 per cent,
                    of silica. Dr Haughton has found an exceptionally low proportion of this oxide
                    in some of the Irish granites (58 ’ 44 per cent., <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>
                    in some Donegal granite, <hi rend="italic">Quark Jourη. Geol. Soc.,</hi> xviii.,
                    1862, p. 408). The specific gravity of granite varies from 2 ’ 59 to 273.</p>
                <p>Orthoclase, or potash felspar, is the principal constituent of most granites.
                    This mineral occurs either in simple crystals, or in twins formed on what is
                    known as the “Carlsbad type,” such crystals being common at Carlsbad in Bohemia.
                    In porphyritic granites, such as those of Cornwall and Devon, the orthoclase
                    crystals may attain to a length of several inches, and the twinning is marked on
                    the fractured crystals by a line running longitudinally down the middle, and
                    dividing the crystal into two halves. In colour the orthoclase generally varies
                    between snow-white and flesh-red. The green felspar known as Amazon stone, which
                    occurs in certain granites, has lately been shown by Des Cloiseaux to belong to
                    the species <hi rend="italic">microcline,</hi> and not, as previously supposed,
                    to orthoclase <hi rend="italic">(Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">d. Ch.,</hi> 5
                    ser., ix., 1876, p. 433). The plagioclastic, anorthic, or triclinic felspar of
                    granite occurs in crystals which are generally smaller than those of the
                    orthoclase, and which exhibit, even to the naked eye, their characteristic twin
                    striation. Moreover the lustre is frequently resinous or fatty, while that of
                    the orthoclase is pearly on the cleavage-planes. In most cases the plagioclase
                    is the soda-lime felspar called <hi rend="italic">oligoclase</hi>; but in some
                    granites it is <hi rend="italic">albite</hi> or soda felspar, as shown by
                    Haughton in many of the Irish and Cornish granites <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Roy.
                    Soc.,</hi> xvii., 1869, p. 209). When a granite becomes weathered, the felspar
                    may decompose into <hi rend="italic">kaolin</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >china-clay</hi>; the commencement of this alteration is indicated under the
                    microscope by the turbidity of the felspar, by the ill-defined edges of the
                    crystals, and in the case of plagioclase by disappearance of the characteristic
                    striae.</p>
                <p>The quartz of granite occurs generally in irregularly-shaped angular grains; but
                    occasionally in distinct crystals which are double hexagonal pyramids with or
                    without the corresponding prism. Colourless quartz is most common, but grey,
                    brown, or bluish varieties also occur. Whatever its colour, it is as a rule
                    transparent in microscopic sections, though sometimes rendered milky by the
                    presence of vast numbers of minute cavities containing liquid (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Geology,</hi><hi rend="italic">ut supra,</hi> and for Sorby’s
                    original researches <hi rend="italic">Quart. Joum. Geol. Soc.,</hi> xiv. p.
                    453). In many granites the quartz fills up the spaces between the crystals of
                    felspar and of mica, and receives impressions from these minerals. This fact has
                    been advanced against the view that granite has existed in a state of fusion;
                    since it is assumed that, as the quartz is the most infusible of the three
                    component minerals, it would have been the first to solidify on the cooling of
                    the magma, whereas the relation of the quartz to the associated minerals in most
                    cases shows that it must have solidified after the crystallization of the
                    felspar and mica. In some granites, however, the quartz is developed in free
                    crystals, thus pointing to an early solidification of this mineral. The mica,
                    which is usually the least abundant constituent of the granite, occurs in thin
                    scales of irregular shape or in hexagonal plates. It is either a white biaxial
                    potash mica <hi rend="italic">(muscovite)</hi> or a dark-brown magnesian mica,
                    generally uniaxial <hi rend="italic">(biotite).</hi> Both species may occur in
                    the same granite. Haughton has shown that some of the white mica of the Cornish
                    granites is <hi rend="italic">lepidolite,</hi> or lithia mica; while some of the
                    black mica in the same rocks is the iron-potash<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n58/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0058-0049"/> mica, <hi rend="italic">lepidomelane (Proc. Roy.
                    Soc.,</hi> xvii. p. 209). Professor Heddle finds that the black mica of most
                    Soottish granites is a distinct species, which he calls <hi rend="italic"
                    >Haughtonite (Mineralog. Hag.,</hi> No. 13,1879, p. 72). A large number of
                    accessory minerals occur in granite, no fewer than forty-four being cited by
                    Zirkel <hi rend="italic">(Lehrb. d. Petrog.,i.</hi> p. 481). Upon the presence
                    of these supplementary minerals numerous varieties of granite have been founded.
                    Thus, if tourmaline be present, the rock is a <hi rend="italic"
                    >schorlaceous</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tourmaline granite;</hi> when
                    cassiterite or tin-stone occurs, it forms a <hi rend="italic">stanniferous
                    granite</hi>; the presence of epidote gives rise to an <hi rend="italic">epidote
                    granite;</hi> and so on with other minerals. The most common accessory
                    constituent of granite is hornblende, a mineral which appears to replace to some
                    extent the mica, and thus produces a <hi rend="italic">horηblendic</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">syenitic granite.</hi> This rock was formerly, and by some
                    petrographers is still, termed <hi rend="italic">syenite</hi>; it is the <hi
                    rend="italic">syenites</hi> of Pliny, so named from Syene in Upper Egypt, where
                    a smiliar rock was quarried by the ancient Egyptians. By modern petrographers,
                    however, the term syenite is usually restricted to a rock which is an aggregate
                    of orthoclase and hornblende,—in other words, a granite in which the quartz has
                    disappeared while the mica lias been superseded by hornblende. A beautiful
                    schorlaceous rock, which is apparently a variety of granite, has been described
                    by Pisani under the name of <hi rend="italic">luxullianite</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(Comptes Rendus,</hi> lix., 1864, p. 913). It occurs in the parish of
                    Luxullian, near Lostwithiel, in Cornwall, where it is found in the form of
                    boulders, but has not been detected <hi rend="italic">in situ.</hi> This rock is
                    composed of tourmaline, or schorl, with quartz and orthoclase; the last named
                    mineral occurring in large flesh-coloured crystals, which by contrast with the
                    dark base produce a very beautiful effect. Two varieties of tourmaline, one
                    brown and the other bluish, have been detected by Γrofessor Bonney <hi
                    rend="italic">(Mineralog. Mag.,</hi> No. 7, 1877, p. 215). The sarcophagus of
                    the duke of Wellington, in St Paul’s Cathedral, is wrought out of a splendid
                    block of luxullianite. Many varieties of granite are founded upon structural
                    characteristics. Occasionally the constituents are developed in such large
                    individuals as to form a <hi rend="italic">giant granite.</hi> Crystals of
                    orthoclase, associated with quartz in a peculiar parallel arrangement, produce
                    the variety known as <hi rend="italic">graphic granite</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lapis Judaicus—</hi> names which refer to the resemblance which the rock
                    presents, when cut in certain directions, to lines of Hebrew characters. Graphic
                    granite was termed by Hauyρ¾77nα^te, but this name is now generally applied to a
                    coarse admixture of 0rth0cla3e, quartz, and silvery mica. When any of the
                    component minerals occur in large crystals, embedded in a fine-grained base, a
                    <hi rend="italic">porphyritic granite</hi> is produced. Generally the crystals
                    are those of orthoclase, as in many of the West of England granites, and in the
                    characteristic rock of Shap Fell in Westmoreland. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Graηitite</hi> is a name applied to a variety of granite made up of orthoclase
                    and quartz, with more or less plagioclase and a small proportion of mica. A
                    granite composed of only felspar and quartz is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >hoplite</hi> or <hi rend="italic">semi-granite.</hi> Some of the micaless
                    varieties are known as <hi rend="italic">granulite.</hi> When, instead of the
                    mica disappearing, the felspar is absent, the resulting aggregate of quartz and
                    mica is termed <hi rend="italic">greisen</hi>; it is frequently a tin-bearing
                    rock. Occasionally the granite, when fine in grain, loses its mica, and an
                    intimate mixture of orthoclase and quartz is thus obtained; such a rock is known
                    as a <hi rend="italic">felstone.</hi> Crystals of orthoclase disseminated
                    through a felsitic matrix, either compact or microcrystalline, give rise to a
                    <hi rend="italic">felspar porphyry</hi>; while crystals or rounded grains of
                    quartz in a similar felsitic base produce a <hi rend="italic"
                    >quartz-porphyry</hi> or <hi rend="italic">quartz-felsite.</hi> By Cornish
                    miners these quartz-porphyries are termed <hi rend="italic">elvans
                    (elvanite</hi> of Jukes); but this name is also applied to fine grained granites
                    and to almost any rock which occurs as a dyke running through the killas or clay
                    slate.</p>
                <p>Few questions have been more warmly discussed than the origin of granite. When
                    this rock is found forcing its way through older rocks, and appearing at the
                    surface in large bosses from which veins are sent forth in all directions, there
                    can be little doubt of its eruptive character. The small width of some of these
                    granitic veins, or apophyses, suggests that the rock must have existed in a
                    condition of perfect fusion or complete liquidity, and not simply as a viscous
                    paste, before it could have been injected into such narrow fissures as those
                    which are now occupied by granite. In many cases, the rocks which are penetrated
                    by the granitic veins are altered in such a manner as to indicate a considerable
                    elevation of temperature: a limestone in the neighbourhood of the veins may
                    become saccharoidal, and shales may become indurated or even converted into
                    hornstone, while new minerals are often developed in the vicinity of the
                    intruded veins. In these veins the granite is apt to change its mineralogical
                    constitution, becoming either fine-grained or felsitic, or even reduced at the
                    extremities of the vein to quartz. From the days of Hutton it has been generally
                    admitted that most granite is of igneous origin. Since it appears to have been
                    solidified at great depths beneath the surface, it has been distinguished as a
                    <hi rend="italic">plutonic</hi> rock, while those eruptive rocks which have
                    risen to the surface, and have there consolidated, are termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >volcanic</hi> rocks. The older geologists regarded granite as the primitive
                    rock of the earth’s crust, forming the floor of all stratified deposits and the
                    nucleus of mountain chains. Such a view, however, has been long exploded. It is
                    known indeed that granite, so far from being in all cases an original rock, may
                    be of almost any geological age. Some is undoubtedly as old as the Silurian
                    period, while other granites are certainly as young as the Tertiary rocks, and
                    perhaps of even more recent date. By many field-geologists granite has of late
                    years been regarded as a metamorphic rather than as a truly igneous rock.
                    Metamorphism, however, is a term which has been so vaguely used that most of our
                    eruptive rocks may, in a certain sense, be said to be metamorphic. Still, in the
                    case of granite, it has often been pointed out that a passage may be traced from
                    this rock into gneiss, and that gneiss itself may be regarded as an altered
                    sedimentary rock. Thus so experienced an observer as Professor Ramsay expresses
                    his opinion that “granite is sometimes merely gneiss still further metamorphosed
                    by heat in the presence of moisture” <hi rend="italic">(Phys. Geol. of Gt.
                    Brit.,</hi> 5 ed., 1878, p. 42). For a number of instances in which granite is
                    said to pass into gneissose rocks, and these in turn, by numerous gradations,
                    into undoubtedly stratified deposits, see Green’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geology,</hi> part i. p. 307, and also <hi rend="smallcaps">Geology,</hi> vol.
                    x, p. 309.</p>
                <p>Chemists have also brought forward arguments against the igneous origin of
                    granite. Thus it has been argued that the specific gravity of the quartz of
                    granite is about 2^6, while that of silica after fusion is only 2 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 2. It must be remembered, however, that the quartz of
                    granite has solidified under great pressure, as proved by Mr Sorby’s
                    observations, and it is probable that such pressure would increase the density
                    of the silica. ΔIoreover, it has been pointed out by the late D. Forbes <hi
                    rend="italic">(Geol. Mag.,</hi> iv., No. 10, 1867, p. 443) that the siliceous
                    tests of certain infusoria, which assuredly have not been fused, are as low as
                    <hi rend="italic">2'2.</hi> Another argument which has been advanced against the
                    igneous origin of granitic rocks is based on the fact that they contain minerals
                    of a basic character which could not have existed in a state of fusion in the
                    presence of free silica, without forming a combination with the latter. Again,
                    some of the accessory minerals in granite would suffer change by an elevation of
                    temperature, while many of them contain water which, it is assumed, would be
                    expelled on fusion. Probably, however, these minerals are in most <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n59/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0059-0050"/> cases of secondary origin, and have been produced
                    by the alteration of the granite. The mere presence of water is not incompatible
                    with a pyrognostic origin; and Forbes has asserted <hi rend="italic">(op.
                    cit.)</hi> that specimens of lava, taken from a current on Etna while the lava
                    was still flowing, contained crystals of stilbite, a mineral containing 16 per
                    cent, of water. Mr Sorby has shown, too, that the quartz of volcanic rocks
                    contains microscopic cavities enclosing liquid. It appears, indeed, that in the
                    fusion of all eruptive rocks water has played a very important part. Dr Haughton
                    has sought to reconcile the opposing views as to the origin of granite by
                    admitting what he calls a <hi rend="italic">hydrometamorphic</hi> origin for
                    this rock. He believes that the rock, having been poured into veins and dykes
                    when in a state of fusion, was subsequently altered by the action of water at
                    temperatures which, though high, were insufficient for the fusion of the granite
                    <hi rend="italic">(On the Origin of Granite: an Address to the Geol. Soc. of
                    Dublin,</hi> 1862).</p>
                <p>Granitic rocks are extensively used for constructive and decorative purposes,
                    though their industrial applications are necessarily restricted by the expense
                    of working so hard a material. Although some granites are apt to decompose on
                    exposure to atmospheric influences, the felspar passing into china-clay, other
                    varieties are remarkable for their extreme durability, as attested by the
                    monuments of ancient Egypt, on which the incised hieroglyphics still retain
                    their sharpness. It appears that in England granite was not brought into
                    extensive use much before the beginning of the present century (Creasy). It is
                    now largely employed for massive structures, such as bridges and sea-walls, as
                    also for kerbs and paving-sets. The best known granites are the grey variety
                    from Aberdeen and the red granite of Peterhead, 30 miles north of Aberdeen. The
                    granite of Dartmoor in Devonshire, and of the huge bosses which protrude through
                    the clay slate of Cornwall, are largely worked as building and ornamental stones
                    (for description of these granites see Sir H. T. de la Beche’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Report on the Ged. of Cornwall and Devon).</hi> In Ireland there is much fine
                    granite, which is quarried to a limited extent,—the Castlewellan granite having
                    been used in the Albert Memorial in Hyde Park (Hull’s <hi rend="italic">Building
                    and 0rnam. Stones,</hi> 1872). The hornblendic varieties of granite are
                    remarkably tough, and are largely employed for road-metal. For this purpose
                    great quantities are quarried in the Channel Islands. Red granite occurs in
                    abundance on the coasts of Maine, U.S., as well as in New Brunswick, and grey
                    granite at Quincy and elsewhere in Massachusetts. Granite is frequently polished
                    when used for monumental and decorative purposes. The polishing is effected by
                    an iron tool, worked first with sand and water, then with emery, and lastly with
                    putty-powder or oxide of tin; when the emery and putty are used, a surface of
                    flannel is interposed between the granite and the iron tool (“On Granite
                    Working,” by Geo. W. Muir, <hi rend="italic">Jourη. Soc. Arts,</hi> xiv., 1866,
                    p. 470).</p>
                <p>As an element of scenery granite generally forms rounded hills, scantily clad
                    with vegetation; but it sometimes rises into sharp pinnacles, as in the <hi
                    rend="italic">aiguilles</hi> of the Alps. By denudation the rock may break up
                    into cuboidal blocks, which often remain piled upon each other, forming the
                    characteristic “tors” of Cornwall and Devon. Hills of granite are frequently
                    surmounted by masses of weathered rock of spheroidal form, such as the Cornish
                    rocking-stones or logan stones. The weathering of granite often produces
                    boulder-shaped masses in such numbers as to form, around the summit of the hill,
                    a “sea of rocks” <hi rend="italic">(Felsenmeer).</hi></p>
                <p>In addition to the references given in the body of this article, the following
                    authorities may be cited:— <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Petrographie,</hi> by
                    F. Zirkel, 2 vols., Bonn, 1866; <hi rend="italic">Elemente der
                    Petrographie,</hi> by Von Lasaulx, Bonn, 1875; Cotta’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lithology,</hi> translated by P. H. Lawrence, 2d ed., London, 1878; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Study of</hi><hi rend="italic">Rocks,</hi> by F. Rutley,
                    London, 1879; and the numerous contributions by the</p>
                <p>Rev. Prof. Haughton in <hi rend="italic">Proc. Irish Acad.,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Quark Journ. Geol. Soc. Loud.</hi> For chemical composition of
                    Cleopatra’s Needle, by G. W. Wigner, see the <hi rend="italic">Analyst,</hi>
                    1878, p. 382. (F. W. R,*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
