<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0908-0876-0841-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FABRICIUS, Joannes Albertus (9th edition, volume 8,
                    page 841)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29k07">Adversaria</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c0c">Logic</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:951507">Harmonica</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n876/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FABRICIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joannes Albertus</hi></label>
                    (1668-1736), one of the most learned, laborious, and useful of bibliographers,
                    was born at Leipsic, November 11, 1668. His father, Werner Fabricius, director
                    of music in the church of St Paul at Leipsic, was the author of several works,
                    particularly <hi rend="italic">Delicice Harmonica?,</hi> published in 1657.
                    Joannes Albertus himself commenced his studies under his father, who on his
                    deathbed recommended him to the care of Valentine Alberti. He studied under
                    Wenceslas Buhl and J. S. Herrichen, and afterwards at Quedlinburg under Samuel
                    Schmidt It was in Schmidt’s library, as he afterwards said, that he found the
                    two works, Barthuiss’s <hi rend="italic">Adversaria</hi> and Morhoffs <hi
                        rend="italic">Polyhistor,</hi> which suggested to him the idea of his
                    Bibliothecae, the kind of work for which he stands pre-eminent among scholars.
                    Having returned to Leipsic in 1686, he was the same year admitted bachelor in
                    philosophy; and in the beginning of 1688 he took the degree of master in the
                    same faculty, shortly after which he published his first work, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scriptorum recentium decas,</hi> an attack on ten writers of the day,
                    Thomasius among them. His <hi rend="italic">Decas Decadum, sive plagiarorum et
                        pseudonymorum centuria,</hi> published in the following year, is the only
                    one of his works to which ho signs the name Faber. He then applied himself to
                    the study of medicine, which, however, he relinquished for that of theology; and
                    having gone to Hamburg in 1693, he proposed to travel abroad, when the
                    unexpected tidings that the expense of his education had absorbed his whole
                    patrimony, and even left him in debt to his trustee, forced him to abandon his
                    project. He therefore remained at Hamburg, where J. F. Mayer employed him in the
                    capacity of librarian. In 1696 he accompanied his patron to Sweden; <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n877/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0877-0842"/> and, on his return to Hamburg, not long
                    afterwards, he competed for the chair of logic and philosophy. The suffrages
                    being equally divided between Fabricius and Sebastian Edzardi, one of his
                    opponents, the appointment was decided by lot in favour of Edzardi; but in 1699
                    Fabricius succeeded Vincent Placciu3 in the chair of rhetoric and ethics, after
                    which he took the degree of doctor in theology at Kiel. In 1701 J. F. Mayer, who
                    had established himself at Greifswald, caused the chair of theology in that city
                    co be offered to Fabricius; but he refused it on account of his health. But in
                    1708 he accepted the professorship of theology, logic, and metaphysics, and was
                    preparing to enter on his new office, when the senate of Hamburg induced him to
                    remain, by adding to his professorship the office of rector of the school of St
                    John, then held by his father-in-law Schultz. Schultz died in 1709, but
                    Fabricius retained the rectorship two years longer. In 1719 the landgrave of
                    Hesse-Cassel made him so advantageous an offer that he was on the point of
                    accepting it; but this time also the magistrates, by a seasonable increase of
                    salary, prevailed on him to remain with them. An attempt was subsequently made
                    to draw him to Wittenberg; but he refused to listen to the proposals made to
                    him, and remained at Hamburg, where he died April 30, 1736.</p>
                <p>Niceron and Reimar give a list of 128 books by Fabricius, but very many of them
                    were only works which he had edited. One of the most famed and laborious of his
                    works is the <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Latina, sive notitia auctorum veterum
                        Latinorum quorumeunque scripta ad nos pervenerunt,</hi> Hamburg, 1697, 8vo,
                    a work which was republished in an improved and amended form by J. A. Ernesti,
                    Leipsic, 1773, in three vols. 8vo. The divisions of the compilation are—the
                    writers to the age of Tiberius; thence to that of the Antonines; and thirdly, to
                    the decay of the language; while a fourth gives fragments from old authors, and
                    chapters on early Christian literature. His <hi rend="italic">chef d'oeuvre</hi>
                    is the <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Grceca, sive notitia scriptorum veterum
                        Graxorum quorumeunque monumenta integra aut fragmenta edita extant, turn
                        plcrorumque e manuscript, ac deperditis,</hi> Hamburg, 1705-1728, in 14
                    vols. 4to, a work which has justly been denominated <hi rend="italic">maximus
                        antiques eruditionis thesaurus.</hi> It was rearranged by Harles, at
                    Hamburg, in 1790. Its divisions are marked off by Homer, Plato, Christ,
                    Constantine, and the capture of Constantinople in 1453, while a sixth section is
                    devoted to canon law, jurisprudence, and medicine. Of his remaining works we may
                    mention— <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Antiquaria, sive introductio in notitiam
                        scriptorum qui antiquitates Hebraicas, Grcecas, Romanos, et Christianas
                        scriptis illustrarunt,</hi> 1713 and 1726, 4to; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Centifolium Lutheranum, sive notitia litcraria scriptorum omnis generis de
                        B. D. Luthero,</hi> 1728 and 1730, 8vo; as also <hi rend="italic">Salutaris
                        lux cvangclii toti orbi per divinam gratiam exoriens, sive notitia
                        historico-chronologica, litteraria, ac geographica propagatorum per orbcm
                        totum Christianorum Sacrorum,</hi> 1731, 4to; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hydro-theology,</hi> in German, 1734, 4to. Among the principal works edited
                    by Fabricius may be named <hi rend="italic">Joannis Mabillonii iter Germanicum,
                        et joannis Launoii de Scholis cclebribus a Carolo Magno et post Carolum
                        Magnum in occidcnte instauratis liber,</hi> 1717, 8vo.</p>
                <p>The details of the life of Fabricius are to be found in <hi rend="italic">De Vita
                        et Scriptis</hi><hi rend="italic">J. A.</hi><hi rend="italic">Fabricii
                        Commentarius,</hi> by his son-in-law, H. S. Reimar, published at Hamburg,
                    1757. This is the work whence Niceron, Chauffepie, and other writers on the
                    subject have borrowed their materials. Niceron’s work is entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Mcmoires pour servir a I’histoire des hommes illustrcs dans la
                        republique des lettres, avec un catalogue raisonne de leurs ouvrages,</hi>
                    Paris, 1729-1745.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
