<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0908-0870-0835-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FABIAN GENS, The (9th edition, volume 8, page
                    835)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:876196">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863259">Clans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843068">Buteo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:989788">Labeo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n870/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">FABIAN GENS, <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi></label>, was said
                    by the genealogists to have been descended from Hercules and a daughter of the
                    Arcadian Evander. Niebuhr’s supposition of the Sabine origin of the clan has
                    been held to be inconsistent with the tradition regarding the pre-Sabine
                    institution of the <hi rend="italic">Luper-ccdia,</hi> the yearly festival
                    inaugurated at the sacrifice which Romulus and Remus offered in the Lupercal
                    after the death of Amulius, and at which, according to the legend, they agreed
                    to distinguish their respective adherents by filenames Quinctilii and Fabii. The
                    two colleges of the Luperci retained these designations long after the members
                    of the two clans ceased to exercise exclusive control over the <hi rend="italic"
                        >sacra.</hi> The chief family names of the Fabian gens or clan, during the
                    commonwealth, were Vibulanus, Ambustus, Maximus, Buteo, Pictor, Dorso, Labeo;
                    and Verrucosus, Rullianus, Gurges, Eburnus, ^Emilianus, Allobrogicus, may be
                    enumerated among their <hi rend="italic">agnomina.</hi> Vibulanus and the two
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n871/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0908-0871-0836"/> following names belonged, however, to the
                    same family at different epochs, Q. Fabius Vibulanus, who was consul in 412 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> having been the first to assume the cognomen of
                    Ambustus; while Rullianus, according to some accounts, changed the latter into
                    Maximus, in 312 B.c.—his full name thus being Q. Fabius Maximus Rullianus. Of
                    the Vibulani, first noticed about the year 486 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>
                    the most distinguished w ere the three brothers, Quintus, Kseso, and Marcus, one
                    or other of whom filled one of the two consulships from that date to 479. In
                    that year the Fabii—to the number, it is said, of 306 patricians, exclusive of
                    their numerous dependents—emigrated from Rome under the leadership of Kseso, who
                    had just been consul for the third time, and settled on the banks of the
                    Cremera, a few miles above Rome. Some accounts have attributed that secession to
                    the opposition which the Fabian support of the plebs had aroused among the old
                    patrician families. For two years the exiles or seceders continued to be the
                    city’s chief defence against the Veientes, until at last they were surprised by
                    the latter, and cut off to a man. The only survivor of the gens was the son of
                    Marcus, who had been left behind at Rome, and who thus became the ancestor of
                    the succeeding Fabii. He was consul in 467 B.c., and a member of the second
                    decemvirate in 450. When the Gauls captured Rome in 390 the pontifex maximus was
                    a Fabius Ambustus. The most famous of this line— <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>
                    supposing Rullianus to have been the first Maximus—was the father of Rullianus.
                    He was thrice consul, and was dictator in 351 B.c. His son, Rullianus, called by
                    Arnold the “Talbot of the 5th century of Rome,” was master of the horse in 365
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> to Papirius Cursor, by whom he was degraded
                    for having fought and beaten the Samnites contrary to orders. In 296, when
                    consul for the sixth time, he defeated, at the great battle of Sentinum, the
                    combined forces of the Etrurians, Umbrians, Samnites, and Gauls. But the
                    greatest Roman who bore the name of Fabius—one of the most illustrious Romans of
                    the republic—was Q. Fabius Maximus Verrucosus (see below). Of the later Fabii,
                    Q. Fabius Maximus JEmilianus and Q. Fabius Maximus Allobrogicus were among the
                    most distinguished. The former, a Fabius only by adoption, served in the last
                    Macedonian war, 168 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and was consul in Spain 145
                    B.c., when he conquered Viriathus. He was the pupil and the patron of the
                    historian Polybius. The Fabius named Allobrogicus (after his victory over the
                    Allobroges and their ally Bituitus, king of the Arverni) was consul in 121 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The Fabian name is occasionally met with as late
                    as the 2d century <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi></p>
                <p>Perhaps the most complete work on this family is the <hi rend="italic">Disputatio
                        de Gente Fabia,</hi> hy G. N. Du Rieu, Leyden, 1856, where may also be found
                    a list of previous writers on the same subject.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
