<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-2984-0571-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARMAGH (7th edition, volume 3, page 571)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827162">Banns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845034">Cams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb15">Cams</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193102984?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARMAGH</label>, an inland county in the province of Ulster,
                    in Ireland, is bounded on the north by Lough Neagh, on the east by the county of
                    Down, on the south-east by that of Louth, on the south-west by that of Monaghan,
                    and on the west by the county of Tyrone. According to Ptolemy, it was inhabited
                    by the Vinderii and Voluntii. It afterwards formed part of a territory called
                    Orgial or Uriel, which also extended over Louth, Monaghan, and some smaller
                    districts. It was likewise subdivided into the tracts or countries of
                    Clanbrassil, the M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Cahans or M <hi
                    rend="superscript"> i</hi> Canes, Oirthir or Orior, the O’Hanlons, the Fews, and
                    Hy Niellan. In the reign of James I. it was made shire ground, under its present
                    name. It is now divided into∙l the eight baronies of Armagh, Upper Fews, Lower
                    Fews, O’Neilland East, O’Neilland West, Upper Orior, Lower labour. The result
                    has shown the soundness of Mr Rasbotham’s opinion. It is doubtful whether 30,000
                    persons were employed in all the branches of the cotton manufacture in 1767;
                    whereas, in consequence of those very inventions which the workmen endeavoured
                    to destroy, there are now upwards of 1,000,000 directly engaged in its different
                    departments ι There is, in fact, no idea so groundless and absurd as that which
                    supposes that an increased facility of production can, under any circumstances,
                    be injurious to the labourers.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193102997?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-2997-0572"/>
                <p>Orior, and Turaney. The superficies of the county has been estimated at 293,919
                    acres, or nearly 458 square miles.</p>
                <p>Considered in its ecclesiastical relations, it forms part of the archiépiscopal
                    province of Armagh, which comprises the dioceses of Armagh, Clogher, Meath,
                    Down, Connor, Derry, Raphoe, Kilmore, Dromore, and Ardagh. The archbishopric of
                    Armagh extends over 468,500 acres, in the counties of Armagh, Londonderry,
                    Tyrone, Louth, and Meath. It contains 111 parishes, consolidated into 80
                    benefices, having 78 churches, 75 glebe houses, and 16,324 acres of glebe,
                    which, if equally apportioned among the incumbents, would give an average of 204
                    acres to each. Of these benefices the king presents to 4; the archbishop to 43;
                    other dignitaries of the diocese to 14; laymen to 11; Trinity college, Dublin,
                    to 4; St Patrick’s cathedral, Dublin, to one; besides which, there are two joint
                    presentations, and one disputed. The tithe paid by 48 of these parishes, which
                    have conformed to the provisions of the tithe composition act, amounts to
                    L.19,292, being at the rate of L.402 annually to each parish. If the aggregate
                    of the tithe of those which have not yet compounded bear the same proportion to
                    the number of parishes as those which have, the total tithe of the diocese would
                    amount to L.44,613, which, divided among the 80 incumbents, would afford an
                    income to each of L.557 per annum, independently of glebes, manses, or
                    occasional dues. The archbishop’s income, derived from lands, is estimated at
                    L.22,000 per annum.</p>
                <p>The county of Armagh contains 22 entire parishes, and 5 parts of parishes, the
                    remainder of which are in some of the adjoining counties. The total population,
                    according to the last census, taken in 1821, amounts to 197,427 souls, being at
                    the rate of one individual to every acre and a half, or one family to every
                    eight acres. Of this population, 28,905 are stated in the same census to be
                    employed in agriculture, 67,182 in trade, manufactures, and commerce, and 14,521
                    in other occupations, leaving 86,819 of both sexes and of every age
                    unoccupied.</p>
                <p>The county of Armagh returns three members to the imperial parliament,—two for
                    the county at large, and one for the city. The election for the county is
                    vested, as in all the other counties of Ireland, in the freeholders, whose
                    number, previously to the passing of the Catholic Relief Bill in 1829, amounted
                    to 8746,—a large number for a county, one of the smallest in superficial extent.
                    These were classed as follows,—203 freeholders holding tenures of L.50 value;
                    124 of those of L.20; and 8419 of those of L.2, or, as they are more commonly
                    called, forty shilling freeholders. The abolition of the last-named class, which
                    took place at the period just mentioned, reduced the number of electors to 1361,
                    viz. 235 freeholders of L.50; 186 of L.20; and 940 of L.10, which is now the
                    lowest value of a tenure entitling a freeholder to vote.</p>
                <p>The nature of the soil, and the general character of the land, are well adapted
                    for agricultural purposes. Hills of gentle ascent, of pleasing forms and various
                    altitudes, diversify the surface. Large tracts, particularly in the vicinity of
                    Armagh city, and thence throughout the northern parts, are covered with a
                    stratum of rich productive soil: many of these are well adapted for the culture
                    of wheat, being composed of a strong clay resting on a substratum of excellent
                    limestone. The southern and western parts rise into a rugged, and in many parts
                    a barren elevation, known by the name of the Fews Mountains. The highest of
                    these mountains, and the second in height in the province, is named
                    Slieve-Gallien. Its top is crowned by a large cairn or pile of stones, which
                    forms the roof of a singular cavern of artificial construction, seemingly
                    intended for other than sepulchral purposes.</p>
                <p>Two lower ranges, named the Newry and Fathom Mountains, lie nearer the sea.</p>
                <p>Indications of lead show themselves in several parts; traces of deserted mines of
                    this mineral have also been discovered, but none are now wrought. Marble of good
                    quality and some beauty is raised in large quantities near the city of Armagh. A
                    blue stone, well adapted for building, is common in many places. The steatite or
                    soap-stone has also been found; as likewise good potters’ earth, brilliant cubic
                    pyrites, and ironstone of very rich quality. Chalybeate springs in several parts
                    point out the existence of iron; but this mineral has not been found in
                    sufficient quantities to justify the outlay of money towards raising it. Pearls,
                    the production of a species of shell-fish between the oyster and the muscle,
                    have been found in the river Bann.</p>
                <p>The county is well watered by numerous streams; the principal are the Callen, the
                    Tynan, and the Tallwater, which fall into the Blackwater, a river that, after
                    forming part of the boundary between this county and Tyrone, empties itself into
                    the south-western angle of Lough Neagh. The Tara, the Newtoun Hamilton, the
                    Creggan, and the Fleury, flow into the Bay of Dundalk. The Cam or Cam-lin joins
                    the Bann, which, rising in the Mourne Mountains, in the southern extremity of
                    the county of Down, forms part of the western boundary of Armagh county, and
                    falls into Lough Neagh to the east of the Blackwater. With the aid of a canal,
                    the Bann is navigable for vessels of sixty tons burden through part of its
                    course.</p>
                <p>Lough Neagh, which stretches along the north of Armagh, is confined by it and the
                    four counties of Down, Londonderry, Antrim, and Tyrone. It is of an oblong form,
                    and is computed to cover 94,274 acres. Seven rivers and a number of smaller
                    streams flow into it, while the only vent for its accumulated waters is through
                    the channel of the northern Bann. Though estimable as a means of water
                    communication through an extensive tract of country, it has little of the
                    picturesque or romantic to attract attention. Ram Island, near the Antrim shore,
                    and Derrywarragh, near the mouth of the Blackwater, are its only islands. Some
                    parts of its shores have long been celebrated for the petrifying qualities of
                    its waters. The cause of this phenomenon is not satisfactorily ascertained; for,
                    though logs and branches of trees, in various stages of the petrifactive
                    process, have been found, this effect has not been produced on any pieces of
                    timber laid there for the sake of experiment. Catnlough and Lough Clay, the only
                    lakes within the county, are of small dimensions.</p>
                <p>Tillage cannot be said to be either in a very advanced or a very backward state.
                    Farm manure is much used, but lime still more; which latter, though abundant in
                    some parts of the county, is so scarce in others that it is drawn eight or ten
                    miles for the purposes of tillage. It is chiefly burned with turf raised from
                    bogs dispersed throughout most districts, but chiefly in the northern parts,
                    where they are of fine quality and large dimensions. Fifty barrels of lime are
                    allowed to the Irish acre. The chief succession of crops is oats repeated two or
                    three seasons after potatoes or wheat, with manure. Green crops are every year
                    more attended to, particularly among the wealthier farmers, and the gentry, who
                    hold land in their own hands, and thus give a tone and example to the country
                    for agricultural improvements.</p>
                <p>The farms are in general very small, yet their owners are generally in
                    circumstances of comparative comfort. There are few who do not keep at least one
                    cow, or a few sheep; none but the poorest cottar is without a pig· Their usual
                    diet is oatmeal, potatoes, and milk porridge, varied sometimes by salt herrings.
                    The better description of farmers use animal food, chiefly bacon and
                    poultry.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193103010?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-3010-0573"/>
                <p>Cheese in small quantity, and butter more than sufficient for domestic use,
                    are-obtained from their cows. Their sheep furnish wool, which is manufactured
                    into the coarse cloths, blankets, and druggets, used by themselves and their
                    families.</p>
                <p>The manufacture to which the industry of the country is chiefly directed, and
                    which has given a peculiar tone to the character of the population, is the
                    linen. It is noways necessary to the promotion of this manufacture, that the
                    spinners and weavers should be congregated in large towns, or united in crowded
                    and unwholesome factories. On the contrary, most of its branches can be carried
                    on in the cottages of the peasantry. The men devote to the loom those hours
                    which are not required for the cultivation of their little farms; the women spin
                    and reel the yarn during the intervals of their other domestic occupations.
                    Every female servant is bound to produce a certain quantity of yarn weekly, in
                    addition to her other dudes. Smooth lawns, perennial streams, pure springs, and
                    the open face of heaven, are necessary for perfecting the bleaching process.
                    Hence the extensive bleachers, with all their assistants and machinery, dwell in
                    the country. Such is the effect of this combination of agricultural occupations
                    with domestic manufactures, that the farmers are more than competent to supply
                    the resident population of the county with vegetable, though not with animal
                    food; and some of the less crowded and less productive parts of Ulster receive a
                    considerable supply of oats, barley, and flour from it. Apples are grown in such
                    quantities as to entitle the county to the epithet bestowed on it, of the
                    orchard of Ireland.</p>
                <p>The cause now dwelt upon has had an effect equally striking on the manners and
                    appearance of the people. The men are stout and well proportioned; nor does it
                    appear that their growth is checked or their general health deteriorated by
                    their early application to the sedentary and stooping labour of the loom. The
                    women are generally handsome, and, in consequence∙of being chiefly employed
                    within doors, fairer than those of other districts. On Sundays, and at fairs and
                    similar places of resort, the drcss and manners of both sexes indicate a
                    superior degree of civilization. The interior of their cottages is neat, the
                    exterior and the appendages cleanly. Cockfighting was once a favourite amusement
                    among them, but the taste for it is rapidly declining. They delight in dancing,
                    and have frequent meetings for the enjoyment of it; but hunting seems above all
                    to be their darling recreation. The moment the cry of the hounds is heard, the
                    labourer drops his spade, the weaver rushes from his loom, and the chase is
                    followed with ardour and activity almost incredible; yet it rarely happens that
                    redoubled exertions at their employments do not compensate for the time thus
                    lost. Lively gratitude for favours, and a quick sense of injury or insult, yet
                    seldom tinctured with feelings of revenge, are leading characteristics of their
                    moral temperament.</p>
                <p>In the towns and level parts of the county the protestant religion, in its two
                    principal forms of the established church and the presbyterian discipline,
                    predominates; but the Roman catholic is prevalent in the mountainous and less
                    cultivated parts. As far as may be conjectured from the returns of the
                    commissioners of education, the Roman catholics appear to constitute nearly one
                    half of the gross population.</p>
                <p>' According to those returns, the number of children at school in 1824 amounted
                    to 13,800. If the total number of children between five and fifteen years of
                    age, which may be called the period of education, be 49,000, as stated in the
                    population returns of 1821, upwards of two thirds of the whole remain
                    uninstructed. The religious persuasions of those educated are as
                    follows:—Established church 4655, presbyterians 2864, other dissenters 511,
                    Roman catholics <hi rend="superscript"> χ</hi> 5281. The number of schools is
                    333, of which 264, containing 9151 students, are supported wholly by the fees of
                    the pupils; the remaining 69 are maintained either by grants of public money or
                    by the voluntary contributions of the wealthier classes; viz. 44 schools,
                    educating 3153 pupils, are supported by the former means, and 25 schools,
                    educating 1540 pupils, by the latter.</p>
                <p>The population, as may be inferred from the preceding statements, is chiefly
                    rural. The county can boast but of four towns of more than 1000 inhabitants
                    each, viz. Armagh city 8493 ;. Lurgan 2715; part of Newry, the other and more
                    populous part being in the county of Down, 2543; and Tanderagee 1158: total
                    population of the larger towns 14,909. That of the remaining towns and villages,
                    17 in number, amounts but to 6987 souls; the rural population, therefore, is
                    175,431, being nearly in the ratio of 12 to 1 with respect to that of the larger
                    towns, and of 8 to 1 with respect to that of the towns and villages of every
                    description.</p>
                <p>The city of Armagh is 82 miles north of Dublin, being in 54° 20' 55" N. lat., and
                    in 6° 37' 57" W. long. Though now much reduced in population, it was once
                    considered as the metropolis of the island, and second only to Dublin in the
                    number of its inhabitants. The honour of being its founder is attributed to St
                    Patrick. It was built on an eminence named Druimsailech, or the Hill of Willows;
                    its present name is supposed to be a slight corruption of Ard-macha, the High
                    Place or Field. In 448 a synod was held here, the canons of which are still in
                    existence. During the period anterior to the arrival of the English in Ireland,
                    it suffered extremely from the assaults of the Danes, by whom it was repeatedly
                    plundered and burnt. Nor was its condition much bettered by the change of
                    masters. De Courcy, FitzAdelm, and De Lacy, pillaged it in turn in their
                    attempts to subdue Ulster; and it was exposed to similar calamities during the
                    wars by which the north of Ireland was desolated in the reign of Elizabeth. Her
                    successor, James I., granted it a charter, according to which it has since been
                    governed. Its decline was still farther increased by the non-residence of the
                    archbishops, who, in consequence of the unsettled state of the northern
                    province, fixed their residence for many years at Drogheda. From this deplorable
                    state it was raised by LprdRokeby, better known by the name of Primate Robinson.
                    When he determined to make it the seat of his permanent residence, this
                    venerable city was little more than a collection of cabins. He erected in it an
                    archiépiscopal palace, a college or grammar school for classical education, a
                    library now containing upwards of 12,000 volumes, and an observatory well
                    furnished with astronomical instruments. Besides these, the city now contains a
                    Roman Catholic chapel and a Presbyterian meeting-house, both on a large scale;
                    and several places of worship for other religious denominations. Its other
                    public buildings are, the cathedral, a cruciform building, more remarkable for
                    its antiquity than its architectural beauty; the court-house, the prison, the
                    charter-school, the barrack, the county infirmary, the lunatic asylum, and the
                    fever hospital, which last was erected and is maintained at the expense of Lord
                    John Beresford, the present primate. The number of poor relieved at the
                    charitable institutions just mentioned amounted in the year 1829 to 2678, and
                    occasioned an expenditure of L.2562. Besides these there are eleven dispensaries
                    in various parts of the county, the returns from six of which give an aggregate
                    of 9558 individuals relieved during the same year, at an expenditure of L.967,
                    one moiety of which is derived from the contributions of individuals, the other
                    from grants of public money. In <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193103023?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-3023-0574"/> Armagh city
                    there is a mendicity society, which maintained 500 paupers during the same year,
                    at an expenditure of L.584, being at the rate of L.l. 3s. 4∣d. each. The city is
                    governed by a sovereign and twelve burgesses, who, when deaths occur, elect to
                    the vacancies. The elective franchise is confined to the burgesses, and they
                    uniformly return the archbishop's nominee as their representative. Although the
                    linen trade has declined considerably, both here and throughout the north of
                    Ireland, much of it is still manufactured in the vicinity of the city, and is
                    disposed of at the market held here every Tuesday. (See Wakefield’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ireland;</hi> Barton’s <hi rend="italic">Natural History of Lough
                    Neagh</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Coote’s <hi rend="italic">Statistical Survey
                    of Armagh</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Shaw Mason’s <hi rend="italic">Parochial
                    Account of Ireland,</hi> articles Creggan, Ballymoyer, and Seagoe; Erck’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Register;</hi> Stewart’s <hi rend="italic">History
                    of the City of Armagh</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Parliamentary Papers; Population Peturns,</hi> 1821; <hi rend="italic">Peports
                    of Commissioners of Education,</hi> 1814, 1824—26; <hi rend="italic">Peport of
                    Committee on the State of the Poor in Ireland,</hi> 1830.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
