<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-4128-0659-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARUNDELIAN Marbles, Oxford Marbles, or Parian Chronicle
                    (7th edition, volume 3, page 659)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193104128?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARUNDELIAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Marbles, Oxford Marbles</hi>,
                    or <hi rend="smallcaps">Parian Chronicle</hi></label>, are ancient stones, as
                    has been supposed, whereon is. inscribed a chronicle of the city of Athens,
                    engraven in capital letters in the island of Paros, one of the Cyclades, 264
                    years before Jesus Christ. They take their first name from Thomas, earl of
                    Arundel, who procured them out of the east, or from Henry his grandson, who
                    presented them to the university of Oxford.</p>
                <p>The Arundelian marbles, in their perfect state, contained a chronological detail
                    of the principal events of Greece during a period of 1318 years, beginning with
                    Cecrops, before Christ 1582 years, and ending with the archonship of Diognetus,
                    before Christ 264. But the chronicle of the last 90 years is lost, so that the
                    part now remaining ends at the archonship of Diotimus, 354 years before the
                    birth of Christ; and in this fragment the inscription is at present so much
                    corroded and effaced, that the sense can only be discovered by very learned and
                    industrious antiquaries, or, more properly speaking, supplied by their
                    conjectures.</p>
                <p>This chronicle, and many other relics of antiquity, real or pretended, were
                    purchased in Asia Minor, in Greece, or in the islands of the archipelago, by Mr
                    William Petty, who, in the year 1624, was sent by Thomas, earl of Arundel, for
                    the purpose of making such collactions for him in the east. They were brought
                    into England about thebeginning of the year 1629, and placed in the gardens
                    belonging to Arundel house in London.</p>
                <p>Soon after their arrival they excited a general curiosity, and were viewed by
                    many inquisitive and learned men, among others by Sir Robert Cotton, who
                    prevailed upon Selden to employ his abilities in explaining the Greek
                    inscriptions. Selden and two of his friends, Patrick Young, or, as he styled
                    himself in Latin, <hi rend="italic">Patricius</hi><hi rend="italic">Junius,</hi>
                    and Richard James, immediately commenced their operations, by cleaning and
                    examining the marble containing the Smymean and Magnesian league, and afterwards
                    proceeded to the Parian chronicle. The following year Selden published a small
                    volume in quarto, including about 39 inscriptions copied from the marbles.</p>
                <p>In the turbulent reign of Charles I. and the subsequent usurpation, Arundel house
                    was often deserted by the illustrious owners; and, in their absence, some of the
                    marbles were defaced and broken, and others either stolen or used for the
                    ordinary purposes of architecture. The chronological marble, in particular, was
                    unfortunately broken and defaced. The upper part, containing 31 epochas, is said
                    to have been worked up in repairing a chimney in Arundel house.</p>
                <p>In the year 1667 the Honourable Henry Howard, afterwards duke of Norfolk, the
                    grandson of the first collector, presented these supposed remains of antiquity
                    to the university of Oxford.</p>
                <p>Selden’s work becoming very scarce, Bishop Fell engaged Mr Prideaux to publish a
                    new edition of the inscriptions, which was printed at Oxford in 1676. In 1732 Mr
                    Maittaire obliged the public with a more comprehensive view of the marbles than
                    either of his predecessors. Lastly, Dr Chandler published a new and improved
                    copy of the marbles in 1763, in which he corrected the mistakes of the former
                    editors; and in some of the inscriptions, particularly that of the Parian
                    chronicle, supplied the <hi rend="italic">lacuna</hi> by many ingenious
                    conjectures.</p>
                <p>The Arundelian marbles have generally been regarded as a curious monument of
                    antiquity. They were, however, discovered in some instances to be inconsistent
                    with the most authentic historical accounts. Sir Isaac Newton and several other
                    modern philosophers paid little or no regard to them; and their absolute
                    authenticity has been severely questioned in an express dissertation upon the
                    subject by Mr Robertson, published in 1788, entitled <hi rend="italic">The
                    Parian Chronicle.</hi> In this dissertation much ingenuity as well as learning
                    is displayed. His doubts, the author observes, arise from the following
                    considerations.</p>
                <p>I. “The characters have no certain or unequivocal marks of antiquity.” The ∏ and
                    Z, which frequently occur in the form supposed to be the most ancient (viz. the
                    perpendicular line of the ∏ on the right -hand only half as long as that on the
                    left, and the Z in the form of a prostrate Μ ), are so well known, that any
                    modem fabricator of a Greek inscription which he intends to impose upon the
                    world as a relic of antiquity would most probably use them in preference to the
                    more common and ordinary forms. But the letters in the Parian chronicle have no
                    appearance of antiquity except this very equivocal one. They do not in the least
                    resemble the Sigean. the Nemean, or the Delian inscriptions, which are supposed
                    to be of a more ancient date. They differ in many respects from the letters on
                    the Marmor Sandvicense, which, according to the learned editor of that
                    inscription, was engraved in the year before Christ 374. They bear no sort of
                    resemblance to the characters on the Farnesian pillars, to those of the
                    Alexandrian manuscript, or others of a later date. They seem, continues our
                    author, to resemble, perhaps more than any other, the letters of the alphabet
                    taken by Montfaucon from the Marmor Cyzicenum at Venice. They are plain and
                    simple in their form, and such as an ordinary stone-cutter of the present age
                    would probably make if he were employed to engrave a Greek inscription according
                    to the alphabet now in use. The small letters intermixed among the larger have,
                    in the opinion of our author, an air of affectation and artifice rather than
                    genuine antiquity; and he is persuaded that the antiquity of an inscription can
                    never be proved by the mere form of the letters, because the most ancient
                    characters may be as easily counterfeited as those which compose our present
                    alphabet?.</p>
                <p>That the learned reader may form a competent idea of the characters in the Parian
                    chronicle, the author has compared them with those of other inscriptions, and
                    given what is usually termed a <hi rend="italic">fax simile.</hi></p>
                <p>In regard to several <hi rend="italic">archaisms,</hi> as they are called in this
                    chronicle, and which our author specifies, he contends that no conclusion can be
                    drawn from them in favour of its antiquity. What reason could there be, he asks,
                    for introducing these into the Parian chronicle? We do not usually find them in
                    Greek writers of the same age, or even in those of the most early date. The
                    reign of Ptolemy Philadelphus, with the 21st year of which the date of the
                    chronicle coincides, was not an age of rude antiquity with respect to the Greek
                    language, being only 130 years after <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193104141?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-4141-0660"/> the time-of
                    Xenophon and Plato, when the Greek was spoken and written in its utmost purity
                    and elegance; and we can scarcely suppose that even a stone-cutter in that
                    refined age would have been permitted to disgrace a superb and learned monument
                    with such barbarisms as occur in the chronicle. The archaisms, however, he
                    remarks, are not uniformly observed in this inscription. He adduces six
                    instances of deviation, and adds, he is almost tempted to suspect that <hi
                    rend="italic">tμ ∏agω, tμ</hi> MαjαSωw, and other pretended archaisms, are owing
                    to a mere affectation of antiquity, or to a corrupted dialect and pronunciation
                    in later ages. Those archaisms, our author acknowledges, appear on other
                    marbles; but he thinks that for that very reason they would naturally be adopted
                    by the fabricator of a supposititious inscription; and the authenticity of those
                    inscriptions in which they appear must be established before they can be urged
                    in opposition to the present argument.</p>
                <p>II. “It is not probable that the chronicle was engraved <hi rend="italic">îor
                    private use.”</hi> Our author thinks it an impossible supposition that such an
                    expensive and cumbersome work could have been executed by a private citizen,
                    either for his own amusement or for the benefit of his fellow-citizens. In the
                    first place, a long inscription could not be engraved in marble without such an
                    expense as few learned Greeks were able to afford; or if its author, by an
                    uncommon felicity, was able to erect such a literary monument, the scheme would
                    have been useless and imprudent, as all the contents of the inscription might
                    have been published more commodiously and effectually by the common mode of
                    writing in use at that time.</p>
                <p>III. “The chronicle does not appear to have been engraved by <hi rend="italic"
                    >public authority.”</hi></p>
                <p>IsĄ The first argument in support of this opinion is, that inscriptions of that
                    kind usually begin with a particular form, as Η BOTΛH KAI Ο ΔΗΜΟΣ. <hi
                    rend="italic">The senate and the people;</hi> or thus, EΔOSEN THI BOTΛHI KAI TOI
                    ΔHM∩I, <hi rend="italic">It pleased the senate and the people,</hi> &amp;c. But
                    the Parian chronicle begins in the manner of a private man, speaking of his own
                    performance in the first person singular. This argument, our author remarks,
                    cannot be much affected by observing that the beginning of the inscription is
                    obliterated; for it is necessarily implied by the words now remaining.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic superscript"> s</hi><hi rend="italic">2,dly,</hi> The facts and
                    dates which are mentioned in this chronicle do not appear to have been extracted
                    from any public records, or calculated to answer the purpose of authentic
                    documents, as many eminent princes and magistrates are passed over without
                    notice, in several instances the transactions of whole centuries are omitted,
                    and the facts chiefly specified are not matters of general or national
                    importance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">⅛dly,</hi> The Parian inscription is such a one as we can
                    hardly suppose the magistrates or the people of Paros would have ordered to be
                    engraved. Stately sepulchres, pillars, triumphal arches, and the like, were
                    erected to perpetuate. the glory of eminent men. The remembrance of events in
                    which nations were interested, the succession of princes, &amp;c. were preserved
                    in the same manner. Leagues, decrees, and laws, were likewise engraved on marble
                    or brass, and fixed to a pillar, the walls of a temple, or other public
                    buildings; because such inscriptions were designed for the inspection of the
                    people, as they essentially concerned their conduct, their property, their
                    liberty, or their lives. But our author asks, for whom could the chronicle of
                    Paros be intended? It contains no encomiums on any of the patriots, the heroes,
                    or the demigods of the country, no decrees of the magistrates, no public
                    records, no laws of state. On the contrary, it is a work of mere speculation and
                    learning, in which the inhabitants of that island, especially the common
                    people,’ had not the least interest or concern.</p>
                <p>These words at the beginning, <hi rend="italic">αξ∙χοvτος ιμ</hi> ∏αgω, would
                    naturally lead us to suppose that the inscription related to Paros. And if so,
                    it would have been natural for the author to have mentioned some óf the most
                    important occurrences in the history of that island. But, says this acute and
                    learned critic, what scheme does our chronologer pursue on this occasion? Does
                    he record the events and revolutions of his own country? Does he mention any of
                    the battles, sieges, and treaties of the Parians; any of their public
                    institutions; any of their poets, patriots, or warriors? Does he mention
                    Archilochus, who was honoured by his countrymen, and distinguished as a poet in
                    a general assembly of the Greeks? Not a syllable on any of these subjects! On
                    the contrary, "he rambles from place to place, and records the transactions of
                    Athens, Corinth, Macedon, Lydia, Crete, Cyprus, Sicily, Persia, and other
                    foreign countries with which Paros had no connection.</p>
                <p>In this view the inscription seems to have been as impertinent in the island of
                    Paros as a marble monument would be in this country recording the antiquities of
                    France or Spain; or one in Jamaica recording the revolutions of England. But,
                    upon supposition that the inscription is a forgery, it is easy to account for
                    this extraordinary circumstance. A few chronological occurrences in the ancient
                    history of Paros would not have been so interesting to the generality of
                    readers, or so valuable in the estimation of every lover of antiquities, or, in
                    short, so profitable to the compiler, as a general system of Grecian
                    chronology.</p>
                <p>iy. “The Greek and Roman writers, for a long time after the date of this work,
                    complain that they had no chronological account of the affairs of ancient
                    Greece." This position is confirmed by the testimony of Julius Africanus, Justin
                    Martyr, Plutarch, Josephus, Varro, Diodorus Siculus, and others; and the
                    following series of interrogatories is subjoined :—“Thucydides, I know, lived
                    140 years before the chronicle is said to have been written; but if Thucydides,
                    as well as other writers, complained that there was nothing but uncertainty in
                    the earlier part of Grecian history, from whence can we suppose the author of
                    this inscription collected such a clear, determinate, and comprehensive system
                    of chronology? If he had any sources of information which were unknown to
                    succeeding writers, how happens it that they should all of them overlook this
                    most considerable, most exact, most creditable author? Why did they omit this
                    ancient account of their early ages? Why did they not copy his most memorable
                    epochas? Why did they not produce his authority? or, at least, why did they not
                    mention his opinion? Surely nothing, to all appearance, could be more elaborate,
                    more important, or of higher authority, than a chronological table which was
                    thought worthy of being engraved on marble.</p>
                <p>V. “The chronicle is not once mentioned by any writers of antiquity.” This,
                    indeed, appears a strong argument against its authenticity. Apollodorus, an
                    Athenian, the disciple of Aristarchus the grammarian, and Panaetius the
                    philosopher, wrote a genealogical and historical work on the early ages of
                    Greece; but though composed 120 years after the date of the Parian chronicle, it
                    does not contain the smallest traces of a systematical chronology. It is
                    remarkable, too, that the chronicle of Apollodorus is quoted by Diodorus
                    Siculus, Strabo, Plutarch, A. Gellius, Lucian, and many other writers of
                    antiquity; while the Parian chronicle, which comprehends a more extensive
                    period, is entirely unnoticed. It contains, however, such wonderful discoveries
                    in ancient history, that if it had ex-isteđ<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193104154?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-4154-0661"/> 264 years
                    before the Christian era, it must have excited a general attention, and been
                    referred to as an authority by writers of succeeding times. But we do not find,
                    in any author of antiquity, either poet or historian, geographer or chronologer,
                    mythologist or scholiast, the most distant allusion to the Parian chronicle;
                    though it was such a common practice among the ancients to mention the works of
                    their predecessors, that in many books we find references and allusions to
                    three, four, five, six, or seven hundred different authors of every
                    denomination.</p>
                <p>VI. “Some of the facts mentioned in the chronicle seem to have been taken from
                    writers of a later date.” Our inquirer collates several passages in the Parian
                    chronicle with parallel passages in Greek authors, to evince that there is, in
                    the former, an appearance of imitation, or a stronger resemblance than such as
                    may be supposed to arise from accident; that there are likewise some
                    improbabilities attending the account of Deucalion, as related in the Parian
                    chronicle; and that the names of six, and, if the <hi rend="italic">lacunae</hi>
                    are properly supplied, the names of twelve cities appear to have been engraved
                    on the marble, exactly as we find them in AElian’s <hi rend="italic">Various
                    History.</hi> But there is not, our author observes, any imaginable reason for
                    this particular arrangement. It does not correspond with the time of their
                    foundation, with their situation in Ionia, with their relative importance, or
                    with the order in which they are placed by other eminent historians. The
                    argument by which our author endeavours to prove that the Parian chronicle has
                    in this instance copied AElian’s <hi rend="italic">Various History,</hi> seems
                    decisive of the fact. He observes that six names may be transposed 720 different
                    ways, and that 12 names admit of 479,001,600 different transpositions.
                    Supposing, then, that there is no particular reason for one arrangement rather
                    than another, it will follow that the chance of two authors placing them in the
                    same order is, in the former case, as 1 to 720; and, in the latter, as 1 to
                    479,001,600. It is therefore, says he, utterly improbable that these names
                    should have been placed in this order on the marble, if the author of the
                    inscription had not transcribed them from the historian.</p>
                <p>It may indeed be urged, with regard to this similarity of arrangement in the
                    Parian chronicle and AElian’s <hi rend="italic">Various History,</hi> that the
                    inference might be the very inverse of that which is specified by our author.
                    But that AElian should have seen the Parian chronicle without once mentioning
                    it, or that he should have exactly copied a list of towns, arranged neither
                    according to chronological or topographical order, is indeed a supposition
                    equally improbable with the other.</p>
                <p>VII. “Parachronisms appear in some of the epochas, which we can scarcely suppose
                    a Greek chronologer in the 129th olympiad would be liable to commit.” After
                    specifying these, our inquirer asks, would a writer of reputation and learning,
                    in one of the most polished and enlightened eras of ancient Greece, commit such
                    mistakes, in opposition to the positive attestations of the most accurate
                    historians, in events of public notoriety? Would a private citizen or a
                    magistrate of Paros order a crude and inaccurate series of epochas to be
                    engraved at a great expense, and transmitted to posterity on a marble monument?
                    It is hardly probable.</p>
                <p>VIII. “The history of the discovery of the Parian chronicle is obscure and
                    unsatisfactory.” Our author observes that it is attended with some suspicious
                    circumstances, and without any of those clear and unequivocal evidences which
                    always discriminate truth from falsehood. There are no data in the inscription
                    by which to discover the place where the marble was erected. The place likewise
                    where it was found is not ascertained, though the generality of writers who have
                    had occasion to mention it have supposed that it was found in the island of
                    Paros. If it was erected at Smyrna, as some imagine, our author asks, for what
                    purpose does the writer mention Astyanax the archon of Paros, and not one
                    circumstance relative to Smyrna? If, adds he, it was erected at Paros, why does
                    he not mention more archons of that city than one? or how shall we account for
                    his profound silence with respect to all the events and revolutions which must
                    have happened in that island, and have been infinitely more interesting to the
                    natives than the transactions of any foreign country?</p>
                <p>The train of circumstances by which the Parian chronicle came into the possession
                    of Mr Petty, whom Lord Arundel had sent into the East for the purpose of
                    collecting antiquities, as well as the subsequent conduct of Peiresc, its former
                    owner, affords our author a strong presumption that “the inscription was
                    actually fabricated with the view of obtaining for it a high price, upon the
                    pretence that it was a relic of great antiquity. It is certain that there is
                    something mysterious in the conduct of the first ostensible proprietors. These
                    marbles had been totally unknown or unnoticed for almost 1900 years, and at last
                    are dug out of the ground—nobody can tell us when or where !”</p>
                <p>IX. “The literary world has been frequently imposed upon by spurious books and
                    inscriptions, and therefore we should be extremely cautious with regard to what
                    we receive under the venerable name of antiquity.” This proposition is
                    illustrated by a great variety of examples, and very properly exposes the
                    forgeries which have disgraced the republic of letters in different ages; and
                    although one of the more recent ones cited, namely, Ossian’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poems,</hi> be a point very far indeed from being established, yet that
                    deceptions of this kind have been practised is an unquestionable fact.</p>
                <p>In endeavouring, towards the end of his Dissertation, to investigate the time of
                    the supposed forgery, he observes that the 16th century, and the prior part of
                    the 17th, produced a multitude of grammarians, critics, and commentators, deeply
                    versed in Grecian literature, and amply qualified for the compilation of such a
                    chronological system as that of the Arundelian marbles. Above all, the science
                    of chronology was particularly studied and investigated about that time: “Nunc
                    fervet chronologia,” says Scaliger in the year 1605, “omnes hoc ferrum
                    excalfaciunt.” Cassaubon treats those persons with contempt who were
                    unacquainted with the improvements which had been made in that department of
                    learning after the revival of letters. Innumerable systems of chronology had
                    been published before the year 1625, from which it was easy to extract a series
                    of memorable events, and give the compilation a Grecian dress. “The avidity,”
                    says our author, “with which all relics of antiquity were then collected, and
                    the high price with which they were purchased, were sufficient inducements to
                    any one, whose avarice or whose necessity was stronger than his integrity, to
                    engrave his labours on marble, and transmit them to Smyrna, as a commodious
                    emporium for such rarities.”</p>
                <p>The foregoing arguments are no doubt possessed of considerable force and
                    plausibility; but they have been ably answered, and the authenticity of the
                    Parian chronicle vindicated, by other writers; particularly the late Professor
                    Porson, in an examination of Mr Robertson’s Dissertation, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Monthly Review</hi> for January 1789. See also Hewlett’s
                    Vindication, in the <hi rend="italic">Archoeologia,</hi> vol. ix.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
