<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0083-0068-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 68</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1002458">Looms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bk43">Levant</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n83/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VAR</label>, a department of France, formed in 1790 of part
                    of Provence, but reduced in 1860 by the formation of the department of
                    Alpes-Maritimes, so that the Var no longer flows through the department to which
                    it gives its name. Situated between 42° 58' and 43° 55' N. lat. and 5° 39' and
                    6° 57' E. long., Var is bounded by the Mediterranean on the S., by
                    Alpes-Maritimes on the E., by Basses-Alpes on the N., and by Bouches-du-Rhône on
                    the W. In the N.W. it touches the department of Vaucluse. The river Verdon on
                    the N. and the Siagne on the N.E. are natural boundaries. The surface of the
                    department is one of the most broken in France; the highest point is in the
                    northeast, where a peak of the Alps rises to 5620 feet and is surrounded by
                    others ranging from 4500 to 5000 feet. These calcareous hills are much fissured
                    and very dry on the higher plateaus, but are rich in springs, which occasion a
                    very beautiful verdure in the valleys. Towards the west rises the St Baume (3700
                    to 3800 feet), which is connected on the south with the hills above Toulon (2300
                    feet). The Maures (2550 feet), which extend between the coast from Hyères to
                    Fréjus, and the valley of the Argens form, geologically speaking, a sort of
                    island in Provence, being composed of granite, gneiss, and schists. To the north
                    of the Argens rises the independent Estérel Range (2020 feet), mostly composed
                    of igneous rocks, with some schists and porphyry. The principal river is the
                    Argens (71 miles), which drains the larger portion of the department, traversing
                    it from west to east, and falling into the sea a little south of Fréjus. Its
                    minimum volume is 72,000 cubic feet, even in the driest weather and when most
                    lavishly drawn on for irrigation. Nominally it is navigable for 11 miles, but in
                    point of fact it is used only for floating timber. Draguignan, the chef-lieu of
                    Var, is <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n84/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0084-0069"/> situated on the Nartuby, the principal tributary
                    of the Argens. Other streams are, in the north the Verdon, a tributary of the
                    Durance, in the west the Huvaune and Arc, in the south the Gapeau, and in the
                    east the Siagne. The coast-line, which is one of the most beautiful and
                    picturesquely varied in France, runs from west to east between the Gulf of La
                    Ciotat and Cape Comarat, then from south-west to north-east between the Gulfs of
                    St Tropez and La Napoule. The shore is dotted from west to east with the
                    sand-covered remains of the Phocaean city of Tauroentum; the little ports of
                    Bandol and St Nazaire; the peninsula of Cape Sicié, 1180 feet high, with its
                    projection Cape Cépet (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Toulon)</hi>; the roads of
                    Toulon; the roads of Giens, the site of the Gallo-Roman town of Pomponiana; the
                    peninsula of Giens, formerly an island attached to the mainland by two long
                    spits of sand, between which lies the lagoon of Les Pesquiers with its
                    “salines”; the great anchorage of Hyères, shut off from the Mediterranean on the
                    south by the hilly and wooded islands of Porquerolles, Port-Cros, and Le Levant;
                    the bold promontories of the Maures Mountains, dividing the coast into lovely
                    bays; Cape Comarat (430 feet), with a lighthouse; the deep Gulf of St Tropez,
                    with perhaps the best anchorage in all Provence; the Gulf of Fréjus, where owing
                    to the accumulated alluvial deposits of the Argens the site of the Roman port of
                    Forum Julii is now occupied by the inland town of St Raphael; the porphyry
                    headlands of the Estérel Range, with the roads of Agay between them; and Cape
                    Roux (1486 feet). The climate is remarkably fine and mild on the coast, where
                    there is complete shelter from the north wind, but is more severe in the
                    mountains. Hyères and St Raphael are favourite invalid resorts. The average
                    temperature is 58° Fahr. at Toulon, 59° at Hyères. The annual rainfall is 19
                    inches at Toulon and 24 in the valley of the Argens.</p>
                <p>Of the total area of 1,489,488 acres 379,021 are arable, 529,660 under wood,
                    185,333 under vineyards, 14,857 are meadows and orchards, 49,606 pasture, and
                    142,466 uncultivated. The live stock includes 8460 horses (many of Arab blood),
                    13,230 mules, 5420 asses, 3015 cattle, 105,840 sheep (wool-clip in 1879, 234
                    tons 4 cwts., valued at £10,000), 19,900 pigs, and 14,815 goats. There were
                    14,380 beehives (42 tons 10 cwts. of honey and 28 tons 7 cwts. of wax in 1879).
                    In 1884 366 tons 15 cwts. of silk cocoons were produced. The crops in 1884 were
                    1,485,000 bushels of wheat, 13,200 of meslin, 11,000 of rye, 30,250 of barley,
                    7150 of maize, 2640 of millet, 125,400 of oats, 4,840,000 of potatoes, 2512 tons
                    of beetroot, and 103,000 tons of different kinds of fodder. The vines, reduced
                    by 60 per cent. since 1875 by the phylloxera, yielded in 1884 over 7,000,000
                    gallons of wine (average of previous 10 years over 29,000,000 gallons). In 1879
                    olives occupied 77,777 acres and yielded 1,384,856 bushels; four-fifths of the
                    crop was pressed for oil and yielded 5256 tons. Mulberries, strawberries, pears,
                    peaches, plums, figs, almonds, oranges, pomegranates, lemons, jujubes, guavas,
                    and Japanese medlars are grown; and the laurel, palm tree, date tree,
                    eucalyptus, cactus, and sugar cane flourish. An export trade is carried on in
                    flowers, and also in truffles, capers, and onions. The forests are planted with
                    white and evergreen oaks, cork trees, maritime pines, and chestnuts. In the
                    dense, and almost virgin, forest of St Baume are beeches, maples, limes, oaks,
                    elms, yews, and pines, and the flora of the district is botanically most
                    interesting. Var possesses mines of iron, lead, aluminium, and coal (2846 tons
                    of coal, 2075 tons of lignite in 1885). From 300 to 400 workmen are employed in
                    the production of salt and chemicals. Hyères (population 13,170 in 1886)
                    produces annually from 20,000 to 25,000 tons of salt. Marble, plaster, stone,
                    chalk, clay, sandstone, and sand for glass are quarried or dug. There are 200
                    manufactories of pottery, earthenware, and tiles. Toulon (57,635), La Seyne
                    (12,186), St Tropez (3622), and Bandol, where ships are built, are the chief
                    industrial centres. There are silk, woollen (250 spindles, 6 looms), and cotton
                    (350 spindles, 9 looms) mills, hat, cloth, and cork manufactories (1000
                    workmen), tan-yards, paper-mills (670 tons in 1879), printing establishments,
                    tinned food manufactories, soap-works (172 tons), breweries, glass-works,
                    oil-mills—in all 173 establishments. There are tunny, anchovy, and sardine
                    fisheries. The department has 140 miles of railway, 164 of national roads, and
                    2448 of other roads. About half the population of 288,577 (1881) were
                    agricultural, 46,691 manufacturing, and 30,228 marine. In 1886 the total
                    population of the department numbered 283,689. Var is divided into 3
                    arrondissements (Draguignan, the chef-lieu, with 8562 inhabitants in 1886;
                    Brignoles, with 4393 inhabitants; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Toulon</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> 28 cantons, and 145 communes; it forms the diocese of
                    Fréjus, and belongs to the jurisdiction of the Aix court of appeal and to the
                    district of the Marseilles army corps.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
