<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0065-0052-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VAMPIRE (9th edition, volume 24, page 52)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968611">Incisors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828821">Bats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:886455">Czechs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804157">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205578">Ecuador</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34ms27">Bats</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jw08">Servians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46w96c07">Czechs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16p3t">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n65/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VAMPIRE</label>, a term, apparently of Servian origin <hi
                        rend="italic">(wampir),</hi> originally applied in eastern Europe to
                    bloodsucking ghosts, but in modern usage transferred to one or more species of
                    blood-sucking bats inhabiting South America.</p>
                <p>In the first-mentioned meaning a vampire is usually supposed to be the soul of a
                    dead man which quits the buried body by night to suck the blood of living
                    persons. Hence, when the vampire’s grave is opened, his corpse is found to be
                    fresh and rosy from the blood which he has thus absorbed. To put a stop to his
                    ravages, a stake is driven through the corpse, or the head cut off, or the heart
                    torn out and the body burned, or boiling water and vinegar are poured on the
                    grave. The persons who turn vampires are generally wizards, witches, suicides,
                    and persons who have come to a violent end or have been cursed by their parents
                    or by the church. But any one may become a vampire if an animal (especially a
                    cat) leaps over his corpse or a bird flies over it. Sometimes the vampire is
                    thought to be the soul of a living man which leaves his body in sleep, to go in
                    the form of a straw or fluff of down and suck the blood of other sleepers. The
                    belief in vampires chiefly prevails in Slavonic lands, as in Russia (especially
                    White Russia and the Ukraine), Poland, and Servia, and among the Czechs of
                    Bohemia and the other Slavonic races of Austria. It became specially prevalent
                    in Hungary between the years 1730 and 1735, whence all Europe was filled with
                    reports of the exploits of vampires. Several treatises were written on the
                    subject, among which may be mentioned Ranft’s <hi rend="italic">De Masticatione
                        Mortuorum in Tumulis</hi> (1734) and Calmet’s <hi rend="italic">Dissertation
                        on the Vampires of Hungary,</hi> translated into English in 1750. It is
                    probable that this superstition gained much ground from the reports of those who
                    had examined the bodies of persons who had been buried alive though believed to
                    be dead, and was based on the twisted position of the corpse, the marks of blood
                    on the shroud and on the face and hands,—results of the frenzied struggle in the
                    coffin before life became extinct. The belief in vampirism has also taken root
                    among the Albanians and modern Greeks, but here it may be due to Slavonic
                    influence.</p>
                <p>Two species of blood-sucking bats (the only species known)— <hi rend="italic"
                        >Desmodus rufus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Diphylla ecaudata—</hi>
                    representing two genera (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mammalia,</hi> vol. xv. p.
                    415), inhabit the tropical and part of the subtropical regions of the New World,
                    and are restricted to South and Central America. They appear to be confined
                    chiefly to the forestclad parts, and their attacks on men and other warmblooded
                    animals were noticed by some of the earliest writers. Thus Peter Martyr
                    (Anghiera), who wrote soon after the conquest of South America, says that in the
                    Isthmus of Darien there were bats which sucked the blood of men and cattle when
                    asleep to such a degree as to even kill them. Condamine, a writer of the 18th
                    century, remarks that at Borja (Ecuador) and in other places they had entirely
                    destroyed the cattle introduced by the missionaries. Sir Robert Schomburgk
                    relates that at Wicki, on the river Berbice, no fowls could be kept on account
                    of the ravages of these creatures, which attacked their combs, causing them to
                    appear white from loss of blood. The present writer, when in South and Central
                    America, had many accounts given him as to the attacks of the vampires, and it
                    was agreed upon by most of his informants that these bats when attacking horses
                    showed a decided preference for those of a grey colour. It is interesting to
                    speculate how far the vampire bats may have been instrumental—when they were,
                    perhaps, more abundant—in causing the destruction of the horse, which had
                    disappeared from America previous to the discovery of that continent.</p>
                <p>Although these bats were known thus early to Europeans, the species to which they
                    belonged were not determined until about fifty years ago, several of the large
                    frugivorous species having been wrongly set down as blood-suckers, and named
                    accordingly. Thus the name <hi rend="italic">Vampyrus</hi> was suggested to
                    Geoffroy and adopted by Spix, who also considered that the long-tongued bats of
                    the group <hi rend="italic">Glossophagae</hi> were addicted to blood, and
                    accordingly described <hi rend="italic">Glossophaga soricina</hi> as a very
                    cruel blood-sucker (<hi rend="italic">sanguisuga crudelissima'),</hi> believing
                    that the long brush-tipped tongue was used to increase the flow of blood. <hi
                        rend="italic">Vampyrus spectrum,</hi> L., a large bat inhabiting Brazil, of
                    sufficiently forbidding aspect, which was long considered by naturalists to be
                    thoroughly sanguivorous in its habits, and named accordingly by Geoffroy, has
                    been shown by the observations of modern travellers to be mainly frugivorous,
                    and is considered by the inhabitants of the countries in which it is found to be
                    perfectly harmless. Waterton believed <hi rend="italic">Artibeus
                        planirostris,</hi> a common bat in British Guiana, usually found in the
                    roofs of houses, and now known to be frugivorous, to be the veritable vampire;
                    but neither he nor any of the naturalists that preceded him had succeeded in
                    detecting any bat in the act of drawing blood. It fell to the lot of Charles
                    Darwin to determine one of the blood-sucking species at least, and the following
                    is his account of the circumstances under which the discovery of the
                    sanguivorous habits of <hi rend="italic">Desmodus rufus</hi> was made :— “The
                    vampire bat is often the cause of much trouble by <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0066-0053"/> biting the horses on their withers. The
                    injury is generally not so much owing to the loss of blood as to the
                    inflammation which the pressure of the saddle afterwards produces. The whole
                    circumstance has lately been doubted in England; I was therefore fortunate in
                    being present when one was actually caught on a horse’s back. We were
                    bivouacking late one evening near Coquimbo, in Chili, when my servant, noticing
                    that one of the horses was very restive, went to see what was the matter, and,
                    fancying he could detect something, suddenly put his hand on the beast’s
                    withers, and secured the vampire” (<hi rend="italic">Naturalist’s Voyage Round
                        the World,</hi> p. 22).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Desmodus rufus,</hi> Weid, the common blood-sucking bat, is
                    widely spread over the tropical and subtropical parts of Central and South
                    America from Oaxaca to southern Brazil and Chili. It is a comparatively small
                    bat, a little larger than the common noctule, the head and body about 3 inches
                    in length, the forearm 2½, with a remarkably long and strong thumb; it is
                    destitute of a tail, and has a very peculiar physiognomy, well represented in
                    fig. I. The body is covered with rather short fur of a reddish brown colour but
                    varying in shade, the extremities of the hairs sometimes ashy. The teeth are
                    peculiar and characteristic, admirably adapted for the purposes for which they
                    are employed. The upper front teeth (incisors), of which there are only two, are
                    enormously enlarged (see fig. 2), and in shape obliquely triangular like small
                    guillotines. The canines, though smaller than the incisors, are large and sharp;
                    but the back teeth, so well developed in all other bats, are very small and
                    reduced in number to two above and three below, on each side, with laterally
                    compressed crowns rising but slightly above the level of the gum, their
                    longitudinally disposed cutting edges (in the upper jaw) being continuous with
                    the base of the canine and with each other. The lower front teeth (incisors) are
                    small, bifid, in pairs, and are separated from the canines, with a space in
                    front. The lower back teeth are narrow, like those in the upper jaw, but the
                    anterior tooth is slightly larger than the others, and separated by a small
                    space from the canines. Behind the lower incisors the jaw is deeply hollowed out
                    to receive the extremities of the large upper incisors.</p>
                <p>With this peculiar dentition there is associated as remarkable a departure from
                    the general type in the form of the digestive apparatus. The exceedingly narrow
                    oesophagus opens at right angles into a narrow, intestine-like stomach, which
                    almost immediately terminates on the right, without a distinct pylorus, in the
                    duodenum, but on the left forms a greatly elongated caecum, bent and folded upon
                    itself, which appears at first sight like part of the intestines. This, the
                    cardiac extremity of the stomach, is, for a short distance to the left of the
                    entrance of the oesophagus, still very narrow, but soon increases in size, till
                    near its termination it attains a diameter quite three times that of the short
                    pyloric portion. The length of this cardiac diverticulum of the stomach appears
                    to vary from 2 to 6 inches, the size in each specimen probably depending on the
                    amount of food obtained by the animal before it was captured.</p>
                <p>The only other known species of blood-sucking bat, <hi rend="italic">Diphylla
                        ecaudata,</hi> Spix, inhabits Brazil, and appears to be much less abundant
                    than <hi rend="italic">Desmodus rufus,</hi> from which it is distinguished by
                    its slightly smaller size, by the absence of a groove in the front of the lower
                    lip, by the non-development of the interfemoral membrane in the centre, and by
                    the presence of a short calcaneum (absent in <hi rend="italic">D. rufus),</hi>
                    but more particularly by the presence of an additional rudimentary back tooth (?
                    molar) above and below, and by the very peculiar form of the lower incisors,
                    which are much expanded in the direction of the jaws and pectinated, forming a
                    semicircular row touching each other, the outer incisors being wider than the
                    inner ones, with six notches, the inner incisors with three each.</p>
                <p>Thus constituted, these bats present, in this extraordinary differentiation of
                    the manducatory and digestive apparatus, a departure from the type of other
                    species of the family <hi rend="italic">(Phyllostomidae)</hi> to which they
                    belong unparalleled in any of the other orders of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mammalia,</hi> standing apart from all other mammals as being fitted only
                    for a diet of blood, and capable of sustaining life upon that alone.</p>
                <p>Travellers describe the wounds inflicted by the large sharp-edged incisors as
                    being similar to those caused by a razor when shaving: a portion of the skin is
                    shaved off and, a large number of severed capillary vessels being thus exposed,
                    a constant flow of blood is maintained. From this source the blood is drawn
                    through the exceedingly narrow gullet—too narrow for anything solid to pass—into
                    the intestine-like stomach, whence it is, probably, gradually drawn off during
                    the slow process of digestion, while the animal, sated with food, is hanging in
                    a state of torpidity from the roof of its cave or from the inner sides of a
                    hollow tree. (G. E. D. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
