<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0152-0137-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VENDÉE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 137</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xk87">Bretons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43r0pw3g">Looms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:838487">Bretons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1002458">Looms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n152/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VENDÉE</label>, a maritime department of France, formed in
                    1790 out of Bas-Poitou, and taking its name from an unimportant tributary of the
                    Sèvre Niortaise, lies between 46° 16' and 47° 5' N. lat. and 0° 32' and 2° 10'
                    W. long., and is bounded by Loire-Inférieure and Maine-et-Loire on the N., by
                    Deux-Sèvres on the E., by Charente-Inférieure on the S., and by the Atlantic
                    Ocean on the W. for 93 miles. The islands of Yeu (or Dieu) and Noirmoutier are
                    included. The Sèvre Nantaise on the N.E. and the Sèvre Niortaise on the S.,
                    besides other streams of minor importance, form natural boundaries. The
                    department falls into three divisions—woodland, plain, and marsh. The highest
                    point (945 feet) is situated in the woodland, which occupies the greater part of
                    Vendée, on the water-parting between the Loire and the rivers of the coast. This
                    region, which, geologically, is composed of granite, gneiss, mica-schist,
                    schist, and lias, abounds in springs, and is fresh and verdant; the landscape is
                    characterized by open fields surrounded by trees, which supplied ambushes and
                    retreats to the Vendéans in the civil war at the end of the 18th century. The
                    plain of Vendée is bare and treeless, but fertile, though poor in springs;
                    geologically it is composed of lias and oolite. The marshes, raised above the
                    sea-level within historic times (four centuries ago), consist of two portions,
                    the Breton marsh in the north and the Poitevin marsh in the south. The region
                    includes salt marshes and cultivated areas artificially drained. Its area is
                    constantly being increased by the alluvium of the rivers and the secular
                    elevation of the coast. The department is drained by the Sèvre Nantaise
                    (tributary of the Loire) and the Boulogne (a feeder of Lake Grandlieu in
                    Loire-Inférieure), both draining into the basin of the Loire; and by the Vie,
                    the Lay (with the Yon), and the Sèvre Niortaise (with the Autise and the
                    Vendée), which flow into the Atlantic. The climate is that of the Girondin
                    region, <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n153/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0153-0138"/> mild and damp, the temperature rarely rising
                    above 77° or falling below 18° Fahr.; 120 to 150 days of rain give an annual
                    rainfall of 30 inches. The woodland is colder than the plain, and the marsh is
                    damp and unhealthy.</p>
                <p>Out of the total area of 1,656,531 acres arable land occupies 1,023,275 acres,
                    grass 290,503, vines 37,467, wood 65,853, and moor, pasture, and uncultivated
                    land 136,432. In 1881 the live stock included 29,790 horses, 4500 mules, 1950
                    asses, 471,775 cattle, 379,950 sheep (10,000 being of superior breed; total
                    wool-clip 395 tons), 55,000 pigs, and 1625 goats. There were 10,000 beehives (49
                    tons of honey and 10 tons of wax). The agricultural products in 1884 were
                    returned as follows :—wheat 7,312,316 bushels, meslin 65,736, rye 218,720,
                    barley 1,218,855, buckwheat 358,985, maize 33,000, millet 129,973, oats
                    2,815,436, potatoes 3,938,214, beetroot 324,601 tons, wine 15,569,312 gallons,
                    colza seed 7790 tons, hemp seed 551 tons, linseed 991 tons, flax 1786 tons, and
                    fodder 745,792 tons. The forests (oak, chestnut, pine, poplar, hornbeam, maple,
                    ash, beech, and elm) yielded 3,180,000 cubic feet of wood, a third of which was
                    applied to various industrial uses. Apples, pears, peaches, plums, cherries, and
                    walnuts are the principal fruits grown. The salt marshes, 4572 acres in extent
                    and employing 3500 workmen, yielded 2436 tons of salt in 1882. In 1884 18,409
                    tons of coal were mined. Iron, antimony, lead, “the Vendée diamond” (a kind of
                    quartz), china clay, and slate are obtained; and granite, gneiss, slate schist,
                    limestone, cement, millstones, and clay are objects of industry. The celebrated
                    beds of sea-shells near St Michel-en-l'Herm—2300 feet long, 985 broad, and from
                    30 to 50 feet in depth—show to what an extent the coast has risen. The wool
                    spinning and weaving industry occupies 12,570 spindles and 520 hand-looms;
                    cotton, 3100 spindles and 5 looms; linen, 388 spindles and 478 looms (80 being
                    power looms). There are potteries, paper-mills, tan-yards, dye-works, a
                    glass-work, manufactories of hats, boots and shoes, and lampblack, flour-mills,
                    distilleries, tile-works, and shipbuilding-yards, and sardines and tinned foods
                    are prepared,—in all 575 industrial establishments. The sardine fishery occupies
                    800 boats and 2000 men, and there are extensive oyster-beds near
                    Sables-d’Olonne. Corn, cattle, mules, fish, salt, wine, honey, wood, glass, and
                    manure are exported; wine, wood, building material, and coal are among the
                    imports. The shipping places are Bouin and Beauvoir in the Breton marsh, and
                    Noirmoutier, the island of Yeu, St Gilles-sur-Vie, Sables-d’Olonne, L’Aiguillon,
                    and Luçon in the Poitevin marsh. In 1882 a total of 391 vessels (130,688 tons)
                    entered and cleared from all these ports. Vendee has 212 miles of railway, 335
                    of national and 2966 of other roads, and 82 of navigable rivers and canals. In
                    1881 the population was 421,642, and in 1886 434,808,—an increase of 191,382
                    since 1801. The department forms the diocese of Luçon, has its court of appeal
                    and academy at Poitiers, and is included in the district of the Nantes army
                    corps. There are three arrondissements (La Roche-sur-Yon, the chef-lieu of the
                    department, with 10,991 inhabitants in 1886; Fontenay-le-Comte, 9282; and
                    Sables-d’Olonne, 10,114), 30 cantons, and 300 communes. Luçon (6285 inhabitants)
                    is connected with the sea by a canal, and has a cathedral of the 11th, 13th,
                    14th, 16th, and 18th centuries, with an elegant Gothic spire, a cloister of the
                    15th and 16th centuries, an episcopal palace, and a hospital, with portraits of
                    the bishops of Luçon.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
