<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0048-0035-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VALENS (9th edition, volume 24, page 35)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nv99d8g">Huns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163799">Valentinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964118">Huns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814376">Arianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n48/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VALENS</label>, emperor of the East from 364 to 378, owed his
                    elevation in the thirty-sixth year of his age to his brother Valentinian, who
                    chose him to be his associate in the empire, of which a formal division into
                    East and West was now once for all definitively arranged (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Valentinian</hi> I.). Valens had been attached to Julian’s
                    bodyguard, but he was not much of a soldier, though his father, Gratian of
                    Pannonia, had risen from the ranks to a high position. A revolt headed by
                    Procopius in the second year of his reign, and backed up by the public opinion
                    of Constantinople and the sympathy of the Gothic princes and chiefs on the
                    Danube, seemed so alarming that he thought of negotiation; but in the following
                    year the revolt collapsed at the prompt action of a loyal and able veteran
                    officer. In the year 366 Valens at one stroke reduced the taxes of the empire by
                    one-fourth, a very popular measure, though one of questionable policy in the
                    face of the threatening attitude of the Goths on the lower Danube. Before
                    venturing on a campaign against them, Valens received baptism from Eudoxus, the
                    bishop of Constantinople and the leader of the Arian party. After some small
                    successes over the Goths, won by his generals, Valens concluded a peace with
                    them, which lasted six years, on a general understanding that the Danube was to
                    be the boundary between Goths and Romans. On his return to Constantinople in
                    369-370 Valens began to persecute his orthodox and Catholic subjects. Yet he can
                    hardly have been a hearty and willing persecutor, or he would not have suffered
                    the orthodox Basil to remain bishop of Caesarea in Cappadocia, nor can he have
                    been a thoroughgoing religious fanatic, or he would not have restrained many of
                    his subjects from burying themselves in monasteries to escape the duties of
                    citizens. Indeed he had not the strength of will or force of character to have
                    been either the one or the other.</p>
                <p>In the years 371 to 377 Valens was in Asia Minor, most of the time at the Syrian
                    Antioch. The late war with Persia under the emperors Julian and Jovian had not
                    been satisfactorily concluded: the question as to the possession or the
                    protectorate of Armenia was still in suspense. Valens, though anxious to avoid
                    an Eastern war, because of danger nearer home from the restlessness of the
                    Goths, was compelled to take the field against Sapor, who had invaded and
                    occupied Armenia. It seems that Valens<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Amm. Marc., xxix. 1; the narrative is brief and not very
                            clear.</p></note> crossed the Euphrates in 373, and in Mesopotamia his
                    troops drove back the king of Persia to the farther bank of the Tigris. But the
                    Roman success was by no means decisive, and no definite understanding as to
                    boundaries was come to with Persia. Valens returned to Antioch, where in the
                    winter of 373 a young man of high rank, Theodorus by name, was made to believe
                    by a pack of fortune-tellers and magicians that the emperor’s successor would be
                    a man whose name began with “Theod.” Theodorus was put to death, with many
                    others whose name began with the same fatal letters; and this led to a
                    vindictive persecution throughout the province of Asia of all who professed or
                    practised magic and necromancy. The age was a very superstitious and inquisitive
                    one, and Valens certainly shared its weakness. Between 374 and 377 we read of
                    grievous complaints of injustice and extortion perpetrated under legal forms,
                    the result probably of the recent panic, and pointing to an increasing weakness
                    and timidity at headquarters. Although preparations were made for following up
                    the war with Persia and securing the frontier, a truce was patched up, rather to
                    the disadvantage of the empire, Armenia and the adjacent country being half
                    conquered and annexed by Sapor. The armies of Rome, in fact, were wanted in
                    another quarter. The Huns, of whom we now hear for the first time, were
                    beginning in 376 to press the Goths from the north, and the latter asked leave
                    of the emperor to cross the Danube into Roman territory. This they were allowed
                    to do, on the condition that they came unarmed, and their children were <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n49/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0049-0036"/> transported to Asia as hostages. The
                    conditions, however, were not strictly enforced, and the whole affair was
                    treacherously mismanaged by the imperial generals, who for their own profit
                    forced the new settlers to buy food at famine prices. Accordingly the enraged
                    Goths, under their chief Frithigern, streamed across the Balkans into Thrace and
                    the country round Adrianople, plundering, burning, and slaughtering as they
                    went. They were driven back for a time, but returned in the spring of 378 in
                    greater force, with Huns and Alans to fight with them against the empire; and
                    again, after one or two repulses, they penetrated to the neighbourhood of
                    Adrianople. Valens, who had now returned to Constantinople, left the capital in
                    May 378 with a strong and well-officered army. Without awaiting the arrival of
                    his nephew Gratian, emperor of the West, who had just won a great victory over
                    one of the barbarous tribes of Germany in Alsace, Valens attacked the enemy at
                    once, although his troops had to go into action heated and fatigued by a long
                    march on a sultry August day. The battle was decided mainly by the cavalry of
                    the Alans and Sarmatians, the Roman infantry being outnumbered, outmanoeuvred,
                    and finally so hemmed in that the men could scarcely draw their swords. The
                    slaughter went on for hours, till the imperial army was destroyed. Valens either
                    perished on the field or, as some said, in a cottage fired by the enemy. From
                    the battle of Adrianople the Goths permanently established themselves south of
                    the Danube.</p>
                <p>Ammianus Marcellinus, a contemporary writer, is our chief authority for the
                    reigns of Valens and Valentinian. See also Gibbon’s sketch of the period in the
                    26th and 27th chapters of his <hi rend="italic">Decline and Fall</hi> and
                    Hodgkin’s <hi rend="italic">Italy and her Invaders.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
