<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0194-0175-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VERROCCHIO, Andrea del</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 175</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z22r">Hardness</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4td9ng4n">Polo</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:951374">Hardness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:808746">Angels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827229">Baptism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1070244">Polo</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:810896">Ants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n194/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VERROCCHIO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrea del</hi></label>
                    (1435-1488), one of the most distinguished Florentine artists of the 15th
                    century, equally famed as a goldsmith, sculptor, and painter, was born at
                    Florence in 1435. He was the son of Michele di Francesco de’ Cioni, and took his
                    name from his master, the goldsmith Giuliano Verrocchi. Except through his
                    works, little is known of his life. As a painter he occupies an important
                    position from the fact that Leonardo da Vinci and Lorenzo di Credi worked for
                    many years in his bottega as pupils and assistants. Only one existing painting
                    can be attributed with absolute certainty to Verrocchio’s hand, the celebrated
                    Baptism of Christ, originally painted for the monks of Vallombrosa, and now in
                    the academy of Florence. The figures of Christ and the Baptist are executed with
                    great vigour and refinement of touch, but are rather hard and angular in style.
                    As Vasari says, Verrocchio “ebbe la maniera alquanto dura e crudetta.” The two
                    angels are of a much more graceful cast; the face of one is of especial beauty,
                    and Vasari is probably right in saying that this head was painted by the young
                    Leonardo. Other pictures from Verrocchio’s bottega probably exist, as, for
                    example, two in the National Gallery of London wrongly attributed to Ant.
                    Pollaiuolo—Tobias and the Angel (No. 781) and the very lovely Madonna and Angels
                    (No. 296), both very brilliant and jewel-like in colour. One of the angel faces
                    in the latter picture strongly recalls the expression of Leonardo’s heads, while
                    the whole scheme of pure glowing colour closely resembles that employed by Di
                    Credi in his graceful but slightly weak pictures of the Madonna and Child. This
                    exquisite painting, one of the gems of the National Gallery, may possibly have
                    been painted from Verrocchio’s design by Lorenzo di Credi while he was under the
                    immediate influence of his wonderful fellow-pupil Da Vinci.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Crowe and Cavalcaselle, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Painting in Italy,</hi> London, 1864, ii. p. 400 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sg.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>In examining Verrocchio’s work as a sculptor we are on surer ground. One of his
                    earliest works was the beautiful marble medallion of the Madonna, over the tomb
                    of Leonardo Bruni of Arezzo in the church of Santa Croce at Florence, executed
                    some years after Bruni’s death (1443). In 1472 Verrocchio completed the fine
                    tomb of Giovanni and Piero de’ Medici, between the sacristy and the lady chapel
                    of San Lorenzo at Florence. This consists of a great porphyry sarcophagus
                    enriched with magnificent acanthus foliage in bronze. Above it is a graceful
                    open bronze grill, made like a network of cordage. In 1474 Verrocchio began the
                    monument to Cardinal Forteguerra at the west end of Pistoia cathedral. The
                    kneeling figure of the cardinal was never completed, and now lies in a room of
                    La Sapienza, but the whole design is shown in what is probably Verrocchio’s
                    original clay sketch, now in the South Kensington Museum (see <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n195/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0195-0176"/> fig.). Though this work was designed by
                    Verrocchio, the actual execution of it was entrusted to his assistant, the
                    Florentine Lor-enzetto. In 1476 Verrocchio modelled and cast the fine but too
                    realistic bronze statue of David, now in the Bargello (Florence); and in the
                    following year he completed one of the reliefs of the magnificent silver
                    altar-frontal of the Florentine baptistery, that representing the Be-headingof
                    St John. Verrocchio’s other works in the precious metals are now lost, but
                    Vasari records that he made many elaborate pieces of plate and jewellery, such
                    as morses for copes, as well as a series of silver statues of the Apostles for
                    the pope’s chapel in the Vatican. Between 1478 and 1483 he was occupied in
                    making the bronze group of the Unbelief of St Thomas, which still stands in one
                    of the external niches of Or San Michele (Florence). He received 800 florins for
                    these two figures, which are more remarkable for the excellence of their
                    technique than for their sculpturesque beauty. The attitudes are rather rigid,
                    and the faces hard in expression. Verrocchio’s chief masterpiece was the
                    colossal bronze equestrian statue of the Venetian general Bartolomeo Colleoni,
                    which stands in the piazza of SS. Giovanni e Paolo at Venice. Verrocchio
                    received the order for this statue in 1479, but had only completed the model
                    when he died in 1488. In spite of his request that the casting should be
                    entrusted to his pupil Lorenzo di Credi, the work was given to Alessandro
                    Leopardi by the Venetian senate, and the statue was gilt and unveiled in
                    1496.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Gay, <hi
                    rend="italic">Cart. Inéd.,</hi> i. p. 367.</p></note> There appears to be no
                    doubt that the model was completed by Verrocchio himself, and that' nothing more
                    than its reproduction in bronze should be attributed to the much feebler hand of
                    Leopardi, who, however, has set his own name alone on the belly-band of the
                    horse—ALEXANDER · LEOPARDVS V.</p>
                <p>F. OPUS. This is perhaps the noblest equestrian statue in the world, being in
                    some respects superior to the antique bronze of Marcus Aurelius in Rome and to
                    that of Gattamelata at Padua by Donatello. The horse is designed with wonderful
                    nobility and spirit, and the easy pose of the great general, combining perfect
                    balance with absolute ease and security in the saddle, is a marvel of
                    sculpturesque ability.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sculpture,</hi> vol. xxi. p. 568, fig.
                    18.</p></note> Most remarkable skill is shown by the way in which Verrocchio has
                    exaggerated the strongly marked features of the general, so that nothing of its
                    powerful effect is lost by the lofty position of the head.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Selvatico, <hi rend="italic">Arch. e
                    Scult. in Venezia,</hi> 1847; Cicognara, <hi rend="italic">Fabbriche piu
                    Cospicue di Venezia,</hi> 1853; and Milanesi’s ed. of Vasari, iii. p. 357 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note> According to Vasari, Verrocchio was one of the
                    first sculptors who made a practical use of casts from living and dead subjects.
                    He is said also to have produced plastic works in terra-cotta, wood, and in wax
                    decorated with colour. As a sculptor his chief pupil was Francesco di Simone,
                    the son of that Simone whom Vasari wrongly calls a brother of Donatello. Another
                    pupil was Agnolo di Polo (Paolo), who worked chiefly in terra-cotta.</p>
                <p>Verrocchio died in Venice in 1488, and was buried in the church of St Ambrogio in
                    Florence. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">μ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
