<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0291-0268-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VLACHS (9th edition, volume 24, page 268)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1226682">Albania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1212674">Croatia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1692600">Montenegro</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669847">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4px50">Roumanian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c2b">Avars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16p3t">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841374">Bulgarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120771">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964057">Hungarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887231">Dalmatians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:967439">Illyrians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n291/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VLACHS</label>. Vlach, otherwise written Wallack, is a
                    general name for all the members of the Latin-speaking race inhabiting eastern
                    Europe. The name is in its origin identical with our “Welsh,” “Welshman,” and
                    represents a Slavonic adaptation of a generic term applied by the Teutonic races
                    at the time of the migration of peoples to all Roman provincials. It thus finds
                    its analogies in the German name for Italy—Welschland (Wälischland), in the
                    Walloons of the Low Countries, the “Wallgau” of Tyrol, &amp;c. An early instance
                    of its application to the Roman population of the Eastern empire is found in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Traveller's Song,</hi> where in a passage which in all
                    probability connects itself with the early trade-route between the Baltic staple
                    of Wollin and Byzantium, the gleeman speaks of Caesar’s realm as <hi
                        rend="italic">Walaric =</hi> “Welshry.” In verse 140 he speaks of the
                    “Rum-walas,” and it is to be observed that “Rum” is one of the words by which
                    the Vlachs of eastern Europe still know themselves.</p>
                <p>The Slavs, at least in their principal extent, first knew the Roman empire
                    through a Teutonic medium, and adopted their terms Vlach, Voloch, from the
                    Ostro-Gothic equivalent of the Anglo-Saxon “Wealh.” The name is thus of foreign
                    origin, the native Vlachs continuing to this day to call themselves “<hi
                        rend="italic">Rumeni," Romeni,</hi> or even <hi rend="italic">Romani</hi>;
                    and it is from the native pronunciation of the Roman name that we have the
                    equivalent expression <hi rend="italic">Rouman,</hi> a word which must by no
                    means be confined to that part of the Vlach race inhabiting the present kingdom
                    of Roumania. This Vlach or Rouman race constitutes a distinct division of the
                    Latin family of peoples, widely disseminated throughout eastern Europe, both
                    north and south of the Danube. North of the Danube the Roumans inhabit, besides
                    Walachia and Moldavia, Bessarabia and the adjoining South-Russian districts, a
                    large part of Transylvania and the Hungarian Banat, and extend sporadically from
                    the Bug to the Adriatic. South of the Danube the central glens of Pindus form
                    the principal nucleus of Rouman habitation, but there is besides a considerable
                    colony in the Epirote district of Musakja, in Aetolia and Acarnania, in various
                    districts of Albania, Thessaly, Macedonia, and the Bulgarian principality. In
                    Servia this element is preponderant in the Timok valley, while in Istria it is
                    represented by the Cici, at present largely Slavonized, as are now entirely the
                    kindred Morlachs of Dalmatia.</p>
                <p>The centre of gravity of the Vlach or Rouman race is at present unquestionably
                    north of the Danube, and corresponds roughly to the limits of Trajan’s Dacian
                    province. From this circumstance the popular idea has arisen that the race
                    itself represents the descendants of the Romanized population of Trajan’s Dacia,
                    which was assumed to have maintained an unbroken existencein Walachia,
                    Transylvania, &amp;c., beneath the dominion of a succession of invaders. The
                    Vlachs of Pindus, &amp;c., on this hypothesis, were to be regarded as later
                    immigrants from the lands north of the Danube. In 1871 Roesler published, in a
                    collective form, a series of essays, in which he absolutely denied the claim of
                    the Roumanian and Transylvanian Vlachs to be regarded as Dacian autochthones. He
                    laid stress on the statements of Vopiscus and others as implying the total
                    withdrawal of the Roman provincials from Trajan’s Dacia by Aurelian, and on the
                    non-mention by historians of a Latin population in the lands on the left bank of
                    the lower Danube, during their successive occupation by Goths, Huns, Gepidae,
                    Avars, Slavs, Bulgars, and other barbarian races. He found the first trace of a
                    Rouman settlement north of the Danube in a Transylvanian diploma of 1222.
                    Roesler’s thesis has been generally regarded as an entirely new departure in
                    critical ethnography. As a matter of fact, his conclusions had to a great extent
                    been already anticipated by Sulzer in his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des
                        Transalpinischen Daciens,</hi> published at Vienna in 1781, and at a still
                    earlier date by the Dalmatian historian Lucius of Traü in his work <hi
                        rend="italic">De Regno Dalmatiae et Croatiae,</hi> 1666.</p>
                <p>The theory of the later immigration of the Roumans into their present abodes
                    north of the Danube, as stated in its most extreme form by Roesler, commanded
                    wide acceptance, and in Hungary it was politically utilized as a plea for
                    refusing parity of treatment to a race of comparatively recent intruders. In
                    Roumania itself Roesler’s views were resented as an attack on Rouman
                    nationality. Outside Roumania they found a determined opponent in Dr Jung, of
                    Innsbruck, who in his <hi rend="italic">Anfänge der Romanen</hi> upheld the
                    continuity of the Roman provincial stock in Trajan’s Dacia, disputing from
                    historic analogies the total withdrawal of the provincials by Aurelian; and the
                    reaction against Roesler was carried still further by T. Lad. Pič <hi
                        rend="italic">Ueber die Abstammung der Rumänen,</hi> 1880) and Prof. A. D.
                    Xenopol of Jassy <hi rend="italic">(Les Roumains au Moyen Age,</hi> 1885).</p>
                <p>On the whole,—as often in controversies,—it may be said that the truth lies
                    between the two extremes. Roesler is no doubt so far right that at the time of
                    the migration of peoples, and indeed throughout the early Middle Ages, the bulk
                    of the Rouman people lay south of the Danube.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n292/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0292-0269"/>
                <p>Pič’s view that the population of the Roman provinces of Moesia, &amp;c., were
                    Hellenized rather than Romanized, and that it is to Trajan’s Dacia alone that we
                    must look for the Roman source of the Vlach race, conflicts with what we know of
                    the Latinizing of the Balkan lands from inscriptions, martyrologies, Procopius’s
                    list of Justinian’s Illyrian fortresses, and other sources. This Roman element
                    south of the Danube had further received a great increase at the expense of
                    Trajan’s colonial foundation to the north when Aurelian established his New
                    Dacia on the Moesian side of the river. On the other hand, the analogy supplied
                    by the withdrawal of the Roman provincials from Riparian Noricum tells against
                    the assumption that the official withdrawal of the Roman colonists of Trajan’s
                    Dacia by Aurelian entailed the entire evacuation of the Carpathian regions by
                    their Latin-speaking inhabitants. As on the upper Danube the continuity of the
                    Roman population is attested by the <hi rend="italic">Vici Romanisci</hi> of
                    early mediaeval diplomas and by other traces of a Romanic race still represented
                    by the Ladin es of Tyrol, so it is reasonable to suppose a Latin-speaking
                    population continued to exist in the formerly thickly colonized area embracing
                    the present Transylvania and Little Walachia, with adjoining Carpathian regions.
                    Even as late as Justinian’s time, the official connexion with the old Dacian
                    province was not wholly lost, as is shown by the erection or restoration of
                    certain <hi rend="italic">tetes-de-pont</hi> and <hi rend="italic">castella</hi>
                    on the left bank of the lower Danube.</p>
                <p>We may therefore assume that the Latin race of eastern Europe never wholly lost
                    touch of its former trans-Danubian strongholds. It was, however, on any showing
                    greatly diminished there. The open country, the broad plains of what is now the
                    Roumanian kingdom, and the Banat of Hungary were in barbarian occupation. The
                    centre of gravity of the Roman or Romance element of Illyricum had now shifted
                    south of the Danube. By the 6th century a large part of Thrace, Macedonia, and
                    even of Epirus, had become Latin-speaking.</p>
                <p>What had occurred in Trajan’s Dacia in the 3d century was consummated in the 6th
                    and 7th throughout the greater part of the South-Illyrian provinces, and the
                    Slavonic and Avar conquests severed the official connexion with eastern Rome.
                    The overthrow of civic life and break-down of provincial organization was
                    complete. The Roman element was uprooted from its fixed seats, and swept hither
                    and thither by the barbarian flood. Nomadism became an essential of independent
                    existence. On the other hand, large masses of homeless provincials were dragged
                    off as captives in the train of their barbarian conquerors, to be distributed in
                    servile colonies. They were thus in many cases transported by barbarian
                    chiefs—Slav, Avar, and Bulgarian—to trans-Danubian and Pannonian regions. In the
                        <hi rend="italic">Acts</hi> of St Demetrius of Thessalonica we actually find
                    an account of such a Roman colony, which, having been carried away from
                    South-Illyrian cities by the Avar khagan, and settled by him in the Sirmian
                    district beyond the Save, revolted after seventy years of captivity, made their
                    way once more across the Balkan passes, and finally settled as an independent
                    community in the country inland from Salonica. Others, no doubt, thus
                    transported northwards never returned. It is certain that the earliest Hungarian
                    historians who describe the Magyar invasion of the 9th century speak of the old
                    inhabitants of the country as Romans, and of the country they occupied as <hi
                        rend="italic">Pascua Romanorum·,</hi> and the Russian Nestor, writing about
                    1100, makes the same invaders fight against Slavs and Vlachs (Volochi) in the
                    Carpathian Mountains. So far from the first mention of the Vlachs north of the
                    Danube occurring only in 1222, as Roesler asserts, it appears from a passage of
                    Nicetas of Chonae that they were to be found already in 1164 as far afield as
                    the borders of Galicia.</p>
                <p>It is nevertheless true that throughout the early Middle Ages the bulk of the
                    Rouman population lay south of the Danube. It was in the Balkan lands that the
                    Rouman race and language took their characteristic mould. It is here that this
                    new Illyrian Romance first rises into historic prominence. Already in the 6th
                    century, as we learn from the place names, such as Sceptecasas, Burgualtu,
                    Clisura, &amp;c., given by Procopius, the Rouman language was assuming, so far
                    as its Latin elements were concerned, its typical form. In the somewhat later
                    campaigns of Commentiolus (587) and Priscus, against the Avars and Slovenes, we
                    find the Latin-speaking soldiery of the Eastern emperor making use of such
                    Romance expressions as “torna, frate!” (turn, brother!), or “sculca” (out of
                    bed) applied to a watch <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Rouman “a se culca” =
                    Italian “coricarsi” + ex-(s-) privative). Next we find this warlike Rouman
                    population largely incorporated in the Bulgarian kingdom, and, if we are to
                    judge from the names Paganus and Sabinus, already supplying it with rulers in
                    the 8th century. The blending and close contact during this period of the
                    surviving Latin population with the Slovene settlers of the peninsula
                    impregnated the language with its large Slavonic ingredient; and the
                    considerable Albanian element in Rouman, as well as the still greater element of
                    Rouman in Albanian, is alone sufficient to show that the two languages took
                    their characteristic shapes in a contiguous area. The fact that these
                    peculiarities are common to the Roumans north of the Danube, whose language
                    differs dialectically from that of their southern brothers, shows that it was
                    this southern branch that throughout the early periods of Rouman history was
                    exercising a dominating influence. Migrations, violent transplantation, the
                    intercourse which was kept up between the most outlying members of the race, in
                    its very origin nomadic, at a later period actual colonization <hi rend="italic"
                        >en masse</hi> and the political influence of the Bulgaro-Vlachian empire,
                    no doubt contributed to propagate these southern linguistic acquisitions
                    throughout that northern area to which the Rouman race was destined almost
                    imperceptibly to shift its centre of gravity.</p>
                <p>Byzantium, which had ceased to be Roman, and become Romaic, renewed its
                    acquaintance with the descendants of the Latin provincials of Illyricum through
                    a Slavonic medium, and applied to them the name of “Vlach,” which the Slav
                    himself had borrowed from the Goth. The first mention of Vlachs in a Byzantine
                    source is about the year 976, when Cedrenus (ii. 439) relates the murder of the
                    Bulgarian czar Samuel’s brother “by certain Vlach wayfarers,” at a spot called
                    the Fair Oaks, between Castoria and Prespa. From this period onwards the Rouman
                    inhabitants of the Balkan peninsula are constantly mentioned by this name, and
                    we find a series of political organizations and territorial divisions connected
                    with the name of “Vlachia.” Within the limits of the present article it is
                    impossible to give more than a short synopsis of the most important of these,
                    while for a history of the later Rouman principalities of Walachia and Moldavia
                    the reader is referred to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Roumania.</hi></p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Bulgaro-Vlach Empire.</hi> —After the overthrow of the
                    older Bulgarian czardom by Basil Bulgaroktonos, the Vlach population of Thrace,
                    Haemus, and the Moesian lands passed once more under Byzantine dominion; and in
                    1185 a heavy tax, levied in kind on the cattle of these warlike mountain
                    shepherds, stirred the Vlachs to revolt against the emperor Isaac Angelus, and
                    under the leadership of two brothers, Peter and Asen, to found a new
                    Bulgaro-Vlachian empire, which ended with Kaliman II. in 1257. The dominions of
                    these half-Slavonic half-Rouman emperors extended north of the Danube over a
                    great deal of what is now Roumania, and it was during this period that the Vlach
                    population north of the river seems to have been most largely reinforced. The
                    French traveller Rubruquis speaks of all the country between Don and Danube as
                    “Asen’s land” or “Blakia.”</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Great Walachia</hi> (Mεγάλη Βλαχία).—It is from Anna
                    Comnena, in the second half of the 11th century, that we first hear of <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n293/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0293-0270"/> a Vlach settlement, the nucleus of which was
                    the mountainous region of Thessaly. Benjamin of Tudela, in the succeeding
                    century, gives an interesting account of this Great Walachia, which was then
                    completely independent. It embraced the southern and central ranges of Pindus,
                    and extended over part of Macedonia, thus including the region in which the
                    Roman settlers mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Acts</hi> of St Demetrius had
                    fixed their abode. After the Latin conquest of Constantinople Great Walachia was
                    included in the enlarged despotate of Epirus, but it soon reappears as an
                    independent principality under its old name, which, after passing under the yoke
                    of the Serb emperor Dushan, was finally conquered by the Turks in 1393. Many of
                    their old privileges were still accorded to the inhabitants, and their taxes
                    were limited to an annual tribute to the sultana Valide. Since this period the
                    Megalovlachites have been largely Hellenized, but they are still represented by
                    the flourishing Tzintzar settlements of Pindus, and traces are at present
                    perceptible among them of a national Rouman reaction.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Little Walachia {Μικρά</hi> Βλαχία) was a name applied by
                    Byzantine writers to the Rouman settlements of Aetolia and Acarnania, and with
                    it may be included “Upper Walachia” or Ανώβλαχα. Its inhabitants are still
                    represented by the Tzintzars of the Aspropotamo and the Karaguni (Black Capes)
                    of Acarnania.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Morlachs (Mavrovlachi) of the West.—</hi> These are
                    already mentioned as <hi rend="italic">Nigri Latini</hi> by the Presbyter of
                    Dioclea (<hi rend="italic">circ.</hi> 1150) in the old Dalmatian littoral and
                    the mountains of what is now Montenegro, Herzegovina, and North Albania. Other
                    colonies extended through a great part of the old Servian interior, where is a
                    region still called Stara Vlaska or “Old Walachia.” The great commercial staple
                    of the east Adriatic. shores, the republic of Ragusa, seems in its origin to
                    have been a Rouman settlement, and many Vlach traces survived in its later
                    dialect. Philippus de Diversis, who described the city as it existed in 1440,
                    says that “the various officers of the republic do not make use either of Slav
                    or Italian, with which they converse with strangers, but a certain other dialect
                    only partially intelligible to us Latins,” and cites words with strong Rouman
                    affinities. In the mountains above Ragusa a number of Vlach tribes are mentioned
                    in the archives of that city, and the original relationship of the Ragusans and
                    the nomadic Alpine representatives of the Roman provincials, who preserved a
                    traditional knowledge of the old lines of communication throughout the
                    peninsula, explains the extraordinary development of the Ragusan commerce. In
                    the 14th century the Mavrovlachi or Morlachs extended themselves towards the
                    Croatian borders, and a large part of maritime Croatia and northern Dalmatia
                    began to be known as “Morlacchia.” A “Major Vlachia” was formed about the triple
                    frontier of Bosnia, Croatia, and Dalmatia, and a “Little Walachia” as far north
                    as Posega. The Morlachs have now become Slavonized.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Cici of Istria.—</hi> The extreme Rouman offshoot to the
                    northwest is still represented by the Cici of the Val d’Arsa and adjoining
                    Istrian districts. They represent a 15th-century Morlach colony from the Isle of
                    Veglia, and had formerly a wider extension to Trieste and the counties of
                    Gradisca aud Gorizia. The Cici are at •present rapidly losing their native
                    tongue, which is the last remaining representative of the old Morlach, and forms
                    a connecting link between the Daco-Roman (or Roumanian) and the Macedo-Roman (or
                    Tzintzar) dialects.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Roumans of Transylvania and Hungary.—</hi> As already
                    stated, a large part of the Hungarian plains were, at the coming of the Magyars
                    in the 9th century, known as <hi rend="italic">Pascua Romanorum.</hi> At a later
                    period privileged Rouman communities existed at Fogaras, where was a <hi
                        rend="italic">Silva Vlachorum,</hi> at Marmaros, Deva, Hatzeg, Hunyad, and
                    Lugos, and in the Banat were seven Rouman districts. Two of the greatest figures
                    in Hungarian history—John Corvinus of Hunyad, and his son King Matthias—were due
                    to this element. Oppressed by the dominant race, which had deprived them of
                    their ancient privileges, the Roumans of Transylvania and the Banat rose in 1785
                    under Horia, Closca, and Crischanu. This Rouman “Jacquerie” was suppressed, but
                    Joseph II. declared the peasants free. Since that date the Rouman element in
                    this part of the old Dacian region has largely increased in numbers, though it
                    has hitherto failed to secure its political rights. The contiguous district of
                    the Bukovina, a part of Moldavia annexed to the Hapsburg dominions in 1775,
                    remains under the Austrian Government.</p>
                <p>The present numerical strength of tho Roumanians may approximately be given as
                    follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Southern or Tzintzar branch in Pindus, &amp;c.,</cell>
                        <cell>...225,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Roumans of Tirnok district</cell>
                        <cell>...150,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Roumanians</cell>
                        <cell>4,500,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In Austria-Hungary</cell>
                        <cell>3,500,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In Bessarabia and South Russia</cell>
                        <cell>...600,000</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total</cell>
                        <cell>8,975,000</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In features the Vlachs especially of the Carpathian valleys present decidedly
                    Roman characteristics, and it is not unfrequent to find types which occur in
                    North Italy and amongst Spaniards and Provençale. They are usually short and
                    dark. Those of Pindus have sharper-cut features and some Slovene traits in their
                    physiognomy. The race has a great natural capacity for trade and manufacture.
                    The Vlachs excel as builders and artisans, but notably as workers in metal;
                    their financial enterprise is also remarkable, and some of the principal banking
                    establishments in Vienna are due to members of this race. An extraordinary
                    example of their successful enterprise in the Balkan peninsula is supplied by
                    the history of Moschopolis on the Epirote side of Pindus, which was founded by a
                    Vlach colony in the 16th century, and which not only became a populous
                    commercial staple but a centre of literary culture. Moschopolis possessed a
                    large public library, flourishing schools, and a printing press, from which
                    issued both Greek and Rouman books of a religious and scholastic nature.
                    Joannina, since completely Hellenized, was also of Rouman origin. Metzovo
                    (Minciu) is another flourishing Rouman colony in the same region, and, though
                    Moschopolis has fallen a victim to the ravages of the wild Arnauts, a local
                    successor has sprung up in the rising town of Gjurtza. The Roumans make good
                    soldiers, as was seen at Plevna. In their customs and folk-lore both Latin and
                    Slavonic traditions assert themselves as in their language. Of their Roman
                    traditions the Trajan saga, the celebration of the Rosalia and Kalendae, the
                    belief in the “striga” (witch), the names of the months and days of the week,
                    may be taken as typical examples. Some Roman words connected with the Christian
                    religion, like biserica (basilica) = a church, botez=baptizo, duminica = Sunday,
                    preot (presbyter) = priest, point to a continuous tradition of the Illyrian
                    church, though most of their ecclesiastical terms, like their liturgy and
                    alphabet, were derived from the old Slovene. In most that concerns political
                    organization the Slavonic element is also preponderant, though there are words
                    like imparat=imperator, and domn = dominus, which point to the old stock. Many
                    words relating to kinship are also Latin, some like vitrig (vitricus) =
                    father-in-law being alone preserved by this branch of the Romance family.
                    Although of the actual vocabulary only about one-fifth is Latin, and two-fifths,
                    or about double the amount, Slavonic (see Cihac, <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire
                        d’ Étymologie Daco-Romaine),</hi> the greater proportion of the words in
                    common use is still Latin. Many words, however, of common and indispensable use,
                    those even connected with ideas nearest to the heart, as for instance the Rouman
                    iubesc = to love, and maica=a mother, are themselves of Slavonic origin. Alike
                    in the dwellings, customs, and costumes of the Vlach race we encounter at every
                    turn the dominating influence of the Slav peoples by whom they were surrounded.
                    This external influence, however, has not by any means affected the strong pride
                    of Roman origin which is the heirloom of all members of the Rouman race.
                    Hellenization itself, hitherto successful among the southern Roumans, has
                    received a check in the Pindus region, while north of the Danube the Rouman race
                    is continually gaining at the expense of its neighbours. A glance at the
                    ethnographic map of eastern Europe shows that the reconquest of Trajan’s Dacia
                    by the Latin race is already practically completed, and with the triumphant
                    progress of the principle of nationality in the Danubian lands the reunion of
                        <hi rend="italic">Dacia Romana</hi> under a single sceptre cannot long he
                    deferred. (A. J. E. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
