<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0055-0042-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VALLA, Lorenzo (c (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    42)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dj16">Stoics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133750">Stoics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882694">Creeds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n55/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VALLA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lorenzo (c</hi></label>.
                    1406-1457), one of the most salient personalities of the earlier Italian
                    Renaissance, was born at Rome, of parents derived from Piacenza, possibly in the
                    year 1406-07, or perhaps somewhat earlier. He was educated in the humanistic
                    schools of Rome, according to the customs of that age, learning grammar from
                    some humble dominie and afterwards attending the classes of eminent professors.
                    Valla mentions Leonardo of Arezzo as his chief master in Latin and Giovanni
                    Aurispa in Greek. He wished to establish himself as apostolic secretary in the
                    Eternal City. But for some reason or other this office was refused him. At the
                    age of twenty-four he went to Piacenza on family affairs, and from this city
                    proceeded to Pavia, where he obtained a professorship of eloquence. Like all the
                    scholars of that time, Valla wandered from university to university, accepting
                    short engagements and airing his talents as a lecturer in many cities. It
                    appears that he professed the New Learning in Milan and Genoa as well as Pavia.
                    Somewhere, and at some uncertain date during this period, he came into relations
                    with Alphonso of Aragon, who conquered the kingdom of Naples. Valla did not,
                    however, follow this prince’s fortunes in the early days of their acquaintance.
                    We find him once more in Rome in 1443 during the pontificate of Eugenius IV. At
                    this period of his career Valla won the highest reputation by his dialogue <hi
                        rend="italic">De Voluptate</hi> and his treatise on the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Elegances of the Latin Language.</hi> In the former work he contrasted the
                    principles of the Stoics with the tenets of Epicurus, openly proclaiming his
                    sympathy with those who claimed the right of free indulgence for man’s natural
                    and sensuous appetites. It was a remarkable utterance, since the paganism of the
                    Renaissance here found, for the first time, deliberate expression in a work of
                    scholarly and philosophical value. The <hi rend="italic">Elegantiae</hi> was no
                    less original, though in a different sphere of thought. This work subjected the
                    forms of Latin grammar, the rules of Latin style and rhetoric, to critical
                    investigation. It placed the practice of composition upon a foundation of
                    analysis and inductive reasoning. But there was a third essay composed by Valla
                    during the pontificate of Eugenius which displayed the same originality and a
                    like critical acumen. This bore the title of a <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the
                        Donation of Constantine·,</hi> and in it Valla proved that the claims
                    founded by the Roman see upon that supposed grant reposed on forged documents
                    and legendary fables. It was not published until 1440, when Valla had been
                    already three years resident at Alphonso’s court in Naples.</p>
                <p>There was every reason why the king of Naples should be interested in a man of
                    Valla’s stamp. He wished to attract scholars of the highest ability to his
                    capital, and he was always on bad terms with the papacy. Valla combined the
                    qualities of an elegant humanist, an acute critic, a freethinker, and a venomous
                    pamphleteer who had committed himself to a destructive polemic against the
                    temporalities of Rome. Accordingly the king made him his private secretary,
                    encouraged him to open a school of rhetoric in Naples, and defended him against
                    the attacks of friars and inquisitors. From Naples Valla continued his war of
                    pamphlets against the church. He proved that the letter of Christ to Abgarus was
                    a forgery, ridiculed the Latinity of the Vulgate, questioned the authenticity of
                    the Apostles’ Creed, and accused St Augustine of heresy. It is a singular note
                    of that period in Italy that, on the death of Eugenius IV., his successor,
                    Nicholas V., invited Valla to Rome, not to arraign him before the bar of the
                    Inquisition, not to punish him for his insolent criticism, but in order to
                    confer upon him the post of apostolic secretary, with substantial pecuniary
                    appointments. This entrance of Valla into the Roman curia has been justly called
                    “the triumph of humanism over orthodoxy and tradition.” Nicholas had no other
                    object than that of fixing one of the chief scholars of the age near his own
                    person. He allowed Valla to open a school of eloquence in Rome, and he paid him
                    munificently for translating Thucydides into Latin. Thus, for the sake of his
                    erudition and stylistic talents, the supreme pontiff rewarded a man whose chief
                    titles to fame are the stringent criticism with which he assailed the
                    temporalities of the church, and the frank candour with which he defended a
                    pagan theory of human conduct.</p>
                <p>All the biographical notices of Valla are loaded with long accounts of his
                    literary quarrels. Intolerant of rivalry, inordinately vain, and greedily
                    self-seeking as the scholars of that epoch were, they indulged in the fiercest
                    internecine warfare among themselves. The bulky folios of their works contain
                    hundreds of invectives which may be ranked among the most obscene, the most
                    wearisome, and the most disgraceful products of the human intellect. Valla won a
                    regrettable celebrity by the number and the virulence of his enmities.
                    Bartolomeo Fazio, Georgios Trapezuntios, and Poggio felt the stabbing sharpness
                    of his pen. It must, however, be admitted that these antagonists gave back quite
                    as good as they got. It is almost impossible to form a just estimate of Valla’s
                    private life and character through the dust-clouds of abuse and dirt which these
                    controversies stirred up around his memory. He died at Naples in the year 1457.
                    Posterity honours in him not so much the stylist and the scholar as the
                    initiator of a bold critical method, applied to language, historical documents,
                    and ethical opinions.</p>
                <p>The collected edition of Valla’s <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> is that of Basel,
                    1465. For detailed accounts of his life and work, consult Tiraboschi; Voigt’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Wiederbelebung des Alterthums</hi>; and Symonds’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Renaissance in Italy</hi> (vols. ii. and v.).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
