<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0067-0054-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VANBRUGH, Sir John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 54</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1176383">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:995592">Legends</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j62t">Legends</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nz3s">Hunting</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dn7s">Witnesses</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n67/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VANBRUGH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label> (1666
                    ?-1726), dramatist and architect, was the son of a wealthy sugar-baker in
                    Cheshire and grandson of a Protestant refugee of Ghent. From a passage in one of
                    his letters to Tonson it might be supposed that he was born in the Bastille,
                    though in what year is uncertain, probably in 1666. He was educated in France,
                    but what he learnt there, whether architecture or merely that art of
                    good-fellowship which he found to be the true Aladdin’s lamp of social life, is
                    a question that will be variously answered by those who, like Sir Joshua
                    Reynolds, admire Blenheim and Castle Howard, and those who, like the wits of
                    Vanbrugh’s time, scoff at them. This, however, is certain, that after his return
                    from the Continent to England what he did was, not to pursue architecture, but
                    to work, with a gusto and a success that are humorous and exhilarating, the
                    “Aladdin’s lamp” above mentioned. His first step towards becoming a power in
                    society was, of course, to enter the army. Perhaps, however, had he begun life
                    in any other way his advance would have been just as rapid. For, strong as are
                    social conditions, character is stronger still, and Vanbrugh’s equipment—wit,
                    tempered by good humour, a genuine feeling of comradeship, an exceedingly fine
                    presence (according to Noble’s description), and a winsome face (according to
                    Kneller <hi rend="smallcaps">’s</hi> portrait)—would, under any circumstances,
                    have been irresistible. One of the points of difference between the dialogue in
                    Vanbrugh’s comedies and the dialogue in the comedies of Congreve is this: we
                    feel that the characters in the <hi rend="italic">Relapse</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Confederacy</hi> talk as Vanbrugh must have talked; we feel that
                    the characters in the <hi rend="italic">Old Bachelor</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Way of the World</hi> talk, not as Congreve talked, but as
                    Congreve wrote. We feel that, while such dazzling sword-play as Congreve’s would
                    in society have chilled, even as it illumined the air, talk so hearty,
                    good-humoured, frank, and daring as that we get in Vanbrugh’s plays would have
                    made the fortune of any man of fashion, made it as certainly at a Roman supper
                    party in the time of Augustus as at a London drinking-bout in the days of <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n68/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0068-0055"/> Queen Anne. It is no wonder then that he was a
                    favourite, no wonder that the two best haters of the time, Swift and Pope, tried
                    in vain to hate the “man of wit and honour,” Vanbrugh. During the martial period
                    of his life, Vanbrugh wrote the first sketches of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Relapse</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Provoked Wife.</hi> These he showed to
                    Sir Thomas Skipworth, one of the shareholders of Drury Lane, and with fortunate
                    results.</p>
                <p>In 1695 he was offered—whether through the court interest which he had secured or
                    whether because he really had acquired a knowledge of architecture in France is
                    not known—the post of secretary to the commission for endowing Greenwich
                    Hospital. He accepted the post, and by way of fulfilling his functions as an
                    architect turned his attention to the amours of " Lord Foppington.” His <hi
                    rend="italic">Relapse or Virtue in Danger,</hi> a sequel to Colley Cibber’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Love’s Last Shift,</hi> was produced at Drury Lane in 1697. When a
                    comic dramatist of the school of Wycherley confesses that the fine gentleman of
                    his play, “drinking his mistresses’ health in Nantes brandy from six in the
                    morning to the time he waddled on upon the stage in the evening, had toasted
                    himself up to such a pitch of vigour” that something too outrageous even for
                    such an audience seemed imminent, we may assume that he has enjoyed a
                    satisfactory first night. The success was so triumphant that Montague,
                    afterwards Lord Halifax, asked at once for the <hi rend="italic">Provoked
                    Wife</hi> for the theatre in Lincoln’s Inn Fields, and—Skipworth waiving, for
                    the advantage of Vanbrugh, his own claim upon the play—it was produced at that
                    theatre in the following year. All that could be said in answer to those who
                    condemned it on account of its unblushing libertinism was that Sir John Brute is
                    sufficiently brutal to drive any woman into rebellion, and that since the
                    glorious days of the Restoration a wife’s rebellion and a wife’s adultery were
                    synonymous terms. The play was a complete triumph.</p>
                <p>And now, having succeeded as a man of fashion, as an architectural commissioner,
                    and as a comic dramatist of the school of Wycherley, Vanbrugh turned his
                    attention to morals. Though <hi rend="italic">Aesop—</hi> produced at Drury Lane
                    in the same year as the <hi rend="italic">Provoked Wife—</hi> was an adaptation
                    of Boursault’s dramatic sermon on the same subject, it was an improvement on the
                    French play. As usual with Vanbrugh, who never did things by halves, he
                    surpassed the Frenchman on that very point where the Frenchman had been
                    pronounced unsurpassable. Just as in the <hi rend="italic">Relapse,</hi> when he
                    aspired to be merry, his merriment had entirely surpassed that of Cibber’s play,
                    of which his own was meant to be a sequel, and just as afterwards, when in
                    Castle Howard and Blenheim he aspired to rival in massiveness the “thick
                    rotundity of the earth,” he laid on her a structure only a “few tons lighter
                    than herself,” so now, when he aspired to surpass the Frenchman in gravity, he
                    achieved a kind of dulness compared with which the owllike dulness of Boursault
                    was as the wit of Voltaire. In a word, the humour of the piece lies in the fact
                    that it was written by the author of the <hi rend="italic">Relapse</hi> and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Provoked Wife.</hi> The play ran during a week only. Vanbrugh,
                    accepting the failure with his usual good-temper, seems then to have turned his
                    attention completely to architecture; for the adaptation in 1700 of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pilgrim,</hi> of Beaumont and Fletcher, and the production in 1702
                    of <hi rend="italic">A False Friend,</hi> could hardly have engaged his serious
                    efforts at all, so perfunctory are they and so inferior to all that he had done
                    before.</p>
                <p>Castle Howard in Yorkshire, which he had built for the earl of Carlisle, was a
                    great success so far as pleasing his patron went, who as a reward gave him yet
                    another opening in life by presenting him,—the most ignorant man perhaps in
                    England of heraldry, judging from the fun he made of the appointment,—with the
                    tabard of Clarencieux king-at-arms. But, if the dangerous moment in every man’s
                    life is when he has just scored a brilliant success, it is especially so with
                    genial glowing natures like Vanbrugh’s. It seems to have been the success of
                    Castle Howard that caused him to entertain the rash project of building a
                    theatre, from his own design, for the acting of his own plays. The joyous
                    courage with which, having persuaded thirty people in the fashionable world to
                    aid him in finding the money, and Congreve to aid him in finding the plays, he
                    began to build in perfect unconsciousness of the danger before him is the only
                    passage in his life which may be called pathetic, save of course his struggle
                    with the “wicked woman of Marlborough.” No doubt any architect who builds a
                    theatre is always in danger of letting his ideas run riot in the wide field of
                    experiment, but he who builds a theatre for his own plays seems doomed by the
                    malice aforethought of fate. The magnitude of Vanbrugh’s architectural ideas
                    grew as the work went on, and with the ideas the structure grew till a theatre
                    meant for the delicate <hi rend="italic">bijouterie</hi> work of polite comedy
                    seemed growing to the proportions of the Roman Colosseum. Whether Congreve
                    endeavoured to put a check upon his friend’s architectural and authorial fervour
                    does not appear. But it must be remembered that not only Vanbrugh’s plays but
                    his own were to be acted there, and that, although Congreve was a man of great
                    sagacity, no man, not even he who pretended to set his gentility above his
                    genius, is sagacious when confronted by the surpassing excellence of his own
                    poems and plays.</p>
                <p>When at length the time came to test the acoustics of the pile, it was found to
                    be sadly defective. What changes were made to rectify the errors of structure
                    does not appear. The theatre was opened to the public with an Italian opera,
                    which was followed by three of Molière’s comedies, and these by the <hi
                    rend="italic">Confederacy,</hi> Vanbrugh’s masterpiece on the whole, though
                    perhaps its finest scenes are not equal to the finest scenes in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Relapse.</hi></p>
                <p>Vanbrugh at last withdrew from the disastrous speculation; Congreve had already
                    withdrawn. But a man to whom fortune had been so kind as she had been to
                    Vanbrugh could hardly be depressed by any of her passing frowns. Queen Anne at
                    once sent him abroad on an important state errand, and afterwards he was
                    commissioned to build Blenheim. Upon the merits and demerits of this famous
                    “hollowed quarry” there has been much conflict of opinion. As to the sarcasms by
                    Swift, Walpole, Evans, and the rest, they are as nothing when set against Sir
                    Joshua Reynolds’s defence of Vanbrugh and his style. For in England the general
                    sense for architecture seems to be even rarer than the general sense for poetry
                    and painting. The truth is that Vanbrugh imported largely into architecture what
                    in all the plastic arts should be allowed to fructify but sparsely, namely,
                    literary ideas, and even these literary ideas of his seem to lack that fusion
                    which we see in the works of the great masters. Hence, impressive as are the
                    parts, they do not form an impressive whole. Blenheim, however, was a source of
                    great sorrow to the kindly dramatist. Though Parliament had voted for the
                    building of it, no provision had been made for the supplies. The queen while she
                    lived paid them, and then Vanbrugh was left to the meanness of the duke of
                    Marlborough and afterwards to the insolence of the “wicked woman,” who did her
                    best to embitter his life. Besides Castle Howard and Blenheim, he built many
                    other country mansions, such as Grimsthorpe and Duncombe Hall in Yorkshire,
                    Eastbury in Dorsetshire, Seaton-Delaval in Northumberland, King’s Weston near
                    Bristol, Oulton Hall in Cheshire, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>About the end of 1710 Vanbrugh married Henrietta <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n69/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0069-0056"/> Maria, daughter of Colonel Yarborough of
                    Haslington, and four years afterwards, at the accession of George I., he was
                    knighted. He afterwards wrote again for the stage, and the unfinished fragment
                    left at his death, which took place on 26th March 1726 at his house in Scotland
                    Yard, London, shows that his powers remained to the last as fine as ever.</p>
                <p>In order to find and fix Vanbrugh’s place among English comic dramatists, an
                    examination of the very basis of the comedy of repartee inaugurated by Etheredge
                    would be necessary, and, of course, such an examination would be impossible
                    here. It is chiefly as a humorist, however, that he demands attention.</p>
                <p>Given the humorous temperament—the temperament which impels a man to get his
                    enjoyment by watching the harlequinade of life, and contrasting it with his own
                    ideal standard of good sense, which the harlequinade seems to him to mock and
                    challenge —given this temperament, then the quality of its humorous growths
                    depends of course on the quality of the intellectual forces by means of which
                    the temperament gains expression. Hence it is very likely that in original
                    endowment of humour, as distinguished from wit, Vanbrugh was superior to
                    Congreve. And this is saying a great deal: for, while Congreve’s wit has always
                    been made much of, it has, since Macaulay’s time, been the fashion among critics
                    to do less than justice to his humour,—a humour which, in such scenes as that in
                    <hi rend="italic">Love for Love</hi> where Sir Sampson Legend discourses upon
                    the human appetites and functions, moves beyond the humour of convention and
                    passes into natural humour. It is, however, in spontaneity, in a kind of lawless
                    merriment, almost Aristophanic in its <hi rend="italic">verve,</hi> that
                    Vanbrugh’s humour seems so deep and so fine, seems indeed to spring from a
                    fountain deeper and finer and rarer than Congreve’s. A comedy of wit, like every
                    other drama, is a story told by action and dialogue, but to tell a story lucidly
                    and rapidly by means of repartee is exceedingly difficult, not but that it is
                    easy enough to produce repartee. But in comic dialogue the difficulty is to move
                    rapidly and yet keep up the brilliant ball-throwing demanded in this form, and
                    without lucidity and rapidity no drama, whether of repartee or of character, can
                    live. Etheredge, the father of the comedy of repartee, has at length had justice
                    done to him by Mr Gosse. Not only could Etheredge tell a story by means of
                    repartee alone: he could produce a tableau too; so could Congreve, and so also
                    could Vanbrugh, but often—far too often—Vanbrugh’s tableau is reached, not by
                    fair means, as in the tableau of Congreve, but by a surrendering of probability,
                    by a sacrifice of artistic fusion, by an inartistic mingling of comedy and
                    farce, such as Congreve never indulges in. Jeremy Collier was perfectly right
                    therefore in his strictures upon the farcical improbabilities of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Relapse.</hi> So farcical indeed are the tableaux in that play
                    that the broader portions of it were (as Mr Swinburne discovered) adapted by
                    Voltaire and acted at Sceaux as a farce. Had we space here to contrast the <hi
                    rend="italic">Relapse</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Way of the World,</hi> we
                    should very likely come upon a distinction between comedy and farce such as has
                    never yet been drawn. We should find that farce is not comedy with a broadened
                    grin—Thalia with her girdle loose and run wild—as the critics seem to assume. We
                    should find that the difference between the two is not one of degree at all, but
                    rather one of kind, and that mere breadth of fun has nothing to do with the
                    question. No doubt the fun of comedy may be as broad as that of farce, as is
                    shown indeed by the celebrated Dogberry scenes in <hi rend="italic">Much Ado
                    about Nothing</hi> and by the scene in <hi rend="italic">Love for Love</hi>
                    between Sir Sampson Legend and his son, alluded to above; but here, as in every
                    other department of art, all depends upon the quality of the imaginative belief
                    that the artist seeks to arrest and secure. Of comedy the breath of life is
                    dramatic illusion. Of farce the breath of life is mock illusion. Comedy, whether
                    broad or genteel, pretends that its mimicry is real. Farce, whether broad or
                    genteel, makes no such pretence, but by a thousand tricks, which it keeps up
                    between itself and the audience, says, "My acting is all sham, and you know it.”
                    Now, while Vanbrugh was apt too often to forget this the fundamental difference
                    between comedy and farce, Congreve never forgot it, Wycherley rarely. Not that
                    there should be in any literary form any arbitrary laws. There is no arbitrary
                    law declaring that comedy shall not be mingled with farce, and yet the fact is
                    that in vital drama they cannot be so mingled. The very laws of their existence
                    are in conflict with each other, so much so that where one lives the other must
                    die, as we see in the drama of our own day. The fact seems to be that
                    probability of incident, logical sequence of cause and effect, are as necessary
                    to comedy as they are to tragedy, while farce would stifle in such an air.
                    Rather it would be poisoned by it, just as comedy is poisoned by what farce
                    flourishes on, that is to say, inconsequence of reasoning— topsy-turvy logic.
                    Born in the fairy country of topsy-turvy, the logic of farce would be illogical
                    if it were not upside-down. So with coincidence, with improbable accumulation of
                    convenient events,— farce can no more exist without these than comedy can exist
                    with them. Hence we affirm that Jeremy Collier’s strictures on the farcical
                    adulterations of the <hi rend="italic">Relapse</hi> pierce more deeply into
                    Vanbrugh’s art than do the criticisms of Leigh Hunt and Hazlitt. In other words,
                    perhaps the same lack of fusion which mars Vanbrugh’s architectural ideas mars
                    also his comedy. (T. W. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
