<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0304-0281-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VOLHYNIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 281</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n304/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VOLHYNIA</label>, a government of south-western Russia,
                    bounded by the Polish provinces of Lublin and Siedlce on the W., Grodno and
                    Minsk on the N., Kieff on the E., and Podolia and Galicia (Austria) on the S.,
                    has an area of 27,731 square miles. A broad and flat spur of the Carpathians—the
                    Avratynsk plateau—which enters from the west and spreads eastward towards the
                    Dnieper, occupies its southern portion, reaching a maximum elevation of 1200
                    feet; another branch of the Carpathians in the west of the government ranges
                    between 700 and 900 feet at its highest points. Both are deeply grooved in some
                    places, and the crags give a hilly aspect to the districts where they occur. The
                    remainder of the government, which is quite flat, with an imperceptible slope
                    towards the marshes of Pinsk, is known as the Polyesie (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Minsk).</hi> It is covered by impassable marshes (sometimes as much as 400
                    square miles in extent), sparsely interspersed with forests and traversed by
                    languid streams, with low, almost inaccessible banks, here and there diversified
                    by sandy dunes. The drainage of the Polyesie is, however, being vigorously
                    carried on, and large tracts of meadow land have already been reclaimed by
                    extensive operations recently undertaken by Government. Among the marshes are
                    many small lakes. Volhynia is copiously watered by a number of comparatively
                    unimportant rivers which rise in the Avratynsk Hills and flow northwards towards
                    the Dnieper; the Pripet with the Turia, the Styr, the Goryn, the Slutch, and
                    other smaller tributaries of the Dnieper are navigable by small boats, and
                    considerable quantities of timber and firewood are floated. By the western Bug,
                    which separates Volhynia from Poland, timber is floated and corn and various
                    goods shipped to Prussia.</p>
                <p>The geological formation of Volhynia is very simple. The Avratynsk Hills,
                    consisting of granite and various crystalline rocks, are covered with the Chalk,
                    above which in turn are Tertiary sandstones, sands, and clays containing
                    lignite. The whole is covered by Glacial deposits and Lacustrine clays, reaching
                    a great thickness in the north. Kaolin, pottery clay, and iron ore are the chief
                    mineral products; amber also is occasionally found in the Tertiary-sands. The
                    climate of Volhynia, notwithstanding the influence of its marshes, is much
                    milder than that of central Russia within the same latitudes. The vegetation on
                    the southern slopes of the Avratynsk Hills begins to show something of a
                    West-European character; oaks, maples, and limes prevail, while on the northern
                    slope there are immense forests of Scotch fir. The forests cover more than
                    one-third of the entire area, and it is reckoned that 2,500,000 acres yield
                    timber for building purposes.</p>
                <p>The population of Volhynia in 1884 was 2,096,475, of whom nearly four-fifths were
                    Little Russians (from 70 to 91 per cent. in various districts); there were
                    30,000 White Russians and some 10,000 Great Russians. Next in importance to the
                    Russians come the Jews, who numbered about 12 per cent. of the population. The
                    Poles are variously estimated at from 120,000 to 170,000, but are certainly
                    under 7 per cent. of the total population. The Germans number about 30,000.
                    Agriculture cannot be said to flourish except on the Avratynsk plateau and its
                    slopes, but is still the chief occupation, and more than one-third of the area
                    is under crops. The fertile soil of the south produces a surplusage of corn,
                    which is either used in distilleries or exported; the average crops from 1883 to
                    1885 were 1,606,000 quarters of rye, 550,000 of wheat, 1,145,000 of oats,
                    394,000 of barley, and 1,032,000 of potatoes. Hay is exported, but
                    cattle-breeding has been almost stationary since 1850. In 1883 there were
                    506,500 horses, 655,050 cattle, and 571,500 sheep. Wool is exported. Beet is
                    largely grown for sugar (38,000 acres, producing 4,800,000 cwts., having been
                    under this crop in 1885). The culture of tobacco is rapidly extending (7000
                    tobacco plantations yielding about 8000 cwts. of tobacco in 1885). In the
                    Polyesie the principal occupations are connected with the export of timber and
                    firewood, the preparation of pitch, tar, potash, and various wooden wares, and
                    boat-building. The wild boar, bear, fox, and hare are hunted.</p>
                <p>The manufactures in 1884 yielded 18,884,000 roubles, as against only 2,856,000 in
                    1860. The goods principally produced are sugar, spirits, woollen cloth, paper,
                    china, and metal wares. Wool, corn, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n305/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0305-0282"/> hides, and tallow are partly manufactured within
                    the government, and partly exported to Riga and Poland. Volhynia is traversed by
                    a railway from Kieff <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Berditcheff to Brest-Litovsk,
                    with branches to Lublin and to Lemberg. The traffic by this line is
                    considerable, and the Radziviloff custom-house, on the Austrian frontier, is one
                    of the most important in Russia.</p>
                <p>Volhynia is divided into twelve districts, the chief towns of which are <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Zhitomir (</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> q.v.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">),</hi> which had 54,830 inhabitants in 1884, Dubno(7255),
                    Kovel (13,980), Kremenets (10,560), Lutsk (13,770), Novgrad Volhynskiy (13,590),
                    Ostrog (16,520), Ovrutch (6480), Radziviloff (7350), Kovno (7300),
                    Staro-Konstantinoff (17,980), and Zasłavl (10,120).</p>
                <p>Volhynia has been inhabited by Slavonians from a remote antiquity. In Nestor’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> its people are mentioned under the name of Dulebs,
                    and later in the 12th century they were known as Velhynians and Buzhans
                    (dwellers on the Bug). From the 9th century the towns of Volhynia—Vladimir,
                    Ovrutch, Lutsk, and Dubno—were ruled by descendants of Rurik, and the land of
                    Volhynia remained independent until the 14th century, when it fell under
                    Lithuania. In 1659 it was annexed to Poland, and so remained until 1795, when it
                    was taken possession of by Russia.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
