<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0212-0193-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VESTA (9th edition, volume 24, page 193)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921717">Fasting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1165681">Vestals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205669">Jordan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mh6r">Fasting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v97zz7m">Palladium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n212/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VESTA</label> (Greek Ғ <hi rend="italic">εστία</hi>), the
                    goddess of fire and the domestic hearth. The cults of the Greek Hestia and the
                    Latin Vesta, both of which involved the guardianship of an ever-burning sacred
                    fire, are most probably derived from a very early custom, common to a great
                    variety of races, and practised during many different ages. Among people in a
                    primitive state of development the production of fire is a slow and very
                    laborious process; thus it became the custom for each village to maintain a
                    constant fire for the general use of the community, in order to avoid the
                    troublesome necessity of obtaining a spark by friction in case of the accidental
                    extinction at one time of all the village fires.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Mr J. G. Frazer, in an interesting paper
                            printed in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Philology</hi> (vol. xiv.
                            pp. 145-172), on “the Worship of Vesta and its Connexion with the Greek
                            Prytaneum,” has given many examples of a similar custom still surviving
                            among various savage races.</p></note> This fire, the central hearth or
                    Ғ <hi rend="italic">εστία</hi> of the village (<hi rend="italic">focus
                        publicus),</hi> became a sacred symbol of home and family life, and by
                    degrees grew into a religious cult of great sanctity and importance. The form of
                    the primitive house in which the fire was preserved, probably a round hut made
                    of wattled osiers daubed with clay, appears to have survived both in the
                    circular prytaneum of the Greeks and in the Aedes Vestae in Rome. To watch this
                    fire would naturally be the duty of women, and especially of those who were not
                    burdened with the cares of maternity, and hence may have arisen the Roman order
                    of virgin priestesses, whose chief duty it was to tend the sacred fire. A
                    survival of the prehistoric method of getting a spark appears to have existed in
                    the rule which enacted that, if ever the sacred fire of Vesta did go out, the
                    negligent vestal was to be punished by scourging (Livy, xxviii. 11), and the
                    fire rekindled either by friction of dry sticks<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>An allusion to the earliest method of
                            obtaining fire by rubbing two sticks together is probably contained in
                            the myth of Prometheus, who brought fire to mortals hidden in a hollow
                            wand.</p></note> or, in later times, by the sun’s rays brought to a
                    focus by a concave mirror (Plut., <hi rend="italic">Numa,</hi> 9). In the
                    prytaneum, which existed in every Greek state, a different form of cult was
                    developed, though the essential point, the sacred fire, was kept up, just as in
                    the Latin worship of Vesta; and in both cases the fire was extinguished annually
                    at the beginning of the new year, and solemnly rekindled by one of the primitive
                    and hence sacred methods.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Fire obtained in this way, that is “pure elemental fire,” was
                            commonly thought to possess a special sanctity. Even throughout the
                            Middle Ages in Catholic countries, at Easter, when the new year began,
                            the old pagan rite still survived. On Holy Saturday all lamps in each
                            church were extinguished, and the Paschal candlestick was lighted by the
                            help of flint and steel. From this sacred source the other lights in the
                            church were kindled, and the various households in the parish took a
                            flame to relight their fires and lamps, all of which had been carefully
                            extinguished beforehand.</p></note> In Rome this was done on the first
                    day of March, the Latin New Year’s Day (Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Fast.,</hi> iii.
                    137-145). Both among Greek and early Latin races, at the founding of a new
                    colony fire was solemnly sent from the prytaneum or Vesta temple of the mother
                    colony to kindle a similar sacred fire in the new settlement. Thus we find that,
                    according to tradition, the worship of Vesta in Rome was introduced from Alba
                    Longa (Liv., i. 20, and Ov., <hi rend="italic">Fast.,</hi> iii. 46), which
                    appears to have been the oldest of the Latin colonies in Latium. This intimate
                    connexion between the Greek prytaneum fire, sacred to Hestia, and that of Vesta
                    in Rome has been ably worked out by Mr J. G. Frazer in the paper quoted above.
                    The most generally received Latin legend attributes the founding of the Roman
                    temple of Vesta to Numa, who transferred the centre of the cult from Alba,
                    together with the four vestal virgins, its priestesses (Plut., <hi rend="italic"
                        >Numa,</hi> 10). One of the later kings, either Tarquin I. or Servius
                    Tullius, is said to have increased the number to six (Dion. Hal., iii. 67, and
                    Plut., <hi rend="italic">Numa,</hi> 10), and it is not till the last years of
                    the pagan period that we hear of a seventh vestal having been added (see
                    Ambrose, <hi rend="italic">Epis.,</hi> ed. Pareus, p. 477; also Plut., <hi
                        rend="italic">Rom.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cam.).</hi></p>
                <p>The election <hi rend="italic">(captio)</hi> of the vestal during the early
                    period of Rome was in the hands of the king, and in those of the pontifex
                    maximus under the republic and empire,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>From the time of Augustus the emperors themselves held
                            the office of chief pontiff, and with it the privilege of electing the
                            vestals.</p></note> subject, however, to the following conditions (Aul.
                    Gell., i. 12) ;—(1) the candidate was to be more than six and less than ten
                    years of age; (2) she was to be <hi rend="italic">patrima</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">matrima, i.e.,</hi> having both parents alive; (3) free from
                    physical or mental defects; (4) daughter of a freeborn resident in Italy.
                    Certain details of the election were arranged subject to the provisions of the
                    Lex Papia, now unknown. The selected child had her hair cut off, and was
                    solemnly admitted by the pontifex maximus, who held her by the hand, and,
                    addressing her by the name <hi rend="italic">amata,</hi> pronounced an ancient
                    formula of initiation, which is given by A. Gellius in his interesting chapter
                    on the subject (i. 12). In early times there were certain rules by which girls
                    could be excused from serving as vestals, but the honour soon became so eagerly
                    sought that these provisions were practically useless. Vows were taken by the
                    vestal for a limited period of thirty years, after which she was free to return
                    to private life and even to marry— a thing very rarely done (Aul. Gell., vi. 7).
                    This period of thirty years was divided into three decades: during the first the
                    vestal learnt her duties; during the second she practised them; and during the
                    third she instructed the young vestals. The special dignity of chief of the
                    vestals, or <hi rend="italic">virgo vestalis maxima,</hi> was reached in order
                    of seniority. The inscriptions on the pedestals of statues of various <hi
                        rend="italic">vestales maximae</hi> show that a number of different grades
                    of honour were passed through before reaching the <hi rend="italic">maximatus
                        or</hi> highest dignity.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>These inscriptions are printed in Middleton, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ancient Rome in 1885,</hi> pp. 200-6, and in <hi
                                rend="italic">Archaeologia,</hi> vol. xlix. pp. 414-422.</p></note>
                    The duties of the vestals, besides the chief one of tending the holy fire (Cic.,
                        <hi rend="italic">De Leg.,</hi> ii. 8), consisted in the daily bringing of
                    water from the sacred spring of Egeria, near the Porta Capena, to be used for
                    the ceremonial sweeping and sprinkling of the Aedes Vestae.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The shrine of Vesta was not a <hi
                                rend="italic">templum</hi> in the strict Roman sense, as it was not
                            consecrated by the augurs, its sanctity being far above the necessity of
                            any such ceremony. Other natural springs might be used for the daily
                            sprinkling, but it was forbidden to use water brought in a pipe or other
                            artificial conduit (Tac., <hi rend="italic">Hist.,</hi> iv. 53; see also
                            Guhl and Koner, <hi rend="italic">Vit. Gr. et Rom.,</hi> p.
                        654).</p></note> They also offered sacrifices of salt cakes— <hi
                        rend="italic">muries</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mola salsa—</hi> and poured
                    on the altar of sacred fire libations of wine and oil, as is represented on the
                    reverses of several first brasses and medallions of the empire (see fig. 1). The
                    vestals were bound to offer daily prayers for the welfare of the Roman state,
                    and more especially in times of danger or calamity (Cic., <hi rend="italic">Pro
                        Font.,</hi> 21). They were also the guardians of the seven sacred objects on
                    which the stability of the Roman power was supposed to depend:<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Cancellieri, <hi
                                rend="italic">Le Sette Cose Fatali di Roma Antica,</hi> Rome,
                            1812.</p></note> the chief of these was the Palladium, a rude archaic
                    statue of Pallas, which was said to have been brought by Aeneas from the burning
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n213/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0213-0194"/> Troy. This sacred object was never shown to
                    profane eyes, but it is represented on the reverse of a coin struck by Antoninus
                    Pius in honour of his deified wife Faustina</p>
                <p>(see fig. 1). Strict observance of the vow of chastity was one of the chief
                    obligations of the vestals, and its breach was horribly punished by burial alive
                    at a place near the Porta Collina known as the Campus Sceleratus (see Livy,
                    viii. 15 and 89; Plin., <hi rend="italic">Ep.,</hi> iv. 11; and Suet., <hi
                        rend="italic">Dom.,</hi> 8). Cases of unchastity and its punishment were
                    rare; and, as the evidence against the vestal was usually that of slaves, given
                    under torture, it is probable that in many instances an innocent vestal suffered
                    this cruel death. The case described by the younger Pliny (<hi rend="italic"
                        >sup. cit.)</hi> is one of special pathos, as the vestal appears to have
                    been condemned without any sufficient evidence, simply at the wish of the
                    emperor Domitian. A fanciful reason for this fearful punishment is given by
                    Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Fast,</hi> vi. 459-460.</p>
                <p>The privileges of the vestals and their influential position were very
                    remarkable. They were exempt from any <hi rend="italic">patria potestas,</hi>
                    except that of the pontifex maximus, their religious father; they could dispose
                    by will of their property, and were in most respects not subject to the Roman
                    laws (“legibus non tenetur,” Servius, on Virg., <hi rend="italic">Aen.,</hi> xi.
                    204; <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> Gaius, i. 130, and Dion Cass., lvi. 10). This
                    involved freedom from taxes, and the right to drive through the streets of Rome
                    in carriages <hi rend="italic">{plostrum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">currus
                        arcuatus).</hi> Some bronze plates have been found which were once attached
                    to the carriages of vestals; the inscription on one of them runs thus, <hi
                        rend="italic">Flaviae Publiciae v.v. maximae inmunis in jugo</hi> (see <hi
                        rend="italic">C. I. L.,</hi> vi. 2146-2148; <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> also
                    Pruden., <hi rend="italic">Contr. Symm.,</hi> ii. 1088). They were preceded by a
                    lictor when appearing on state occasions, and enjoyed other semi-royal honours
                    (Plut., <hi rend="italic">Numa,</hi> 10, and Dion Cass., xlvii. 19). At theatres
                    and other places of amusement they enjoyed the best seats, except at some of the
                    nude athletic contests, from which they were excluded; they also took an
                    important part in all the grand religious and state ceremonies, such as when the
                    pontifex maximus offered sacrifice on the occasion of a triumph before the
                    temple of Capitoline Jupiter. They had power to pardon any criminal they met in
                    the street on his way to execution, provided that the meeting were accidental.
                    The vestals alone shared with the emperors the privilege of intramural burial
                    (Serv., <hi rend="italic">Ad Aen.,</hi> xi. 206). During life they were richly
                    dowered by the state (Suet., <hi rend="italic">Aug.,</hi> 31) and had public
                    slaves appointed to serve them (see Tac., <hi rend="italic">Hist.,</hi> i. 43).
                    They were also the guardians of the emperor’s will, and of other important
                    documents of state (Suet., <hi rend="italic">J. Caes.,</hi> 83, and <hi
                        rend="italic">Aug.,</hi> 101; Tac., <hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi> i. 8;
                    Plut., <hi rend="italic">Anton.,</hi> 58; and Appian, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Civ.,</hi> v <hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi> 73). Their influence in the
                    appointment to many offices, both religious and secular, appears to have been
                    very great. Many of the statues to the chief vestals which were found in the
                    Atrium Vestae in 1883-84 have pedestals inscribed with a dedication recording
                    that benefits had been conferred on the donor by the vestalis maxima. Lastly,
                    they lived in a style of very great splendour: their house,<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For a description of this, and also of
                            the temple of Vesta and its vicissitudes, see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Rome,</hi> vol. xix. pp. 818-819; Middleton, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Aneient Rome in 1885,</hi> pp. 181-206; and a paper by the same
                            author in <hi rend="italic">Archaeologia,</hi> vol. xlix. p. 391 <hi
                                rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note> the Atrium</p>
                <p>Vestae, which stood close by the Aedes Vestae, was very large and exceptionally
                    magnificent both in decoration and material. The discovery already mentioned of
                    a number of statues of vestales maximae has thrown new light on the dress of the
                        vestals.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>These
                            statues appear to have been the work of a privileged class of sculptors,
                            who enjoyed the title of “fictores virginum vestalium,”— an honour which
                            is recorded in some of the dedicatory inscriptions on the
                        pedestals.</p></note> With one or two exceptions the costume of these
                    statues is much the same: they have a long sleeveless tunic or <hi rend="italic"
                        >stola,</hi> girdled by the <hi rend="italic">zona</hi> immediately below
                    the breast. One only wears the <hi rend="italic">diploidion</hi> over the upper
                    part of her figure. The outer garment is an ample <hi rend="italic"
                        >pallium,</hi> wrapped round the body in a great variety of folds, and in
                    some cases brought over the head like a hood. All seem to have long hair,
                    showing that the process of cutting off the hair at initiation was not repeated.
                    One figure (see fig. 2) wears the <hi rend="italic">suffibulum,</hi> a
                    rectangular piece of white cloth bordered by a purple stripe, worn over the head
                    and fastened on the breast by a <hi rend="italic">fibula.</hi><note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The form of the <hi
                                rend="italic">suffibulum</hi> as shown on this statue has a curious
                            similarity to the amice worn by the mediaeval clergy.</p></note></p>
                <p>According to Festus (ed. Müller, p. 348), this sacred garment was worn by the
                    vestals only during the act of sacrificing (see also Varro, <hi rend="italic">De
                        Ling. Lat.,</hi> vi. 21). This is probably the only existing statue on which
                    this rare garment is represented. In all cases the head is closely bound by <hi
                        rend="italic">vittae,</hi> rope-like twists of woollen cloth, the ends of
                    which usually fall in loops on each shoulder (see Servius, <hi rend="italic">Ad
                        Aen., X. 538).</hi></p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Regia,</hi> or official <hi rend="italic">fanum</hi> of the
                    pontifex maximus, was adjacent to the vestal’s house: —</p>
                <p>“Hic locus est Vestae, qui Pallada servat et ignem;</p>
                <p>Hic fuit antiqui Regia parva Numae."<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>Ov., <hi rend="italic">Tris.,</hi> iii. 29. For the
                            history of the Regia and its existing remains, see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Rome,</hi> vol. xix. p. 819, and <hi rend="italic"
                                >Archaeologia,</hi> vol. xlix. p. 398 <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>When Augustus, after his election to the office of pontifex maximus in 12 B.c.,
                    moved his place of residence from the Regia to the Palatine, he built a new
                    Aedes Vestae near his palace, in the magnificent Area Apollinis. This appears to
                    have been a copy of the older temple of Vesta. No traces of it now exist; but
                    Pirro Ligorio, in the latter part of the 16th century, made some sketches of
                    what then existed of this second temple, to illustrate his great MS. on Roman
                    antiquities, which is now preserved in the royal library at Turin (see Ovid, <hi
                        rend="italic">Fast.,</hi> iv. 949-954, and <hi rend="italic">Metam.,</hi>
                    XV. 864). The original course of the Sacra Via was supposed to have passed close
                    to the temple of Vesta; but excavations made in 1886 have shown that this was
                    not <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n214/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0214-0195"/> the case, the supposed line of the road being
                    really blocked by a very early structure. There is reason to believe that this
                    formed part of the original Regia, which was rebuilt during the reign of
                    Augustus in a more magnificent way by Domitius Calvinus, after his Spanish
                    triumph.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Vestalia,</hi> or chief festival in honour of Vesta, was
                    held on 9th June (Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Fast.,</hi> vi. 249), after which the
                    temple was closed for five days for a ceremonial cleansing.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The solemn decade of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Vestalia</hi> began on 5th June and ended on the 15th,
                            when the temple was closed.</p></note> In private houses the feast was
                    celebrated by a meal of fish, bread, and herbs, eaten, not on the usual
                    triclinium, but by the domestic hearth, in front of the effigies of the Dii
                    Penates (Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Fast.,</hi> vi. 309-310). The feast inaugurated
                    by Augustus in honour of Vesta Palatina was held on 28th April, the anniversary
                    of its consecration.</p>
                <p>With regard to statues of the goddess, though the Greek Hestia was frequently
                    represented in plastic art, yet among the Romans Vesta appears to have been
                    rarely so treated. The Athenian prytaneum contained a statue of Hestia. But
                    there was no effigy in the Roman temple of Vesta, although one is commonly shown
                    on reverses of coins which have a representation of the temple, and it appears
                    to have been commonly thought in Rome that a statue of Vesta did exist inside
                    her shrine,—a mistake which Ovid corrects <hi rend="italic">(Fast.,</hi> vi.
                    297-300). No Roman statue now known can be certainly considered to represent
                    Vesta, though a very beautiful standing figure of a female with veiled head (in
                    the Torlonia collection) has, with some probability, had this name given to
                    it.</p>
                <p>The worship of Vesta appears to have died out slowly in the 4th century, after
                    the adoption of Christianity as the state religion by Constantine. Zosimus (<hi
                        rend="italic">Hist. Nov.,</hi> V. 38) tells an interesting story of a visit
                    made to the Atrium Vestae at the end of the 4th century by Serena, the wife of
                    the Vandal Stilicho, who took a valuable necklace from one of the statues, in
                    spite of the remonstrances of an aged woman, the last survivor of the vestal
                    virgins. Soon after that time the building appears to have fallen into decay,
                    its valuable marble linings and other ornaments having been stripped from its
                    walls.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> For further information the reader is
                    referred, in addition to the works quoted above, to Lipsius, <hi rend="italic"
                        >De Vesta et Vestalibus Syntagma,</hi> printed in Graevius, <hi
                        rend="italic">Thes. Ant. Rom.,</hi> vol. v.; Cramer, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kleine Schriften,</hi> ed. by Ratjen, Leipsic, 1837, p. 89 <hi
                        rend="italic">sq.;</hi> Klausen, <hi rend="italic">Aeneas und die
                        Penaten,</hi> ii. p. 624 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; Nardini, <hi
                        rend="italic">Roma Antica,</hi> ed. of 1818-20, ii. p. 185 <hi rend="italic"
                        >sq.</hi>; Brohm, <hi rend="italic">De Jure Virginum Vestalium,</hi> Thorn,
                    1835; Preuner, <hi rend="italic">Hestia-Vesta,</hi> Tübingen, 1864; Jordan, <hi
                        rend="italic">Vesta und die Laren,</hi> Berlin, 1865, and more recent
                    papers; Maes, <hi rend="italic">Vesta e Vestali,</hi> Rome, 1883; Lanciani, <hi
                        rend="italic">L' Atrio di Vesta,</hi> Rome, 1884; and <hi rend="italic">C.
                        I. L.,</hi> vi. p. 594, No. 2131 <hi rend="italic">sq. (</hi> J <hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi> H. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
