<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0045-0032-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VALDES, Juan de (c (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    32)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68c45">Trinitarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n45/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VALDES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Juan de (c</hi></label>.
                    1500-1541), Spanish religious writer, born about 1500 at Cuenca in Castile, was
                    the younger of twin sons of Fernando de Valdes, hereditary regidor of Cuenca.
                    Juan has often been confounded with his twin-brother Alphonso, who was in the
                    suite of Charles V. in 1520, acted as his Latin secretary from 1524, and died in
                    1532 at Vienna. It has been conjectured that Juan studied at the university of
                    Alcala. We first meet him as the anonymous author of a politico-religious <hi
                        rend="italic">Diálogo de Mercurio y Caron,</hi> apparently written in 1528
                    and published then or soon after. As this <hi rend="italic">Diálogo</hi>
                    reflected strongly on the corruptions of the Roman Church, Valdes got into
                    difficulties with the Spanish Inquisition, and left Spain for Naples in 1530. He
                    removed in 1531 to Rome. On 12th January 1533 he writes from Bologna, where he
                    was in attendance upon the pope, Clement VII.; his criticisms of papal policy
                    had been condoned, inasmuch as in his <hi rend="italic">Dialogo</hi> he had
                    defended the validity of the marriage of Catherine of Aragon to Henry VIII. But
                    in the autumn of 1533 he returned to Naples, and seems never to have left it
                    again. His name has been Italianized into Valdesso and Val d’Esso. It has
                    frequently been asserted that he was appointed by Charles V. as secretary to the
                    viceroy at Naples, Don Pedro de Toledo; but of this there is no evidence, and it
                    seems a “harmonizing” conjecture, based on the confusion between Alphonso and
                    Juan. Curione (writing in 1544) calls him “cavalliere di Cesare,” but there is
                    no proof of his having ever held an official appointment. At his house on the
                    Chiaja he was the centre of a very distinguished circle, literary and religious,
                    and the influence of his conversations and his writings, chiefly circulated in
                    manuscript, stimulated the desire for a spiritual reformation of the church. The
                    first-fruit of his cultured leisure at Naples was a philological treatise, <hi
                        rend="italic">Dialogo de la Lengua</hi> (written 1533); but, though his
                    friends urged him to seek distinction by his humanistic studies, his bent was
                    towards the spiritual problems of Biblical interpretation and the deep things of
                    the devout life. Vermigli (Peter Martyr) and Marcantonio Flaminio were leading
                    spirits in the coterie of Valdes, which included Vittoria Colonna and her
                    sister-in-law Giulia Gonzaga. On Ochino, whom he furnished with themes for
                    sermons, his influence was very great. Carnesecchi, who had known Valdes at Rome
                    as “a modest and wellbred courtier,” found him at Naples in 1540 “wholly intent
                    upon the study of Holy Scripture,” portions of which he translated from the
                    Hebrew and Greek into Spanish, with comments and suggestive prefaces. To his
                    teaching Carnesecchi ascribes his own complete adoption of the Evangelical
                    doctrine of justification by faith, and at the same time his estrangement from
                    the policy of the Lutheran schism. Valdes died at Naples in May 1541.</p>
                <p>The death of Valdes scattered his band of associates. Ochino and Vermigli
                    abandoned the hope of a regenerated Catholicism, and left Italy. By degrees some
                    of Valdes’s writings were translated into Italian and published. They exhibit
                    great originality and penetration, combined with a delicate vein of
                    semi-mystical spirituality, and retain a large measure of that personal charm
                    which is attributed to their author in all contemporary notices. Llorente finds
                    traces in Valdes of the influence of Tauler’s writings; any such influence must
                    have been at second hand. Valdes was in relations with Fra Benedetto of Mantua,
                    the anonymous author of <hi rend="italic">Del Benefizio di Gesù Cristo
                        Crocefisso,</hi> which was revised by Flaminio (reprinted by Dr Babington,
                    Cambridge, 1855). The suggestion that Valdes was unsound on the doctrine of the
                    Trinity was first made in 1567 by the Transylvanian bishop, Francis David (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Socinus,</hi> vol. xxii. p. 230); it has been adopted
                    by Sand (1684), Wallace (1850), and other anti-Trinitarian writers, and is
                    countenanced by Bayle. Some colour has been given to this view by isolated
                    expressions in his writings, and by the subsequent course of Ochino, whose
                    orthodoxy seems, however, to have been unjustly suspected, from the speculative
                    insight with which he presented objections. But Valdes, though he never treats
                    of the Trinity, even when commenting upon Matt. xxviii. 19, reserving it in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Latte Spirituale</hi> as a topic for advanced Christians,
                    explicitly affirms the consubstantiality of the Son, whom he unites in
                    doxologies with the Father and the Holy Spirit <hi rend="italic">(Opusc.,</hi>
                    p. 145). His interest centred in matters of practical rather than of speculative
                    theology: his great aim was the promotion of a healthy and personal piety.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of his writings.</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Dialogo de Mercurio y Caron,</hi> 8vo (no date or place of
                    printing; 1528 ?). An Italian translation, by Nicolo Franco, was printed at
                    Venice without date, and reprinted at the same place in 1545. Both with the
                    original and the translation is generally found a <hi rend="italic">Dialogo</hi>
                    on the sack of Rome in 1527, by Alphonso de Valdes, printed at the same time.
                    Both are ascribed to Juan in the reprint <hi rend="italic">Dos Dialogos</hi> of
                    1850. (2) <hi rend="italic">Diálogo de la Lengua,</hi> written in 1533, first
                    printed at Madrid, 1737, reprinted 1860 and 1873. (3) <hi rend="italic">Quai
                        Maniera si devrebbe tenere a informare . . . gli Figliuoli de Christiani
                        delle Cose della Religione</hi> (no date or place of printing; before 1545,
                    as it was made use of by the Italian translator of Calvin’s catechism, 1545). No
                    Spanish original is known. It was reproduced as <hi rend="italic">Latte
                        Spirituale,</hi> Basel, 1549, and Paris, 1550. A Latin version, by
                    Pier-paolo Vergerio, was published in 1554 and again in 1557; it has been
                    translated into German twice, into Polish, into English by J. T. Betts, 1882,
                    and into Spanish by Ed. Boehmer, in <hi rend="italic">Revista Cristiana,</hi>
                    Madrid, February 1882 (also separately published). (4) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Trataditos,</hi> first published at Bonn, 1881, from a manuscript in the
                    Palatine Library <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n46/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0046-0033"/> at Vienna. An Italian translation, <hi
                        rend="italic">1 Cinque Tratatelli Evangelici,</hi> was published at Rome,
                    1545, reprinted 1869. An English translation, by J. T. Betts, is in <hi
                        rend="italic">XVII. Opuscules,</hi> 1882. (5) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Alfabeto</hi><hi rend="italic">Christiano,</hi> Venice, 1545, an Italian
                    translation of an unpublished and lost Spanish original. An English version, by
                    B. B. Wiffen, was published in 1861. (6) <hi rend="italic">Çiento i Diez
                        Conçideraçiones;</hi> the ori ginal is said to have been published, and all
                    copies suppressed by the Spanish Inquisition; thirty-nine of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Conçideraçiones</hi> were published with the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Trataditos</hi> from a Vienna manuscript. An Italian translation, by Celio
                    Secondo Curione, <hi rend="italic">Le Cento et Dieci Divine Considerationi,</hi>
                    was published at Basel, 1550, 8vo. A French translation, by Claude de
                    Kerquifinen, was published at Lyons, 1563, 8vo, and Paris, 1565, 8vo. The
                    English translation by Nicholas Ferrar was published at Oxford, 1638, 4to, at
                    the instance of George Herbert; it was reprinted at Cambridge, 1646; a new
                    translation, by J. T. Betts, was issued in 1865. A translation into Spanish from
                    the Italian, by Luis Usóz i Rio, was published in 1855. (7) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Seven</hi><hi rend="italic">Doctrinal Letters,</hi> printed with the <hi
                        rend="italic">Trataditos,</hi> from a Vienna manuscript, and translated by
                    J. T. Betts in the <hi rend="italic">XVII. Opuscules.</hi> (8) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Comentario Breve . . . sobre la Epistola de San Pablo a los Romanos,</hi>
                    Venice, 1556; translation and commentary, edited by Juan Perez de Pineda,
                    reprinted 1856; English version, by J. T. Betts, 1883. (9) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Comentario Breve . . . sobre la Primera Epistola de San Pablo a los
                        Corintios,</hi> Venice, 1557; translation and commentary, edited, reprinted,
                    and translated as No. 8. (10) <hi rend="italic">El Evangelio de San</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Mateo,</hi> translation and commentary, first published in
                    1881, from a Vienna manuscript; English version, by J. T. Betts, 1883. (11)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">El Salterio,</hi> translation of the Psalms from Hebrew into
                    Spanish, published with the <hi rend="italic">Trataditos,</hi> from a Vienna
                    manuscript. (12) At Vienna is an unpublished commentary in Spanish on Psalms
                    i.-xli. (13) Sand mentions a commentary on St John’s Gospel, which is not known
                    to exist.</p>
                <p>The notices of Valdes in Sand <hi rend="italic">(Biblioth. Antitrinitar.,</hi>
                    1684, p. 2), Bayle, and Wallace <hi rend="italic">(Antitrin. Biog.,</hi> 1850,
                    ii. 8) are very inadequate. The revival of interest in him is due to M'Crie, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hist. Ref. in Italy,</hi> 1827, and <hi rend="italic">Hist.
                        Ref. in Spain,</hi> 1829. But the full knowledge of his life and teachings
                    was first opened up by Benjamin B. Wiffen, whose <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of
                    Valdes was prefixed in 1865 to the new translation of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Considerations.</hi> Since then important discoveries have been made in the
                    Aulic Library, Vienna, by Dr Edward Boehmer; compare his <hi rend="italic">Span.
                        Reformers of Two Centuries,</hi> 1874, and <hi rend="italic">Lives of the
                        Twin Brothers, J. and A. de Valdes,</hi> prefixed to <hi rend="italic"
                        >Biblioth. Wiffeniana,</hi> 1882, also separately, with introd. by J. T.
                    Betts. For an interesting sketch of Valdes, see Benrath’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bernardino Ochino,</hi> 1875. Respecting his theological standpoint,
                    compare Bonet-Maury, <hi rend="italic">Early Sources of Eng. Unit.
                        Christianity,</hi> trans. by Hall, 1884. (A. GO.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
