<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0228-0209-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VICENTE, Gil (c. 1470 (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    209)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n228/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VICENTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Gil (c. 1470</hi></label>- <hi
                        rend="italic                     smallcaps"> c</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >.</hi> 1536), Portuguese dramatist, with an honourable position also in the
                    history of Spanish literature, was born, most probably in Lisbon, about the year
                    1470. He was of good family, and, after studying law at the then university of
                    Lisbon, became attached to the royal court, in what capacity is unknown. In June
                    1502 he produced and took the leading part in the performance of his first
                    piece, a kind of dramatic pastoral, after the manner of Juan de la Encina, on
                    occasion of the birth of an heir to the throne (John III.). So successful was
                    this appearance that he soon became the recognized provider of such
                    entertainments at court, during the reign both of Emmanuel and of John. Of his
                    domestic history nothing is known, except that he married a lady named Branca
                    Bezerra, by whom he had a son and a daughter. His outward circumstances,
                    especially in his later years, if some apparently personal allusions in his
                    works are to be literally interpreted, do not seem to have been prosperous.
                    Almost the only personal incident that has come down to us is his successful
                    remonstrance with the clergy of Santarem in <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n229/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0229-0210"/> 1531, for having taken the earthquakes of
                    that year as a text from which to rouse orthodox fanaticism against the Jews or
                    “Neo-Christians”; the circumstances are related by Vicente in a letter to the
                    king. The time and place of his death are alike uncertain; most probably it
                    occurred at Evora not much later than 1536.</p>
                <p>Vicente published various of his pieces during his lifetime, but the first
                    collected edition of his works, edited by his son Luis, did not appear till
                    1562. It is in black letter folio, and only one copy, that in the Gottingen
                    university library, is now known to exist. A second edition, “emended by the
                    Holy Office,” appeared in 1585, of which also only a single copy is now extant
                    (in Lisbon). The disfavour with which they were viewed by the Inquisition caused
                    them to fall into unmerited neglect, and they do not appear to have been again
                    reprinted till 1834, when they were carefully edited by Feio and Monteiro
                    (Hamburg, 3 vols.). They number forty-two in all, of which seventeen are written
                    wholly in Portuguese and ten wholly in Spanish, while in the remainder both
                    languages are employed. The principles determining his choice of language are
                    not easy to discover, and indeed he seems to have used either indifferently,
                    perhaps in this accommodating himself to the aptitudes of particular actors. It
                    may be observed, however, that, while in the 14th century it had been
                    fashionable for all court poets in the western half of the peninsula to use
                    Galician or Old Portuguese, the practice had changed in the days of John II. of
                    Castile, when Castilian became the favourite speech. In writing chiefly in
                    Portuguese Vicente thus reverted to the older practice; but, on the other hand,
                    it is not surprising that he should have freely used Spanish at a court which
                    stood in such intimate personal relations with that of Castile (of Emmanuel’s
                    three wives two were Castilian princesses and the third was a sister of Charles
                    V. ), and where he had taken Encina as his avowed model. According to their form
                    the works of Vicente are conveniently divided into—(1) <hi rend="italic">obras
                        de devoçao</hi> or <hi rend="italic">autos,</hi> (2) comedies and
                    tragi-comedies, and (3) farces. The first class includes twelve autos or sacred
                    pieces, intended for performance at Christmas, Epiphany, and other religious
                    festivals. The plots are quaint and conceived entirely in the mediaeval spirit;
                    in their working out many touches of poetical feeling and also of sarcastic
                    humour are introduced. There is a vein of pleasing romance in such compositions
                    as his <hi rend="italic">Dom Duardos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Amadis de
                        Gaula,</hi> while the genuine mirthfulness of his farces <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Inez Pereira</hi> and others), as well as their originality, well entitle
                    him to be spoken of by his compatriots as their “father of comedy” and the
                    national Plautus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Some typical examples of Vicente’s works may be read in Böhl
                        von Faber’s</hi> Teatro Espanοl anterior á Lope de Vega <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Hamburg, 1832) and in Ochoa’s</hi> Tesoro del Teatro Español <hi
                        rend="italic">(Paris, 1838). An interesting essay, with analyses of many of
                        the plays, occurs in vol. lxxix. of the</hi> Quarterly Review <hi
                        rend="italic">(1846-47); see also Ferdinand Wolf's article “Gil-Vicente” in
                        Ersch and Gruber’s</hi> Encykl. <hi rend="italic">(sec. i. vol.
                        lxvii.).</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
