<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0278-0255-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VIRGIL, Polydore (c</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 255</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xc0z">Proverbs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n278/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VIRGIL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Polydore (c</hi></label>.
                    1470-1555), author of the <hi rend="italic">Historia Anglica,</hi> otherwise
                    known as P. V. <hi rend="smallcaps">Castellensis,</hi> was a kinsman of Cardinal
                    Hadrian Castellensis, a native of Castro in Etruria. His father’s name is said
                    to have been George Virgil; his great-grandfather, Anthony Virgil, “a man well
                    skilled in medicine and astrology,” had professed philosophy at Paris, as did
                    Polydore’s own brother and protégé, John Matthew Virgil, at Pavia, in 1517. A
                    third brother was a London merchant in 1511. Polydore is said to have been
                    educated at Bologna, and was probably in the service of Guido Ubaldo, duke of
                    Urbino, before 1498, as in the dedication of his first work, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Liber Proverbiorum</hi> (April 1498), he styles himself this prince’s client.
                    Polydore’s second book, <hi rend="italic">De Inventoribus Herum,</hi> is
                    dedicated to Guido’s tutor, Ludovicus Odaxius, from Urbino, in August 1499.
                    After being chamberlain to Alexander VI. he came to England in 1501 as deputy
                    collector of Peter’s pence for the cardinal. As Hadrian’s proxy, he was
                    enthroned bishop of Bath and Wells in October 1504. It was at Henry VII.’s
                    instance that he commenced his <hi rend="italic">Historia Anglica—</hi> a work
                    which, though seemingly begun as early as 1505, was not completed till August
                    1533, the date of its dedication to Henry VIII., nor published till 1534. In May
                    1514 he and his patron the cardinal are found supporting Wolsey’s claims to the
                    cardinalship, but he had lost the great minister’s favour before the year was
                    out. A rash letter, reflecting severely on Henry VIII. and Wolsey, was
                    intercepted early in 1515, after which Polydore was cast into prison and
                    supplanted in his collectorship (March and April). He was not without some
                    powerful supporters, as both Catherine de’ Medici and Leo X. wrote to the king
                    on his behalf. From his prison he sent an abject and almost blasphemous letter
                    to the offended minister, begging that the fast approaching Christmas—a time
                    which witnessed the restitution of a world—might see his pardon also. He was set
                    at liberty before Christmas 1515, though he never regained his collectorship. In
                    1525 he published the first edition of Gildas, dedicating the work to Tunstall,
                    bishop of London. Next year appeared his <hi rend="italic">Liber de
                    Prodigiis,</hi> dedicated from London (July) to Francesco Maria, duke of Urbino.
                    Somewhere about 1538 he left England, and remained in Italy for some time.
                    Ill-health, he tells us, forbade him on his return to continue his custom of
                    making daily notes on contemporary events. About the end of 1551 he went home to
                    Urbino, where he appears to have died in 1555. He had been naturalized in
                    October 1510, and had held several clerical appointments in England. In 1508 he
                    was appointed archdeacon of Wells, and in 1513 prebendary of Oxgate in St Paul’s
                    Cathedral, both of which offices he held after his return to Urbino.</p>
                <p>The first edition of the <hi rend="italic">Historia Anglica</hi> (twenty-six
                    books) was printed at Basel in 1534; the twenty-seventh book, dealing with the
                    reign of Henry VIII. down to the birth of Edward VI. (October 1536), was added
                    to the third edition of 1555. Polydore claims to have been very careful in
                    collecting materials for this work, and takes credit for using foreign
                    historians as well as English; for which reason, he remarks, the English,
                    Scotch, and French will find several things reported in his pages far
                    differently from the way in which they are told in current national story. In
                    his search after information he applied to James IV. of Scotland for a list of
                    the Scottish kings and their annals; but not even his friendship for Gavin
                    Douglas could induce him to give credit to the historical notions of this
                    accomplished bishop, who traced the pedigree of the Scots down from the banished
                    son of an Athenian king and Scotta the daughter of the Egyptian tyrant of the
                    Israelites. A similar scepticism made him doubt the veracity of Geoffrey of
                    Monmouth, and thus called forth Leland’s <hi rend="italic">Defensio
                    Gallofridi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Assertio Incomparabilis Arturii.</hi> This
                    doubting instinct led to his being accused of many offences against learning,
                    such as that of burning cartloads of MSS. lest his errors should be discovered,
                    of purloining books from libraries and shipping them off by the vesselful to
                    Rome. As a matter of fact, it is of course mainly from the time of Henry VI.,
                    where our contemporary records begin to fail so sadly, that Polydore’s work is
                    useful. He must have been personally acquainted with many men whose memories
                    could carry them back to the beginning of the Wars of the Roses. Dr Brewer
                    speaks somewhat harshly of him as an authority for the reign of Henry VIII., and
                    indeed his spite against Wolsey is evident; but it is impossible to read his
                    social and geographical accounts of England and Scotland without gratitude for a
                    writer who has preserved so many interesting details. Polydore’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Adagia</hi> (Venice, April 1498) was the first collection of Latin
                    proverbs ever printed; it preceded Erasmus’s by two years, and the slight
                    misunderstanding that arose for the moment out of rival claims gave place to a
                    sincere friendship. A second senes of Biblical proverbs (553 in number) was
                    dedicated to Wolsey’s follower Richard Pace, and is preceded by an interesting
                    letter (June 1519), which gives the names of many of Polydore’s English friends,
                    from More and Archbishop Warham to Linacre and Tunstall. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >De Inventoribus,</hi> treating of the origin of all things whether
                    ecclesiastical or lay (Paris, 1499), originally consisted of only seven books,
                    but was increased to eight in 1521. It was exceedingly popular, and was early
                    translated into French (1521), German (1537), English (1546), and Spanish
                    (1551). All editions, however, except those following the text sanctioned by
                    Gregory XIII. in 1576, are on the Index Expurgatorius. The <hi rend="italic">De
                    Prodigiis</hi> also achieved a great popularity, and was soon translated into
                    Italian (1543), English (1546), and Spanish (1550). This treatise takes the form
                    of a Latin dialogue between Polydore and his Cambridge friend Robert Ridley. It
                    takes place in the open air, at Polydore’s country house near London. Polydore’s
                    duty is to state the problems and supply the historical illustrations; his
                    friend’s to explain, rationalize, and depreciate as best he can. Here, as in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Historia Anglica,</hi> it is plain that the writer plumes
                    himself specially on the excellence of his Latin, which in Sir Henry Ellis’s
                    opinion is purer than that of any of his contemporaries.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
