<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0187-0168-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">VERNET</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 168</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1157239">Triumph</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844959">Camps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1050567">Painting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nx1c">Painting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7764s">Paintings</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc55">Paint</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n187/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VERNET</label>, the name of three eminent French
                    painters.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude Joseph Vernet</hi> (1714-1789), who was born at
                    Avignon on 14th August 1714, when only fourteen years of age aided his father, a
                    skilful decorative painter, in the most important parts of his work. But the
                    panels <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n188/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0188-0169"/> of sedan chairs could not satisfy his ambition
                    and he started for Rome. The sight of the sea at Marseilles and his voyage
                    thence to Civita Vecchia made a deep impression on him, and immediately after
                    his arrival he entered the studio of a marine painter, Bernardino Fergioni.
                    Slowly but surely Claude Joseph made his way and attracted notice. With a
                    certain conventionality in design, proper to his day, he allied the results of
                    constant and honest observation of natural effects of atmosphere, which he
                    rendered with unusual pictorial art. Perhaps no painter of landscapes or
                    sea-pieces has ever made the human figure so completely a part of the scene
                    depicted or so important a factor in his design. “Others may know better,” he
                    said, with just pride, “how to paint the sky, the earth, the ocean; no one knows
                    better than I how to paint a picture.” For twenty years Vernet lived on in Rome,
                    producing views of seaports, storms, calms, moonlights, &amp;c., when he was
                    recalled (1753) to Paris, and executed, by royal command, the remarkable series
                    of the seaports of France (Louvre) by which he is best known. On his return he
                    became a member of the academy, but he had previously contributed to the
                    exhibitions of 1746 and following years, and he continued to exhibit, with rare
                    exceptions, down to the date of his death, which took place in his lodgings in
                    the Louvre on 3d December 1789. Amongst the very numerous engravers of his works
                    may be specially cited Le Bas, Cochin, Basan, Duret, Flipart, and Le Veau in
                    France, and in England Vivares.</p>
                <p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoine Charles Horace Vernet</hi> (1758-1835), commonly
                    called <hi rend="smallcaps">Carle,</hi> the youngest child of the above-named,
                    was born at Bordeaux in 1758, where his father was painting the view from the
                    chateau of La Trompette (Louvre). He showed, at the age of five, an
                    extraordinary passion for drawing horses, but went through the regular
                    academical course as a pupil of Lépicié. Strangely enough, on arriving in Italy
                    after carrying off the great prize (1782) he lost all ambition and interest in
                    his profession, so that his father had to recall him to France to prevent his
                    entering a monastery. In Paris Carle Vernet became himself again and
                    distinguished himself at the exhibition of 1791 by his Triumph of Paulus
                    Aemilius, a work in which he broke with reigning traditions in classical
                    subjects and drew the horse with the forms he had learnt from nature in stables
                    and riding-schools. But the Revolution drew on and Carle Vernet’s career for
                    awhile seemed to end in the anguish of his sister’s death on the scaffold. When
                    he again began to produce, it was as the man of another era: his drawings of the
                    Italian campaign brought him fresh laurels; his vast canvas, the Battle of
                    Marengo, obtained great success; and for his Morning of Austerlitz Napoleon
                    bestowed on him the Legion of Honour. His hunting-pieces, races, landscapes, and
                    work as a lithographer (chiefly under the restoration) had also a great vogue.
                    From Louis XVIII. he received the order of St Michael. In 1827 he accompanied
                    his son Horace (see below) to Rome, and died in Paris on his return, 17th
                    November 1835, having produced but little during the last years of his life.</p>
                <p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Émile Jean Horace Vernet</hi> (1789-1863), born in
                    Paris, 30th June 1789, was one of the most characteristic, if not one of the
                    ablest, of the military painters of France. He was just twenty when he exhibited
                    the Taking of an Entrenched Camp—a work which showed no depth of observation,
                    but was distinguished by a good deal of character. His picture of his own studio
                    (the rendezvous of the Liberals under the restoration), in which he represented
                    himself painting tranquilly, whilst boxing, fencing, drum and horn playing,
                    &amp;c., were going on, in the midst of a medley of visitors, horses, dogs, and
                    models, is one of his best works, and, together with his Defence of the Barrier
                    at Clichy (Louvre), won for him an immense popularity. Enjoying equal favour
                    with the court and with the opposition, he was most improperly appointed
                    director of the school of France at Rome, from 1828 to 1835, and thither he
                    carried the atmosphere of racket in which he habitually lived.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See a letter of Mendelssohn’s
                    cited by C. Blanc.</p></note> After his return the whole of the Constantine room
                    at Versailles was decorated by him in the short space of three years. This vast
                    work shows Vernet at his best and at his worst: as a picture it begins and ends
                    nowhere and the composition is all to pieces; but it has good qualities of
                    faithful and exact representation. He died at Paris on 17th January 1863. The
                    twenty works which were exhibited after his death confirmed his reputation for
                    extraordinary facility; he had tried every sort of subject, showing affinity for
                    all that was anecdotic rather than dramatic, failing most wherever most was
                    demanded of him, and never reaching either beauty of colour or dignity of line.
                    Vernet was in short a brilliant off-hand sketcher of all he saw, as he said
                    himself, “from his window,” and even in this work there was a good deal of
                    affectation of the impromptu.</p>
                <p>See Lagrange, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Vernet et la Peinture au X VIII.
                    Siècle;</hi> C. Blanc, <hi rend="italic">Uist. de l’École Française</hi>; and T.
                    Sylvestre, <hi rend="italic">Peintres Contemporains.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
