<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0254-0233-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VILNA, or Wilno (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    233)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1000435">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4697039w">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n254/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VILNA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilno</hi></label>, a
                    Lithuanian government of west Russia, has the Polish province of Suwatki on the
                    W., Kovno and Vitebsk on the N. and E., and Minsk and Grodno on the E. and S.
                    Its area is 16,421 square miles. Vilna lies on the broad marshy swelling, dotted
                    with lakes, which separates <hi rend="smallcaps">Poland</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >(q.v.)</hi> from East Prussia and stretches east-north-east towards the
                    Valdai Plateau. Its highest parts are a little more than 1000 feet above
                    sea-level. On its western and eastern boundaries Vilna is deeply trenched by the
                    valleys of the Niemen and the Dwina. Devonian limestones crop out in the
                    northeast. Elsewhere they are concealed by the marine and freshwater limestones
                    and sandstones of the Eocene period, which cover nearly the whole of Vilna; and
                    these in their turn are overlain by thick layers of boulder clay, sands, and
                    lacustrine deposits. The soil is for the most part clayey or sandy, fertile loam
                    appearing only in the depression watered by the Vilia. Numerous lakes and
                    marshes, partly covered with forests, and scarcely passable except when frozen,
                    as well as wet meadow-land, occupy a large area in the central parts of Vilna.
                    The Niemen, which flows along the southern and western borders for more than 200
                    miles, is the chief artery of trade for the government, and its importance in
                    this respect is enhanced by its tributary the Vilia, which flows west for more
                    than 200 miles through the central parts of Vilna, receiving many affluents on
                    its course. Among the tributaries of the Niemen is the Berezina, which acquired
                    renown during Napoleon’s retreat in 1812; it flows in a marshy valley in the
                    south-east. The Dwina for 50 miles of its course separates Vilna from Vitebsk.
                    The combined traffic on the Niemen and the Dwina was valued at nearly £200,000
                    in 1883. The climate of the government is only slightly tempered by its
                    proximity to the Baltic Sea (January 21°∙8 Fahr.; July 64° ∙5); the average
                    temperature at the town of Vilna is only 43° ∙5. But in winter the thermometer
                    descends very low, the minimum observed during the last sixty years being - 30°.
                    The flora and fauna are intermediate between those of Poland and middle Russia.
                    The population of Vilna, which amounted to 1,223,260 in 1883, consists chiefly
                    of Lithuanians (35 per cent.) in the west and north and White Russians (45 per
                    cent.) in the south and east. Jews make up 11 per cent. of the population; and
                    the Poles, who constitute the landed aristocracy and the artisan classes of the
                    towns, reach 7 per cent. A few Great Russians and Tatars, descendants of Crimean
                    prisoners, must be added to the above. Roman Catholicism is the prevailing creed
                    among the Lithuanians and Poles; and the White Russians belong for the most part
                    to the Greek and Nonconformist Churches.</p>
                <p>In spite of the unfertile soil, sufficient cereals are grown for the needs of the
                    population and to supply the distilleries. The average crops of 1882-1885 were
                    1,010,000 quarters of rye, 44,000 of wheat, 790,000 of various kinds of grain,
                    and 9,840,000 bushels of potatoes. Apart from finer breeds kept by a few
                    landowners, the cattle of the peasantry belong to inferior varieties. In 1883
                    there were 203,620 horses, 303,100 horned cattle, 277,800 sheep, and 238,800
                    pigs. More than one-third of the area is covered with forests, whence a
                    considerable quantity of timber is exported, partly to Germany, for
                    shipbuilding. A variety of petty trades are carried on in the villages of the
                    forest region,—sledges, cars, wheels, and wooden ware being made by the
                    peasants. Tar, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n255/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0255-0234"/> pitch, and potash are exported. The
                    manufactures have only begun to develop of late. In 1884 there were 300
                    establishments employing 3020 men, and giving an annual output valued at
                    £885,100 (as against £200,000 in 1860). An active trade in timber, corn, and
                    flax (exported) and in manufactured goods (imported) is carried on. Vilna is
                    divided into seven districts, the chief towns of which (with their populations
                    in 1883) are—Vilna (see below), Vileika (3905), Disna (8030), Lidy or Lida
                    (7940), Oshmiany (4470), Svienciany (8510), and Troki (2440).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
