<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-4136-0379-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONAGHAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:864579">Cloning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193824136?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MONAGHAN</label>, an inland county in the province
                    of Ulster, in Ireland, is bounded on the north by the county of Tyrone, on the
                    east by those of Armagh and Louth, on the south by those of Louth and Cavan, and
                    on the west by those of Cavan and Fermanagh. It extends over a surface of
                    327,048 acres, of which 309,968 acres are capable of cultivation, 9236 are
                    unprofitable mountain or bog, and 7844 are under water.</p>
                <p part="N">According to Whitaker, the tribe of the Scoti, which spread itself over
                    the greater part of the interior of Ireland, inhabited this county in the time
                    of Ptolemy. In a subsequent period of Irish history it formed part of the
                    territory of Uriel or Orgial; and, from the principal family which then resided
                    in it, was also known by the name of M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Mahon <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s country. In the reign of Elizabeth it was
                    reduced into shire-ground, and was divided into the five baronies which still
                    exist, namely, those of Cremorne, Dar-try, Farney, Monaghan, and Trough. These
                    are subdivided into nineteen parishes, and four parts of parishes, the remainder
                    of which are in some of the adjoining counties.</p>
                <p part="N">According to the ecclesiastical arrangements of the country, Monaghan is
                    wholly included in the diocese of Clogher, the see of which is in the city of
                    the same name in the county of Tyrone. It contains twenty-one parishes.</p>
                <p part="N">The general appearance of the surface is hilly, yet not rising into
                    heights of considerable elevation. Its principal mountain range is that of
                    Slievebaugh, a rugged and barren tract which separates it from Tyrone. Its
                    highest summit, called Cairnrnore, commands an extensive view of the surrounding
                    country on every side. Crieve Mountain, in the south, is still more elevated,
                    but of smaller superficial extent. There are no rivers of any consequence. The
                    Finn, which rises near the centre of the county, scarcely merits the title <hi
                        rend="italic">of</hi> river until after its entrance into Fermanagh; and the
                    Blackwater, forming part of the northeastern boundary towards Tyrone, is the
                    receptacle of many of the smaller rivulets which take their rise here. But,
                    though deficient in rivers of magnitude, it is amply furnished with stι earns of
                    running water, well suited to the purposes of agriculture and of manufacturing
                    industry; nor can any other county boast of such a number of lakes, although few
                    of them are of an extent such as to entitle them to specific notice. The number
                    of these lakes is 184, thirty of which are considerable sheets of water. The
                    most remarkable are Lough Eagish, on Crieve Mountain, which supplies water for a
                    long Succession of mills and bleaching-greens; Lakes Damby, Camm, and Oona.
                    Others near Castleblaney, Dawson Grove, and Mount Lewis, are celebrated for the
                    beauty of the surrounding scenery.</p>
                <p part="N">The soil is of various kinds. In the central parts it consists of a rich
                    limestone. The southern districts are partly of the same quality, and partly a
                    deep clay, capable of a high degree of cultivation under judicious management.
                    The north consists mostly of a stiff’ retentive clay, marshy in winter, and
                    hardening quickly by the heat of summer, yet interspersed in many parts with
                    tracts of valuable limestone soil. Whilst the limestone formation predominates
                    in the level districts, the more elevated portions exhibit traces of a different
                    character. To the north the hills show sandstone; but those in the south are of
                    basalt or whinstone. Coal has been found in more than one place, but in veins so
                    poor and scanty as not to encourage the outlay of capital upon its exploration.
                    Slates of good quality are quarried in Crieve Mountain. A lead mine was also
                    worked there, but has long since been relinquished as unprofitable. Ochre,
                    potters’ clay of such quality as to cause an exportation of it to Dundalk for
                    the manufacture of glazed earthenware, brick clay, manganese, antimony, and
                    fullers’ earth, are also found here. There is a chalybeate spring at
                    Drumtubberbuy, on Cairnmore, the water of which casts up a thick scum of ochre.
                    A well near Clones is much celebrated for its efficacy in cases of jaundice,
                    whence it has acquired its name of Granabuymore, or “the great yellow cure.” A
                    spring at Tullaghan throws up water which, although perfectly tasteless and
                    clear, deposits an incrustation on the banks near its source. This county has a
                    large proportion of bog, which, together with its great number of lakes, and its
                    exposure to the north-western winds, render it very damp, although it is far
                    from being unwholesome.</p>
                <p part="N">The results of inquiries as to the population, made at different
                    periods, are as follow:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Authority.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Population.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1760</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">De Burgo</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">.... 49,848</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1792</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Beaufort</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">... 118,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1812</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Parliamentary
                            return...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">.... 140,433</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">....174,697</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Ditto</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...195,521</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">The comparison of the amount of population, according to the latest of
                    these returns, with the superficies of the county, gives a result of one
                    individual to every acre and a half.</p>
                <p part="N">This population was represented in the Irish parliament by four members;
                    two for the county at large, and two for the borough of Monaghan. Those for the
                    borough were struck off at the period of the Union; and no alteration to the
                    arrangement then made has taken place under the reform act.</p>
                <p part="N">The constituency, as it was constituted at three periods, viz. 1st,
                    previously to the disqualification of the forty-shilling freeholders; 2d,
                    subsequently to their disqualification; and, 3d, under the reform act, exhibits
                    the following changes:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">L.50.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">L.20.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">L.10.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">40s.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1st Jan. 1829..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...300....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">107...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">. .. — .-.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">... 12,453..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">..12,860</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1st Jan. 1830..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...322...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">194..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">....632..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">— ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">.. 1,148</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1st May 1831..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...464...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">254...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">,...946..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">• ∙∙ ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">.. 1,664</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">The local government is vested in a lieutenant, fourteen
                    deputy-lieutenants, and sixty-one magistrates, who are supported by a
                    constabulary force, consisting of four chief and eighty sub-constables. The
                    constabulary establishment is maintained at an expense of about L.4000, being at
                    an <pb break="no" facs="nls:193824149?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0715-4149-0380"/>average of somewhat more than L.47 per annum
                    for each man. Under the provisions of the new constabulary act, this force
                    consists of a sub-inspector, five chief constables, and ten head constables,
                    with eighty constables and sub-constables.</p>
                <p part="N">The state of education, as collected from the parliamentary returns made
                    in 1821 and 1831, is shown in the following table. The returns made by the
                    commissioners of public instruction in 1834 cannot be stated, in consequence of
                    their having been made up according to dioceses instead of counties:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Boys.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Girls.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Sex not
                            ascertained.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">....4517</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2743...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">. ...7,260</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1824-6...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">....6694</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">4205...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">320</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...11,219</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">Of the numbers stated in the latter of these returns, 2471 were
                    Episcopalian Protestants, 2166 Protestant Dissenters, and 6408 Roman Catholics;
                    the religious persuasion of 174 was not ascertained. The proportion of
                    Protestants to Roman Catholics, as far as can be inferred from the relative
                    numbers of the children of each religious persuasion attending public schools,
                    is as two to three nearly. The total number of schools was 281; of which 19,
                    containing 1006 children, were supported by grants of public money; 37,
                    containing 2551 children, were supported by the voluntary contributions of
                    societies or individuals; the remaining 225 schools, which afforded the means of
                    education to 7662 children, were maintained wholly by the fees of the pupils.
                    The diocesan school of the see of Clogher is in the town of Monaghan. There is
                    also an endowed school at Carrickmacross.</p>
                <p part="N">The population is chiefly rural, dispersed either in detached dwellings
                    throughout the country, or in small villages. The total number of residents in
                    towns containing upwards of one thousand inhabitants each, is only 13,000, out
                    of a population which may be statedin round numbers at 200,000; and there are
                    but five towns of this description, so that their average population is but 2600
                    souls each.</p>
                <p part="N">Die estates in land are of every value, from L.20,000 per annum to L.20;
                    being partly held under grants of the escheated lands in Ulster in the time of
                    James I., and partly arising out of the forfeitures in the time of Cromwell.
                    Leases are for short terms, usually twenty-one years, and one or three lives.
                    The mountainous districts are frequently held in joint tenancy by a large number
                    of occupants. The tenants of one of those mountain districts once formed a
                    community of very singular character. Their village consisted of nearly two
                    hundred cabins, on a tract of 500 acres of bog, at Blackstaff, near
                    Carrickmacross, but so barren as not to afford the means of the lowest animal
                    subsistence, so that they were forced to derive their support from patches of
                    land rented by them ata considerable distance from their place of residence. The
                    community allowed itself to be governed by a mayor, chosen annually by all the
                    members. The holder of the largest potatogarden was sure to be elected. All
                    disputes w ere referred to him, and no appeal was known to be made from his
                    decision. His fee was a bottle of whisky, which was invariably shared by him
                    with the contending parties. The office was one of honour rather than of profit;
                    for there was no instance of a mayor holding his post for two successive years.
                    The community was broken up in consequence of the rebellion of 1798, at which
                    time the members were compelled to quit their village, and to reside upon their
                    detached plots; yet, for several years afterwards, they held an annual convivial
                    meeting on the site of their deserted village.</p>
                <p part="N">The mansions of the landed proprietors are numerous and elegant; the
                    houses of the wealthier farmers, and more particularly of those who combine
                    manufactures with agriculture, exhibit every indication of comfort; but the
                    dwellings of cottiers and labourers are miserable in the extreme. The dress of
                    the male peasantry is home manufactured frize, dyed blue; that of the female
                    generally cotton. Flesh meat seldom forms a part of their dietary. The cottiers
                    in the districts remote from towns are unable to procure any food but potatoes
                    seasoned with salt. Fuel is cheap and abundant, in consequence of the quantity
                    of bog. The language is both English and Irish; but the latter predominates in
                    the more retired parts of the county.</p>
                <p part="N">The state of agriculture has improved with great rapidity during the
                    last twenty or thirty years. The accounts given shortly after the year 1800
                    describe the old country plough of clumsy construction, the slide-car without
                    wheels, the conveyance of the manure and field produce on horses or asses’
                    backs, and the application of manual labour and spade-husbandry as being
                    generally prevalent. At present all the improvements introduced by scientific
                    •agriculturists are to be seen in practice here, as far as they have been found
                    consistent with the peculiar nature of the soil and climate. Ploughs on the most
                    improved plan, Scotch carts, and implements of various kinds to supersede the
                    improvident exertion of manual labour, are universal; yet in some parts where
                    the nature of the ground forbids the use of the plough, considerable tracts of
                    land are still cultivated by the spade. The old, stunted, and ill-conditioned
                    breeds of black cattle, sheep, and hogs, have given way to the most esteemed
                    British or foreign stocks, the character of which has not unfrequently been made
                    more suitable to the agricultural localities by judicious crossings with the
                    native breeds. Wheat and oats are the principal species of grain. Barley and
                    bear are largely grown in the hilly districts. Clover is much encouraged, and
                    few farmers are without a patch of it, however small. It is cut green for soil,
                    and is found extremely economical. The tops of furze or gorse are also used,
                    when pounded, as food for horses, and prove highly palatable to the animal, as
                    well as very nutritious. Flax, for the growth of which the soil is peculiarly
                    favourable, is very generally raised. The manure is formed of composts, of which
                    lime and burned turf mould are generally component parts; marl, though common,
                    is little used. The fences in some parts are of white thorn, interspersed with
                    sallows; in others a slight mound of earth serves rather to determine the
                    boundary than to prevent trespassing. Asses and pigs are numerous. Fish abound
                    in the numerous lakes. The county was once almost a continuous forest, excepting
                    the higher lands, which appear to be of a nature ungenial to the growth of
                    trees. The numerous demesnes of the nobility and gentry are richly embellished
                    by plantations of modern growth. Ash and sycamore are much encouraged. The wood
                    of the latter is in great repute for some parts of mill-machinery. Osieries are
                    frequently to be found in the marshy bottoms at the foot of hills, and prove
                    highly profitable.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal manufacture is that of linen, which was long carried on
                    with great spirit, and produced a considerable export; but it has latterly
                    declined, partly in consequence of the increasing preference given to cotton
                    goods. The woollen manufacture is chiefly employed in supplying the domestic
                    consumption. The sand or gritstone of Cairnmore has given rise to a manufacture
                    of millstones there, which are in considerable demand. Tanyards are frequent.
                    Coarse earthenware is manufactured at Glasslough, and a small iron-work near
                    Clones supplies most of the agricultural implements used in the county.</p>
                <p part="N">The remains of antiquity are but few. The most remarkable are two round
                    or pillar towers; one in the burial-ground of Clones, and the other at
                    Inniskeen, on the borders of Louth. The former consisted of five stories, the
                    traces of which are still visible in the walls; and its door is about four feet
                    above the level of the ground. Near it is a large stone coffin, above ground,
                    with a cover of the same <pb break="no" facs="nls:193824162?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0715-4162-0381"/>material shaped like the roof of a house. The
                    latter of these towers is in a much inferior state of preservation, and is
                    unique, as having its door upon a level with the surrounding country, although
                    this is supposed by some to be the effect of a modern alteration. Near Clones
                    arc two large raths; one in good preservation, exhibiting distinct traces of its
                    fossesand embankments; the other smaller, and much decayed. Danish forts are
                    numerous. The only monastic structure of which any vestiges remain is that of
                    Clones, which was a foundation of regular canons. It was destroyed by Hugh de
                    Lacy, shortly after the arrival of the English; but was rebuilt soon afterwards,
                    and secured from a similar fate by the erection of a castle in its
                    neighbourhood. An abbey of Conventual Franciscans was founded at Monaghan by one
                    of the M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Mahons; but it was afterwards totally
                    destroyed, and a castle erected on its site, which also was in a ruinous state
                    in the reign of James I. Ruins of castles are to be seen at Donaghmoyne and
                    Dawson’s Grove.</p>
                <p part="N">Monaghan, the county town, is situated near the centre of the county, at
                    a short distance from the Blackwater, to the south. Its ancient name was
                    Muinechan, “the town of Monks,” given to it from the religious establishment
                    formerly existing there. The principal buildings are a market-house, in which a
                    brisk linen trade is carried on, erected by Lord Rossmore in 1792; a
                    court-house; and a parislu church. In the immediate vicinity of the town is a
                    Roman Catholic chapel, a Presbyterian meeting-house in the New Market, the
                    county infirmary, the diocesan school-house, the barrack for cavalry at the
                    northern entrance of the town, and an extensive county prison, which has been
                    built at an expense of L 20,000. The town contains a brewery, and carries on a
                    pretty considerable trade in linen. Its population in 1831 amounted to 3848
                    souls. The other towns whose population exceeds 1000 souls are as
                    follow:—Carrickmacross, 2979; Clones, 2381; Balli-bay, 1947; and Castleblayney,
                    1828.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
