<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-4734-0425-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONTAIGNE, Michel de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193824734?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MONTAIGNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Michel
                        de</hi></label>, a <hi rend="italic">philosophe-moraliste,</hi> famous for
                    his book of essays, was born at the castle of Montaigne, in Périgord, on the
                    28th of February 1533, being descended of an ancient family named Eyghem,
                    originally from England. His father, a brave and loyal squire, who had served in
                    Spain and Italy, where he had cultivatedhis mind and improved his taste,
                    bestowed much attention on his education, and, in particular, initiated him in
                    the knowledge of languages by a process much less tardy and laborious than that
                    pursued in the schools. The expedient he adopted was to provide his son with a
                    German master, who, being entirely ignorant of French, but well versed in Latin,
                    spoke to him only in the latter tongue, which he consequently acquired as a
                    vernacular language, and, at the age of six, was able to converse in it with
                    tolerable freedom and fluency. Greek was also taught him as a sort of diversion.
                    “Nous pelotions nos déclinaisons,” says he, “à la manière de ceux qui, par
                    certains jeux de <hi rend="italic">tablier</hi> (échiquier), apprennent
                    l’arithmétique et la géométrie.” By means equally gentle and attractive, he was
                    insensibly led to acquire some knowledge of science; and, without forcing his
                    inclination, or imposing the necessity of application, his habits were formed,
                    and his powers agreeably exercised. All this care and attention he repaid by the
                    most tender affection for the memory of his father; indeed filial piety is said
                    to have formed a conspicuous trait in his character, though it must be confessed
                    that he sometimes displayed it in a manner sufficiently singular. At an early
                    age he was sent to the college of Guienne, at Bordeaux, then the most
                    flourishing in France, and there he had as masters Nicolas Grouchy, William
                    Guérente, George Buchanan, and Muretus, under whom he appears to have made
                    considerable proficiency. Having completed his studies at the age of thirteen,
                    Montaigne resolved to study law; and although his mind, naturally averse to all
                    constraint, must have been repιdsed by the conflicting and complicated mass of
                    consuetudinary ju <pb break="no" facs="nls:193824747?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0715-4747-0426"/>risprudence with which the tribunals were then
                    surcharged, yet, in 1554, he became a counsellor or advocate at Bordeaux, and
                    continued to practise as such until the death of his elder brother, when he
                    abandoned a profession to which he never had any real liking, and which he
                    appeared afterwards to consider as derogatory. On quitting the bar, for the
                    business of which he had evidently no aptitude, he applied himself to the study
                    of men and manners, and in prosecution of this object travelled through various
                    parts of France, Germany, Switzerland, and Italy, making his observations on
                    every thing curious or interesting in society, and receiving several marks of
                    distinction in the course of his peregrinations. In 1581 he was admitted a
                    citizen of Rome, in which city he then sojourned; and the same year he was
                    elected mayor of Bordeaux, an office in which he seems to have given much
                    satisfaction to his fellow-citizens. In 1582 he was sent on a special mission to
                    court about some affairs of importance, and on the expiration of his mayoralty
                    he was again elected to the same office. In 1588 he appeared to some advantage
                    at the assembly of the states at Blois, and, though not a deputy, took a share
                    in the proceedings, but on what pretence or in what capacity does not clearly
                    appear. During one of his visits to court he received the cordon of the order of
                    Saint Michel, a distinction which he appears to have greatly coveted, though we
                    afterwards find him complaining of the discredit into which it had fallen.
                    Having retired to his family residence, he devoted himself to study; but his
                    tranquillity was disturbed by the civil wars which desolated Guienne; and being
                    driven from his house, he wandered about during six months seeking for his
                    family, and often with difficulty obtaining an asylum amongst those who had
                    shared his hospitality. It appears, from a statement of De Thou, that Montaigne
                    had sought to bring about a reconciliation between the Duke of Guise and the
                    King of Navarre, afterwards Henry IV.; and on his return from Paris, where he
                    had completed the impression of his Essays, in 1588, he was with the historian
                    at Blois when the Duke of Guise was there assassinated. In his old age he was
                    very much afflicted with stone and nephritic colic, which led him to observe
                    that “la mort le pinçait continuellement à la gorge ou aux reins ;” but he never
                    could be prevailed on to take physic, in which he had no faith whatever. He died
                    on the 13th of September 1589, and was buried in the church of the Feuillants at
                    Bordeaux, where a monument was erected to his memory. Notwithstanding his
                    constitutional tendency to scepticism, and certain unguarded expressions which
                    seem to intimate an entire extinction of the sentiment of religion, he is said
                    to have died a Christian, probably because he had mass celebrated in his chamber
                    in his last moments, and expired during the elevation of the host.</p>
                <p part="N">His reputation as a writer is founded solely on his Essays, which were
                    at one time extremely popular, and which are still read with pleasure by a
                    numerous class of persons, who, pardoning the delusions of’self-love and
                    self-deceit, are charmed by the acuteness and originality mingled with good
                    nature and sensibility which he displays, and captivated by the inviting
                    frankness and vivacity with which he unbosoms himself about all his domestic
                    habits and concerns. As a writer, he imparted to the French language an energy
                    which it did not possess before, and which has not become antiquated, because it
                    resides in the thoughts and sentiments rather than in the expression. As a
                    philosopher, his object was to describe man as he is, without reserve and
                    without exaggeration; he studied himself more than any other subject, and
                    recorded his observations with an acuteness and fidelity which have rendered his
                    work an authentic record of many interesting facts relative to human nature. He
                    united in a high degree the powers of observation and reflection, without which
                    the study of man can never be successfully prosecuted; and although there is no
                    doubt much truth in the acute but severe strictures on his character contained
                    in a masterly section of the Port-royal Logic, where his vanity, his self-love,
                    and the indulgent manner in which he speaks of his vices, to say nothing of the
                    use of language indicating a total absence of religious’principle and sentiment,
                    are very freely exposed, yet, as Mr Stewart observes, “this consideration, so
                    far from diminishing the value of his Essays, is one of the most instructive
                    lessons they afford to those who, after the example of the author, may undertake
                    the salutary but humiliating task of self-examination.” In the first Preliminary
                    Dissertation (part i. section ii.), to which the reader is referred, will be
                    found an exposition of the philosophical merits and defects of Montaigne, not
                    less remarkable for ability and discrimination, than for the fair and equitable
                    spirit in which both are distinguished and appreciated. Montaigne’s life was
                    first written by the President Bouhier, and prefixed to a supplementary volume
                    of his works in 1740. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
