<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-0067-0066-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MILITARY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125233">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193820067?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MILITARY</label>, something belonging to or
                    connected with the profession of a soldier.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Military Discipline,</hi> the training of soldiers,
                    and the due enforcement of the laws and regulations instituted by authority for
                    securing obedience and repressing all disorderly habits or tendencies. Next to
                    the forming of troops, military discipline is an object of the first importance.
                    It is the soul of all armies; and, unless it be established with great prudence,
                    supported with unshaken resolution, and enforced with rigour tempered by
                    judgment, an army is no better than an armed mob, and is more formidable to the
                    state that maintains it than dangerous to its declared enemies.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Military Execution,</hi> the ravaging or destroying
                    of a country or town which refuses to pay the contributions imposed upon them,
                    or which has incurred that penalty from any transgression of the usages of
                    war.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Military State,</hi> in British polity, is one of
                    the three divisions of the laity. This state includes the whole of the soldiery,
                    or such persons as are peculiarly appointed for the safeguard and defence of the
                    realm.</p>
                <p part="N">In the time of the Anglo-Saxons, the military force of England was in
                    the hands of the dukes or heretochs, who were constituted throughout every
                    province and county in the kingdom, being taken from the principal nobility, and
                    such as were most remarkable for being <hi rend="italic">sapientes, fideles, et
                        animosi.</hi> Their duty was to conduct and regulate the English armies with
                    unlimited power, <hi rend="italic">prout eis</hi><hi rend="italic">visum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">fuerit,</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >honorem</hi><hi rend="italic">coronae</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">utilitatem regni.</hi> And because of
                    this great power, they were elected by the people in full assembly, that is, by
                    folkmote, in the same manner as sheriffs were elected; according to the
                    fundamental maxim of the Saxon constitution, that where any officer was to be
                    intrusted with such power as, if abused, might tend to the oppression of the
                    people, that power should be delegated to him by the vote of the people
                    themselves. The ancient Germans, the ancestors of our Saxon forefathers, had
                    also their dukes, as well as kings; with an independent power over the military,
                    as the kings had over the civil state. The dukes were elective, the kings
                    hereditary; <hi rend="italic">reges</hi><hi rend="italic">ex</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">nobilitate,</hi><hi rend="italic">duces ex</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">virtute sumunt.</hi> In constituting their kings, the family
                    or blood royal was regarded; in choosing their dukes or leaders, they had
                    respect to warlike merit alone. Caesar relates of their ancestors in his time,
                    that whenever they went to war, either offensively or defensively, they elected
                    leaders to command them. This large share of power, thus conferred by the
                    people, though intended to preserve the liberty of the subject, was perhaps
                    unreasonably detrimental to the prerogative of the crown. Accordingly we find
                    that, in the reign of King Edmund Ironside, a very bad use was made of it by
                    Edric, duke of Mercia, who, by his office of duke o.r heretoch, was entitled to
                    a large command in the king’s army, and by his repeated treachery at last
                    transferred the crown to Canute the Dane.</p>
                <p part="N">It seems to be universally agreed by all historians, that Alfred first
                    settled a national militia in this kingdom, and by his prudent discipline made
                    all the subjects of his dominions soldiers. But we are unfortunately left in the
                    dark as to the particulars of this celebrated regulation; although, from what
                    has been observed, the dukes seem to have been left in possession of a power so
                    large and independent that, on the death of Edward the Confessor, it enabled
                    Duke Harold, though a stranger to the blood royal, to ascend the throne of this
                    kingdom, in prejudice of Edgar Etheling, the rightful heir.</p>
                <p part="N">Upon the Norman conquest, the feudal law, in all its rigour, was
                    introduced into this country, the whole of that system being built on a military
                    plan. Hence all the lands in the kingdom were divided into what were called <hi
                        rend="italic">knights fees,</hi> in number above sixty thousand; and for
                    every knight’s fee, a knight or soldier, <hi rend="italic">miles,</hi> was bound
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193820080?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0715-0080-0067"/>to attend the king in his wars for forty days
                    annually; in which time, before war was reduced to a science, the campaign was
                    generally finished, and a kingdom either conquered or victorious. By this means
                    the king had, without any expense, an army of sixty thousand men always ready at
                    his command. Accordingly we find one amongst the laws of William the Conqueror,
                    which commands and enjoins the personal attendance of all knights and others,
                        <hi rend="italic">quod</hi><hi rend="italic">habeant</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >et</hi><hi rend="italic">teneant</hi><hi rend="italic">se semper</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">in armis et equis,</hi><hi rend="italic">ut</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">decet</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >oportet;</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">quod semper</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sint prompti et parati ad servitium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >swum</hi><hi rend="italic">integrum nobis explendum et peragendum, cum opus
                        adfuerit, secundum quod debent</hi><hi rend="italic">de feodis et
                        tenementis</hi><hi rend="italic">suis de jure nobis facere.</hi> This
                    personal service in process of time degenerated into pecuniary commutations or
                    aids; and at last the military part of the feudal system was at the Restoration
                    abolished, by statute 12 Car. II. c. 24.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Military</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Martial
                        Law,</hi> is that branch of the laws of war which respects military
                    discipline, or the government and control of persons employed in the operations
                    or for the purposes of war. Military law is not exclusive of the common law; for
                    a man, by becomingia soldier, does not cease to be a citizen or a member of the
                    commonwealth. He is a citizen still, capable of performing the duties of a
                    subject, and answerable in the ordinary course of law for his conduct in that
                    capacity. Martial law is, therefore, a system of rule superadded to the common
                    law, for regulating the citizen in his additional character of soldier; a
                    temporary character assumed for a special end, and to be laid aside when that
                    end has been attained, and when the disturbance which gave occasion to it has
                    subsided. For, as the law knows nothing of a mere soldier, or one bred up to no
                    other profession than that of arms, so a perpetual standing army is against the
                    principles of the constitution, and, if without consent of parliament, is
                    clearly against law.</p>
                <p part="N">Throughout all Europe, in the feudal times, property was commonly held
                    upon condition of military service; and the possessors of land were, by virtue
                    of their right, at once its cultivators in peace and its defenders in war. But
                    the fetters of land under the feudal system were incompatible with a state of
                    commerce, and the arbitrary power of lords over their vassals was adverse to
                    civil liberty; its strictness declined; the services of tenants were commuted
                    for money, and with money were purchased the services of mercenaries, who were
                    ready to make war a trade. The disorders incident to the disbanding of these
                    troops, the changes which had taken place in the mode of warfare, and the
                    necessity of attending to the balance of power in Europe, all concurred to
                    suggest the idea of a disciplined standing army, which was formed first in
                    France, and then in the other states of Europe. The military despotism, however,
                    which ensued on the Continent was in this country happily prevented by the
                    spirit of a free people; and at the Revolution it was asserted and declared,
                    that tlιe raising or keeping up a standing army within the kingdom, in time of
                    peace, without consent of parliament, is contrary to law. The expediency of a
                    standing army is admitted, and at the same time the liberties of the people are
                    maintained. A standing army therefore exists, but primarily for the benefit,
                    because only with the consent, of the people.</p>
                <p part="N">In early times the king’s justiciar was <hi rend="italic">caput</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">legis</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >militiae</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> at the head not only of the law, but
                    also of the military force of the kingdom. But in England, on the division of
                    the <hi rend="italic">aula</hi><hi rend="italic">regis,</hi> the constable and
                    marischal presided over a court of chivalry for the determination of matters of
                    honour and arms. From time to time, however, other tribunals were subsequently
                    instituted for the administration of martial law; and at length, after the
                    Revolution, when, in addition to the militia* and other local troops of the
                    kingdom, a regular standing army was judged ne cessary for the safety of the
                    realm, the defence of the possessions of the crown, and the preservation of the
                    balance of power in Europe, acts were passed for the maintenance of military
                    order and discipline. Scotland differed from’ England in this respect, that
                    there was here no distribution of the powers of the lord justiciar, such as took
                    place in England, nor was there ever any court of chivalry. In other respects
                    the two countries were, in as far as concerns martial law, very much alike.</p>
                <p part="N">The first of the military acts which passed after the Revolution was
                    occasioned by a mutiny in a body of English and Scotch troops (amongst whom were
                    the regiment of dragoons now called the Scotch Greys, and the royal Scotch
                    regiment of foot), on being ordered to Holland to replace some of the troops of
                    that country which King William had brought over with him. The circumstance was
                    communicated to parliament, andon the 3d April 1689 an act was passed for
                    punishing mutiny, desertion, &amp;c. It authorized the king to grant commissions
                    to certain officers to hold courts martial, for the trial of crimes committed by
                    officers and soldiers; and this act, which has been renewed from time to time,
                    has since the Union been extended to Scotland.</p>
                <p part="N">An act of the same nature was passed in the parliament of England, 13
                    Cha. II. stat. i. c. 9, authorizing the lord high admiral to grant commission to
                    inferior vice-admirals, &amp;c. to assemble courts-martial for the trial of
                    offences committed at sea by officers, marines, or others in the king’s naval
                    service. But this statute was in many points altered by subsequent enactments,
                    till at last all the laws relating to courts-martial for the sea service were
                    reduced into one act, applying equally to the whole united kingdom, namely, 22
                    Geo. II. c. 33, explained and amended by 19 Geo. HI. c. 17.</p>
                <p part="N">The more recent statutes for the government of the forces, naval and
                    military, are 1 Will. IV. c. 14, 15; 2 and 3 Will. IV. c. 23, 28; 3 and 4 Will.
                    IV. c. 5, 6; 4 and 5 Will. IV. c. 4, 5, &amp;c. To detail the provisions of
                    these acts would extend this article beyond the limits allowed to it; and it is
                    not necessary to do so, as the acts themselves, which are very full and
                    explicit, must be in the possession of those interested in them. We shall only
                    observe, that the judgments of courts-martial, like those of other courts, are
                    liable to be taken cognizance of in the superior courts of common law, and the
                    members punished for illegal proceedings, and for all wilful and corrupt abuse
                    of authority against the known, obvious, and common principles of justice.</p>
                <p part="N">(See Tytler on <hi rend="italic">Courts-Martial</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> A dye on <hi rend="italic">Courts-Martial</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> and M‘Arthur on <hi rend="italic">Courts-Martial.')</hi> u. u.
                    u.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Military</hi><hi rend="italic">Tenures.</hi> See
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Feθdal System,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Knight.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
