<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-7048-0603-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MUSHED, or Mesched</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1021986">Minarets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:798948">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1111969">Selling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152439">Tombs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh0c">Afghans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193827048?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MUSHED, or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mesched</hi></label>, a city of Persia, the capital of the province of
                    Khorassan, surrounded by a wall, and said by some to be twelve miles in circuit,
                    but by Fraser estimated at not more than six miles. The greatest length to which
                    the town extends is not above two miles, and the enclosed space presents a sad
                    picture of desolation; the approach to the centre of the city, where the
                    inhabitants exclusively reside, being through masses of ruins. There are
                    thirty-two divisions in the city, each being nominally governed by its own
                    magistrate; but of these many are totally devoid of either houses or
                    inhabitants, and the greater part of the rest are very thinly tenanted. The city
                    appears to have been built of sun-dried bricks or mud, so that the whole aspect
                    of the place presents the monotonous gray earthy colour common to all Persian
                    towns; and even the houses which remain entire are miserably poor and mean in
                    their outward appearance, nor are they much better furnished within. The
                    approach to these houses harmonizes with all the other details, being for the
                    most part through dark lanes and narrowalleys, extremely inconvenient and
                    filthy. Fraser informs us, that in his walks he occasionally stumbled upon the
                    strangest holes and corners, where houses peered out that were half hid in filth
                    and rubbish. He adds, that the path among such places sometimes burrows under
                    the earth, or beneath a heap of build ings which have been raised over it, upon
                    a floor of beams and mats; and that, after thus descending, as it seemed, into
                    the bowels of the earth, a door was opened into a small parterre, surrounded
                    with various apartments, and fitted up with reservoirs and fountains of water,
                    trees, and flowers. There is only one street worthy of the name, which extends
                    throughout the whole length of the town, running north-west and south-east. In
                    the centre is a canal, which serves as a receptacle for all the filth of the
                    town, and is in a state of great disrepair. A row of shops extends along the
                    pathway on either side; and there is a bazaar in another quarter, which extends
                    from 500 to 600 yards in one direction. The public buildings of Mushed are very
                    splendid, and highly celebrated for their sanctity. The tomb in which repose the
                    ashes of the Imam Reza and of the Kaliph Haroun Al Raschid, is an extensive and
                    most magnificent structure, which has been embellished and enriched by different
                    princes. This magnificent cluster of domes and minarets is situated in the
                    centre of the city, where there is a noble oblong square, 160 yards in length by
                    75 in breadth, with gateways at either end, and forms a splendid specimen of the
                    style of eastern architecture. The mausoleum itself comprises a mass of
                    buildings which appear to be of the octagon form; and a silver gate, the gift of
                    Nadir Shah, admits into the passage to the chief apartment, beneath a gilded
                    cupola of magnificent dimensions, rising loftily into a fine*dome, from the
                    centre of which depends a huge branched candlestick of solid silver. There are
                    numerous other apartments, a description of which will be found in Fraser’s
                    account of his journey to Khorassan. Mushed contains no other religious shrine
                    worthy of notice. There is a large ruined mosque with two minarets; and there
                    are numerous other smaller ones to be found in all quarters of the city. There
                    are also sixteen schools or colleges, ten or twelve public baths, and at least
                    twenty-five or thirty caravanserais; many of them spacious and handsome
                    establishments, whilst others are in ruins. The palace of the prince is a poor
                    fabric, scarcely deserving of notice. Mushed contains the tombs of Nadir Shah
                    and his son, though not their dust; their remains having been dug up by their
                    bitter enemy Mahommed Khan, and carried to Teheran. This city rose into
                    importance during the contests between the Mahommedan sects of the Soonies and
                    the Sheahs, under the patronage of Tahmareb, a zealous Sheah, and a prince of
                    the Suffanean dynasty, who decorated the tomb of Imam Reza. It was taken and
                    pillaged by the Tartar tribes; and it was again utterly ruined by the Afghans,
                    and scarcely restored to its former magnificence by all the favours which were
                    lavished on it by Nadir Shah. Its commerce is considerable, <hi rend="subscript"
                        > t</hi> being an entrepôt for that of the surrounding countries, and rich
                    caravans daily arriving from Bockhara, Khyvah, Herat, Kerman, Yezd, Cashan,
                    Ispahan, and other cities. There are in Mushed many merchants, with a
                    considerable number of shopkeepers and tradesmen; and one quarter of the city is
                    appropriated to the Jews, who are here tolerably numerous, and exercise their
                    customary profession of scrap sellers. Of travellers, whether in the way of
                    religion or of commerce, numbers are to be seen from all the surrounding
                    countries, such as Arabs, Turks, Afghans, Turcomans, Usbecks, in the different
                    caravanserais and bazaars of Mushed. It is famed for the manufacture of velvets,
                    which are esteemed the best in Persia; and of sword-blades, which sell, many of
                    them, at from fifteen to a hundred reals a piece, or from L.l to between L.6 and
                    L.7. Those of them made by the old workmen sell as high as 2000 reals; and even
                    more is sometimes demanded for a blade of known antiquity and goodness. The
                    vicinity of the turquoise mines gives employment to numerous stone-cutters. The
                    population is estimated by Fraser at 31,000. Long. 57. E. Lat. 37. 35. N.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193827061?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0715-7061-0604"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
