<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-8390-0086-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COLLINS, Anthony</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wv7t">Paganism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wr06">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050321">Paganism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194748390?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">COLLINS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anthony</hi></label>,
                    a polemical writer, born at Hes-ten, near Hounslow, in the county of Middlesex,
                    in 1676, was the son of Henry Collins, a gentleman of about L.1500 a-year. He
                    was first bred at Eton College, and then went to King’s College, Cambridge,
                    where he had for his tutor Mr Francis Hare, afterwards Bishop of Chichester. He
                    was subsequently a student of the Temple; but not relishing the law, lie soon
                    abandoned the study. He was an ingenious man, and the author of several curious
                    books. His first remarkable piece was published in 1707, being entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">An Essay concerning the Use of Reason in Propositions, the
                        Evidence whereof depends on Human Testimony.</hi> In 1702, he entered into
                    the controversy between Mr Clarke and Dr Dodwell concerning the immortality of
                    the soul. In 1713, he published his discourse on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Free-thinking,</hi> which made a prodigious noise. In 1725 he retired into
                    the county of Essex, and acted as a justice of peace and deputy-lieutenant for
                    the same county, as he had before done for that of Middlesex and the liberty of
                    Westminster. The same year he published a <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Essay
                        concerning Human Liberty.</hi> In 1718 he was chosen treasurer of the county
                    of Essex; and this office he discharged with great credit. In 1724 he published
                    his <hi rend="italic">Historical and Critical Essay on the Thirty-nine
                        Articles.</hi> Soon afterwards he published his <hi rend="italic">Discourse
                        of the Grounds and Deasons of the Christian Religion</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> to which is prefixed <hi rend="italic">An Apology for Free Debate
                        and Liberty of Writing;</hi> which piece was immediately attacked by a great
                    number of authors. In 1726 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Scheme of Literary
                        Prophecy considered, in a View of the Controversy occasioned by a late Hook,
                        entitled A Discourse of the Grounds,</hi> &lt;S-'C. In this Discourse he
                    mentions a manuscript dissertation of his, showing that the Sibylline oracles
                    were a forgery executed in the times of the primitive Christians, who, for that
                    reason, were called <hi rend="italic">Sibyllists</hi> by the Pagans; but it
                    never appeared in print. His <hi rend="italic">Scheme of Literary Prophecy</hi>
                    was replied to by several writers, and particularly by Dr John Rogers, in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Necessity of Divine Revelation asserted;</hi> in answer to
                    which our author wrote <hi rend="italic">A Letter to the Reverend Dr
                        Rogers,</hi> on the occasion on this publication. His health began to
                    decline some years before his death; and he was much afflicted with the stone,
                    which at last put an end to his life, at his house in Harley Square, in 1729. He
                    was interred in Oxford Chapel, where a monument, with an epitaph in Latin, was
                    erected to his memory. His curious library was open to men of letters, to whom
                    he readily communicated all the assistance<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194748403?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-8403-0087"/> in his
                    power; he even furnished his antagonists with books to confute himself, and
                    directed them how to give their arguments ail the force of which they were
                    capable. He was, independently of his scepticism, a sincerely good man.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Collins,</hi><hi rend="italic">William,</hi> an
                    admired poet, was born at Chichester about the year 1724. He received his
                    classical education at Winchester, after which he studied at New College in
                    Oxford, was admitted a commoner of King’s College in the same university, and at
                    length elected a demy of Magdalene College. Whilst at Oxford he applied himself
                    to the study of poetry, and published his Oriental Eclogues; after which he came
                    to London. He was naturally possessed of an car for all the varieties of harmony
                    and modulation; his heart was susceptible of the finest feelings of tenderness
                    and humanity, and was particularly carried away by that high enthusiasm which
                    gives to imagination its strongest colouring; and he was at once capable of
                    soothing the ear with the melody of his numbers, of influencing the passions by
                    the force of pathos, and of gratifying the fancy by the luxury of description.
                    With these powers he attempted lyric poetry, and in 1746 published his Odes
                    descriptive and allegorical; but the sale of this work being not at all
                    answerable to its merit, he, from a feeling of indignation, burnt the remaining
                    copies. Being a man of a liberal spirit and small fortune, his pecuniary
                    resources were unhappily soon exhausted; and his life became a miserable example
                    of necessity, indolence, and dissipation. He projected books which he was well
                    able to execute, and became in idea an historian, a critic, and a dramatic poet;
                    but he wanted the means and encouragement to carry these ideas into execution.
                    Day succeeded day, for the support of which he had made no provision; and he was
                    obliged to subsist, either by the repeated contributions of friends or the
                    generosity of casual acquaintance. His spirits became oppressed, and he sunk
                    into a sullen despondence. Whilst in this gloomy state of mind, his uncle
                    Colonel Martin died, and left him a considerable fortune. But this came too late
                    for enjoyment; he had been so long harassed by anxiety and distress, that he
                    fell into a nervous disorder, which at length reduced the finest understanding
                    to the most deplorable childishness. In the first stages of this disorder he
                    endeavoured to relieve himself by travelling, and passed into France; but his
                    growing malady obliged him to return; and having, with short intervals,
                    continued in this pitiable state till the year 1756, he died in the arms of his
                    sister.</p>
                <p part="N">The following character of the poetry of Collins is drawn by Mrs
                    Barbauld, and is extracted from an essay prefixed to an edition of his works
                    published in 1797. “Fie will be acknowledged to possess imagination, sweetness,
                    bold and figurative language. His numbers dwell on the ear, and easily fix
                    themselves in the memory. His vein of sentiment is by turns tender and lofty,
                    always tinged with a degree of melancholy, but not possessing any claim to
                    originality. His originality consists in his manner, in the highly figurative
                    garb &lt;n which he clothes abstract ideas, in the felicity of his expressions,
                    and his skill in embodying ideal creations. He had much of the mysticism of
                    poetry, and sometimes became obscure, by aiming at impressions stronger than he
                    had clear and well-defined ideas to support. Had his life been prolonged, and
                    had lie with life enjoyed that ease which is necessary for the undisturbed
                    exercise of the faculties, he would probably have risen far above most of his
                    contemporaries.”</p>
                <p part="N">lhe last and best edition of his works is that published by the Rev. A.
                    Dyce in 1827, in 8vo. It contains his Life by Dr Johnson, observations on his
                    writings by Dr Langhorne, and biographical and critical notes by the editor.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
