<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-4448-0552-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CURRENT, or Currant</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207659">Cambodia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205085">Romania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134302">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025743">Monsoons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p025">Currents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nq8t">Driving</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fq16">Monsoons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194754448?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CURRENT, or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Currant</hi></label>, a term used to express the present time. W <hi
                        rend="superscript"> τ</hi> ith regard to commerce, the price current of any
                    merchandise is the known and ordinary price which is given for it. The term is
                    also used for any thing which has course, or is received in commerce; in which
                    sense we say, <hi rend="italic">current coin, current wages,</hi> and the
                    like.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Current,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Navigation,</hi>
                    a certain progressive movement of the water of the sea, by which all bodies
                    floating therein are compelled to alter their course or velocity, or both, and
                    submit to the laws imposed on them by the current.</p>
                <p part="N">In the sea, currents are either natural and general, arising from the
                    diurnal rotation of the earth about its axis, or accidental and particular,
                    caused by the waters being driven against promontories, or into gulfsand
                    straits, where, wanting room to spread, they are driven back, and thus disturb
                    the ordinary flux of the sea. Currents arc various, and directed towards
                    different parts of the ocean; and some are constant, while others are
                    periodical. The most extraordinary current of the sea is that by which part of
                    the Atlantic or African Ocean moves about Guinea from Cape Verd towards the
                    curvature or Bay of Africa, which is called Fernando Po, namely, from west to
                    east, contrary to the general motion; and such is the force of this current,
                    that when ships approach too near the shore, it carries them violently towards
                    the bay, and deceives the mariners in their reckoning. There are a great variety
                    of shifting currents, which do not last, but return at certain periods; most of
                    these, however, depend upon and follow the anniversary winds or monsoons, which,
                    by blowing in one place, may cause a current in another. Varenius informs us,
                    that at Java, in the Straits of Sunda, when the monsoons blow from the west,
                    that is, in the month of May, the currents set to the eastward, contrary to the
                    general motion. Between the islands of Celebes and Madura, when the western
                    monsoons set in, that is, in December, January, and February, or when the winds
                    blow from the north-west, or between the north and west, the currents set to the
                    south-east, or between the south and east. At Ceylon,from the middle of March
                    till October, the currents set to the southward, and in the other parts of the
                    year to the northward, because at this time the southern monsoons blow, and at
                    the other times the northern. Between Cochin-China and Malacca, when the western
                    monsoons blow, that is, from April to August, the currents set eastward against
                    the general motion; but the rest of the year they set westward, the monsoon
                    conspiring with the general motion. They run so strongly in these seas, that
                    unexperienced sailors mistake them for waves which beat upon the rocks, and are
                    usually known by the name of breakers. In like manner, for some months after the
                    middle of February, the currents set from the Maldives towards India on the
                    east, against the general motion of the sea. On the shore of China and Cambodia,
                    in the months of October, November, and December, the currents set to the
                    north-west, and from January to the south-west, when they run with such rapidity
                    about the shoals of Parcel, that they seem swifter than an arrow. At Pulo
                    Condorc, upon the coast of Cambodia, though the monsoons are shifting, yet the
                    currents set strongly towards the east, even when they blow to a contrary point.
                    Along the coasts of the Bay of Bengal, as far as Cape Romania, at∣ the extreme
                    point of Malacca, the current runs southward in November and December. When the
                    monsoons blow from China to Malacca, the sea runs swiftly from Pulo Cambi to
                    Pulo Condore, on the coast of Cambodia. In the Bay of Sans Bras, not far from
                    the Cape of Good Hope, there is a remarkable current, where the sea runs from
                    east to west to the landward; and the more vehemently that it is opposed by
                    winds from a contrary direction. The cause is undoubtedly owing to some adjacent
                    shore which is higher than this. In the Straits of Gibraltar the currents almost
                    constantly drive to the eastward, and carry ships into the Mediterranean ,∙ they
                    are also found to drive the same way into St George’s Channel.</p>
                <p part="N">The setting or progressive motion of the current may be cither quite
                    down to the bottom, or to a certain determinate depth. As the knowledge of the
                    direction and velocity of currents is a very material point in navigation, it is
                    highly necessary to discover both, in order to ascertain the ship’s situation
                    and course with as much accuracy as possible. The most successful method which
                    has been hitherto practised by mariners for this purpose, is the following:—A
                    common iron pot, containing four or five gallons, is suspended by a small rope,
                    fastened to its ear or handles, so as to hang directly upright, as when placed
                    upon the fire. This rope, which may be from seventy to a hundred fathoms in
                    length, being prepared for the experiment, is coiled in the boat, which is
                    hoisted out of the ship at a proper opportunity, when there is little or no wind
                    to ruffle the surface of the sea. The pot being then thrown overboard into the
                    water, and immediately sinking, the line is slackened till about seventy or
                    eighty fathoms are run out; after which it is fastened to the boat’s stem, by
                    which she is accordingly restrained and rides at an anchor. The velocity of the
                    current is then easily tried by the log and half-minute glass, the usual method
                    of discovering the rate of a ship’s sailing at sea. The course of the stream is
                    next obtained by the compass provided for this operation. And having thus found
                    the setting and drift of the current, it next remains to apply this experiment
                    to nautical purposes; for which sec the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Navigation.</hi><hi rend="italic">Under-Cυr</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"
                        > i</hi><hi rend="italic">RF.Nτs</hi> are distinct from the upper or
                    apparent currents, and in different places set or drive a contrary way.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
