<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1028-0988-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42n4zk6c">Complexion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079619">Protectionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1738976">Employability</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885283">Curing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1028" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZINZENDQRF, <hi rend="smallcaps">NIcholas Lewis, Count
                            of</hi></label>, the noted founder of the German religious sect called
                        <hi rend="italic">Moravians</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Herrnhutters,</hi> or,
                    as they pretend, the restorer of that society, was born in the year 1700. From
                    his own narrative it appears, that when he came of age in 1721, his thoughts
                    were wholly bent on gathering together a little society of believers, among whom
                    he might live, and who should entirely employ themselves in exercises of
                    devotion under him. He accordingly purchased an estate at Ber-tholsdorf in Upper
                    Lusatia, where, being joined by some followers, he gave the cure of the village
                    to a person of his own complexion; and Bertholsdorf soon became conspicuous for
                    a new mode of piety. One Christian David, a carpenter, brought a few proselytes
                    from Moravia: they began a new town about half a league from the village, where
                    Count Zinzendorf fixed his residence among them, and whither great numbers of
                    Moravians flocked and established themselves under his protection; so that in
                    1732 their number amounted to 600. An adjacent hill, called the <hi
                        rend="italic">Huthberg,</hi> gave occasion to these colonists to call their
                    new settlement <hi rend="italic">Huth des Herrn,</hi> and afterwards <hi
                        rend="italic">Herrnhuth;</hi> which may be interpreted “The guard or
                    protection of the Lord ;” and from this the whole sect have taken their name.
                    The count spared neither pains nor money to propagate his opinions: he went
                    himself over all Europe, and at least twice to America; and sent missionaries
                    throughout the world. He died at Herrnhutt on the 9th of May 1760.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
