<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-1029-0989-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899028">Drum</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141797">Tabor</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06587">Drum</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=1029" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZISKA, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, a famous
                    general of the forces of the Hussites, was born in Bohemia about the year 1380.
                    His proper name was Trocznow; but he entered very young into the army, and after
                    distinguishing himself on several occasions, lost an eye in a battle, whence he
                    was called <hi rend="italic">Ziska,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">One-eyed.</hi> At
                    length the reformation, begun by John Huss, spreading throughout almost all
                    Bohemia, Ziska placed himself at the head of the Hussites, and had soon under
                    his command a body of 40,000 men. With this army he gained several victories
                    over those of the Romish religion, who carried on a kind of crusade against
                    them; and built a town in an advantageous situation, to which he gave the name
                    of <hi rend="italic">Tabor,</hi> whence the Hussites were afterwards called <hi
                        rend="italic">Tabοrites.</hi> Ziska lost his other eye by an arrow at the
                    siege of the city of Rubi; but this did not prevent his continuing the war, his
                    fighting battles, and gaining several great victories, among which was that of
                    Ausig on the Elbe, in which 9000 of the enemy were left dead on the field. The
                    emperor Sigismund, alarmed at his progress, caused very advantageous proposals
                    to be made to him, which he readily accepted, and set out to meet Sigismund, but
                    died on the road, on the 11th of October 1424. He ordered that his body should
                    be left a prey to the birds and wild beasts, and that a drum should be made of
                    his skin, being persuaded that the enemy would fly as soon as they heard the
                    sound. It is added that the Hussites executed his will; and that the news of
                    this order made such an impression on the disturbed imaginations of the German
                    papists, that in many battles they actually fled at the beat of the drum with
                    the utmost precipitation, leaving their baggage and artillery behind them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
