<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-2030-0366-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CORNWALL (7th edition, volume 7, page 366)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:879476">Cornish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151376">Tinning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151272">Tin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047551">Ores</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nk3w">Tin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7c14w">Tinning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194752030?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CORNWALL</label> is the most westerly county in England, and
                    stretches also farthest to the south. It is bounded on all sides by the sea,
                    except on the east, where it meets Devonshire in a few places, and is separated
                    from it, for the most part, by the river Tamar. From this last boundary its
                    breadth is diminished till it terminates on the west at the Land’s End, in west
                    longitude 6°, and on the south at the Lizard Point, in north latitude 49° 57'
                    30". assuming somewhat of the form of a cornucopia; its boundaries, the Bristol
                    Channel on the north and the English Channel on the south, meeting in a point at
                    the promontory on the west. It is situated in the diocese of Exeter, belongs to
                    the western circuit, extends over 758,484 acres, or a little more than 1185
                    square miles, and contains nine hundreds, 201 parishes, twenty-three market
                    towns, and, in 1811, 216,667 inhabitants, being nearly 183 to the square mile,
                    or about one individual for every three acres and a half. The waste lands are
                    about one fifth of the whole. The surface is very irregular, ascending and
                    descending in rapid succession. The interior is high and generally unfertile,
                    consisting for the most part of rugged heaths and moors; yet Brown Willy, the
                    highest hill, is only 1868 feet above the level of the sea at low water. Some
                    beautifully picturesque valleys intervene, richly diversified with corn, woods,
                    coppices, orchards, rivulets, and verdant meadows. The stupendous rocks which
                    form the great barriers against the ocean, particularly about the Land’s End and
                    the Lizard, are fitted to inspire the mind with the most sublime conceptions;
                    whilst the remains of an early age, military, civil, and religious, dispersed
                    over the county, present, in striking contrast, the small scale on which the
                    works of man are conducted, and the instability of human affairs. Throughout the
                    higher lands the soil is a light black earth, intermixed with gravel, the
                    detritus of the granite, or <hi rend="italic">growarì,</hi> as it is here
                    called; but a light loam, mixed with slaty matter, is the most prevalent on the
                    gentle declivities and lower grounds. Clay is found in different places, of
                    various quality. One kind is made into bricks, which are in request for
                    furnaces, and another is much valued when formed into moulds for casting metals.
                    For nine months in the year the wind blows from points between the west and
                    south, bringing with it from the Atlantic vast bodies of clouds, which, being
                    broken by the narrow ridge-like hills of the county, descend in frequent
                    showers. Storms are more frequent and violent than in the inland parts of
                    England, particularly from the north-west; but from this quarter the wind is
                    generally dry, and brings fair weather. The climate is healthy, and there are
                    numerous instances of longevity. Snow seldom lies for a few days. The myrtle,
                    the bahn of Gilead, and many other tender plants and shrubs, live and thrive in
                    the open air; yet the most hardy trees on the sea coast sustain much injury from
                    the violence of the westerly wind, and the sea spray, which it drives with great
                    force before it. The only shrub which seems to bear the sea air is the tamarisk,
                    which grows to the height of ten or twelve feet in seven years, in situations
                    most exposed to <pb break="no" facs="nls:194752043?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-2043-0367"/> the sea, forming an admirable shelter, and, as it
                    bears cutting, might be useful also as a fence; yet it is destroyed by severe
                    frosts. The cuttings by which it is propagated take root without difficulty.
                    Till within these few years, the attempt to raise plantations was scarcely ever
                    successful; but latterly, the pĩneaster being first planted as a shelter to the
                    more tender trees, their appearance is more promising. The principal rivers are
                    the Tamar, the Lyn-her, the Looe, the Fawy, the Camel or Alan, and the Fal. The
                    Tamar is the most considerable. It rises on the summit of a moor in the parish
                    of Morvinstow, the most northern in the county, and, taking a southerly
                    direction, falls, along with several tributary streams, into the spacious basin
                    called the Hamoaze, and issuing thence between Mount Edgecumbe and the Devil’s
                    Point, unites with the waters of the Plym; and the conflux of these rivers with
                    the sea forms the noble road for shipping named Plymouth Sound.</p>
                <p>The landed property of Cornwall is very much divided, few estates producing a
                    rent of more than L.3000, exclusive of the underground revenues, which are
                    continually fluctuating. What are called the Duchy lands are far more extensive.
                    The income derived from them, and from the duty on the coinage of tin, are the
                    only parts unalienated of the immense hereditary revenues which formerly
                    constituted an independent provision for the heir-apparent to the crown. This
                    provision was originally made by Edward III. for his eldest son, Edward the
                    Black Prince, whom he created Duke of Cornwall, with special limitation to the
                    first begotten sons of him and his sons, kings of England for ever. The
                    occupiers of these estates are lessees under the Dnke of Cornwall, and generally
                    purchase an interest in the land during three lives, the consideration being a
                    fine paid at the time of the grant, and also a reserved rent during the lease. A
                    lease for three lives is common on church lands, and formerly was not unfrequent
                    also on private estates. Leases at rack-rent seldom exceed fourteen years. The
                    farms are in general very small, the rents, even in the most fertile parts,
                    being only from L.30 to L.50, and, in the western and mining’ districts, they
                    are chiefly cottage holdings. Agriculture, being but a subordinate concern here,
                    is not generally pursued with much spirit and success; and the fines paid for
                    their long leases deprive the farmers <hi rend="italic">of</hi> that capital
                    which should be invested in the improvement of the soil from year to year. Their
                    best cattle are of the North Devon breed, which is much employed in labour. The
                    native sheep of the county, now nearly extinct, was one of the worst
                    descriptions in Britain. A great many different breeds have been introduced from
                    other districts. The backs of horses or mules are used more frequently than
                    carts or waggons as the means of transport. Barley, oats, and potatoes are grow
                    n beyond the consumption, though the course of cropping is generally most
                    exhausting; but a large quantity of wheat or flour is imported for the mining
                    districts. In the neighbourhood of Penzance two crops of potatoes are commonly
                    obtained every year. Sea-sand, sea-weed, and damaged pilchards, are used to a
                    considerable extent as manure.</p>
                <p>Cornwall has long been distinguished by its mineral treasures, of which the most
                    considerable are tin and copper. The strata in which these metals are found
                    extend from the Land’s End, in a direction from west to east, to the Dartmoor
                    Hills, in Devonshire, and consist chiefly of granite and a variety of the
                    grauwackc, here called <hi rend="italic">killas.</hi> The chief seat of the
                    mines now lies in the neighbourhood and to the westward of St Λustel, from which
                    place to the Land’s End the principal mines are to be found, extending along the
                    northern coast, and keeping a breadth of about seven miles. These metals are
                    commonly found in veins or fissures called <hi rend="italic">lodes, of</hi>
                    which the sides or walls do not always consist of the same substance, nor are
                    they equally hard; for, though one side -of the fissure may be a dense stone,'
                    the other is sometimes as soft as clay. Many lesser veins branch from the great
                    lodes like the boughs of a tree, and at last terminate in threads. The
                    indications of a vein of metal are varions, such as scattered fragments of ore,
                    called <hi rend="italic">shades,</hi> and the metallic taste of springs. Many
                    rich lodes have been discovered by working <hi rend="italic">drifts</hi> across
                    the county, in the directions of north and south. From the course (if the metals
                    being from west to east, the lode will thus be cut at right angles. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mining.</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> z</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Tin,</hi> the most important mineral of this county, is found
                    collected and fixed, and also in a loose and dispersed form. In the former
                    state, it is either in a lode, or <hi rend="italic">a floor</hi> which is a
                    horizontal layer of the ore; or interspersed in grains and small masses in the
                    natural rock. The same lode that has continued perpendicular for several
                    fathoms, is sometimes found to extend suddenly into a floor. In its dispersed
                    form it is met with either in a pulverized state, in separate stones called <hi
                    rend="italic">shades,</hi> cr in a continued course of stones called a <hi
                    rend="italic">stream.</hi> These streams are of different breadths, seldom less
                    than a fathom, and often scattered, though in different quantities, over the
                    whole tract in which they are found. When several streams meet they frequently
                    make a very rich floor. The principal stream work is at Carnon, between Truro
                    and Penryn.</p>
                <p>The most common state in which tin is found in this county is the calcifonn, the
                    greater part of the ore being indurated or glass-like, and its most prevalent
                    matrix is either an argillaceous or a siliceous substance, or a stone composed
                    of both, called by the miners <hi rend="italic">caple.</hi> None of the
                    calcareous genus ever appears contiguous to the ore, except the <hi
                    rend="italic">fluors.</hi> The oxides of iron and arsenic are those with which
                    the. tin is most frequently blended. When raised from the mine it is divided
                    into as many shares or <hi rend="italic">doles</hi> as there are lords and
                    adventurers. Every mine possesses the privilege of having the ore distributed on
                    the adjacent fields. It is generally pounded or stamped on the spot, and when it
                    is small enough to pass through the holes of an iron grate fixed in one end of
                    the box where the <hi rend="italic">lifters</hi> work, it is carried by a small
                    stream into pits, from which it is transferred into a large vat, washed, and
                    rendered sufficiently clear for the smelting-house. The tin, when wrought into
                    metal, is cast into blocks weighing from to cwt. each, which are not saleable
                    till assayed by the proper officers, and stamped with the duchy seal. This is
                    termed <hi rend="italic">coining</hi> the tin. Since the reign of Henry VIII.
                    the coinages have been held regularly four times annually, at Lady Day,
                    Midsummer, Michaelmas, and Christmas, at the stannary towns of Launceston,
                    Lostwithiel, Truro, and Helston, to which Penzance was added by Charles II. The
                    annual produce of the tin mines is about 25,000 blocks, each worth ten guineas
                    on an average.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Copper ores</hi> are found in great abundance and variety.
                    Veins are frequently discovered in cliff’s that are laid bare by the sea. The
                    most encouraging indication of a rich ore is an earthy ochreous stone, called
                    <hi rend="italic">gossan,</hi> which is of a reddish colour, and crumbles like
                    the rust of iron. The ore does not lie at any particular depth, but it is a
                    general rule, that, when copper is discovered in any fissure, the lode should be
                    sunk upon, as it commonly proves best at some distance below the surface. When
                    the metal has been properly refined, it is poured into oblong iron moulds, each
                    containing about 150 lbs. weight. In the General View of the county, printed in
                    1794, the produce of all the copper mines is said to be about 40,000 tons of
                    ore, yielding 4700 tons of copper, then worth L.8 a ton.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194752056?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-2056-0368"/>
                <p>Many other minerals have been found in this county, and much eapital and labour
                    have been employed in working some of them, without their yielding any adequate
                    return; yet the success has been in a few instances so great, that new mines are
                    opened as fast as the old ones are abandoned. We ean only mention some of the
                    more important. <hi rend="italic">Lead</hi> mines are not numerous; and the kind
                    of ore most frequently found is <hi rend="italic">galena,</hi> or pure sulphuret
                    of lead, whieh is met with both crystallized and in masses. The principal mines
                    are Hucl Pool and Huel Rose, near Hcl-ston. <hi rend="italic">Gold</hi> has been
                    discovered, but not in such quantity as to warrant expensive operations to
                    proeure it. <hi rend="italic">Silver</hi> is reported to have been obtained here
                    in so large a quantity, in the reigns of Edward I. and Edward III., as
                    materially to aid the warlike enterprises of these monarchs; but recent searehes
                    have not been so successful. <hi rend="italic">Iron</hi> ores; <hi rend="italic"
                    >sulphuret of iron,</hi> of the various colours of blue, green, purple, gold,
                    silver, and eopper, often intermixed with the eopper lodes; <hi rend="italic"
                    >bismuth, zinc, antimony, cobalt, arsenic, manganese, wolfram, menachanitc,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">molybdena</hi> or sulphuret of molybdenum, are all found
                    here, most of them in considerable abundance. According to Phillips’ map of the
                    mines in 1800, there were wrought at that time forty-five of eopper,
                    twenty-eight of tin, eighteen of copper and tin, two of lead, one of silver, one
                    of lead and silver, one of copper and silver, one of copper and cobalt, one of
                    tin and eobalt, and one of antimony.</p>
                <p>Among the other fossil substances of this county, those that deserve to be
                    mentioned for their value are <hi rend="italic">slate,</hi> of which there is an
                    excellent quality wrought near Tintagel, in the northern part of the county; a
                    <hi rend="italic">freestone,</hi> resembling the Portland and Bath stone, in the
                    parishes of Carantoe and the lower St Colomb; and the celebrated <hi
                    rend="italic">soap-rock,</hi> between the Lizard and Mullion, used in the
                    manufacture of porcelain, and rented by the proprietors of that establishment in
                    Worcester. But the most important of these substances is what is ealled the <hi
                    rend="italic">Chinastone,</hi> found in the parish of St Stephen, near St
                    Anstcl, which forms a principal ingredient in all the Staffordshire pottery. It
                    is a decomposed granite, the felspar of whieh has lost the property of
                    fusibility. At Truro it has been manufactured into retorts and crucibles. To
                    these may be added the <hi rend="italic">Cornish diamonds,</hi> supposed to be
                    the finest in England, consisting of beautifully transparent quartz,
                    crystallized in six-sided pyramids; and a curious production, called the <hi
                    rend="italic">swimming stone,</hi> found in a copper mine near Redruth, the
                    cellular structure of which renders it lighter than water.</p>
                <p>Of the fish whieh frequent the Cornish coast, the pilchard is the most abundant
                    and valuable. In size and form it differs but little from the common herring.
                    Immense shoals appear during the summer and autumn, the first generally arriving
                    at the Land’s End in the middle of July. The principal fisheries on the southern
                    coast are in Mount’s Bay, and thence eastward to Devonshire; and, on the
                    northern side, at St Ives. The pilehards are caught in nets called <hi
                    rend="italic">seenes,</hi> each of which is managed by three boats, containing
                    from seventeen to twenty-four men, the largest kind being two hundred and twenty
                    fathoms long, sixteen fathoms deep in the middle, and fourteen at each end. When
                    brought on shore they are carried to storehouses, or <hi rend="italic"
                    >cellars</hi> as they are termed, where the small and broken fish are picked
                    out. They are then disposed in layers on the pavement of the cellar, salt being
                    strewed between every layer. In this state they remain for about six weeks,
                    after which they are taken up, washed, and placed in hogsheads, where, by means
                    of a powerful lever, they are pressed so closely as, when turned out, to appear
                    in a eompact state. By this process the oil is extracted, which runs out of the
                    casks through holes made for the purpose. Forty-eight hogsheads generally yield
                    a tun of two hundred and fifty-two gallons. The <hi rend="italic">blower</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">Jin fish,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">grampus,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">porpoise or sea-hog,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">blue shark,</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">seafox,</hi> visit the coasts of this county. Among
                    the flat fish is a most uncommon one named <hi rend="italic">the monk</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">angel</hi> fish, the <hi rend="italic">turbot,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">sea-adder,</hi> and the singular fish called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >sunfish. Mackarel</hi> is caught in great plenty on the southern coast; also
                    the <hi rend="italic">red mullet,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">John
                    Dory</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">conger cels of</hi> an
                    extremely large size, weighing from sixty to a hundred and twenty pounds, are
                    met with near the shores. <hi rend="italic">Oysters</hi> are also found in great
                    abundance.</p>
                <p>The name of Cornwall is supposed by some to be compounded of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Carn,</hi> signifying “a rock” in the British lan- <hi rend="superscript">
                    l</hi> guage, and <hi rend="italic">Gauls</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Waals,</hi>
                    the name whieh the Saxons gave to the Britons. Others, however, think it is
                    derived from the Latin <hi rend="italic">cornu,</hi> or the British <hi
                    rend="italic">kern,</hi> “a horn on account of its running out into the sea
                    somewhat in the form of a horn. Hither the ancient Britons, as in Wales, retired
                    on the intrusion of the Saxons, where they opposed their further conquests. In
                    this part of the island theyform-ed a kingdom which existed for many years
                    afterwards under different princes, amongst whom were Ambrosius Aurelius, and
                    the justly celebrated Arthur; nor were they subdued till the middle of the
                    seventh century, from which time Cornwall was considered as subject to the West
                    Saxon kings, who began their sovereignty in 519, and continued it till 828,
                    under eighteen sovereigns, the last of whom was the great Egbert, who subdued
                    all the others, and, by uniting them, formed the kingdom of England, when this
                    country was included in the county of Devon, then the ninth division. This
                    accounts for Alfred’s not mentioning Cornwall, which, on forming the cireuĩts
                    after the Norman conquest, was included in the western eircuit. In 1337 Edward
                    III. erected it into a dukedom, and invested with it Edward the Black Prince.
                    But this, according to the express words of the grant, is limited to the first
                    born son and heir, on whieh account Richard II. was created duke of Cornwall by
                    charter. So was Henry V. by his father Henry IV. Henry VI. delivered the duchy
                    to his son Prinee Edward, and Edward IV. ereated his son Edward V. Duke of
                    Cornwall, as did Henry VII. his son, afterwards Henry VIII. upon the death of
                    his elder brother Arthur. James I. ereated his son Henry duke of Cornwall, which
                    title on his decease came to his brother Charles. The eldest sons of succeeding
                    kings have enjoyed this title by inheritance. These not only appoint the
                    sheriff, but all writs, deeds, &amp;c. are in their name, and not in the king’s;
                    and they have also peculiar royalties and prerogatives distinct from the crown,
                    for which they appoint officers.</p>
                <p>The Cornish language is a dialect of that which, till thel Saxons came in, was
                    common to all Britain, and more anciently to Ireland and Gaul; but the
                    inhabitants of this island being dispersed before those conquests, and driven
                    into Wales and Cornwall, and thence into Bretagne, the same language, for want
                    of frequent intercourse, became differently pronounced and written, and in
                    different degrees mixed with other languages. Hence arose the Welsh, the
                    Cornish, and the Armorie dialects, the roots of which are so much alike that
                    they are known and admitted by the inhabitants of either eountry; but the
                    grammar is so varied that they cannot converse. The Cornish is reckoned the most
                    pleasing of the three. It was spoken so generally here down to the reign of
                    Henry VIII. that Dr John Moreman, vicar ofMynhinet, is said to have been the
                    first who taught his parishioners the Lord’s prayer, the creed, and ten
                    commandments, in English; and at the reformation the natives desired the service
                    in English.</p>
                <p>Cornwall returns four members to parliament.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194752069?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0707-2069-0369"/>
                <p>The following are the returns of the population for the years ending 1811, 1S21,
                    and 1831.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>YEARS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>
                            0</p><p>ω</p><p>i</p><p>Λ C</p><p>M</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many <hi rend="superscript">
                            r</hi> Families occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript"> r</hi>
                            β</p><p>Q</p><p>Lθ</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">CS</hi></p><p>.s ’S
                            Þ</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, or Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding classes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1811</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37,971</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44,189</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17,465</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10,954</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15,770</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>103,310</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>113,357</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>216,667</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>43,873</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>51,202</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1820</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19,302</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15,543</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16,357</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>124,817</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>132,630</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>257,447</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>146,949</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>155,491</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>302,440</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
