<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-8888-0145-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CARLYLE, Joseph Dacre (7th edition, volume 6, page
                    145)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn1111w">Scholars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:861575">Circassians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193348888?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CARLYLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph Dacre</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished orientalist, and general scholar, was the son of a physician at
                    Carlisle, and was born there in the year 1759. He received his early education
                    in the learned languages at the grammar-school of that city. In 1775 he
                    proceeded to Cambridge, obtained his bachelor’s degree in 1779, and was elected
                    a fellow of Queen’s College in that university. He left college in 1783, after
                    taking his master’s degree, and returned to his native city, where he obtained
                    some church preferment. In 1793, upon the resignation of Dr Paley, he succeeded
                    to the chancellorship of the diocesc of Carlisle.</p>
                <p>Mr Carlyle had early devoted much of his attention to an accurate study of the
                    Arabic language, in which pursuit he had been assisted by a native of Bagdad,
                    who resided some time with him at the university. Having thus attained to great
                    proficiency in the language and literature of the Arabians, he in 1792 appeared
                    before the public as the translator of an inedited historical work in that
                    language, known under the name of the <hi rend="italic">Aĩaured Allatafet.</hi>
                    The author of this work was Jemaleddin, a person of the rank of Emir, and
                    distinguished among the eastern writers by the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historiographer of Egypt,</hi> on account of his great attention to the
                    improvement of its history. The <hi rend="italic">Maured Allatafet</hi> is an
                    epitome made by Jemaleddin himself of a larger work, which comprised a complete
                    history of that country, from the first establishment of the Arabian government
                    to the eight hundred and fifty-seventh year of the Hegira. In reviewing the
                    epitome with a view to its publication, Mr Carlyle thought proper to retrench
                    that part of it which relates to the caliphs of Bagdad, thcir history being, as
                    he conceived, sufficiently illustrated in other writings; so that his
                    publication· commences with the first of the <hi rend="italic">Fatimite</hi>
                    caliphs, who reigned in Egypt; and it ends, where the original epitome also
                    terminates, with the reign of Almalec Alashrof, the twelfth of the Circassian
                    race of sultans, thus comprising a period of nearly five hundred years. However
                    creditable to Mr Carlyle’s attainments in eastern learning, this treatise is not
                    thought to have added much to the stock of historical knowledge, or to suggest
                    any high ideas of the merit of that larger work from which it was abridged, and
                    which procured Jemaleddin so much renown in the East. The title of Mr Carlyle’s
                    publication is as follows :—“<hi rend="italic">Maured Allatafet
                    Jenιaleddini,</hi><hi rend="italic">filii</hi><hi rend="italic">Togri
                    Pardii,</hi> seu rerum Egypticarum Annales, ab anno Christi 971, usque ad annum
                    1453. E Codice MS. Bibliothecae Acadcmiae Cambrigiensis. Arab, et Lat. 4to.”</p>
                <p>In 1794 Mr Carlyle was elected professor of Arabic in the University of
                    Cambridge; and in 1796 he gave to the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193348901?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-8901-0146"/> world another
                    and more pleasing proof of his zealous endeavours to illustrate the literature
                    of the East, in a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Specimens of Arabian Poetry,
                    from the earliest time to the extinction of the Caliphat</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi><hi rend="italic">with some Account of the Authors.</hi> Arab, and Eng.
                    8vo. His object was, by arranging the pieces in chronological order, and
                    accompanying each with some account of the author, and of the occasion of the
                    composition, to exhibit a sort of history of Arabian poetry during the most
                    splendid period of the Mahommedan empire. Many of these pieces possess
                    considerable beauty; but as Mr Carlyle had it in view to exemplify the different
                    species of poetical composition, he has accordingly translated some specimens,
                    in which he was himself sensible there was nothing to be prized, either in the
                    thought or the execution. Like most of those who have become eminent in eastern
                    learning, Professor Carlyle is thought to have formed too high an estimate of
                    its merits; but all must admit that his <hi rend="italic">Specimens,</hi> with
                    their prefaces, form an elegant and interesting work; one which, to use his own
                    words, cannot but prove acceptable to “those who wish to gain an insight into
                    the history of manners, and who love to trace the operations of the human mind
                    in distant countries and various situations.” A second edition of this work was
                    published in 1810.</p>
                <p>When the Earl of Elgin was appointed ambassador to the Porte in 1799, Professor
                    Carlyle was invited to accompany him as an accredited agent of the British
                    government, for the purpose of literary research; and in that capacity he
                    accordingly proceeded to the East. After remaining some time in Constantinople,
                    he left that capital in January 1800, and proceeded through Asia Minor and
                    Cyprus to Palestine; in which tour he was employed till the following July, when
                    he returned to Constantinople. He again quitted this city in March 1801, and
                    visited the Troad, the convents of Mount Athos, and several parts of Greece. He
                    appears to have spent three weeks amongst these celebrated convents, where,
                    being furnished with recommendations from the government, and the Patriarch of
                    Constantinople, he was received with marked kindness, and enjoyed every
                    opportunity for literary research. From Athens, where he spent some time,
                    assisted in his inquiries by the artists employed by Lord Elgin, he proceeded in
                    a Ragusan vessel to Malta, and afterwards to Naples, where he arrived in July
                    1801. Soon thereafter he set out for England, and reached his native city early
                    in the month of October. <hi rend="italic">(Addenda to the Remains of John
                    Tweddall,</hi> 1816, 4to.)</p>
                <p>Soon after his return he was presented by the Bishop of Carlisle to the living of
                    Newcastle-upon-Tyne; but this he did not long enjoy, for he fell into bad
                    health, and died in the prime of life in April 1804 <hi rend="italic">(Gent.
                    Mag.</hi> 1804). His premature death cut short some useful literary
                    undertakings, and deprived the world of the full fruits of his observations on
                    many interesting scenes, which he had surveyed with the eye of a scholar and the
                    feeling of a poet; for all that the public has derived from his travels is a
                    posthumous volume of poems, with remarks suggested by these scenes; and which,
                    though bearing testimony to his learning and taste, is but a poor substitute for
                    such a work as, with his knowledge and means of information, he could not have
                    failed to produce. The title of this posthumous volume is as follows :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Poems, suggested chiefly by scenes in Asia Minor, Syria, and
                    Greece, with Prefaces extracted from the Authors Journal.</hi> It was published
                    in 4to in 1805, and is embellished with some fine engravings.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
