<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-0857-0530-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GLADIA (7th edition, volume 10, page 530)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qz22m4b">Exhibitions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sn82">Combat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v67j">Fighting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9rd17">Trojans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j97c33">Ostrogoths</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1157298">Trojans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750271">Ostrogoths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120522">Slaves</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918097">Exhibitions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:868926">Combat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814226">Arenas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193520857?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GLADIA</label> Ι ORS, in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi>
                    persons who fought chiefly in the arena of the amphitheatre at Rome, for the
                    entertainment of the people. The gladiators were generally slaves, and fought
                    from necessity <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> though sometimes freemen took to the
                    same profession, like our prize-fighters, for a livelihood. Γhe Romans borrowed
                    this cruel diversion from the Asiatics; and some suppose that there was policy m
                    the practice, the frequent combats of gladiators Unding to accustom the people
                    to despise danger and</p>
                <p>The origin of these combats seems obvious. From the earliest times it had been
                    the custom to sacrifice captives, or prisoners of war, to the manes of the great
                    men who had died in battle. Thus Achilles, in the <hi rend="italic">Iliad,</hi>
                    (lib. xxiii.), sacrificed twelve young Trojans to the manes of Patroclus; and in
                    Virgil (lib. xi. ver. 81), AEneas sent captives to Evander to be sacrificed at
                    the funeral of his son Pallas. But in process of time they came also to
                    sacrifice slaves at the funerals of all persons of condition; and this was even
                    esteemed a necessary part of the ceremony; butas it would have appeared
                    barbarous to massacre them like beasts, they were appointed to fight with each
                    other, and to endeavour to save their own lives by killing their adversary. This
                    seemed somewhat less inhuman, because there was a possibility of avoiding death,
                    by an exertion of skill and courage. The profession of gladiator thus became an
                    art; and hence arose masters of the art, men learned in fighting and exercise.
                    These masters, whom the Latins called <hi rend="italic">lanistoe,</hi> bought
                    slaves to be trained up to this cruel trade, and afterwards sold them to such as
                    had occasion to present the people with so horrible a show.</p>
                <p>The exhibitions were at first performed near the sepulchre of the deceased, or
                    around the funeral pile; but they were afterwards removed to the circus and
                    amphitheatres, and became ordinary amusements. The first show of gladiators,
                    called <hi rend="italic">munus gladiatorium,</hi> was, according to Valerius
                    Maximus, exhibited at Rome by Marcus and Decius Brutus, upon the death of their
                    father, in the year of the city 490. On this occasion there were probably only
                    three pairs of gladiators. In 537 the three sons of Μ. AEmilius Lepidus the
                    augur, who had been thrice consul, entertained the people with the cruel
                    pleasure of seeing twenty-two gladiators fight in the forum. In 547, the first
                    Africanus diverted his army at New Carthage (Carthagena), with a show of
                    gladiators, which ħς exhibited in honour of his father and uncle, who had begun
                    the reduction of Spain. In process of time the Romans became so fond of these
                    bloody entertainments, that not only the heir of any great and rich citizen
                    lately deceased, but all the principal magistrates, presented the people with
                    shows of this nature, to procure their favour. The aediles, praetors, consuls,
                    and, above all, the candidates for offices, made their court to the people by
                    entertaining them frequently with these fights; and even the priests were
                    sometimes exhibitors of these barbarous shows; for we meet with the <hi
                    rend="italic">ludi pontificales</hi> in Suetonius <hi rend="italic"
                    >(August,</hi> cap. 44), and with the <hi rend="italic">ludi sacerdotales,</hi>
                    in Pliny <hi rend="italic">(Ľpist.</hi> lib. vii.). As for the emperors, it was
                    so much their interest to ingratiate themselves with the populace, that they
                    obliged them with combats of gladiators upon almost all occasions; and as these
                    multiplied, the number of combatants likewise increased. Accordingly, Julius
                    Caesar, in his aedileship, diverted the people with the exhibition of three
                    hundred and twenty couples. Titus exhibited a show of gladiators, wild beasts,
                    and representations of sea-fights, which lasted a hundred days; and Trajan
                    continued a solemnity of this nature for a hundred and twenty-three days, during
                    which time he brought out a thousand pairs of gladiators. Before this time, and
                    under the republic, the number of gladiators was so great, that when the
                    conspiracy of Catiline broke out, the senate ordered them to be dispersed into
                    the garrisons and secured, lest they should join the disaffected party.</p>
                <p>These sports at length became so common, and their consequences in a variety of
                    respects proved so dangerous, that Cicero caused a law to be enacted that no
                    person should exhibit a show of gladiators within two years before he appeared
                    as a candidate for any office. Julius Caesar gave orders that only a certain
                    number of men of this profession should be in Rome at a time; Augustus decreed
                    that only two shows of gladiators should be presented in a year, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193520870?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0710-0870-0531"/> and never
                    above sixty couples of combatants in a show; and Tiberius provided by an order
                    of senate, that no person should have the privilege of gratifying the people
                    with such a solemnity unless he was worth 500,000 sesterces. The same
                    exhibitions were also regulated by Nerva. The Emperor Claudius restrained them
                    to certain occasions; but he soon afterwards annulled what he had decreed;
                    private persons began to exhibit them as usual, and some carried the brutal
                    satisfaction so far as to have them at their ordinary feasts.</p>
                <p>The master of the gladiators made them all swear that they would fight to death;
                    and, if they failed, they were put to death by fire, swords, clubs, whips, or
                    the like. It was a crime for the wretches to complain when they were wounded, or
                    to ask for death or seek to avoid it when overcome; but it was usual for the
                    emperor or the people to grant them life when they exhibited no signs of fear,
                    but waited the fatal stroke with courage and intrepidity. Augustus even decreed
                    that life should always be granted them.</p>
                <p>From slaves and freemen the inhuman sport at length spread to people of rank and
                    condition; so that Augustus was obliged to issue an edict providing that none of
                    the senatorian order should become gladiators; and soon afterwards he imposed
                    the same constraint on the knights. Nevertheless Nero is related to have brought
                    upwards of four hundred senators and six hundred Roman knights upon the arena;
                    though Lipsius supposes both these numbers to be falsified, and not without
                    reason reduces them to forty senators and sixty knights. But Domitian refined on
                    the practice of Nero, and exhibited combats of women in the night time.</p>
                <p>Constantine the Great is said to have first prohibited the combats of gladiators
                    in the East; at least he forbade those who were condemned to death for their
                    crimes being employed in these exhibitions; and there is still extant an order
                    to the <hi rend="italic">profectus</hi><hi rend="italic">proetorii,</hi> dated
                    at Berytus in Phoenicia the 1st of October 325.</p>
                <p>The Emperor Honorius forbade them at Rome on occasion of the death of Telemachus,
                    who coming from the East to Rome at the time of one of these spectacles, went
                    down into the arena, and used all his endeavours to prevent the gladiators from
                    continuing the sport; upon which the spectators of the carnage, fired with
                    indignation, stoned him to death. It must be observed, however, that the
                    practice was not entirely abolished in the West before the time of Theodoric
                    king of the Ostrogoths. Honorius, on the occasion first mentioned, had
                    prohibited them; but the prohibition does not seem to have been enforced.
                    Theodoric, in the year 500, finally abolished them.</p>
                <p>Some time before the day of combat, the person who presented the people with
                    these shows gave notice of his intention by programmes or bills, containing the
                    names of the gladiators, and the marks by which they were to be distinguished;
                    for each had his peculiar badge, which was commonly a peacock’s feather, as
                    appears from the scholiast of Juvenal on the 158th verse of the third satire,
                    and also from Turnebus <hi rend="italic">(Advers.</hi> lib. ii. cap 8). They
                    also gave notice how long the shows would last, and how many couples of
                    gladiators were to exhibit; and it even appears, from the seventh satire of the
                    second book of Horace, that they sometimes made representations of these things
                    in painting, as is practised among us by those who have any thing to exhibit at
                    fairs.</p>
                <p>The day being come, they began the entertainment by bringing two kinds of
                    weapons; the first being staves or wooden foils, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >rudes,</hi> and the second effective weapons, as swords, poniards, and the
                    like. The first were called <hi rend="italic">arma lusoria,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">exercitoria</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the second <hi
                    rend="italic">decretoria,</hi> as being given by decree or sentence by the
                    praetor, or by him at whose expense the spectacle was exhibited. They began to
                    fence or skirmish with the first, which usually formed the prelude to the
                    battle; and from these, when well warmed, they advanced to the second at the
                    sound of the trumpets, with which they fought naked. Then they were said <hi
                    rend="italic">vertere</hi><hi rend="italic">arma.</hi> The terms of striking
                    were <hi rend="italic">petere et repetere</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> of
                    avoiding a blow, <hi rend="italic">exire</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi> and when
                    one of the combatants received a remarkable wound, his adversary or the people
                    cried out, <hi rend="italic">Habet,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">hoc</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">habet.</hi> The first part of the engagement was called <hi
                    rend="italic">ventilare, proludere;</hi> and the second, <hi rend="italic"
                    >dimicare</hi><hi rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">certum,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">or</hi><hi rend="italic">versis armis pugnare</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and some authors think, with much probability, that it is
                    to these two kinds of combat that St Paul alludes in the passage(1 Cor. ix. 26,
                    27) where he says, “Ifight not as one that beateth the air; but I keep my body,
                    and bring it into subjection.”</p>
                <p>If the vanquished surrendered his arms, it was not in the victor’s power to grant
                    him life; it was the people during the time of the republic, and the prince or
                    people during the time of the empire, who were alone empowered to grant this
                    boon. The reward of the conqueror was a branch of palm tree, and a sum of money,
                    probably collected amongst the spectators; sometimes they gave him his congé, or
                    dismissed him by putting one of the wooden foils or <hi rend="italic">rudes</hi>
                    in his hand; and sometimes they even granted him his freedom, putting the
                    pilaeus on his head. The sign or indication by which the spectators showed that
                    they granted the favour, was <hi rend="italic">premere pollicem,</hi> which Μ.
                    Dacier takes to be a clenching of the figures of both hands between one another,
                    and so holding the two thumbs upright, close together; and, when they desired to
                    have the combat finished and the vanquished slain, <hi rend="italic">verterunt
                    pollicem,</hi> they bent back the thumb, as we learn from Juvenal. (Sat. iii.
                    ver. 36.) The gladiators challenged or defied each other by showing the little
                    finger; and, by extending this, or some other, during the combat, they owned
                    themselves vanquished, and begged mercy from the people. <hi rend="italic">Victi
                    ostensam digiti veniam a populo postulabant,</hi> says the old scholiast on
                    Perseus.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
