<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-1642-0141-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ADANSON, Michael (7th edition, volume 2, page
                    141)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047777">Organization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938974">Baobab</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193031642?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ADANSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Michael</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated naturalist, was descended from a Scotish family which had at the
                    Revolution attached itself to the fortunes of the house of Stuart; and was born
                    the 7th of April 1727 at Aix in Provence, where his father was in the service of
                    Μ. de Vin-timille, then archbishop of that province. On the translation of this
                    prelate to the archbishopric of Paris, about the year 1730, the elder Adanson
                    also repaired thither, accompanied by his infant family of five children, all of
                    whom were provided for by their father’s patron. A small canonry fell to the lot
                    of our future naturalist, the revenue of which defrayed the expenses of his
                    education at the college of Plessis. While there, he was distinguished for great
                    quickness of apprehension, strength of memory, and mental ardour; but his genius
                    took no particular bent, until he received a microscope from the celebrated
                    Tuberville Needham, who happened to be present at one of the public
                    examinations, and was struck with admiration of his talents and acquirements.
                    „From the moment that young Adanson received this donation, to the last hour of
                    his life, he persevered, with a zeal almost unexampled, in the observation and
                    study of nature.</p>
                <p>On leaving college, his youthful ardour was well employed in the cabinets of
                    Reaumur and Bernard de Jussieu, as well as in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Jardin</hi><hi rend="italic">des Plantes.</hi> Such was his zeal, that he
                    repeated the instructions of the professors to such of his fellow-students as
                    could not advance with a rapidity equal to his own; and before he had completed
                    his 19th year, he had actually described (for his own improvement) four thousand
                    species of the three kingdoms of nature. In this way he soon exhausted the rich
                    stores of accumulated knowledge in Europe; and having obtained a small
                    appointment in the colony of Senegal, he resigned his canonry, and embarked on
                    the 20th of December 1748 for Africa.</p>
                <p>The motives which decided the choice of Senegal as the scene of his observations
                    are recorded by himself, and are too remarkably indicative of his ardent thirst
                    of knowledge not to be noticed. “It was,” says he, in a memorandum found after
                    his death, “of all European establishments the most difficult to penetrate, the
                    most hot, the most unhealthy, the most dangerous in every respect, and
                    consequently the least known to naturalists.”</p>
                <p>His ardour remained unabated during the five years that he remained in Africa, in
                    which period he collected and described an immense number of animals and plants;
                    delineated maps of the country, and made astronomical observations; prepared
                    grammars and dictionaries of the languages spoken on the banks of the Senegal;
                    kept meteorological registers; composed a detailed account of all the plants of
                    the country; and collected specimens of every object of commerce. Μ. Cuvier
                    mentions that he had seen the produce and results of all these multifarious and
                    laborious exertions.</p>
                <p>The situation in which Adanson was placed was admirably adapted to foster
                    originality of genius; but it was also attended with every disadvantage that can
                    arise from <pb break="no" facs="nls:193031655?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-1655-0142"/> a want of comparison and rivalry. The collision
                    of kindred intellects generally diminishes an overweening conceit; whilst entire
                    seclusion from literary society as generally increases the presumption of
                    genius, and renders errors familiar by long uncorrected repetition. To these
                    causes, and to the secluded life which he continued to lead even after his
                    return to Europe, may probably be traced some of the peculiar features of
                    Adanson’s character. Thus, he chose to distinguish himself by a new system of
                    orthography; and, instead of a simple and convenient nomenclature, he employed a
                    set of arbitrary terms, whose etymology could not be traced, and the synonymes
                    to which he rarely condescended to point out. He was opinionative in no small
                    degree; and his vanity and self-confidencc too often led him to overlook or to
                    undervalue the labours of those who were engaged in the same field of
                    inquiry.</p>
                <p>Aboüt the period of Adanson’s return to Europe, which took place in 1754, natural
                    history had undergone a very important revolution, from the valuable though
                    widely differing labours of Buffon and Linnaeus. The one, giving loose to his
                    imagination, pursued a path as seductive as beautiful; the other, entering with
                    minute discrimination into every department, furnished a text-book to
                    philosophers, leaving the splendid paintings of his eloquent rival to those who
                    delight rather in brilliancy of colouring than in the chaste portraiture of
                    nature. Both of these distinguished men, from too closely confining themselves
                    to their individual views, appear to have in a great measure overlooked a most
                    interesting branch of their subject, viz. the general relations of all beings,
                    from which is deduced the division of them into families; which division is
                    founded on their peculiar characters. This had formed an important branch of
                    Adanson’s solitary reflections; and the boldness with which he developed his
                    views soon attracted the admiration of naturalists. To appreciate thoroughly the
                    value of his labours, it will be necessary to exhibit a rapid sketch of the
                    general principles which influence <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> arrangements,
                    and the particular views entertained by Adanson.</p>
                <p>Every organized being is to be considered as an assemblage of parts, which by
                    reciprocal actions produce certain effects. Between all of these parts a mutual
                    dependence subsists, and no modification can be effected in any one member of
                    the series, without sensibly affecting all the others in a greater or less
                    degree. It is obvious that there can only be a certain number of possible
                    combinations, which may be divided into two great classes, the primary and the
                    subordinate.</p>
                <p>The first step towards the knowledge of these combinations would be an accurate
                    acquaintance with all the actually existing organs. If this were attained, and
                    if a complete view of all possible combinations were deduced, every organized
                    being would be allotted to a determinate place, according to its organs; and
                    there would be a correct systematic arrangement of all organic nature; every
                    relation, every property, would be reducible to general laws; every function
                    might be demonstrated; and natural history would become a precise science. Such,
                    however, is only the ideal perfection at which we aim in attempting natural
                    methods, to which we cannot expect the rapid advance fancied by some visionary
                    theorists, but to which a steady perseverance, unclouded by preconceived
                    prejudices, will ultimately enable us to approach.</p>
                <p>The most direct means of calculating the effects of the before-mentioned
                    modifications would be, to determine the function and the influence of each
                    organ. In this way, the great divisions might be made according to the most
                    important organs, and the inferior would be naturally founded on the relations
                    of the less important organs. A scale would thus be established, not less
                    correct as regarding the order of nature, than if it had been formed
                    subsequently to a full examination of all her works. This principle of
                    classification has been named by some philosophers <hi rend="italic">the
                    subordination of characters.</hi> It is rational and philosophical, but its
                    application presupposes an advancement in science far beyond that which existed
                    at the period when Adanson commenced his labours. Accordingly, he adopted a more
                    experimental method—that of a complete comparison of species; and the mode of
                    applying his scheme is abundantly ingenious, and entirely his own.</p>
                <p>He founded his classification of all known organized beings on the consideration
                    of each individual organ. As each organ gave birth to new relations, so he
                    established a corresponding number of arbitrary arrangements. Those beings
                    possessing the greatest number of similar organs were referred to one great
                    division, and the relationship was considered more remote in proportion to the
                    dissimilarity of organs.</p>
                <p>The chief defect of this method consists in presupposing a knowledge, not less
                    difficult of attainment than the former, of species and their organization. It
                    gives, however, distinct ideas of the degree of affinity subsisting between
                    organized beings, independent of all physiological science. Of this <hi
                    rend="italic">universal method,</hi> as he called it, Adan-son gave some account
                    in an essay contained in his Treatise on Shells, published at the end of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic">au Sénégal.</hi></p>
                <p>Until the appearance of this work, the animals inhabiting shells had been much
                    neglected. On this branch of his subject our author exercised his wonted zeal,
                    while his methodical distribution, founded on not less than twenty of the
                    partial classifications already alluded to, is decidedly superior to that of any
                    of his predecessors. Like every first attempt, however, it had its
                    imperfections, and these arose from not having examined the anatomical structure
                    of the animals; from which cause he omitted, in his arrangement of the class of
                    <hi rend="italic">Mollusca,</hi> all <hi rend="italic">molluscous</hi> animals
                    without shells.</p>
                <p>His original plan was to have published the whole of the observations made during
                    his residence at Senegal, in eight volumes; but being deterred by the
                    difficulties attending so extensive a publication, he abandoned the scheme, and
                    applied himself entirely to his <hi rend="italic">Families of Plants,</hi> which
                    he published in 1763. In this he found the application of his general principle
                    not less advantageous than in his preceding works.</p>
                <p>The distribution of plants into <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> families has
                    attracted the notice of botanists since the middle of the seventeenth century.
                    Bernard de Jussieu, the friend and instructor of Adanson, bestowed much
                    attention on this subject; but, dissatisfied with his success, has left no other
                    memorial of his labours than the arrangement which he introduced in the gardens
                    of Trianon in 1758. Prompted by his own bold genius, as well as by the example
                    of so distinguished a friend, Adanson undertook the task; and although he fell
                    into errors which had been avoided by Jussieu, he executed it, upon the whole,
                    with consummate ability. In the preface to this work he gave an elaborate
                    account of the history of botany; and here it is not difficult to perceive, that
                    one of his chief objects was to insinuate his own claims to be placed at the
                    head of scientific botanists.</p>
                <p>In 1774 (eleven years after the appearance of his <hi rend="italic">Families of
                    Plants'),</hi> he submitted to the consideration of the Academy of Sciences an
                    immense work, containing what may be called the <hi rend="italic">universal
                    application of his universal method</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> for it extended
                    to all known beings and <pb break="no" facs="nls:193031668?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-1668-0143"/> substances, whether in the heavens or on the
                    earth. Twenty-seven large volumes of manuscripts were employed in displaying the
                    general relations of all these matters, and their distribution. One hundred and
                    fifty volumes more were occupied with the alphabetical arrangement of 40,000
                    species. There was also a vocabulary, which contained 200,000 words, with their
                    explanations; and the whole was closed by a number of detached memoirs, 40,000
                    figures, and 30,000 specimens of the three kingdoms of nature. The committee of
                    the academy, to which the inspection of this enormous mass had been intrusted,
                    warmly recommended to Adanson to separate'and publish all that was peculiarly
                    his own, leaving out what was merely compilation: but he obstinately rejected
                    this reasonable advice; by which means science has been deprived of many essays,
                    which, if we may judge from others which he at different times gave to the
                    world, would have possessed great merit.</p>
                <p>In the midst of his scientific ardour, Adanson devoted much of his attention to a
                    subject on which his feelings had probably been powerfully awakened during his
                    residence in Senegal:—we need scarcely name the slave trade. Anxious to
                    contribute to the comforts of Europe, as well as to the security of Africa, he
                    addressed a memoir to the minister, in which he attempted to demonstrate that
                    Senegal was well fitted for the production of all the valuable produce of the
                    West Indian Archipelago, and that by suitable encouragement free negroes might
                    be induced to engage in the cultivation of the soil. This proposition received
                    no encouragement either from the minister or the French African Company; and as
                    his mistaken notions of patriotism led him to reject all overtures from the
                    friends of the abolition in England, the details of his plan still remain
                    unknown to the world.</p>
                <p>Of Adanson’s public life little further remains to be said; for after his
                    rejection of the proffered counsel of the academicians, he seems to have pursued
                    his philosophic career in silent and unobtιusive retirement. Engaged in such
                    occupations, it might have been supposed that he would have been exempted from
                    the evils of that terrible revolution which has been productive of so many
                    calamities to his country and to Europe. But the case was very different. As he
                    had devoted his life to science for its own sake, he had never made it the means
                    of acquiring wealth; and having no patrimony from his ancestors, his only
                    fortune consisted of pensions, the reward of his labours in Senegal, and the
                    price of the specimens furnished by him to the royal cabinet. W ith an injustice
                    and illibcrality distinctive of revolutionary Frenchmen, the Constituent
                    Assembly deprived this harmless man, who was known only as an. ornament to
                    science, of what he had so hardly earned. A trifling pension from the academy
                    still remained, and was sufficiept for his limited wants; but on the dissolution
                    of that respectable body by the fanatical republicans, this his last resource
                    was also annihilated. When the revolutionary frenzy had subsided, and science
                    again received the homage of Frenchmen, the reproachful poverty of this veteran
                    sage was at length relieved from the public funds; and the founders of the
                    Institute were proud to enrol his name in the catalogue of its members. But his
                    life was now drawing near to its close. He died, after many months of severe
                    suffering, on the 3d of August 1806.</p>
                <p>Adanson was never married. In his will he requested, as the only decoration of
                    his grave, a garland of flowers gathered from the fifty-eight families which he
                    had established ;—“a touching though transitory image,” says Cuvier, “of the
                    more durable monument which he has erected to himself in his works.” His zeal
                    for science, his unwearied industry, and his talents as a philosophical
                    observer, are conspicuous in all his writings. The serenity of his temper, and
                    the unaffected goodness of his heart, endeared him to the few who knew him
                    intimately. On the other hand, it must be admitted, that, from early habits, he
                    trusted too exclusively to his own talents, and would never deign to examine the
                    discoveries of others; so that he persisted in a thousand times refuted errors,
                    with as much pertinacity as he did in the most unquestionable truths of science.
                    Cuvier relates a remarkable instance of his contempt for every thing that did
                    not fall within the scope of his own observations. Although he had bestowed much
                    care on the subject of <hi rend="italic">mosses,</hi> yet, in 1800, he was
                    ignorant not only of the discoveries, but even of the very existence, of Hedwig.
                    But though his vanity was great, it was not accompanied with any malignant
                    feelings; and, notwithstanding his misfortunes, he was never heard to accuse any
                    person of having contributed to inflict them.</p>
                <p>His most important works are, his <hi rend="italic">Voyage to Senegal,</hi> and
                    his <hi rend="italic">Families of Plants.</hi> To the former some essays,
                    already noticed, were subjoined; and various others were published, at different
                    times, in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Academy of Sciences.</hi>
                    The volumes for the years 1759 and 1761 contain his observations upon the <hi
                    rend="italic">Taret</hi> (a species of shell-fish exceedingly destructive to
                    vessels), and his account of the <hi rend="italic">Baobab,</hi> an enormous
                    African tree, now known under the name of <hi rend="italic">Adansonia.</hi> The
                    volume for 1769 contains an interesting discussion by Adanson, upon the origin
                    of the varieties of cultivated plants; and in those for 1773 and 1779 will be
                    found his valuable observations on gum-bearing trees. In the Transactions of
                    1767 he gave an account of the <hi rend="italic">Oscillatoria Adansonii,</hi>
                    which he considered a sclf-moving vegetable; but which ought, according to some
                    observations of Μ. Vaucher, to be ranked as a zoophyte. Besides these essays,
                    Adanson contributed several valuable articles in natural history to the earlier
                    part of the Supplement to the first <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie;</hi> and he
                    is also supposed to have been the author of an essay on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Electricity of the Tourmaline</hi> (Paris 1757), which bears the name of the
                    duke of Noya Caraffa. See <hi rend="italic">Eloge Historique de M. Adanson,</hi>
                    par Cuvier; <hi rend="italic">Mém. Mathem. et Physiques de l'Inst.
                    National,</hi> tom. vii. (<hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
