<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-1486-0129-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 2, page 129</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193031486" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ACT</label>, in general, denotes the exertion of power; and
                    differs from power, as the effect from the cause.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Act,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Logic,</hi> is particularly
                    understood of an operation of the human mind. Thus, to discern and examine are
                    acts of the understanding; to judge and affirm are acts of the will.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Act,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Universities,</hi>
                    signifies a thesis maintained in public by a candidate for a degree; or to show
                    the capacity and proficiency of a student.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ACT of Faith, Auto da Fe,</hi> in the Romish church, is a
                    solemn day held by the inquisition, for the punishment of heretics and the
                    absolution of the innocent accused. They usually contrive the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Auto</hi> to fall on some great festival, that the execution may pass with the
                    more awe and regard; at least it is always on a Sunday.</p>
                <p>The Auto da Fe may be called the last act of the inquisitorial tragedy: it is a
                    kind of jail delivery, appointed as oft as a competent number of prisoners in
                    the inquisition are convicted of heresy, either by their own voluntary or
                    extorted confession, or on the evidence of certain witnesses. The process is
                    thus: In the morning they are brought into a great hall, where they have certain
                    habits put on, which they are to wear in the procession. The procession is led
                    up by Dominican friars; after which come the penitents, some with san-benitos
                    and some without, according to the nature of their crimes; being all in black
                    coats without sleeves, and barefooted, with a wax candle in their hands. These
                    are followed by the penitents who have narrowly escaped being burnt, who over
                    their black coats have flames painted, with their points turned downwards, <hi
                    rend="italic">fuego revolto.</hi> Next come the negative and relapsed, who are
                    to be burnt, having flames on their habits pointing upwards. After these come
                    such as profess doctrines contrary to the faith of Rome, who, besides flames
                    pointed upwards, have their picture painted on their breasts, with dogs,
                    serpents, and devils, all open-mouthed, about it. Each prisoner is attended with
                    a familiar of the inquisition; and those to be burnt have also a Jesuit on each
                    hand, who are continually preaching to them to abjure. After the prisoners comes
                    a troop of familiars on horseback; and after them the inquisitors, and other
                    officers of the court, on mules; last of all, the inquisitor-general on a white
                    horse, led by two men with black hats and green hat-bands. A scaffold is erected
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Terreiro</hi><hi rend="italic">de Paço,</hi> big enough
                    for two or three thousand people; at one end of which are the prisoners, at the
                    other the inquisitors. After a sermon made up of encomiums on the inquisition,
                    and invectives against heretics, a priest ascends a desk near the middle of the
                    scaffold, and having taken the abjuration of the penitents, recites the final
                    sentence of those who are to be put to death; and delivers them to the secular
                    arm, earnestly beseeching at the same time the secular power not to touch their
                    blood, or put their lives in danger. The prisoners being thus in the hands of
                    the civil magistrate, are presently loaded with chains, and carried first to the
                    secular jail, and from thence in an hour or two brought before the civil judge;
                    who, after asking in what religion they intend to die, pronounces sentence on
                    such as declare they die in ,the communion of the church of Rome, that they
                    shall be first strangled, and then burnt to ashes; on such as die in any other
                    faith, that they be burnt alive. Both are immediately carried to the Ribera, the
                    place of execution, where there are as many stakes set up as there arc prisoners
                    to be burnt, with a quantity of dry furze about them. The stakes of the
                    professed, that is, such as persist in their heresy, are about four yards high,
                    having a small board towards the top for the prisoner to be seated on. The
                    negative and relapsed being first strangled and burnt, the professed mount their
                    stakes by a ladder; and the Jesuits, after several repeated exhortations to be
                    reconciled to the church, part with them, telling them they leave, them to the
                    devil, who is standing at their elbow to receiver their souls, and carry them
                    with him into the flames of hell. On this a great shout is raised; and the cry
                    is, Let the dogs’ <hi rend="italic">beards be made</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    which is done by thrusting flaming furzes fastened to long poles against their
                    faces, till their faces are burnt to a coal, which is accompanied with the
                    loudest acclamations of joy. At last, fire is set to the furze at the bottom of
                    the stake, over which the professed are chained so high that the top of the
                    flame seldom reaches higher than the seat they sit on, so that they rather seem
                    roasted than burnt. There cannot be a more atrocious spectacle, yet it is beheld
                    by all sexes and ages with transports of joy and satisfaction.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Act,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Dramatic Poetry,</hi>
                    signifies a certain division or part of a play, designed to give some respite
                    both to the actors and spectators. The Romans were the first who divided their
                    theatrical pieces into acts; for no such divisions appear in the works of the
                    first dramatic poets. Their pieces indeed consisted of several parts or
                    divisions, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193031499" xml:id="kp-eb0702-1499-0130"
                    />which they called <hi rend="italic">protasis, epitasis, catastasis,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">catastrophe</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but these divisions
                    were not marked by any real interruptions in the theatre. Nor does Aristotle
                    mention any thing of acts in his <hi rend="italic">Art of Poetry.</hi> But, in
                    the time of Horace, all regular and finished pieces were divided into five
                    acts.</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Neve minor</hi><hi rend="italic">neu</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sit</hi><hi rend="italic">quinto production actu</hi></l>
                    <l part="N"><hi rend="italic">Fabula,</hi><hi rend="italic">quoe</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">posci vult, et spectata reponi.</hi></l>
                </lg>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> If you would have your play deserve success, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Give it five acts complete, nor more nor less. </l>
                </lg>
                <bibl default="false" status="draft"><author><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Francis.</hi></author></bibl>
                <p>The first act, according to some critics, besides introducing upon the stage the
                    principal characters of the play, ought to propose the argument or subject of
                    the piece; the second, to exhibit this to the audience, by carrying the fable
                    into execution; the third, to raise obstacles and difficulties; the fourth, to
                    remove these, or raise new ones in the attempt; and the fifth, to conclude the
                    piece, by introducing some accident that may unravel the whole affair. This
                    division, however, is not essentially necessary, but may be varied according to
                    the humour of the author or the nature of the subject.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Act,</hi> among lawyers, is an instrument in writing for
                    declaring or justifying the truth of any thing; in which sense records, decrees,
                    sentences, reports, certificates, &amp;c. are called <hi rend="italic"
                    >acts.</hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Act</hi> of Parliament</hi> is
                    a positive law, consisting of two parts, the words of the act, and its true
                    sense and meaning; which being joined, make the law. The words of acts of
                    parliament should be taken in a lawful sense. Cases of the same nature are
                    within the intention, though without the letter, of the act; and some acts
                    extend by equity to things not mentioned therein.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Acts</hi> also denote the deliberations and resolutions of
                    an assembly, senate, or convention; as acts of parliament, &amp;c.; likewise
                    matters of fact transmitted to posterity in certain authentic books and
                    memoirs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Αcta</hi><hi rend="italic">Consistorii,</hi> the
                    edicts or declarations of the council of state of the Roman emperors. These
                    edicts were generally expressed in such terms as these: “The august emperors,
                    <hi rend="italic">Dioclesian</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Maximin,</hi> in council
                    declare, That the children of decurions shall not be exposed to wild beasts in
                    the amphitheatre.”—The senate and soldiers often swore, either through abject
                    flattery or by compulsion, upon the edicts of the emperor, as we do upon the
                    Bible. And the name of Apidius Merula was erased by Nero out of the register of
                    senators, because he refused to swear upon the edicts of the Emperor
                    Augustus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic  smallcaps">Acta Diurna,</hi> was a sort of Roman gazette,
                    containing an authorized narrative of the transactions worthy of notice which
                    happened at Rome. Petronius has given us a specimen of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >acta diurna</hi> in his account of Trimalchi; and as it may not perhaps be
                    unentertaining to see how exactly a Roman newspaper runs in the style of an
                    English one, the following articles are extracted from it:</p>
                <p>“On the 26th of July, 30 boys and ,40 girls were born at Trimalchi’s estate at
                    Cuma.</p>
                <p>“At the same time a slave was put to death for uttering disrespectful words
                    against his lord.</p>
                <p>“The same day a fire broke out in Pompey’s gardens, which began in the night, in
                    the steward’s apartment.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Ρopuli,</hi> among the
                    Romans, were journals or registers of the daily occurrences; as assemblies,
                    trials, executions, buildings, births, marriages, deaths, &amp;c. of illustrious
                    persons, and the like. These were otherwise called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Publica</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Acta Diurna,</hi>
                    or simply <hi rend="italic">Acta.</hi> The Acta differed from Annals, in that
                    only the greater and more important matters were in the latter, and those of
                    less note were in the former. Their origin is attributed to Julius Caesar, who
                    first ordered the keeping and making public the acts of the people. Some trace
                    them higher, to Servius Tullius; who, to discover the number of persons born,
                    dead, and alive, ordered that the next of kin, upon a birth, should put a
                    certain piece of money into the treasury of Juno Lucina; upon a death, into that
                    of Venus Libitina: the like was also to be done upon assuming the toga virilis,
                    &amp;c. Under Marcus Antoninus, this was carried further: persons were obliged
                    to notify the births of their children, with their names and surnames, the day,
                    consul, and whether legitimate or spurious, to the prefects of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Aerariurn</hi><hi rend="italic">Saturni,</hi> to be entered in the
                    public acts; though before this time the births of persons of quality appear to
                    have been thus registered.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">Senatus,</hi> among the Romans, were
                    minutes of what passed and was debated in the senate-house. These were also
                    called <hi rend="italic">Commentarii,</hi> and by a Greek name <hi rend="italic"
                    >υπομνηματα.</hi> They had their origin in the consulship of Julius Caesar, who
                    ordered them both to be kept and published. The keeping of them was continued
                    under Augustus, but the publication was abrogated. Afterwards all writings
                    relating to the decrees or sentences of the judges, or what passed and was done
                    before them, or by their authority, in any cause, were also called by the name
                    <hi rend="italic">Acta</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi> in which sense we read of
                    civil acts, criminal acts, intervenient acts; <hi rend="italic">acta</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">civilia, criminalia, intervenientia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Acts of the Apostles,</hi> one of the sacred books of the New
                    Testament, containing the history of the infant church during the space of 29 or
                    30 years, from the ascension of our Lord to the year of Christ 63. It was
                    written by St Luke, and addressed to Theophilus, the person to whom the
                    evangelist had before dedicated his Gospel. We here find the accomplishment of
                    several of the promises made by our Saviour; his ascension, the descent of the
                    Holy Ghost, the first preaching of the apostles, and the miracles whereby their
                    doctrines were confirmed; an admirable picture of the manners of the primitive
                    Christians; and, in short, every thing that passed in the church till the
                    dispersion of the apostles, who separated themselves in order to propagate the
                    gospel throughout the world. From the period of that separation, St Luke quits
                    the history of the other apostles, who were then at too great a distance from
                    him, and confines himself more particularly to that of St Paul, who had chosen
                    him for the companion of his labours. He follows that apostle in all his
                    missions, and even to Rome itself; for it appears that the Acts were published
                    in the second year of St Paul’s residence in that city, or the 36th year of the
                    Christian era, and in the ninth or tenth year of Nero’s reign. The style of this
                    work, which was originally composed in Greek, is much purer than that of the
                    other canonical writers; and it is observable that St Luke, who was much better
                    acquainted with* the Greek than with the Hebrew language, always, in his
                    quotations from the Old Testament, makes use of the Septuagint version. The
                    council of Laodicea places the Acts of the Apostles among the canonical books,
                    and all the churches have acknowledged it as such without any controversy.</p>
                <p>There were several <hi rend="italic">spurious</hi> Acts of the Apostles;
                    particularly, 1. <hi rend="italic">Acts,</hi> supposed to be written by Abdias,
                    the pretended bishop of Babylon, who gave out that he was ordained bishop by the
                    apostles themselves when they were upon their journey into Persia. 2. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Acts of St Peter</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi> this book came
                    originally from the school of the Ebionites. 3. <hi rend="italic">The Acts of St
                    Paul</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> which is entirely lost. Eusebius, who had seen
                    it, pronounces it of no authority. 4. <hi rend="italic">The Acts of St John the
                    Evangelist</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> a book made use of by the Encratites,
                    Manichaeans, and Priscillianists. õ. <hi rend="italic">The Acts of St
                    Andrew;</hi> received by the Mani<pb break="no" facs="nls:193031512"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0702-1512-0131"/>chaeans, Encratites, and Apotactics. 6. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Acts of St</hi><hi rend="italic">Thomas</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >the Apostle</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> received particularly by the Mani- ,
                    chaeans. 7. <hi rend="italic">The Acts of St Philip.</hi> This book the Gnostics
                    made use of. 8. <hi rend="italic">The Acts of St Matthias.</hi> Some have
                    imagined that the Jews for a long time had concealed the original Acts of the
                    life and death of St Matthias, written in Hebrew; and that a monk of the abbey
                    of St Matthias at Treves, having got them out of their hands, procured them to
                    be translated into Latin, and published them; but the critics will not allow
                    them to be genuine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Acts of Pilate,</hi> a relation sent by Pilate to the Emperor
                    Tiberius, concerning Jesus Christ, his death, resurrection, ascension, and the
                    crimes of which he was convicted before him.<note anchored="true" place="margin"
                    type="authorial"><p><supplied cert="high" evidence="external" instant="false"
                    reason="overbinding" source="#UWI-HT"> Eusebii <hi rend="italic">Hist.
                    Eccl.</hi> lib. ii. cap. 2. and ix. 5. </supplied></p></note> It was a custom
                    among the Romans, that the proconsuls and governors of provinces should draw up
                    acts, or memoirs, of what happened in the course of their government, and send
                    them to the emperor and senate. The genuine <hi rend="italic">acts</hi> of
                    Pilate were sent by him to Tiberius, who reported them to the senate; but they
                    were rejected by that assembly, because not immediately addressed to them; as is
                    testified by Tertullian, in his <hi rend="italic">Apol.</hi> cap. 5. and 20, 21.
                    The heretics forged acts in imitation of them: in the reign of the Emperor
                    Maximin, the Gentiles, to throw an odium on the Christian name, spread about
                    spurious Acts of Pilate; which the emperor, by a solemn edict, ordered to be
                    sent into all the provinces of the empire, and enjoined the schoolmasters to
                    teach and explain them to their scholars, and make them learn them by heart.
                    These acts, both the genuine and the spurious, are lost. There is indeed extant,
                    in the Pseudo-Hegesippus, a letter from Pilate to the Emepror Claudius,
                    concerning Jesus Christ;<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial"
                    ><p><supplied cert="high" evidence="external" instant="false"
                    reason="overbinding" source="#UWI-HT"> Cave <hi rend="italic">Hist.
                    Literar.</hi></supplied></p></note> but it discovers itself at first sight to be
                    spurious.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
