<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6595-0522-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLEIN, Joseph (7th edition, volume 2, page
                    522)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1112660">Sentimentalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45t2j">Truth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7g36p">Rectors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036595?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ALLEIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi></label>, the son of
                    Tobias Allein, was born at Devizes, in Wiltshire, in 1633, and educated at
                    Oxford. In 1655 he became assistant to Mr Newton, in Taunton Magdalen, in
                    Somersetshire; but was deprived for nonconformity. He died in 1668, aged 35. He
                    was a man of great learning, and greater charity; preserving, though a
                    nonconformist, and a severe sufferer on that account, great respect for the
                    church, and loyalty to his sovereign. He wrote several books of piety, which are
                    highly esteemed; but his <hi rend="italic">Alarm to Unconverted Sinners</hi> is
                    more famous than the rest. There have been many editions of this little pious
                    work, the sale of which has been very great; of the edition 1672 there were
                    20,000 sold ∙' of that of 1675, with this title, <hi rend="italic">A Sure Guide
                    to Heaven</hi> 50,000. There was also a large impression of it with its first
                    title in 1720.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Allein,</hi><hi rend="italic">Richard,</hi> an English
                    nonconformist divine, a native of Ditchet, in Somersetshire, was born in the
                    year 1611. His father was rector of Ditchet, and conducted the education of his
                    son until he was prepared for the university. There he soon obtained the degree
                    of master of arts; and after he entered into holy orders, first as an assistant
                    to his father, and afterwards as rector of Batcomb, in Somersetshire, he
                    discharged the duties of a clergyman with great industry and singular fidelity.
                    From his education he conceived an early predilection for the sentiments of the
                    Puritans, and, consequently, in the contest between Charles I. and the
                    parliament he firmly adhered to the latter. Having adopted these sentiments, he
                    sometimes received a little disturbance from the king’s forces; but he never
                    carried his opposition to any undue length. He, along with several others,
                    signed a paper entitled, “The testimony of the Ministers of Somersetshire to the
                    truth of Christ,” in which their declared principles and becoming candour were
                    amply displayed. Along with his father, he was employed by the commissioners
                    appointed by parliament for ejecting scandalous ministers; a commission which
                    was executed with rigour, and originated in intolerance.</p>
                <p>Upon the Restoration he manifested a disposition to loyalty, but, unable with a
                    good conscience to unite in the act of conformity, he resigned his living after
                    enjoying it for 20 years, and ranked with the meritorious band of sufferers, to
                    the number of 2000, commonly denominated the <hi rend="italic">ejected
                    ministers.</hi> In the house of Mr More, who had been a member of the
                    parliament, he exercised the duties of his ministerial office under the penalty
                    of that act, and was consequently reprimanded by the magistrates and imprisoned;
                    but his piety and exemplary conduct procured him a mitigation of punishment. But
                    no dangers could deter him from duty; for although constrained to remove from
                    that place in consequence of the “five-mile act,” he continued in the discharge
                    of his ministerial office atFrome-Selwood. Here he remained until he terminated
                    his labours by death, in 1681.</p>
                <p>Piety, boldness, activity, and candour, shone in the character of Richard Allein.
                    He was admired as a pathetic and practical preacher, and justly respected for
                    the diligence with which he discharged the public and private duties of his
                    profession. Mr Jenkins, the vicar of the parish where he resided, preached his
                    funeral sermon, and bore an honourable testimony to his activity, moderation,
                    and piety. Richard Allein, similar to his nonconformist brethren, chiefly
                    confined his studies and publications to subjects of religion. His works are
                    strongly marked with the peculiar features of the religious character then
                    prevalent among the nonconformists. They have been frequently reprinted, and
                    very much perused. His most celebrated work is <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vindiciae</hi><hi rend="italic">Pietatis,</hi> or a Vindication or Godliness in
                    its greatest Strictness and Spirituality; with Directions for a Godly Life. This
                    book was published in 1665 without a printer’s name; and being unlicensed, the
                    copies of it were seized and sent to the king’s kitchen for waste paper. The
                    other productions of his pen are, Heaven Opened, or a brief and plain discovery
                    of the riches of God’s Covenant of Grace, printed in 1665; the V orld Conquered,
                    published in 8vo, in 1668; Godly Fear, printed in 8vo, in 1674; a Rebuke to
                    Backsliders, and a Spur for Loiterers, printed in 8vo, in 1677; a Companion for
                    Prayer, in 12mo, 1680; a Brief Character of Mr Joseph <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193036608?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-6608-0523"/> Allein; and
                    Instructions about Heart-work, what is to be done on God’s part and ours for the
                    cure and keeping of the heart,—a posthumous piece published in 8vo, by Dr
                    Annesley, in the year 1681. <hi rend="italic">( Gen. Biog.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
