<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-8493-0668-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMPHITHEATRE (7th edition, volume 2, page 668)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q814s63">Beasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880335">Corridors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814226">Arenas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:868845">Columns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193038493?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AMPHITHEATRE</label>, in ancient architecture, a building of
                    an elliptic form, of two or more stories of open arcades, with a number of
                    interior galleries and arched passages, which served both as a communication and
                    support to several rows of seats which rose above each other, and were arranged
                    round a large space called the <hi rend="italic">arena.</hi> The derivation of
                    the word <hi rend="italic">amphitheatre</hi> indicates that it is a place where
                    the spectators, circuitously arranged, saw the performance equally well on all
                    sides.</p>
                <p>The history of amphitheatres is of considerable importance, in consequence of its
                    connection with ancient manners. These structures owed their origin to the
                    barbarity of the ancients, and their ruin to the humanity of the moderns. They
                    are the production of Roman invention in the last ages of the republic. The
                    Romans were immoderately fond of every amusement of a bloody and horrible
                    nature. Their rulers improved this general feature in the Roman character, to
                    rouse and foster that martial spirit which rendered them masters of the world.
                    After the Samnite war had extended the Roman sceptre over Etruria and the whole
                    peninsula of Italy, the first gladiatory conflicts were exhibited in Rome in the
                    year of the city 490. Lucius Metellus brought into the circus the elephants
                    which were part of the spoil of the Carthaginians, in the year 502, and this
                    proved the introduction of wild beasts into the spectacles of Rome. This
                    addition λvas equally agreeable to the Roman taste; and those who courted the
                    popular favour vied with each other in entertaining the people in this barbarous
                    manner. This soon gave birth to a profession of men denominated <hi
                    rend="italic">gladiators,</hi> who were trained to the combat, and for reward
                    slaughtered one another in the forum, whilst every devouring animal which the
                    wilds of Asia or Africa produced added to the horrid scene.</p>
                <p>In the days of Pompey and Caesar these barbarous amusements were given with an
                    astonishing profusion. In these games given by Pompey, the elephants attempted
                    to break down the barrier between them and the people: this circumstance, and
                    the form of the circus not enabling all the spectators to have a full view,
                    induced Caesar to alter the original form, and construct edifices where the
                    people might be entertained without danger or interruption. Amphitheatres were
                    suited to this purpose; therefore they were adopted, and became the common place
                    for the exhibitions both of gladiators and wild beasts.</p>
                <p>It is supposed that the first amphitheatre was composed of those singular
                    machines, formed bv Caius Curio, for the games which Caesar presented among the
                    funeral honours of his father. In a semicircular form Caius made two large
                    theatres, and opposed their backs to each other; and having amused the people in
                    these the one half of the day, then they wheeled round, forming one spacious
                    theatre, where the gladiators contended during the remainder of the day. Pliny
                    is the only one who makes mention of this amphitheatre; and from his account it
                    is difficult to ascertain whether this was the first idea of an amphitheatre, or
                    whether the previous sight of one had suggested this huge and wonderful
                    structure. It is reported that Julius Caesar, a few years after, formed a
                    hunting theatre of wood; and, in consequence of the circular position of the
                    seats, it obtained the name of anβwι- <hi rend="italic">phitheatre.</hi> This
                    appears to have been of a very superior kind, and in great estimation.</p>
                <p>In the reign of Augustus, Statilius Taurus erected one of stone, but it seems to
                    have been seldom used; and, from its being consumed by fire in the time of Nero,
                    it is evident that it was not wholly of stone. These wooden buildings appear to
                    have been generally temporary, but a few of them permanent, from the
                    establishment conferred upon them. The politic spirit of Augustus induced him to
                    erect several of these; and Caligula began one, which he left unfinished. Nero
                    formed a large and spacious one, which is said to have been a year in building.
                    Herod of Judaea erected amphitheatres both in Jerusalem and in Caesarea. During
                    the reign of Tiberius, one was built at Fidenae, which Tacitus informs us fell
                    while the games were performing, and slew or hurt about 50,000 persons. There
                    was another at Placentia, reported to have been the most spacious in Italy; but
                    it was destroyed by fire in the contest between Vitellius and Otho.</p>
                <p>The unfortunate accidents which happened to these wooden buildings led to the
                    construction of others of a more durable and stronger nature, where the crowd
                    might be entertained without danger. This honour was reserved to Vespasian and
                    Titus. In his eighth consulate the former began the amphitheatre, which the
                    latter finished during his reign. It is said that the expense of this building
                    would have erected a capital city, and it is deservedly esteemed one of the most
                    celebrated edifices of ancient times. Dio says, that 9000 wild beasts were
                    destroyed at the dedication of this huge building, but Eutropius restricts their
                    number to 5000. After the hunting of these ferocious animals was ended,
                    instantly the arena was filled with water, and sea animals were made to contend,
                    and a sea-fight exhibited. This immense building obtained the appellation of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Coliseum.</hi></p>
                <p>This amphitheatre became the model of other amphitheatres throughout the empire.
                    Compared with the original model, these were natural valleys, with seats formed
                    in the surrounding heights similar to the amphitheatre at Corinth. On the
                    declivity of two hills seats of stones were sometimes placed, and the extremes
                    formed by regular works of stone. Of this kind was that of Gortyna in Candia.
                    One in the vicinity of Sandwich in Kent had its benches formed of turf; and
                    similar must have been those amphitheatres which were formed along with the
                    camps and military stations of the Roman soldiers.</p>
                <p>When Christianity became the religion of the empire, it meliorated the
                    dispositions of the Romans, and induced them to lay aside this barbarous custom.
                    Constantine the Great terminated the gladiatory combats in the east during his
                    reign; but they were not finally abolished at Rome until the beginning of the
                    fifth century, in the reign of Honorius. The combats of wild beasts continued,
                    however, some time longer; but during tlιe progress of the fifth century these
                    gradually declined, until they were <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193038506?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8506-0669"/> finally
                    abolished, and the amphitheatres were abandoned to the ravages of time and
                    accident. During the middle ages they were sometimes employed for judicial
                    conflicts, tilts, and tournaments; but these practices having been discontinued,
                    the amphitheatres experienced universal neglect and ruin.</p>
                <p>It is scarcely possible to give a clear idea of the manner in which such immense
                    crowds of people were seated and arranged, and how they had a convenient
                    entrance and a returning. It has already been mentioned, that these buildings
                    were circuitous, and that the exterior circuit was composed of two or more
                    stories of arcades; and it may now be added, that the number of these stories
                    varied according to the nature of the building. A corresponding number of arched
                    passages and staircases opened upon the ground floor towards these stories, in
                    the direction of radii towards the arena. These communications were again
                    intersected by arched passages, which encircled the whole structure, and
                    afforded an uninterrupted entrance to every part of the amphitheatre. Sometimes
                    an intermediate gallery surrounded the whole in the centre of the fabric, and
                    served as a common place of resort to all the stairs which led to the higher
                    galleries. This was the form of one at Nismes. Sometimes each staircase had its
                    distinct communication by itself. Such was the case with one at Verona.</p>
                <p>The four radiating entries on the diameter were usually more capacious; and by
                    the two principal of these the emperor, the senate, and other persons of
                    distinction, were conducted to their seats on a place which was called the <hi
                    rend="italic">podium.</hi> The other two led to the arena, and by these the
                    gladiators and beasts made their entrance. The various ranks of the people
                    passed by the staircases, which led to their respective seats. The doors which
                    opened from the staircases were called <hi rend="italic">vomitories,</hi> and
                    varied in magnitude, according to the extent of the amphitheatre and the number
                    of exterior arches. The number of seats between the several vomitories was
                    unequal, and seems to have been subject to no positive regulation. These benches
                    were about one foot and eight inches in height, and about two feet four inches
                    in breadth. A platform four feet eight inches broad was formed of one of these
                    benches, which served as a circular communication to the whole building. These
                    obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">precinctions,</hi> and the boundaries on
                    the side were called <hi rend="italic">belts.</hi> The latter were surrounded by
                    balustrades, to protect the persons from falling who occupied the benches in the
                    vicinity. The podium was more spacious than the precinctions, and was a platform
                    encircling the arena. From one precinction to the belt of another, a flight of
                    stairs two feet six inches in breadth descended opposite to every vomitory.
                    Small canals were cut in the tops of the benches, by which the rain and urine
                    were conducted from bench to bench, until they reached the instruments prepared
                    to convey them to the drains below. These stairs radiated from the highest bench
                    to the podium; so that, with the precinctions, they separated the whole cavity
                    into wedge-like divisions, which the people occupied according to their
                    rank.</p>
                <p>The amphitheatre called the <hi rend="italic">Coliseum</hi> was of an elliptical
                    form, whose longest diameter was about 615 English feet six inches, and the
                    shortest 510. The length of the diameter of the arena was about 281 feet, and
                    the breadth 176, reserving a space for the seats and galleries of about 157 feet
                    in breadth. The external circumference covered a superficies of about five acres
                    and a half, and could scarcely be included in a parallelogram of seven acres.
                    Three stories of arcades, adorned with columns of the Doric, Ionic, and
                    Corinthian orders, and inclosed with a pilastrade of the Corinthian order,
                    composed the external elevation. The first story rose about four feet from the
                    ground, and the pavement supported the basis of the columns. The columns which
                    supported the upper stories were placed upon pedestals. A stylobata supported
                    the pilastrade, in which were the windows of an intermediate gallery, and in
                    every second interpilaster was a window to illuminate the highest gallery. A
                    cantaliver cornice, perforated with square holes, through which the erect pieces
                    of wood passed that supported the awning to a range of corbels, about the centre
                    of the pilastrade, crowned the building. These various columns, pilasters, and
                    stories, appear to have been continued without interruption around the whole
                    edifice. The height of the first story was about 33 feet six inches, the second
                    about 39, and the third about 38; the pilastrade about 46; and the whole,
                    including the blocking course and the steps, was about 164 feet in height.</p>
                <p>An ellipsis of 80 open arches formed the exterior circuit of the ground plan <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi>; the piers, with three-quarter columns in front, of
                    about two feet 10 inches diameter. The four which corresponded to the four
                    semi-diameters formerly mentioned, were about 14 feet two inches, and 76 of the
                    arches were about 13 feet eight inches.· These arches led to a large double
                    corridor, that encircled the whole: this corridor is a magnificent and
                    distinguishing feature in the Coliseum theatre. Square openings in the
                    precinction above, illuminated the interior corridor; and the corridor which was
                    united with the wall of the podium appears to have been illuminated in a similar
                    manner. A double corridor was seen on the floor of the second story, directly
                    above the corridor of the lower floor, and an interior corridor which sent forth
                    stairs leading to a range of vomitories on the one hand, and on the other hand
                    an intermediate corridor which formed a mezzanine floor above the double
                    corridor of the interior circuit Here the stairs began to ascend to the next
                    story, and square holes in the upper floor enlightened this gallery. A double
                    corridor formed the third story, and it appears that here the stairs commenced
                    that led to the galleries above. There were also some windows in the interior
                    wall, and vomitories which opened to the uppermost cunei of benches. In a
                    similar manner were other three stories constructed and filled above; the whole
                    composing a most magnificent and spacious structure.</p>
                <p>Justus Lipsius supposes that this amphitheatre was capable of containing 87,000
                    spectators on the benches; and Fontana adds 22,000 for the galleries and other
                    passages. Upon a fair calculation it appears, that if all was crowded, it might
                    contain about 80,000. This magnificent structure certainly excelled the
                    monuments both of Grecian and Egyptian genius which have reached our times. When
                    this amphitheatre was in its glory, and crowded with Romans, the sight must have
                    been magnificent and striking. If the report is accurate that this was completed
                    in two years and nine months, it affords an astonishing instance of Roman vigour
                    and persevering industry. Besides former depredations, Michael Angelo removed
                    near the one half of the external wall to build the Palazzo Farnese. To prevent
                    these depredations, Pope Benedict XIV. consecrated these ruins, and erected
                    several altars, which were much frequented on the Sundays and Fridays, before
                    the revolution in France. To guard these relics, a hermit was stationed in a
                    small dwelling near the centre.</p>
                <p>The different kinds of amusement have already been mentioned during the progress
                    of the history. Gladiators contended together, or entered the lists with wild
                    beasts. These wild animals were hunted or encountered, or left to <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193038519?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8519-0670"/> devour each
                    other, according to the humour of the times, or the taste of him who gave the
                    entertainment. It appears also, that criminals were sometimes forced to fight
                    with these ferocious creatures, for the entertainment of the people of Rome;
                    and, in the dawn of Christianity, many of the Christians suffered death in this
                    brutal manner. It is also reported, that artificial mountains were sometimes
                    constructed with caves below, from whence these devouring animals rushed forth
                    to attack their prey.</p>
                <p>Information concerning the laws that regulated the amphitheatre is rather scanty;
                    but the following are among the number. In the centre of one side of the podium
                    was the emperor’s seat, called the <hi rend="italic">suggestum,</hi> and highly
                    adorned. The remainder of the podium was occupied by senators; and when this
                    space was not sufficient, several of the adjacent wedges were appropriated to
                    the other senators and to persons of distinction. The equestrians, and the civil
                    and military tribunes, had their places next assigned them. From this order both
                    the liberti and the legati were excluded. The married men sat by themselves. The
                    young men were also arranged by themselves, and their tutors sat near them to
                    observe their conduct. The attendants and servants occupied the highest gallery.
                    The vestals were seated, and frequently the princesses and the ladies of
                    distinguished rank sat along with them. The front of the gallery was assigned to
                    the women, who were placed on chairs; and the lowest order of plebeians stood
                    behind them. It appears also, that for the better accommodation of the people,
                    the different tribes had particular wedges allotted to them. It is also proper
                    to remark, that the arrangement in the different provinces was different from
                    that of Rome, as circumstances varied. The general direction of the amphitheatre
                    was under the care of an officer, named <hi rend="italic">villicus
                    amphitheatri</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and different officers, who were
                    called <hi rend="italic">locarii,</hi> had the direction of the cunei. By
                    carefully preventing any person from occupying a place to which he was not
                    entitled, all confusion was prevented, and strict order maintained.</p>
                <p>The means used by Pope Benedict to preserve the Coliseum at Rome have already
                    been mentioned. Of one which was erected at Verona, only four arches of the
                    external circuit remained at the commencement of the eighteenth century. These
                    consist of three stories of about 90 English feet. The whole building was
                    erected without cement, and joined and secured by iron cramps, overlaid with
                    lead. The superficies is about four acres and nearly one third. One erected at
                    Nismes has suffered much dilapidation; but the remains are yet worthy of the
                    attention of the traveller. At Pola in Istria, there are the remains of an
                    amphitheatre built on the declivity of a hill. It was erected of stone, with
                    cramps of iron; and all the benches and other parts constructed of wood have
                    been destroyed.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
