<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-4094-0779-11" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GRONOVIUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw48036">Erudition</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:958978">Holsteiners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100080">Romanies</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193524094?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">GRONOVIUS</label>, the Latinized form of <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Gronov, John Frederick,</hi> a learned scholar and critic,
                    was born at Hamburg on the 10th of September 1611. His father, who was
                    councillor to the Duke of Holstein, having been appointed syndic or town-clerk
                    of Bremen, carried his son to that city, where he went through his early studies
                    with great distinction. He then visited the universities of Leipsic and Iena,
                    and proceeded to Altdorf, where he studied law under the learned professors who
                    had conferred celebrity on that school. After the death of his father he
                    returned to Bremen, and having settled his affairs, he, in 1634, repaired to
                    Groningen to enjoy the benefit of the society and instructions of Antony
                    Mathieu, a great jurisconsult, and the friend of his family. Here, however, he
                    remained only a short time. For, being desirous to extend his knowledge by
                    travel, he visited the principal cities of Holland, in order to converse with
                    the learned and explore the libraries; passed, with the same design, into
                    England in 1639; and the year following proceeded to France. He stopped several
                    months at Paris; received the degree of doctor of law at Angers; and then
                    travelled into Italy, whence he returned, through Switzerland and Germany, to
                    Deventer, where he was offered the chair of literature and history. In 1658, he
                    succeeded Daniel Heinsius, the celebrated professor of belles-lettres in the
                    university of Leyden, and died in that city on the 28th of December 1671.
                    Gronovius was a man of equal learning and modesty, and, as he was naturally
                    disinclined to controversy, he avoided those literary disputes by which so many
                    then sought to obtain distinction. For a correct list of his numerous works, we
                    refer to the <hi rend="italic">Bibliolh. ErudU. Proecoc.</hi> of Klefeker, and
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Diclionaire</hi> of Chauflepié, and shall only mention
                    the following: 1. Diatribe in Statii poetse Sylvas, Hague, 1637, in 8vo; 2. De
                    Sesterciis sive subsesivorum Pecuniae veteris Graecae et Roman« libri iv.
                    Deventer, 1643, in 4to; 3. Observationum libri iv. Deventer, 1662, in 12mo; 4.
                    Laudatio funebris Joannie Golii, Leyden, 1668, in 8vo; 5. De Musaeo Alexandrino
                    Exercitationes Academic«, inserted in the eighth volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Thesaurus</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquitatum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Groecarum;</hi> 6. Lectiones Plautinae, quibus non tantum fabulae Plautin«
                    et Teren-tianae, verum etiam C«sar, Cicero, Livius illustrantur, Amsterdam,
                    1740, in 8vo; 7. Notes on the treatise of Grotius <hi rend="italic">De Jure
                        Belli</hi><hi rend="italic">et Pacis.</hi> Gronovius also revised <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193524107?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0710-4107-0780"
                    />the text, and published editions with notes, of Titus Livius, Statius, Pliny
                    the Elder, Justin, Tacitus, the Senecas, Aulus Gellius, Phaedrus, and Paulinus,
                    almost all of which form part of the <hi rend="italic">Variorum</hi> collection.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Gronovius,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">James,</hi> son of the preceding, and one of the most
                    laborious philologers of the seventeenth century, was born at Deventer on the
                    20th of October 1645. At an early age he had read all the masterpieces of
                    antiquity, and appreciated their beauties; but this precocious discernment was
                    not so much the result of natural genius as of obstinate perseverance. Having
                    resolved to travel through part of Europe to acquire knowledge, and visit the
                    old friends of his father, he came over to England, where he remained several
                    months, during which he occupied himself in collating the manuscripts in the
                    libraries of Oxford and Cambridge. He then returned to Leyden, and there
                    published, in the year 1670, an edition of Polybius, with notes, amongst which
                    he inserted those that Casaubon had on his death-bed bequeathed to him. This
                    first editorial effort did him much honour, and well merited the offer, which
                    was in consequence made him, of a chair in the academy of Deventer. But
                    entertaining the intention of continuing his travels, he declined the proffered
                    situation, and almost immediately set out for Paris, where he met with a most
                    distinguished reception. The death of his father obliged him to return a second
                    time to Leyden; but as soon as he had arranged his affairs, he again set out,
                    along with Μ. Paats, ambassador of the states-general, to Spain; and having seen
                    all that is curious or interesting in that country, he embarked for Italy. The
                    Grand Duke of Tuscany retained him in his states by appointing him professor in
                    the university of Pisa; and Gronovius profited by the facility he had of
                    visiting Florence, to form a connection with Magliabecchi, who placed at his
                    disposal all the treasures of the Medicean library. At the end of two years he
                    prevailed on the grand duke to accept his resignation; visited Venice and Padua;
                    and traversed Germany on his way to Deventer, where it was his intention to
                    settle. But scarcely had he arrived in that city when the curators of the
                    university of Leyden tendered him a chair, and pressed their offer so urgently
                    that he was induced to accept. His opening discourse increased the high idea
                    which had been formed of his knowledge; and the curators, to testify their
                    desire of retaining him, immediately raised his salary to four hundred florins.
                    Gronovius was very sensible of this mark of esteem, and constantly refused the
                    propositions which were made to draw him to Kiel, to Padua, and to other
                    universities of Germany and Italy. If he inherited the erudition of his father,
                    he had neither his gentleness nor his moderation. Never was there a man fonder
                    of disputation, or more unjust towards the adversaries whom, for the most part,
                    he raised up against himself by his asperity and haughtiness. It would be
                    tedious, if not disgusting, to enter into details respecting the quarrels he had
                    to maintain with Fabretti on the sense of some passages in Livy; with Feller and
                    Perizonius as to the manner of Judas’s death; with Vossius on Pomponius Mela;
                    with Bentley and John Leclerc on the corrections of Menander; with Küster on
                    Suidas, &amp;c. The scurrility he indulged in these discussions, which did not
                    always terminate to his advantage, and his exorbitant vanity, caused him to be
                    compared to Scioppius, and procured for him the unenviable distinction of a
                    place in die work of Mencken on the Empiricism of the Learned. But though the
                    temper of Gronovius was thus violent, his heart was sound, and he loved his
                    children with so much tenderness that the grief occasioned by the loss of his
                    daughter accelerated his own death, which took place at Leyden on the 21st of
                    October 1716, in the seventy-first year of his age. In the Memoirs of Niceron
                    will be found a notice of his life, followed by a catalogue of his works,
                    forty-six in number. The most celebrated, as well as the most important, of
                    these, is the <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Antiquitatum</hi><hi rend="italic">Grcecarum,</hi> Leyden, 1697 and the
                    following years, in 13 vols, folio. For this invaluable collection he adopted
                    the plan traced out by Graevius in the <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Antiquitatum Romanarum,</hi> Utrecht, 1694, in 12 vols, folio.
                    Both works ought to be united; and, to form a complete collection of
                    antiquities, there should be added, 1. <hi rend="italic">Novus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquitatum</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Romanarum,</hi> by Sallengre, Hague, 1716, in 3 vols, folio;
                    2. <hi rend="italic">Utriusque Thesauri Nova</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Supplementa,</hi> by Polleni, Venice, 1737, in 5 vols, folio; 3. <hi
                        rend="italic">Inscriptiones Antiqua totius Orbis Romani,</hi> by Gruter,
                    Amsterdam, 1707, in 4 vols, folio; 4. <hi rend="italic">Lexicon</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Antiquitatum Romanarum,</hi> by Pitiscus, Leuwarden, 1713, in
                    2 vols, folio. Gronovius published new editions of several authors already
                    commented on by his father, such as Seneca the tragic poet, Aulus Gellius,
                    Phaedrus, and others; and he also edited Macrobius, Polybius, Tacitus, Pomponius
                    Mela, Cicero, Ammianus Marcel)inus, Quintus Curtius, Suetonius, Arrian, Minutius
                    Felix, Herodotus, Cebes, and some ancient geographers; the poem of Manetho on
                    the stars; the <hi rend="italic">Dactylotheca</hi> of Gorlaeus; the <hi
                        rend="italic">Lexicon</hi> of Harpocration, &amp;c. the greater part of
                    which, enriched with corrections and notes, form part of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Variorum</hi> collection, though, in general, not held in much estimation.
                    The other productions of Gronovius consist of Theses, Discourses, and Diatribes,
                    of which a list will be found in the Memoirs of Niceron, and also in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ľiblioth.</hi><hi rend="italic">Erudit.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Pracocium</hi> of Klefeker. <hi rend="smallcaps">(λ.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
