<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0710-0870-0531-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GLAMORGANSHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193520870?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">GLAMORGANSHIRE</label>, a county of South Wales,
                    stretching, in a circular line, along the northern shore of the Bristol Channel,
                    from east to west about forty-two miles, and extending to the mountains in some
                    parts to the distance of twenty-two or twenty-three miles. It is bounded on the
                    north by Caermarthen and Brecknock, on the east by Monmouthshire, and on the
                    south and west by the Bristol Channel. Its whole area is 822 miles, or 526,080
                    statute acres, in which are included the watercourses, roads, and sites of
                    buildings, which occupy a large surface.</p>
                <p part="N">The county may be divided into two districts of a very opposite
                    character, according to the nature of the soil, rather than into those ten
                    hundreds by which its parts are politically denominated. About one half the
                    county, on the sea-shore, is rich and fertile land, and produces excellent crops
                    of wheat, oats, beans, and barley. The soil is generally of moderate
                    consistence, and of a loamy nature, some parts being mixed with day, others with
                    sand, and almost all resting on a calcareous substratum. It is easily ploughed,
                    very friable, and, when laid down in grass, yields excellent herbage, by which
                    many cattle are fattened, and much good butter is made. The manure principally
                    used is lime, which is rendered very cheap from the vicinity of coals to the
                    limestone district.</p>
                <p part="N">The inland part of the county rises gradually from hills to mountains,
                    and in that district the agriculture is in a very backward state. The soil
                    between these hills and mountains is composed generally of a black peat, but
                    sometimes of a brown gravelly earth. Lime applied to the former is beneficial
                    for a few years, but its good effect then ceases; and having but little cattle
                    to make manure, and that manure being neglected to be preserved with due <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193520883?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0710-0883-0532"
                    />care, the agricultural produce of the district is insufficient for the
                    subsistence of the inhabitants. On some of the mountain farms the land is sowed
                    with corn as long as it will yield any increase without fallow or manure, and
                    when so far exhausted it is left without cultivation for many years. Much of the
                    unenclosed mountain tract is devoted wholly to feeding sheep, and the occupiers
                    of land around them having rights of common without stint, so overstock them,
                    that the animals seldom attain their full growth; but when removed to better
                    pasture, and fattened, their mutton is excellent. The farms are mostly of very
                    small value, varying in rent from L.5toL.200 annually; the average of the whole
                    is not L.50, though in many instances the rent has been tripled, and even
                    quadrupled, within the last twenty years. The ploughing is generally executed by
                    oxen, and their ploughs being of clumsy construction, sometimes six or eight are
                    used to perform the work, and yet perform it ill; in some cases two, in others
                    four, are harnessed to plough with two horses .before them. The most commendable
                    part of the rural economy of the county is the construction of the houses,
                    barns, and other farming erections. These are solidly and substantially built,
                    and being uniformly white-washed on the outside, have a clean and neat
                    appearance.</p>
                <p part="N">The agriculture of this county, valuable as it is in the more southern
                    part, is the least productive source of its riches. The greater part of it
                    abounds with minerals, which, owing to the great extension of good roads, of
                    navigable canals and railways, within the last few years, have become a most
                    important source of wealth. The northern and middle parts of the county
                    comprehend a portion of that great mineral tract which begins at Pontypool in
                    Monmouthshire, and terminates at St Bride’s Bay in Pembrokeshire. The exterior
                    stratum or boundary consists of a bed of limestone, within which are contained
                    all the strata of the other minerals in the following position. On the north
                    side of a line drawn from east to west through the middle of the district, all
                    the strata rise gradually to the north, and on the south side of the same line
                    they rise to the south till they come to the surface, except at the east end,
                    where they rise to the eastward. In the centre of this tract, the iron and coal
                    mines in the vicinity of Myrthr-Tydvil are both the richest and most abundant.
                    The whole of the coal is at the depth of 440 feet beneath the surface of the
                    ground, which is composed of argillaceous strata, with occasional veins of hard
                    rock. The coal is about fifty-two feet deep, the thickness of the veins varying
                    from twelve inches to nine feet in thickness. The ironstone lies under the stone
                    at a depth of about 108 feet, and is separated by argillaceous earth and stone
                    into eighteen different veins, each about four feet ten inches in thickness.
                    When this ore is smelted, it yields iron to the amount of three tenths of the
                    weight of the ore.</p>
                <p part="N">Coal is found in vast quantities both in the north and south divisions
                    of the county, but of different natures. That in the south is of the bituminous
                    kind, or coaking coal, like the coals of Newcastle. That of the north (when
                    large, called stone-coal and small culm) is difficult to kindle, burns slowly,
                    but emits an intense heat with little or no smoke, and without being distended.
                    This latter is principally used by the maltsters and lime-burners.</p>
                <p part="N">Although the abundance and excellence of the coal and iron have caused
                    the erection of blast-furnaces in many parts of the county, yet the largest and
                    most numerous are those near the recently-built town of Myrthr-Tydvil, which,
                    within a few years, has grown up from an obscure village to be the most populous
                    village in the whole principality of Wales, and contained, in 1811, 11,000, and
                    in 1831, 22,000 inhabitants.</p>
                <p part="N">There are seventeen blast-furnaces near this place, each of which can
                    make from 100 to 180 tons of iror weekly. The most extensive of the works, that
                    of Cyfar-tha, belonging to Messrs Crawshay and Company, produce annually upwards
                    of 20,000 tons of pig-iron, and somewhat more bar-iron. The fires of the
                    furnaces are blown by a steam-engine of fifty horse power, and an overshot wheel
                    of fifty feet in diameter, which requires twenty-five tons of water each minute
                    to keep it at work. The number of men employed at Messrs Crawshay’s work is from
                    1500 to 2000, making, with their families, more than three thousand persons,
                    whose yearly wages amount to more than L.140,000.</p>
                <p part="N">The next considerable manufactory is that commonly called tin plates.
                    The cheapness of iron and coal causes the tin of Cornwall to be sent here, and
                    spread over those iron plates, which are afterwards dispersed all over the
                    world.</p>
                <p part="N">In like manner, the copper ore from Cornwall, from North Wales, and from
                    Ireland, is attracted to Glamorganshire by the cheapness of coal; and it is
                    smelted in works upon a most extensive scale, in the vicinity of Aberavon,
                    Neath, and Swansea, whence it is forwarded by water-carriage to the places where
                    it receives its final appropriations to the several purposes for which it is
                    wanted. There are some extensive manufactories of earthen ware, which are
                    increasing in their operations; and small concerns adapted for making soap,
                    salt, and woollen cloths.</p>
                <p part="N">The most considerable exported production from this county is coals from
                    the ports of Swansea and Neath. At the former of these ports, the facility of
                    loading vessels is so great, that ships of three hundred tons burden enter with
                    one tide, are loaded and enabled to sail sometimes the next, but usually the
                    next tide but one. The quantity annually exported amounts to about 450,000 tons,
                    and more might be shipped, but for some superior privileges in the city of
                    Bristol, which favour the coal-mines of Monmouthshire and Gloucestershire.</p>
                <p part="N">The rivers of Glamorganshire are, ls&lt;, The Taf or Tave, over which is
                    the celebrated bridge of one arch, supposed to be the largest in the world,
                    being one hundred and forty feet in the span, planned and executed by an
                    untaught country mason, a native of the county; 2d, the Elay, a stream of short
                    course, near Llantrissent; 3d, the Ogmore, crossing the county, and entering the
                    sea near Bridgend; 4fΛ, the Nedd or Neath, passing from Brecknockshire, through
                    most romantic valleys, by Neath, to the sea at Britton Ferry; and, <hi
                        rend="italic">ι&gt;th,</hi> the Tawy, which discharges itself into Swansea
                    Bay.</p>
                <p part="N">As these rivers are scarcely navigable, and the two which are so, but
                    for a short distance, canals have been constructed for the conveyance of the
                    heavy productions of the county, and have produced a wonderful effect both on
                    its wealth and population. These are the Cardiff Canal, which affords
                    water-carriage from Myrthr-Tydvil to Pe-narth Bay; the Neath Canal, which
                    traverses the county from south to north; and the Swansea Canal, which runs to
                    the north till it reaches Brecknockshire. The number of railroads communicating
                    between the iron-works and coal-mines and the canals are too numerous to admit
                    of being enumerated, and have proved very beneficial undertakings both to the
                    constructors and to the public.</p>
                <p part="N">The peasantry of this county generally use the Welsh language, and
                    either cannot or will not speak English. In the towns, however, the latter is
                    very commonly spoken, and in the churches the service is occasionally conducted
                    in it. There is, however, a portion of the county, to the south of the mountains
                    round Oxwich Bay, where the Welsh language is quite unknown, whilst, on the
                    opposite side of the same mountains, the inhabitants are unacquainted with
                    English.</p>
                <p part="N">Glamorganshire returns to the House of Commons two members for the
                    county, and one for the newly created·</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193520896?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0710-0896-0533"/>
                <p part="N">borough of Myrthr-Tydvil, and also one for the old united boroughs of
                    Cardiff, Cowbridge, and Llantrissent. The population returns of the four
                    decennial censuses give the inhabitants in 1801, 71,525; in 1811, 85,067; in
                    1821, 101,737; and in 1831, 126,200.</p>
                <p part="N">The county town is Cardiff, and it-is the chief place for shipping the
                    iron of Myrthr-Tydvil. Its pier is now accessible for ships of two hundred tons,
                    but some improvements are in progress which will enlarge the harbour, and adapt
                    it for the reception of vessels of a greater draught of water than can now reach
                    it. The chief towns, and their population, are as follow :—Myrthr-Tydvil,
                    22,083; Swansea, 13,256; Cardiff, 6187; Neath, 4034; Llansamlet, 3187; and
                    Llantrissent, 2789. Landaff, though a city and the seat of a bishop, has only
                    1299 inhabitants.</p>
                <p part="N">As the picturesque beauty of many parts of the county is very great, it
                    has ever been the favourite resort of many families of respectability. That it
                    was so in ancient times, the number of ruins of ancient castles clearly evince;
                    and few parts of the island, excepting the immediate vicinity of the metropolis,
                    have so many gentlemen’s seats within them. The principal of these are, Gnoll
                    Castle, the seat of the Mackworths, now Mr Grant; Cardiff Castle, Marquis of
                    Bute; Dunraven, Thomas Wyndham, Esq.; Penlline Castle, Lord Vernon; Margram, Mr
                    Talbot; Classmont, Sir John Morris; Southall, John Lucas, Esq.; Gellyhir, Sir
                    Gabriel Powell; Penllergaer, John Llewelyn, Esq.; Penrice Castle, R. Μ. Talbot,
                    Esq.; Woodlands, General Ward; and Penderi, Thomas Morgan, Esq.; with many
                    others.</p>
                <p part="N">(See Rees’s <hi rend="italic">South Wales;</hi> Malkin’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Scenery of South Wales</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Parliamentary Returns.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
