<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0188-0179-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EMPEROR (9th edition, volume 8, page 179)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6rb7d">Voting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:985749">Kaiserring</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1169232">Voting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n188/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EMPEROR</label> (imperator, αυτοκράτωρ, Kaiser), a title
                    formerly borne by the sovereigns of the Roman empire (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Empire),</hi> and since their time by a variety of other potentates. The term
                    imperator seems to have originally belonged to every Roman magistrate who
                    received from the comitia curiata the imperium (‰e,, the power of the sword and
                    authority to command in war). It was, therefore, in strictness not a title but a
                    descriptive epithet. Towards the end of the Roman republic, however, it had
                    become rather a special title of honour bestowed by the acclamations of a
                    victorious army on their general, or by a vote of the senate as a reward for
                    distinguished services (see Tac., Ann., iii-. 74; Cic., Philipp., xiv. 4), and
                    in this sense it continued to be used during the earlier period of the empire.
                    Julius Caesar, however, assumed it (under a vote of the senate) in a different
                    sense, viz., as a permanent title, or rather as a part of his name (proenomen),
                    denoting the absolute military power which had come into his hands; and it was
                    given by the senate, in like manner and with a like significance, to Augustus
                    (see Dion Cassius, lii. 41, liii. 17.) Tiberius and Claudius refused it; but
                    under their successors it soon became established as the regular official title
                    of the monarch of the Roman world, ultimately superseding the name of princeps.
                    W hen Greek became the sole language of the Eastern Roman empire, imperator was
                    rendered sometimes by ∕3ασιλ∈υς and sometimes by αυτοκράτωρ, the former word
                    being the usual designation of a sovereign, the latter specially denoting that
                    despotic power which the imperator held, and being in fact the official
                    translation of imperator.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n189/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0189-0180"/>
                <p>Justinian uses αντοκράτωρ as his formal title, and ∕3ασιλ∈υς as the popular term.
                    On the revival of the Roman empire in the West by Charles the Great in 800 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> the title (at first in the form imperator, or
                    imperator Augustus, afterwards Romanorum imperator Augustus) was taken by him
                    and by his Frankish, Italian, and German successors, heads of the Holy Roman
                    Empire, down till the abdication of the emperor Francis II. in 1806. The
                    doctrine had, however, grown up in the earlier Middle Ages (about the time of
                    the emperor Henry IL, 1002-1024) that although the emperor was chosen in Germany
                    (at first by the nation, afterwards by a small body of electors), and entitled
                    from the moment of his election to be crowned in Rome by the pope, be could not
                    use the title of emperor until that coronation had actually taken place. The
                    German sovereign, therefore, though he exercised, as soon as chosen, full
                    imperial powers both in Germany and Italy, called himself merely “King of the
                    Romans” (Romanorum rex semper Augustus) until he had received the sacred crown
                    in the sacred city. In 1508 Maximilian I., being refused a passage to Rome by
                    the Venetians, obtained from Pope Julius II. a bull permitting him to style
                    himself emperor elect (imperator electus, erwählter Kaiser). This title was
                    taken by Ferdinand I. (1558) and all succeeding emperors, immediately upon their
                    coronation iu Germany; and it was until 1806 their strict legal designation, and
                    was always employed by them in proclamations and other official documents. The
                    term “elect” was, however, omitted even in formal documents when the sovereign
                    was addressed, or was spoken of in the third person.</p>
                <p>According to mediaeval theory, there was and could be only one emperor in the
                    world, the direct vicegerent of God, who . represented the unity of mankind and
                    of the Christian people on its temporal side as the pope did on its spiritual.
                    Hence during those ages the Western monarch and Western writers did not admit in
                    principle, though they sometimes recognized in fact, the title of the emperor
                    who reigned at Constantinople; and the Easterns in like manner denied the
                    existence of an emperor in the West, and maintained that the heads of the Holy
                    Roman Empire were merely German intruders. In spite, however, of the universal
                    acceptance of the theory above mentioned, the title of emperor was one which
                    other princes seem to have hankered after. In 1053 Ferdinand the Great of
                    Castile, in the pride of his victories over the Moors, assumed the style of
                    Hispanice imperator, but was forced by the remonstrances of the emperor Henry
                    III. to abandon it. In the 12th century it was again assumed by Alphonso VIT. of
                    Castile, but not by any of his successors. In England the Anglo-Saxon kings
                    frequently used the term basileus, and sometimes also imperator, partly from a
                    desire to imitate the pomp of the Byzantine court, partly in order to claim à
                    sovereignty over the minor kingdoms and races of the British isles corresponding
                    to that which the emperor was held to have over Europe generally (see Freeman,
                    Norman Conquest, vol. i., Appendix, who however attaches too much importance to
                    this English use).</p>
                <p>In comparatively modern times, the title of emperor has been taken by the
                    monarchs of Russia (Vassili, about 1520, his predecessors at Moscow having been
                    called Great Dukes of Muscovy, and the title of Czar or Tsar being apparently a
                    Slavonic word for prince, not related to Caesar), France (Napoleon Bonaparte in
                    1804, Louis Napoleon Bonaparte in 1853), Austria (1805), Brazil (1822), Germany
                    (December 31, 1870), Great Britain and Ireland in respect of the Indiau
                    dominions of the crown (1876). Usurpers who have reigned in Hayti, a certain
                    Augustin Iturbide who (in 1822) became ruler of Mexico after the revolt
                    against</p>
                <p>Spain, and the archduke Maximilian of Austria during his short tenure of power in
                    Mexico, also called themselves emperors; and modern usage applies the term to
                    various semi-civilized potentates, such as the sovereigns of China and Morocco.
                    It can, therefore, hardly be said that the name has at present any definite
                    descriptive force, such as it had in the Middle Ages, although its associations
                    are chiefly with arbitrary military power, and it is vaguely supposed to imply a
                    sort of precedence over kings. In the cases of Germany, Austria, and Britain in
                    respect of India, it may perhaps be taken to denote that general over-lordship
                    which their sovereigns exercise over minor princes and over their various
                    territories, and which is distinct from their position as sovereigns of one or
                    more particular kingdom or kingdoms, the German emperor being also king of
                    Prussia, as the emperor of Austria is king of Hungary, and the empress of India
                    queen of Great Britain and Ireland.</p>
                <p>See Selden, Titles of Honour; Bryce, Holy Roman Empire; Sir E. Colebrooke, “On
                    Imperial and other Titles,” in the Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society, 1877. .
                    (J. BR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
