<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0810-0775-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EWALD, Johannes (9th edition, volume 8, page
                    775)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn5q">Patriotism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vv86">Enteritis</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926174">Fishers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:912601">Enteritis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n810/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EWALD, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johannes</hi></label>
                    (1743-1781), the greatest lyrical poet of Denmark, was the son of a melancholy
                    and sickly chaplain at Copenhagen, where he was born on the 18th of November
                    1713. At the age of eleven he was sent to school at Schleswig, his father’s
                    birth-place, and returned to the capital only to enter the university in 1758.
                    His father was by that time dead, and in his mother, a frivolous and foolish
                    woman, he found neither sympathy nor moral support. At fifteen, he fell
                    passionately in love with “the delicate, noble, majestic Arense,” a girl whose
                    father, later on, married the poet’s mother; and the romantic boy resolved on
                    various modes of making himself admired by the young lady. He began to learn
                    Abyssinian, for the purpose of going out as a missionary to Africa, but this
                    scheme was soon given up, and he persuaded a brother, four <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n811/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0811-0776"/> years older thau himself, to run away that they
                    might enlist as hussars in the Prussian army. They managed to reach Hamburg just
                    when the Seven Years’ War was commencing, and were allowed to enter a regiment.
                    But the elder brother soon got tired and ran away, while the poet, after a
                    series of extraordinary adventures, deserted to the Austrian army, where from
                    being drummer he rose to being sergeant, and was only not made an officer
                    because he was a Protestant. In 1760 he was weary of a soldier’s life, and
                    deserted again, getting safe back to Denmark. For the next two years he worked
                    with great diligence at the university, but the Arense for whom he had gone
                    through so much hardship and taken so much pains married another man almost
                    immediately after Ewald’s final and very successful examination. The
                    disappointment was one from which he never recovered. He plunged into
                    dissipation of every kind, and gave his serious thoughts only to poetry. Iu 1763
                    his first work, a perfunctory dissertation <hi rend="italic">De Pyrologia
                    Sacra,</hi> first saw the light. In 1764 he made a considerable success with a
                    short prose story, <hi rend="italic">Lykkens Tempel</hi> (The Temple of
                    Fortune), which was translated into German and Icelandic. On the death of
                    Frederick V., however, Ewald first appeared prominently as a poet; he published
                    in 1766 three <hi rend="italic">Elegies</hi> over the dead king, which were
                    received with universal acclamation, and of which one, at least, is a veritable
                    masterpiece. But his dramatic poem <hi rend="italic">Adam og Eοa</hi> (Adam and
                    Eve), by far the finest imaginative work produced in Denmark up to that time,
                    was rejected by the Society of Arts in 1767, and was not published until 1769.
                    At the latter date, however, its merits were perceived. In 1770 Ewald attained
                    success with <hi rend="italic">Philet,</hi> a narrative and lyrical poem, and
                    still more with his splendid <hi rend="italic">Rolf Krage,</hi> the first
                    original Danish tragedy. For the next ten years Ewald was occupied in producing
                    one brilliant poetical work after another, in rapid succession. In 1771 he
                    published <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">brutale</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Klαppers</hi> (The Brutal Clappers), a tragi-comedy or parody
                    satirizing the dispute then raging between the critics and the manager of the
                    Royal Theatre; in 1772 he translated from the German the lyrical drama of <hi
                    rend="italic">Philemon and Baucis,</hi> and brought out his comedy of <hi
                    rend="italic">Harlequin Patriot,</hi> a satire on the passion for political
                    scribbling created by Struensee’s introduction of the liberty of the press. In
                    1773 he published <hi rend="italic">Pebersυendene</hi> (Old Bachelors), a
                    comedy. In 1771 he had already collected some of his lyrical poems under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Adskilligt af Johannes Ewald</hi> (Miscellanies). Iu
                    1774 appeared the heroic opera of <hi rend="italic">BaldeTs D'od</hi> (Balder’s
                    Death), and in 1779 the finest of his works, the lyrical drama <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eiskerne</hi> (The Fishers), which contains the Danish National Song, “King
                    Christian stood by the high Mast,” his most famous lyric. Iu the two poems last
                    mentioned, however, Ewald passed beyond contemporary taste, and these great
                    works, the pride of Danish literature, were coldly received. But while the new
                    poetry was slowly winning its way into popular esteem, the poet did not lack
                    admirers, and at the head of these he founded in 1775 the Danish Literary
                    Society, a body which became influential, and which made the study of Ewald a
                    cultus. But the poet’s health had broken; when he was writing <hi rend="italic"
                    >Rolf Krage</hi> he was already an inmate of the Consumptive Hospital, and when
                    he seemed to be recovering, his health was shattered again by a night spent in
                    the frosty streets. He embittered his existence by the recklessness of his
                    private life, and finally, through a fall from a horse, he ended by becoming a
                    complete invalid. His last ten years were full of acute suffering; his mother
                    treated him with cruelty, his family with neglect, and but few even of his
                    friends showed any manliness or generosity towards him. In 1774 he was placed in
                    the house of an inspector of fisheries at Rungsted, where Anna Hedevig Jacobsen,
                    the daughter of the house, tended the wasted poet with infinite tenderness and
                    skill. He stayed in this house for three years, and wrote there some of his
                    finest later lyrics. Meanwhile he had fallen deeply in love with the charming
                    solace of his sufferings, and won her consent to a marriage. This step, however,
                    was prevented by his family, who roughly removed him to their own keeping near
                    Kronborg. Here he was treated so infamously that he insisted on being taken back
                    to Copenhagen in 1777, where he found an older, but no less tender nurse, in
                    Madame Schouw. Here he wrote <hi rend="italic">Fiskerne,</hi> with his
                    imagination full of the familiar shore at Hornbaek, near Rungsted. In 1780 he
                    was a little better, and managed to be present at the theatre at the first
                    performance of his poem. But this excitement destroyed him, and after months of
                    extreme agony, he died on the 17th of March 1781, and was carried to the grave
                    by a large assembly of his admirers, since he was now just recognized by the
                    public for the first time as the greatest national poet. Among his papers were
                    found fragments of three dramas, two on old Scandinavian subjects, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Frode</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Helyo,</hi> and the third a
                    tragedy on the story of <hi rend="italic">Hamlet,</hi> which he meant to treat
                    iu a way wholly distinct from Shakespeare’s.</p>
                <p>Ewald belongs to the race of poetical reformers who appeared in all countries of
                    Europe at the end of last century; but it is interesting to observe that in
                    point of time he preceded all of them. He was born six years earlier than Goethe
                    and Alfieri, sixteen years before Schiller, nine years before André Chénier, and
                    twenty-seven years earlier than Wordsworth, but he did for Denmark what each
                    ofthese poets did for his own country. Ewald found Danish literature given over
                    to tasteless rhetoric, and without art or vigour. He introduced vivacity of
                    style, freshness and brevity of form, and an imaginative study of nature which
                    was then unprecedented. But perhaps his greatest claim to notice is the fact
                    that he was the first person to call the attention of the Scandinavian peoples
                    to the treasuries of their ancient history and mythology, and to suggest the use
                    of these in imaginative w riting. With a colouring more distinctly modern than
                    that of Collins and Gray, his lyrics yet resemble the odes of these his English
                    contemporaries more closely than those of any Continental poet; from another
                    point of view his ballads remind us of those of Schiller, which they preceded.
                    His dramas, which had an immense influence on the Danish stage, are now chiefly
                    of antiquarian interest, with the exception of “The Fishers,” a work that must
                    always live as a great national poem. In personal character and in fate Ewald
                    seems to have been not unlike Heinrich Heine.</p>
                <p>The first collected edition of Ewald’s works began to appear in his life-time. It
                    is in four volumes, 1780-1784. They have constantly been reprinted, but the
                    standard edition is that by Liebenberg, in 8 vols., 1850-1855. (E. W. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
