<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0593-0572-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ETHEREDGE, Sir George (9th edition, volume 8, page
                    572)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174932">Widowers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174951">Widows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852494">Charms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c824g3w">Charms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q84g">Widows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n593/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ETHEREDGE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir George</hi></label> (c.
                    1636-1689), an English dramatist, was born in or near London about the year <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n594/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0594-0573"/> 1636. He was a scion of an ancient and
                    distinguished family of Oxfordshire. He was educated at Cambridge, but left the
                    university early to travel in France and Flanders. It is probable that he
                    witnessed in Paris the performances of some of Molière’s earliest comedies; and
                    he seems, from an allusion in one of his plays, to have been personally
                    acquainted with Bussy Rabutin. On his return to London he studied the law at one
                    of the Inns of Court. His tastes were those of a fine gentleman, and he indulged
                    freely in pleasure. Sometime soon after the Restoration he composed his comedy
                    of <hi rend="italic">The Comical Revenge, or Love in a Tub,</hi> which
                    introduced him to Lord Buckhurst, afterwards the earl of Dorset. This was
                    brought out at the Duke’s Theatre in 1664, and a few copies were printed in the
                    same year. The main edition of this play, however, was not issued until 1669. It
                    is partly in rhymed heroic verse, like the stilted tragedies of the Howards and
                    Killi-grews, but it contains comic scenes that are exceedingly bright and fresh.
                    The sparring between Sir Frederick and the Widow introduced a style of wit
                    hitherto unknown upon the English stage. The success of this play was very
                    great, but Etheredge waited four years before he repeated his experiment.
                    Meanwhile he gained the highest reputation as a poetical beau, and moved in the
                    circle of Sir Charles Sedley, Lord Rochester, and the other noble wits of the
                    day. In 1668 he brought out <hi rend="italic">She would if she could,</hi> a
                    comedy in many respects admirable, full of action, wit, and spirit, but to the
                    last degree frivolous and immoral. But in this play Etheredge first shows
                    himself a new power in literature; lie has nothing of the rudeness of his
                    predecessors or the grossness of his contemporaries. We move in an airy and
                    fantastic world, where flirtation is the only serious business of life. At this
                    time Etheredge was living a life no less frivolous and unprincipled than those
                    of his Courtals and Freemans. He formed an alliance with the famous actress Mrs
                    Barry; she bore him a daughter, on whom he settled £6000, but who unhappily died
                    in her youth. His wealth and wit, the distinction and charm of his manners, won
                    him the general worship of society, and his temperament is best shown by the
                    names his contemporaries gave him, of “gentle George” and “easy Etheredge.” The
                    age upbraided him for inattention to literature; and at last, after a silence of
                    eight years, he came forward with one more play, unfortunately his last. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Man of Mode, or Sir Folding Flutter,</hi> indisputably the
                    best comedy of intrigue written in England before the days of Congreve, was
                    acted and printed in 1676, and had an unbounded success. Besides the merit of
                    its plot and wit, it had the personal charm of being supposed to satirize, or at
                    least to paint, persons well known in London. Sir Fopling Flutter was a portrait
                    of Beau Hewit, the reigning exquisite of the hour; in Dorimant the poet drew the
                    elegant Sir Charles Sedley, and in Medley a portrait of himself; while even the
                    drunken shoemaker was a real character, who made his fortune from being thus
                    brought into public notice. After this brilliant success Etheredge retired from
                    literature; his gallantries and his gambling in a few years deprived him of his
                    fortune, and he looked about for a rich match. In 1683 he met with a wealthy
                    elderly widow, who consented to marry him if he made a lady of her. He
                    accordingly got himself knighted, and gained her hand and her money, It is said
                    that before this, about 1680, he had been sent on an embassy to Turkey; it is
                    certain that in 1686 he was appointed resident minister in the Imperial German
                    Court at Ratisbon. He was very uncomfortable in Germany, and solaced himself by
                    writing amusing epistles in prose and verse to his friends in England. In 1688
                    he published a prose <hi rend="italic">Account of the rejoicing at the Diet of
                    Ratisbon.</hi> In 1689 he is believed to have died in Ratisbon in a tragical
                    manner, for whilst conducting a party of friends to the stairs after a banquet
                    at his house, he fell over into the court below and broke his neck. But his
                    death occurred at the moment when England was convulsed with revolution, and no
                    one has preserved the exact date of it.</p>
                <p>Etheredge deserves to hold a more distinguished place in our literature than has
                    generally been allotted to him. In a dull and heavy age, he inaugurated a period
                    of genuine wit and sprightliness. He invented the comedy of intrigue, and led
                    the way for the masterpieces of Congreve and Sheridan. Before his time the
                    manner of Ben Jonson had prevailed in comedy, and traditional “humours” and
                    typical eccentricities, instead of real characters, had crowded the comic stage.
                    Etheredge paints with a light faint hand, but it is from nature, and his
                    portraits of fops and beaux are simply unexcelled. No one knows better than he
                    how to present a gay young gentleman, a Dorimant, “an unconfinable rover after
                    amorous adventures.” His genius is as light as thistledown; he is frivolous,
                    without force of conviction, without principle; but his wit is very sparkling,
                    and his style pure and singularly picturesque. No one approaches Etheredge in
                    delicate touches of dress, furniture, and scene; he makes the fine airs of
                    London gentlemen and ladies live before our eyes even more vividly than Congreve
                    does; but he has less insight and less energy than Congreve. Had he been poor or
                    ambitious he might have been to England almost what Molière was to France, but
                    he was a rich man living at his ease, and he disdained to excel in literature.
                    Etheredge was “a fair, slender, genteel man, but spoiled his countenance with
                    diinking.” His contemporaries all agree in acknowledging that he was the soul of
                    affability and sprightly good-nature.</p>
                <p>There is no recent edition of the works of Sir George Etheredge. A critical
                    collection of them would fill a very important gap in our literature.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
