<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0115-0106-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELECTROLYSIS (9th edition, volume 8, page 106)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1021794">Millers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term ref="fast:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978705">Ions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878331">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb50">Ions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j1r">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n115/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELECTROLYSIS</label>. A very slight acquaintance with the
                    phenomena of conduction of electricity by different bodies shows us that
                    conductors may be arranged in two very distinct classes. In one the passage of
                    electricity produces no change in the chemical composition of the substance,
                    unless indeed the electromotive force be so great that disruptive discharge
                    occurs, or so large an amount of heat is generated that chemical effects ensue;
                    the conductivity diminishes slowly as the temperature rises, and if the
                    resistance of the rest of the circuit be small compared with that of the
                    substance under consideration, an amount of heat is produced in the latter
                    equivalent to the energy expended by the sources of electricity. To this class
                    of conductors probably belong all solids, with the exception of hot glass, which
                    conducts with decomposition at a temperature below the fusing point. Tiιe
                    conductivity differs enormously in the different cases; those which conduct most
                    readily are the metals, alloys, the chemical elements generally, and some few
                    metallic oxides and sulphides (Faraday, Exp. lies., 440, ser. iv.; Skey, Chenι.
                    News, xxiii.). Besides fused metals Faraday added one liquid, fused periodide of
                    mercury, to the list, but subsequently gave reasons for considering that it was
                    misplaced {Exp. lies., 691, ser. vii.). The other class of conductors presents a
                    remarkable contrast to the one just described. In these the passage of
                    electricity results in the chemical decomposition<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>We have not space here to discuss whether or
                    not conduction in electrolytes is always attended with decomposition, although
                    the question has engaged the attention of many writers on the subject. The
                    reader who wishes for information upon the point may consult Faraday, Exp. Res.
                    966-987⅜, ser. viii.; Despretz, Cornpt. Rend., t. xlii. p. 707; De la Rive,
                    Archives, t. xxxii. p. 38; Logeman and Van Breda, Phil. Mag. [4], viii. 465;
                    Buff, Ann,, d. Ckern. u. Pharrn., Bd. xciv. s. 15; Foucault, Cornpt. Rend., t.
                    xxxvii. p. 580; De la Rive, Ann. de Chimie, [3], t. xlvi. p. 41; Favre, Cornpt.
                    Rend., lxxiii. p. 1463; Helmholtz, Berlin Monatsbericht, 1873, Nachtrag zum
                    Juliheft; and, for a summary of results, Wiedemann, Galv., Bd. i. §314-316, and
                    Nachtrag, 36, § 334.</p></note> of the substance of the conductor at the points
                    where the electric current<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The standard direction of the current is taken, as usual, to be from the
                    copper through the wire to the zinc of an ordinary zinccopper cell.</p></note>
                    enters and leaves the body; a rise of temperature produces in such bodies a very
                    considerable increase in the conductivity, but the specific resistance of even
                    the best conducting among them is always very great compared with that of the
                    metals. (For details see article <hi rend="smallcaps">Electricity,</hi> p. 46
                    sqq.) Only part of the energy of the circuit is spent in heating the conductor,
                    as a transformation of energy takes place in the chemical and molecular actions
                    at the points where the current enters and leaves the conductor.</p>
                <p>It is the behaviour of the second class of bodies under the influence of the
                    electric current that we have now to discuss. The physical side of the subject
                    has already been considered in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Electricity;</hi> so we shall principally confine our attention to the
                    phenomena of electrolysis which bear on the laws and principles of chemistry.
                    Before going further it will be necessary to introduce the technical terms which
                    have now become familiar, and, in order to be definite, we will consider
                    somewhat closely a particular instance of electrochemical decomposition of the
                    simplest type.</p>
                <p>The cell in which the action takes place consists of a wide tube of hard glass,
                    bent into a V-shape; into this is introduced some silver chloride, which is kept
                    fused during the experiment; into the liquid in one leg of the tube is dipped a
                    platinum wire connected with the negative pole (zinc) of a battery<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is not necessary to use a
                    voltaic battery,—any source of electricity serves,—but either a voltaic or a
                    thermoelectric battery is usually employed, ’ since these so conveniently supply
                    a large quantity of electricity, with an electromotive force sufficient for the
                    purpose.</p></note> of 3 or 4 Grove’s cells, and into that in the other a piece
                    of graphite or gas carbon connected with the positive pole of the same battery.
                    We will suppose a galvanometer introduced into the circuit, and that the current
                    strength as indicated thereby is, roughly speaking, constant, so that the
                    quantity of electricity which passes can be measured roughly by the time
                    occupied in passing. After the circuit has been closed a short time, bubbles of
                    chlorine will begin to come off from the carbon, while pure silver is deposited
                    upon the platinum wire, but except at these points no alteration will take place
                    at any part of the fluid. If the platinum wire with the attached silver be
                    weighed at intervals, it will be found that the amount deposited after the
                    current has become constant is proportional to the time, i.e., to the amount of
                    electricity which has passed through the liquid.. The same will be true of the
                    chlorine if collected in the other leg of the tube, due allowance being made for
                    the small bubbles retained by the carbon, &amp;c. And the amount of chlorine
                    will be chemically equivalent to the amount of silver; thus for every 108
                    grammes of silver on the platinum there will be 35 5 grammes of chlorine set
                    free in the other leg of the tube. Moreover if the current be varied by varying
                    the number of battery cells, it will be found that the amount of decomposition
                    in a given time is proportional to the current, that is, again, to the quantity
                    of electricity which traverses the substance.</p>
                <p>Faraday, who was the first to define the laws which hold in electrochemical
                    decomposition, introduced, for the sake of precision, a system of nomenclature
                    which has since been generally employed. Wishing to regard the terminals
                    corresponding, in any similar case, to the carbon and platinum in the above
                    experiment merely as the “doors” by which the electricity enters and leaves the
                    liquid, he denominated them electrodes, and, comparing the “path” of the current
                    to those of the currents which may produce terrestrial magnetism, and hence to
                    the course of the sun, he called the homologue of the carbon (where the current,
                    so to speak, “rose,” or entered) the anode, that of the platinum (where the
                    current “set,” or left) the cathode. The component parts, no matter how complex,
                    into which the liquid was decomposed, corresponding to the Ag and Cl of the
                    above, received the name of “ions ”—that component which went down with the
                    current to the cathode, and there either was set free or combined with the
                    cathode or the surrounding liquid, beiug the cation, and that which went up
                    against the current, and appeared or promoted some chemical action at the anode,
                    the anion. Moreover, the substance decomposed was called an electrolyte, and the
                    process itself electrolysis. (Faraday, Exp. Res., 662 sqq.)</p>
                <p>The phenomena which occur at the electrodes when the ions there set free react
                    upon the electrode or the surrounding fluid, so that the resulting products of
                    electrolysis are not the ions themselves, are called secondary actions.</p>
                <p>The anion and the cation are frequently called the negative and positive ion
                    respectively. Similarly the cathode and anode are termed the negative and
                    positive electrodes; Daniell denoted them the platinode and the zincode, but
                    these terms have fallen into disuse.</p>
                <p>Of the bodies which are capable of electrolytic conduction nearly all,if not all,
                    are liquids. Faraday {Exp.Res., 433, 1340) apparently obtained some chemical
                    decomposition iu sulphuret of silver and a few other salts when solid, but this
                    did not alter his opinion that the mobility secured in the fluid state, either
                    by fusion or by solution, was necessary to the phenomena of electrolysis; and
                    his view, which he supported by experiments on ice and other solids that conduct
                    when fused {Exp. lies., 380-397, 419-428), still obtains. Electrolytic action
                    doubtless sometimes takes place in gases, but accurate investigation of the
                    subject is difficult on account of the extreme mobility of the particles <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0116-0107"/> and the danger of confusing electrolytic effects
                    with effects due to disruptive discharge by convection. Gases have, however,
                    been decomposed by the silent discharge, as CO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> into
                    CO + O.</p>
                <p>From Faraday’s time attempts have continually been made to classify strictly,
                    according to their chemical composition or constitution, the liquids capable of
                    electrolytic conduction, but hitherto without very much success. It must be
                    remembered that, as the resistance of a liquid increases, the tests of
                    electrolytic conduction become less and less sensitive. We cau consider a body
                    an electrolyte if we can (1) collect the products of decomposition, or (2)
                    demonstrate their presence on the electrodes by means of the return current due
                    to polarization. If the resistance be very great the former method becomes
                    evidently very difficult, and in the latter complications are introduced which
                    cannot here be discussed (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Electricity).</hi> On the
                    other hand, we might easily be misled into considering a body an electrolyte
                    from the presence of mere traces of a foreign substance. Thus at one time water
                    was regarded as the only electrolyte, but it is found that the purer the water
                    is the less does it conduct electricity, and now Kohlrausch and Nippoldt have
                    shown that the presence of one 10-millionth of II <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> would be sufficient to account for its observed
                    conducting power, so that the weight of evidence goes to show that water itself
                    is not an electrolyte at alL</p>
                <p>It is not, then, surprising that views on the question of what constitutes an
                    electrolyte have changed considerably. Davy and the older chemists, as mentioned
                    above, considered water to be the only electrolyte; Faraday, by electrolysing
                    fused chlorides, &amp;c., dissipated these notions, but still regarded water as
                    the electrolyte which was decomposed when acids were subjected to the electric
                    current, and his general conclusion was that an electrolyte must be a compound
                    consisting of an equal number of chemical equivalents of its elements, that is,
                    in modern notation, must be of the type M∞R ’ ^ where <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >λ∙</hi> and y are the atomicities or valencies of the elements whose atomic
                    ινeights are represented by M and R, and thus that two elements would by uniting
                    form only one electrolyte (Exp. lies., C79-70l, 830). The oxygen salts for which
                    Faraday assigned no law were included by Daniell in the same formula as binary
                    compounds, of which the part R acting as anion was no longer an element but a
                    compound; thus ZnSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> was shown to be split up by
                    electrolysis into Zn and SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>; in that case y would
                    represent the basicity of the acid forming the salt.</p>
                <p>This hypothesis lacks definiteness, on account of the variation of the atomicity
                    of the elements, and falls through altogether in the case of copper and iron,
                    which form each two chlorides, (CuCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>,Cu <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Cl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>), (FeCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>,Fe <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Cl <hi rend="subscript"
                    > c</hi>), both electrolytes, and in consequence Wiedemann (Galv., Bd. i. §§
                    295, 34Ga, 418 (5)) modifies the statement of the hypothesis, and considers that
                    for a body to be an electrolyte it must be capable of formation by double
                    decomposition from one of the simple binary electrolytes, the exchanging atoms
                    or groups of atoms forming the ions of the new compound. Thus silver acetate
                    gives, by double decomposition with sodium chloride, silver chloride and sodium
                    acetate. Sodium acetate and silver chloride are therefore electrolytes of which
                    Ag, Cl, Na, C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> are the respective ions. This hypothesis may be
                    illustrated by a great number of instances:— the case of the decomposition of
                    uranium compounds, as UOC1 into UO and Cl, is a very good example. But
                    Wiedemann’s view would indicate that a body, in order to be an electrolyte, need
                    but be one of a “series of salts,” and we then see no reason for excluding the
                    hydrogen salts from the class; thus H.,0 and HC1 can be easily formed by double
                    decomposition, yet the former is, when pure, one of the worst liquid conductors,
                    while the latter as liquefied gas is apparently not decomposed even by 5640
                    cells of De la Rue’s chloride of silver battery, but gives vibrations indicating
                    very high resistance.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Bleekrode and De la Rue, Proc. Roy. Soe., xxv. p. 323. In fact, disruptive
                    discharge occurs by convection currents, or, if the electrodes be sufficiently
                    near, by spark. Similar phenomena may be observed by immersing the poles of a
                    Holtz machine in paraffin oil.</p></note> Bleekrode has also shown that, of all
                    the pure liquefied hydrogen acids, only HCN is an electrolyte. On the other
                    hand, liquefied NH <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, which is not formed, so far as
                    we are aware, by double decomposition, is electrolysable by only a moderate
                    battery of Bunsen's cells, giving a blue liquid at the cathode. Moreover, Buff
                    (Ann. d. Chem. und Pharm,, Bd. cx.) has electrolysed molybdic and vanadic
                    anhydrides after the manner MυO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> = MυO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + O, but these bodies are not obtainable by double
                    decomposition with a simple electrolyte.</p>
                <p>Miller (Elements Chem., i. § 282 (v) ) considers that an electrolyte must be a
                    combination of a conductor and a nonconductor, and so the majority of
                    electrolytes are. But alloys behave to a certain extent as electrolytes when
                    fused (see Wied., Galv., Bd. i. § 328), and SnCl <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>,
                    though consisting of a conductor and a non-conductor, is not an electrolyte; so
                    that this classification is not exclusive.</p>
                <p>It would therefore appear that the condition does not lie in the chemical
                    constitution of the body, but rather in its molecular state, and to this points
                    the fact that two nonconductors, as 1I <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O and HC1,
                    on being mixed form a very good conductor. In addition to this, quantitative
                    measurements of the resistance of electrolytes show that, iu the case of many
                    salt and acid solutions, there is a point of concentration below saturation, for
                    which the conductivity is a maximum. This would scarcely be the case if one
                    alone of the bodies were the conductor.</p>
                <p>The liquids which do not conduct are very various, including, besides oils and
                    resins and other organic bodies, benzine, iodide of sulphur, carbon disulphide,
                    glacial acetic acid, fused boracic anhydride, antimonic oxide and oxychloride,
                    the higher halogen salts of tin, liquid sulphurous anhydride, pure water, and
                    pure halogen acids. For others see article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Electricity,</hi> p. 51.</p>
                <p>In the description of the phenomena, in the typical case of electrolysis given
                    above, it was stated that the amount of chemical decomposition in any time is
                    proportional to the whole quantity of electricity which passes through the
                    liquid in that time; this is true in all cases of electrolysis, and was
                    established by Faraday (Exp. lies., v. 505, and ser. vii.). It forms part of the
                    general law to which his name is attached, but we prefer to consider it
                    separately for reasons that will appear when we discuss th i statement of that
                    law. We may put it thus:—If W be he mass of an electrolyte,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In what follows, the term electrolyte is used
                    in its most general sense, to signify any liquid or mixture of liquids through
                    which the current passes, and not necessarily ore definite chemical compound,
                    lienee the necessity for the condition that the ions shall not vary, as in mixed
                    electrolytes ions for high electromotive forces are different from those for low
                    (t∙i&lt;Z. inf. ).</p></note> decomposed by the passage of a qb αntity E of
                    electricity, then, as long as the ions remain of tl e same nature,</p>
                <p>W = KE . ... ... (1), where K is a constant dependent only on the nature of the
                    electrolyte, and therefore independent of the nature or size of the electrodes
                    and of any secondary actions which may take place.</p>
                <p>It is evident that if we cau prove the truth of this law for one electrolyte,
                    with ions which do not vary with variations of electromotive force, we shall
                    have a very convenient means of measuring the total amount of electricity which
                    passes through any circuit in a given time by introducing such an electrolyte
                    into the circuit, and measuring the amount of defcomposition in the given time.
                    Faraday<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n117/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0117-0108"/> demonstrated the truth of the law in the case of
                    dilute sulphuric acid by experiments with vessels in which the products of
                    decomposition of the dilute acid between platinum electrodes could be
                    conveniently collected, either separately or together, and measured [Exp. Res.,
                    714— 728.) Such an instrument he called a volta-electrometer, and subsequently a
                    voltameter. After demonstrating that the amount of decomposition was independent
                    of the size of the electrodes, he connected up two voltameters A and B, in
                    multiple arc, as in the accompanying diagram, and then passed the whole current
                    through a third C, and found that the amount of decomposition in C was equal to
                    the sum of the amounts in A and B. He therefore applied the voltameter<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Many corrections have to be
                    applied to the observations with a water voltameter in consequence of—(1) the
                    formation of ozone in the collected oxygen; (2) the formation of HO; (3) the
                    solution of the evolved gases in the water, varying with different strengths of
                    acid, and greater for oxygen than hydrogen; (4) the re-combination of the oxygen
                    and hydrogen if in contact with platinum (see Wied. Galυ., l.c.}. A diagram and
                    description of the water voltameter will be found in any of the numerous works
                    on the subject.</p></note> to measure quantities of electricity in other
                    cases.</p>
                <p>Various forms of voltameter have been employed (see Wiedemann, Calvaιιismus, Bd.
                    i. § 317-319). The most accurate is the silver voltameter of Poggendorff, which
                    consists of a vertical rod of silver with the lower end immersed in a solution
                    of silver nitrate contained in a platinum vessel; the silver is connected with
                    the positive, the platinum vessel with the negative pole of the battery, and the
                    amount of decomposition is ascertained by weighing the platinum vessel with the
                    attached silver before and after the experiment. Buff directly proved the truth
                    of equation (1) for such an instrument by electrolysing silver nitrate solutions
                    of different strengths between silver electrodes. The currents employed were
                    varied for different experiments, and were measured by a tangent galvanometer,
                    and the quantity E of electricity was deduced by observing the time of passage
                    of the current. {Ann. d. Chem. u. Pharm., xciv. 15.)</p>
                <p>We have, then, in order to demonstrate generally the law expressed in equation
                    (1), to measure the amount of the ions set free in any case of electrolysis,
                    while the amount of electricity is measured at the same time by means of a
                    voltameter included in the circuit. But the measurement of the amount of ions
                    liberated is not always an easy task; in the great majority of cases secondary
                    actions (see above, p. 106) occur, the primary results of electrolysis are
                    obscured, and in order to determine the nature and amount of the ions special
                    apparatus and further investigation are necessary.</p>
                <p>Since the ions are liberated at the electrodes the products of secondary action
                    will remain in the immediate neighbourhood if the action be not too long
                    continued. We may therefore determine the ions by collecting any gaseous
                    products, ascertaining the loss or gain in weight of the electrodes, and
                    analysing the electrolyte in the immediate neighbourhood of the electrodes,
                    taking care that the products at the two do not mix by gravitation, by
                    diffusion, or otherwise.</p>
                <p>For instance, if a fused chloride {e.g., PbCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>) be
                    electrolysed with platinum electrodes, no chlorine will be evolved at the anode,
                    although Pb will be deposited at the cathode; but if the liquid round the anode
                    be analysed, for every 414 grammes of lead at the cathode will be found 339
                    grammes of PtCl <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> round the anode. Now the platinum
                    must have been derived from the anode, which will be found to have lost 197
                    grammes in weight, consequently the 142 grammes of Cl were derived by the
                    electrolysis from the PbCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and hence PbCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> is electrolysed as Pb + Cl <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>.</p>
                <p>In order to separate the fluids at the two electrodes, various forms of apparatus
                    have been employed. For fused electrolytes a W-shaped tube, which can be divided
                    after the fluid has solidified, is sufficient; with solutions, however, where
                    the solvent introduces new complications the separation is more difficult, owing
                    to the “migration of the ions” and other causes which will be considered below.
                    Daniell and Miller {Phil. Trans., 1844) used a cylindrical glass vessel
                    separated into three compartments by porous clay diaphragms, the two end
                    compartments containing the electrodes, and having tubes for conducting away
                    gaseous products; while Hittorf, in a classical series of experiments {Pogg.
                    Ann., lxxxix. xcviii. ciii. cvi.), used a number of bell-shaped glass vessels
                    fitted to each other with indiarubber washers, the electrodes being inserted in
                    the bottom and top vessels respectively. The lower end of each bell was covered
                    with membrane to prevent mixing of the products; the whole apparatus was filled
                    with the electrolyte to be decomposed; and the products at the two electrodes
                    were known to be separated if the composition of the fluid in one of the
                    intermediate bells remained the same throughout the experiment.</p>
                <p>Great numbers of experiments have been made by different experimenters in one or
                    other of the ways mentioned, and they have thus proved that, whatever the
                    electrodes, and whatever the electromotive force, the secondary action at the
                    electrodes has no effect upon the amount of chemical decomposition,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Of course, if the products of
                    decomposition be allowed to accumulate until the electrode is surrounded with an
                    envelope of liquid differing from the original electrolyte, the whole character
                    of the decomposition changes.</p></note> and therefore the law of equation (1)
                    always holds.</p>
                <p>We can give here but a few examples of secondary action. A very good account will
                    be found in Wiedemann, Bd. i. § 326-385, with, however, the drawback of the use
                    of an obsolete chemical notation.</p>
                <p>(1.) The ions themselves are set free, but separate into component parts. That
                    this is the case with oxygen salts, which are separated into the metal and a
                    complex anion which is resolved into oxygen and an anhydride, was pointed out by
                    Daniell CΡhil. Trans., 1839), who gave to the SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>,
                    derived as electro-negative ion from sulphates, the name of oxysulphion, and so
                    on. Many similar cases occur in electrolyses of organic compounds. Thus
                    potassium acetate is electrolysed originally as KC <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> = K + C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> O <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>; hut the anion splits up (partly at least) thus: 2C <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> ≈ C <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> + 2CO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. All the potassium salts of the fatty acids behave
                    similarly, so that this becomes a general method of preparing the normal
                    paraffins.</p>
                <p>(2.) The ions appear in an abnormal molecular state. The deposit of copper in
                    Gladstone and Tribe’s ZnCu couple is a black crystalline powder (see p. 114).
                    The most important instance, however, is the formation of ozone in the oxygen
                    liberated at the anode by the electrolysis of acid solutions, which was
                    recognized by Schönbein in 1840, although the smell and powerful oxidizing
                    properties of the gas evolved had previously been noticed liy Franklin and Van
                    Marum. The amount of ozone, though very small, may be recognized by all the
                    ordinary tests (KI, indigo, &amp;c.); it diminishes with rise of the temperature
                    at which the electrolysis takes place, and is above 2 per cent, when the
                    electrolyte dilute H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi> is cooled by ice and salt, and the electrodes are platinum-iridium wires
                    (Soret). With dilute H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi> at 6° C., 100 c.c. of oxygen contained Ό0009 gramme ozone, and <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 00027 gramme at a mean temperature of — 9° C. *
                    dilute H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> CrO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> gave at
                    0° C. ’ 00052 gramme per 100 c.c. of oxygen (Soret). The amount varies with the
                    different acids, solutions of chromic an&lt;l permanganic acids giving the
                    largest percentage.</p>
                <p>These points are of importance in correcting observations by the water
                    voltameter.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n118/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0118-0109"/>
                <p>The molecular state of the deposit varies very much with the density of the
                    current, i.e., the current strength per unit area of electrode (Bunsen, Pogg.
                    Ann., xci. 619). With small current density the metals are deposited as
                    well-shaped crystals; on increasing the density, reguline metal (similar to the
                    metal when smelted) is obtained, but with great density the deposit is
                    amorphous, botryoidal, or pulverulent. With some metals, the molecular state
                    differs with the solutions from which they are deposited. Thus silver from
                    dilute solution of the nitrate, with great current density, appears as a black
                    powder, becoming grey-white and crystalline when the current ceases (Wied.,
                    Galv., Bd. 1. § 336a) but from solution of potassium silver cyanide it is
                    electrolysed as reguline metal. Gold and platinum exhibit a similar behaviour.
                    For a good instance of amorphous deposit, see the account of Gore’s explosive
                    antimony in his Electrometallurgy, p. 103.</p>
                <p>(3.) The ions very frequently react upon the electrodes and produce in some cases
                    very interesting chemical actions. If the cation and cathode are both metals, an
                    alloy of the two is the usual if not universal result. This is well known in the
                    case of the electrolysis of many metals and salts with mercury electrodes, and
                    the combination of the hydrogen set free by electrolysis with electrodes of
                    palladium, nickel, and iron may be similarly regarded; and perhaps the compounds
                    derived when ammonium salts are decomposed with a mercury cathode. Copper, when
                    deposited on platinum, alloys with it to a certain extent, the alloy penetrating
                    to a considerable depth (Gore, Electro-metallurgy, p. 47). Faraday noticed the
                    combination of tin and lead with platinum electrodes in the electrolysis of the
                    fused salts of those metals.</p>
                <p>The action of the anion upon the anode furnished Faraday with an accurate and
                    convenient means of estimating the amount of chemical decomposition produced by
                    a definite quantity' of electricity, and thereby of confirming the law given by
                    equation (1) (Exp. Res., 807-822). Thus by varying the anodes, while the cathode
                    remained the same, in the decomposition of acidulated water he found the amount
                    of hydrogen liberated at the cathode, and therefore the chemical decomposition,
                    independent of the nature of the electrodes; and by electrolysing various
                    chlorides, as of silver, tin, lead, with an anode of the same metals
                    respectively, he was enabled to determine very accurately the amount of chlorine
                    separated. We shall have more to say on the bearing of this hereafter. The
                    oxygen liberated by the electrolysis of acidulated water frequently unites with
                    the anode; even if this is of carbon it becomes oxidized to CO and CO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>; this was noticed by Faraday (Exp. Res., 744), and is
                    interesting as showing the active state of the oxygen when separated.</p>
                <p>But perhaps the most interesting examples of the action of the ions on the
                    electrodes are furnished by the capillary phenomena exhibited by mercury’ in
                    contact with dilute acid, on the passage of the current. If we have a drop of
                    water upon a surface of Hg, and the water be connected with the positive, while
                    the Hg is connected with the negative pole of a battery, the water will gather
                    itself up into a spherical drop, and on reversing the current will spread itself
                    overthe metal. This phenomenon is supposed by Wiedemann to be due, in the former
                    case, to the reduction of a film of oxide on the surface of the Hg by the
                    liberated H, thereby giving a cleaner surface with a higher capillary’ constant,
                    and, in the latter, to the oxidation of the surface by the liberated oxygen, and
                    this view is borne out by numerous experiments. Thus a reducing agent, such as
                    crystal of sodium thio-sulphate (Na <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>), introduced into the
                    drop of water produces similar contraction of the drop, while an oxidizing
                    agent, as K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Cr <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 7</hi>, produces on the contrary a similar dispersion. A drop
                    of Hg in dilute sulphuric acid, connected with the positive pole of a battery’,
                    while the negative electrode is near it, extends toward that electrode on the
                    passage of the current, becoming covered with a film of suboxide, which then
                    dissolves in the H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>,
                    and leaves again a bright surface, when the drop returns to its original
                    position, and a series of oscillations are thus set up (see Wied. Galv., i. 368
                    sqg.). With solutions of alkaline cyanides containing mercury Gore obtained
                    oscillations producing sounds (Elec.-Metall., p. 197; Broc. Roy. Soc., 1862). It
                    was observed by Erman that a drop of mercury’ in a horizontal tube, with dilute
                    acid on both sides, moved at the passage of the electric current through the
                    tube towards the negative electrode. These phenomena have been investigated
                    further by Lippmann (B <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> gT Ann., cxlix. 547,
                    trans, in Phil. Mag. [4] xlvii. 281). One of the forms of his apparatus is as
                    follows. A glass tube A, drawn out to a short capillary point of about <hi
                    rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ⅜ <hi rend="subscript"> cr</hi> mm. radius, contains
                    mercury’ which penetrates into the fine point and partly fills it, the remainder
                    being filled with dilute H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi>, into which the capillary opening dips; below the electrolyte is a
                    surface of mercury, serving as the positive electrode, sufficiently bro.td for
                    the capillary effects there to be neglected. The negative electrode is the
                    mercury in the tube A. Lippmann showed by’ this apparatus that, in order to
                    compensate the change in the capillary constant of the mercury produced by a
                    definite electromotive force of polarization, a definite increase of pressure on
                    the mercury in A is required. As for an electromotive force of polarization
                    equivalent to a Daniell cell the compensating pressure was 260 mm., and as the
                    quantity of electricity required to polarize the electrodes is very small, this
                    apparatus, when once it has been graduated by’ observing the compensating
                    pressure for known electromotive forces, may' evidently be employed as a
                    sensitive and convenient electrometer for electromotive forces less than the
                    maximum of polarization of the electrodes.</p>
                <p>We may mention one other exàmple of the action of the ions upon the electrodes.
                    An iron wire is usually attacked by dilute HNO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> (sp.
                    gr. 1 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 3); but if previously to its being immersed
                    in that liquid it is employed as the anode in the electrolysis of diluted oxygen
                    acids, the nitric acid has no longer any effect upon it, not even tarnishing the
                    surface, and the wire differs from ordinary iron in being strongly’
                    electro-negative to it, and indeed to copper, in dilute acids (Martens, Pogg.
                    Ann., lxi. 121). It is then said to be in One passive state, and is considered
                    to be covered with a film of oxide which is strongly electro-negative, and
                    insoluble in dilute nitric acid (Faraday, Phil. Mag., ix. p. 60, 1836, x. p.
                    175, 1837; Beetz, Pogg. Ann., lxii. 234, lxiii. 415). De Regnon, however
                    (Comptes Rendus, lxxix. 299), attributes the phenomena to polarization. This
                    peculiar state may be induced by various processes; Keir (Phil. Trans., 1790)
                    observed it when an iron wire was dipped into strong nitric acid (sp. gr. 1 5),
                    by which its surface is not attacked. A more dilute solution has the same,
                    effect (Schonbein, Pogg. Ann., xxxviii. 444), if the wire be immersed several
                    times, or if the solution contain chromic or sulphuric and permanganic acids
                    (Boutmy and Chateau, Cosmos, xix. 117). Iron when dipped in very strong solution
                    of AgNO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> does not precipitate the silver, and is
                    electro-negative even to that metal. Another method of rendering iron passive,
                    evidently the same in principle as the one first mentioned, is to touch the iron
                    wire immersed in dilute nitric acid, by carbon, platinum, or other
                    electro-negative element itself in contact with the liquid; and on the contrary,
                    passive iron becomes active if it be touched by a body electro-positive to it,
                    as copper or zinc. If a passive wire be partly immersed in the dilute acid, and
                    an active wire in contact with it be slowly introduced into the liquid, the
                    latter becomes passive too; but if they touch under the surface, both are
                    rendered active. Iron is rendered passive also by heating in a current of oxygen
                    or an oxidizing flame until it is tarnished On the other hand, the passive metal
                    becomes active under the influence of any reducing action upon its surface,
                    whether by deposition of H upon it by electrolysis, by heating the metal in a
                    reducing flame, or by abrading the surface. One modification of the electrolytic
                    method is to touch the metal in dilute nitric acid, for a moment, with a copper
                    wire. The point touched becomes immediately active, and therefore
                    electro-positive to the rest, and so currents are set up from active to passive
                    metal through the acid, which accordingly reverse the state of both parts, and a
                    curious series of oscillations result, ending in the whole becoming active.
                    (Schonbein, l.e. Compare these with the phenomena of alternation of passive and
                    active states of iron, and of the oxidized and bright surfaces of amalgamated
                    zinc described by Joule, Phil. Mag., 1844, i. 106).</p>
                <p>Iron is not the only metal which behaves thus. Nickel, cobalt, tin, bismuth, and
                    even copper, all exhibit similar phenomena in strong HN0 <hi rend="subscript">
                    s</hi> and as positive electrodes; and aluminium thus treated is
                    electro-negative even to passive iron (see Wiedemann, Galv., Bd. i. §
                    539-542).</p>
                <p>(4.) The ions act upon the fluid surrounding the electrodes. Actions of this kind
                    in both fused and dissolved electrolytes nearly always occur unless the ions
                    combine with the electrodes; thus perchlorides, if such exist, are formed from
                    the chlorides, and perchlorates from chlorates at the anode (Kolbe). At the
                    cathode the secondary actions are cases of reduction; thus if solution of
                    potassic iodide be electrolysed, corresponding to 1 equivalent of iodine at the
                    anode, there will appear not only 1 equivalent of H, at the cathode, but an
                    equivalent of KHO as well, so that the potassium liberated from the iodine must
                    have acted upon the water and formed KHO. If ammonium chloride be electrolysed,
                    the chlorine at the anode reacts upon the NH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> C1,
                    giving free nitrogen and nitrogen-chloride. The electrolysis of ammonium nitrate
                    is still more interesting, as NH∙ <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> and H are
                    separated at the cathode, where the hydrogen reduces the nitric acid of the
                    nitrate, and nitrogen is evolved, while at the anode NO <hi rend="subscript">
                    3</hi> is deposited, which forms with the water nitric acid and oxygen, the
                    latter reacting upon the ammonia of the nitrate, again evolving nitrogen, so
                    that that element appears at both poles,—at one mixed with ammonia, at the other
                    with oxygen (Miller). Some of the reactions investigated by Kolbe and Burgoin
                    with organic salts are very interesting, but more exclusively to the chemist.
                    The oxidizing and reducing actions are very powerful, as the bodies probably act
                    in the “nascent state.</p>
                <p>Solutions of acetate and nitrate of lead, when electrolysed by currents of small
                    density, deposit at the positive electrode hydrated peroxide of lead as a black
                    powder. If a. polished iron plate be used as the anode, the deposit shows
                    prismatic colours depending on the thickness, and the process has been applied
                    in the arts to colour metallic tovs, under the name of metallochromy. If a fine
                    wire as cathode be placed vertica <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ly above the
                    anode plate.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0119-0110"/>
                <p>the colours are arranged in circles long known as Nohili’s rings. Similar
                    phenomena are exhibited by salts of bismuth, nickel, cobalt, and manganese, all
                    of which are precipitated as peroxides, usually hydrated (Wernicke, Pogg. Ann.,
                    cxli. 109), upon the anode by the action of the oxygen liberated by the passage
                    of electricity. Silver is also thrown down as a black peroxide, together with
                    some oxygen from a solution of sulphate and nitrate, and iron behaves somewhat
                    similarly in an ammoniacal solution of the protoxide in vacuo.</p>
                <p>Such secondary actions vary very conspicuously with the density of the current
                    and the temperature. Bunsen Hogg. Ann., xci.) electrolysed solution of chromic
                    chloride, and by increasing the current density obtained in succession H, Cr,O
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, CrO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, and metallic Cr
                    at the cathode; the reason for this is evidently that with high current
                    densities the supply of ions in any time is greater than can take part in
                    secondary action, and hence some of the original ion is deposited. A rise of
                    temperature favours chemical action, and promotes rapid mixture of the ions with
                    the solution at the same time; so the higher the temperature the greater is the
                    current density required to isolate the ions. From concentrated sulphuric acid,
                    for instance, below 80° only H and 0 are obtained; between 80° and 90° oxygen is
                    given off at the anode, while at the cathode H and S, due to reduction of H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> by hydrogen, appear;
                    above 90° sulphur alone is deposited at the cathode (Warburg, Pogg. Ann., cxxxv.
                    114).</p>
                <p>Instructive and important cases of secondary action occur when the electric
                    current is made to traverse a mixture of several solutions. Magnus Hogg. Ann.,
                    cii. 23) determined by experiments on dilute CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    solution, in an apparatus with a porous diaphragm of clay, colloid paper, or
                    animal membrane, specially arranged that the lines of flow should be parallel,
                    and the current density therefore uniform, that there was a limiting value of
                    the density above which both copper and hydrogen appeared at the cathode, but
                    below only copper. His results show that this density is independent of length
                    of the electrolyte and material of the electrodes, but varies directly as the
                    size of the electrodes. The specific resistance of the constituents, as well as
                    the relative position of the two ions in the “electro-chemical series” (vid.
                    inf), are of great importance, the electro-negative metal always appearing
                    first.</p>
                <p>In order to determine whether the current traversed both electrolytes or only
                    one, Hittorf Hogg. Ann., ciii. 48), with the apparatus above described (p. 108),
                    electrolysed mixed solutions of potassium chloride and iodide in different
                    proportions, and arrived at the important conclusion that for all densities the
                    current traversed both electrolytes, as it were in multiple arc (though the
                    resistance of the mixture apparently bears no definite relation to the
                    resistances of its constituents except for some of the haloid salts); but the
                    products liberated depend on the secondary action at the electrode, and hence on
                    the current density. The formation of an envelope of liquid of altered
                    composition would also introduce complications (Smee, Phil. Mag., xxv. 437).
                    Buff, by experimenting on solution of HC1, with a small amount of H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, substantially confirms
                    Hittorf’s results (Ann. d. Chem. u. Pharm., cv. 156).</p>
                <p>These considerations are, of course, especially useful in effecting the
                    deposition of alloys by electrolysis. The possibility of so doing appears to
                    depend upon the composition of the solution employed. An acid solution of Cu and
                    Zn deposits only copper, but the addition of potassium cyanide determines the
                    deposition of brass. Gore (Electro-metallurgy, p. 51) points out that, in order
                    to deposit an alloy of two metals, there must be no electric separation when the
                    two metals are in contact with the liquid; if indeed such were the case, a
                    deposit of the two metals, say of Cu and Zn, would immediately act as a CuZn
                    couple (see p. 114), and the electro-negative metal alone would be deposited at
                    the expense of the electropositive.</p>
                <p>Although the amount of a salt decomposed by the passage of a given quantity of
                    electricity is the same whether the salt be fused or dissolved in alcohol,
                    water, or other solvent, yet the presence of the solvent produces an important
                    effect upon the electrolyte, which should not be lost sight of in quantitative
                    experiments. The phenomenon is known as the “migration of the ions” (Hittorf),
                    or the “unequal transfer of the ions” (Miller). Suppose, for example, we
                    electrolyse a solution of CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> containing <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 16 gramme of salt per cubic centimetre, in a vessel
                    separated by a porous diaphragm into two portions A and B. Let electricity be
                    passed through the solution between platinum electrodes from B to A, until l <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 59 grammes of CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> have
                    been decomposed. Then—</p>
                <p>(1.) l <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 59 g. of CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    has been removed from the solution;</p>
                <p>(2.) <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 63 g. of Cu has been deposited on the
                    platinum cathode;</p>
                <p>(3.) ’ 16 g. of 0 has been evolved at the anode, and <hi rend="superscript">
                    -</hi> 80 g. of SO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> absorbed there by the water of
                    the solution.</p>
                <p>Now, had the electrolyte been a single fused compound, no com-Elication could
                    have arisen; the liquid remaining must still have een homogeneous (except for
                    the presence of the ions near one or ether electrode). But when the salt is
                    dissolved, it is important to consider from what part of the solution the salt
                    has been removed. Suppose that of the CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    decomposed —th was taken from the vessel B, and therefore ——ths from A. The
                    result of electrolysis may then be exhibited thus (assuming that no diffusion
                    takes place through the diaphragm) :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>In A.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>In B.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Before Electrolysis</p><p>After „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>x g. CuSo <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.</p><p>Λr-- <hi
                            rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 159 g∙ CuSo <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + ∖
                            n</p><p>•63 g. Cu, including Cu deposited.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>y g. CuSo <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.</p><p>(y--i.l∙5S)∖ g. CuSo
                            <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> +</p><p>96 g. So <hi rend="subscript">
                            4</hi>, including oxygen collected.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>I f the volumes of the two vessels are equal, x and y are of course equal, since
                    the fluid is originally homogeneous.</p>
                <p>1 n-1</p>
                <p>Hence A will gain — <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 63 g. Cu, and lose —— ‘96 g.
                    SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.</p>
                <p>1 n-1</p>
                <p>B will lose — '63 g. Cu, and gain —'96 g. SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.</p>
                <p>We may therefore state the result thus :—For every equivalent of copper deposited
                    upon the cathode the entire gain of copper in the vessel A is —th equivalent,
                    and the entire gain of SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> in B is n-1 .</p>
                <p>- — equiv. The experiment shows that the entire gain of copper in A is <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 276 × '63 g., and the gain of SO <hi rend="subscript"
                    > 4</hi> in B is <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 724 × <hi rend="superscript">
                    -</hi> 96 g.; and hence, for solutions of CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> of
                    that strength,—= <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 276, and conn — 1</p>
                <p>sequently ~^^~ = '724, so that, of the CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    decomposed, 72’4 per cent, is taken from A, and 27’6 per cent, from B, and the
                    solution round the cathode is weakened much faster than that round the anode.
                    This will be observable by the depth of the blue colour of the solution. If the
                    anode be of copper and be vertically above the cathode, the effect is well seen;
                    for although the total amount of CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> in solution
                    remains constant, the difference of colour at the two electrodes is very
                    apparent, and, if the action be continued, strong dark-blue solution drops down
                    in thin streams from the anode through the more dilute (Magnus).</p>
                <p>The value of n differs for different salts, and usually for solutions of the same
                    salt of different strengths, though in some cases, as K <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, KN0 <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, NaCl,
                    and KC1, the variations for great difference of concentration are very slight.
                    The following table shows a few of the results obtained by Hittorf, with the
                    apparatus described above, by which errors due to diffusion were avoided. The
                    numbers n — 1</p>
                <p>in the third column indicate what is called above , i.e., the total n excess in
                    equivalents of the anion in the vessel containing the anodes corresponding to a
                    decomposition of one equivalent of salt; or, except in the last few cases, that
                    part of the salt decomposed which is taken from the vessel containing the
                    cathode.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Salt</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>No. of cc. of solvent containing one gramme of salt.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>n—1</p><p>n</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>HC1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'319</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>HC1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>36'2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'168</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>HC1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1409</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'171</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>HC1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2125'9</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'210</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>HBr</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8'6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'178</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="smallcaps">hio</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                            3</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>13 3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'102</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>11 8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>K <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> soi</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>412 8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'498</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>NaCl ’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20'7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'634</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fe <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Cl <hi rend="subscript">
                            β</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25'25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•600</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cdl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> {</p><p>Cdl <hi rend="subscript">
                            2</hi> in alcohol.... ∙∣</p><p>Znl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> in
                            alcohol</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4 2</p><p>116'7</p><p>Γl</p><p>37 2</p><p>05</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1 14</p><p>•613</p><p>2102 1∙318</p><p>216</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The iodides of zinc and cadmium are anomalous, but it may be supposed that they
                    are decomposed as double salts thus :—</p>
                <p>2CdI <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> =Cd+ (CdI <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + I,) ,
                    or</p>
                <p>3CdI,=Cd+ (2 Cdl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + I <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>).</p>
                <p>The total increase in the amount of an ion in one part of a vessel divided by a
                    porous partition is also affected by a mechanical transference of the
                    electrolyte through the pores of the diaphragm, generally in the positive
                    direction of the current, which is very noticeable in cases of electrolytes of
                    high resistance. This was discovered by Reuss in 1807, and observed by Porret
                    soon afterwards<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n120/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0120-0111"/>; it has been investigated by Wiedemann (Pogg.
                    Ann., lxxxvii. 321), and Quincke Hogg. Aim., cxiii. 513). The former worked
                    wit)ι a porous cell, and estimated the effect either by the quantity of the
                    electrolyte which passed through the wall of the cell, the pressure remaining
                    constant, or by the rise of pressure in the porous cell measured by a mercury
                    manometer. A current of moderate intensity through distilled water caused 1777
                    g. of the electrolyte to pass through the diaphragm towards the cathode in a
                    quarter of an hour, and with a 19 per cent, solution of CuSO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, a pressuιe of 176'5 mm. was observed in the cell
                    containing the cathode, due to the current of a battery of DanelΓs cells.
                    Quincke, however, employed, instead of a porous cell, a capillary tube without
                    diaphragm, open at one end, and connected with a reservoir at the other
                    containing one electrode, while the other electrode consisted of one of several
                    pieces of platinum wire, sealed into the tube in various positions. His current
                    was obtained from either a Leyden battery or 40 to 80 Grove s cells. The two
                    ways of experimenting gave concordant results, and showed that the pressure on
                    the cathode vessel varies as the electromotive force between the electrodes, and
                    so diminishes with the resistance if the current be kept constant. It is also,
                    in Quincke’s apparatus, inversely proportional to the square of the diameter of
                    the tube, and, for tubes of the same sectional area, is greatly increased by
                    increasing the perimeter. The direction of motion is, as stated above, usually
                    towards the cathode, and is immediately reversed on a reversal of the current,
                    and stops when the circuit is broken. The rate of transfer is increased by
                    coating the tube with shellac; it is different for different fluids, and with
                    certain specimens of absolute alcohol, and with turpentine oil, the direction is
                    reversed, unless in the latter case the tube is coated with sulphur, when the
                    direction is as before.</p>
                <p>Intimately connected with these phenomena is the motion of solid particles
                    contained in fluids of high resistance. Faraday observed the motion of silk
                    threads in water, and Jürgensen made many experiments on the subject with a
                    capillary tube in the form of three sides of a rectangle with bulbs at the two
                    corners which contained the electrodes; in one was a porous diaphragm as well.
                    Quincke (l.c.) used a similar apparatus to this, as well as the one described
                    above, and observed by means of a microscope a double motion of particles of
                    starch contained in water subject to the action of an electric machine. Near the
                    sides of the tube the particles moved towards the negative electrode, but in the
                    middle in the opposite direction; on turning the machine more quickly the
                    particles near the sides gradually lost their velocity, and then began to move
                    towards the positive electrode in common with those in the middle. So that it is
                    highly probable that near the sides the particles are in the first instance
                    carried along by the motion of the fluid there, but on increasing the current
                    the friction of the liquid in contact with the tube prevents its velocity
                    increasing so fast as that of the particles in the opposite direction, and
                    ultimately the motion of the particles in that direction becomes apparent.
                    Similar phenomena are observed .with many finely divided bodies suspended in
                    water, as gold, copper, graphite, silica, felspar, sulphur, lycopodium, &amp;c.,
                    as well as minute drops of liquid, as CS, and oil of turpentine, and bubbles of
                    oxygen, marsh gas, &amp;c. All these are urged in water towards the positive
                    electrode, but in oil of turpentine the direction is reversed except in the case
                    of particles of sulphur; the direction is also reversed for silica in carbon
                    disulphide.</p>
                <p>Considering now our first equation W = KE established, K being, as stated,
                    dependent only on the nature of the electrolyte, we proceed to examine the
                    constant K and its value for different electrolytes. The primary investigation
                    is due to Faraday, who found that if A and B be two electrolytes, and if a
                    quantity E of electricity decomposes a mass X of A and Y of B, then X and Y are
                    chemically equivalent, that is, are the amouuts of A and B which would take part
                    in a double decomposition between them. According to this view we have for any
                    electrolyte W = ∕χ∈E, where μ. is the amount of the electrolyte chemically
                    equivalent to 1 gramme of water, and « is the number of grammes of water
                    decomposed by a unit of electricity, and is called the electrochemical
                    equivalent of water. This appears to be always true, but the law as usually
                    stated refers to the amounts of the ions separated. The most general statement
                    which the facts allow is the following, known as Faraday’s law;—In any
                    electrolytic decomposition whatever., the mass w of one at least (usually of
                    each) of the ions, simple or complex, separated by the passage of a quαn- ^ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t</hi> y of electricity E, is chemically equivalent to the
                    amount of hydroyen separated by the same quantity of electricity in a water
                    voltameter, and hence w = mhE, where m is the chemi cal equivalent of the ion,
                    and h the electrochemical equivalent of hydrogen.</p>
                <p>Since water contains ∣th its weight of hydrogen h = ’ <hi rend="subscript">
                    £</hi>.</p>
                <p>Faraday admitted as electrolytes only bodies containing an equal number of
                    equivalents of their components, and accordingly found that the amount of either
                    ion was equivalent to the hydrogen evolved in a voltameter included in the
                    circuit. The seventh series of Experimental Researches was devoted to proving
                    this most important law. Two methods were adopted—(I) by collecting and
                    measuring the products of decomposition, a voltameter being included in the
                    circuit, and (2) by introducing an anode with which the anion could combine (as
                    for instance a Pb anode in fused PbCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, a silver one
                    in fused AgCl), and determining the loss in weight of the anode. By these means
                    the law was proved for simple fused electrolytes, such as the chlorides,
                    &lt;fcc. Daniell extended it to oxygen salt solutions, and showed that they were
                    decomposed into a metal and a complex ion, this last splitting up into oxygen
                    and an anhydride which united with water to form the corresponding acid,
                    e.y.,</p>
                <p>ZnSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> =Zn + (SO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> +
                    O).</p>
                <p>Matteucci and E. Becquerel added a large amount of evidence in defence of the
                    law, which was demonstrated with great accuracy (to ⅜ per cent.) by Soret (Ann.
                    de Chim. et de Phys., [3] xlii. 257) for a series of copper salts; and by Buff
                    for great variations of current strength with silver compounds.</p>
                <p>So long as we confine ourselves to normal salts there is little difficulty about
                    the statement of the relation; even with such compounds as the series of
                    phosphates, the double cyanides, &amp;c., which are decomposed as in the
                    following table, the amount of either ion may be considered equivalent to the H
                    of the voltameter.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Electrolyte.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Anim corresponding to H in voltameter.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Cation.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>observer.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>B <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                            0<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This oxygen is
                            set free.</p></note></p><p>3 ^ <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> ^
                            2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Na.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Hittorf.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>KaPo <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>P <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> o <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> o
                            &gt;</p><p>2 ^ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> 2 ’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Na.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>∖</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>l ’ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> 0
                            ∕</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Na.</p><p>1</p><p>Na.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>4'2</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>c</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Na <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> HΓO <hi rend="subscript">
                            4</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="smallcaps">∕p,o, h</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                            j</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">o∖,</hi> o &gt;</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Daniell and Miller,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>â (</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>∖ 4 ^ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> 4 ∕^ <hi rend="superscript">
                            t</hi> ^ 2</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>&gt; Phil. Trant., 1844, p. 1 ‘ <hi rend="superscript">
                            1</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>i</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>NaIINH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> PO <hi rend="subscript">
                            4</hi>...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>H <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> (N∏ <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>)
                            <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> P <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> o <hi
                            rend="subscript"> f</hi>, 0 ·</p><p>2 ^ ’ 2 '</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Na.</p><p>•</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>K <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> FcCv <hi rend="subscript">
                            β</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>I^ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi>
                            Cy.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>κ. ’</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>J</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>AgCy+Cy<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                            well-known deposit of silver in electro-plating is due to second* ary
                            action of the K.</p></note> l(Al <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> 3So <hi
                            rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.+≡2* <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> j <hi
                            rend="superscript"> ,</hi>-</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>κ.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>K <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> Al <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> 4(So
                            <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>K.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Hittorf.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Faraday’s law is nearly always true for both ions, but there are, as before
                    stated, examples of elements forming two series of electrolysable salts,
                    especially when dissolved in water. In these cases the electronegative ion is
                    usually equivalent tothe H of the voltameter, or we may consider that the
                    chemical equivalent of the positive ion varies, while that of the negative ion
                    remains unchanged in the different combinations; so that ferric chloride may be
                    regarded as a dichloride with formula feCl <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>, where
                    fe = ∣Fej cuprous chloride cuCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, where cu = 2Cu,
                    and so on. Considerable confusion, too, arose from the arbitrary numbers for
                    chemical equivalents wlιich formerly obtained, and which caused such compounds
                    as Al,Cl <hi rend="subscript"> g</hi>, SbCl <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>, AuCl
                    <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>, to appear anomalous, and waιτanted E. Becquerel
                    (Ann. de Chirn. et de Phys. [3] t. xi. p. 178) in considering that generally the
                    amount of electro-negative ion alone was equivalent to the II of the
                    voltameter.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The chemical
                    equivalents of Al, Sb, Au were taken to be 13'5, 61 98 respectively, instead of
                    9 1, 40 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 6, 65 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 as
                    now.</p></note> This was borne out by his electrolysis of 2X <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, 7PbO, 3H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O, and N,O <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, 2PbO, H,O,
                    which gave { and $ an equivalent of Pb at the cathode respectively; but the law
                    as thus modified fails in the case of K <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> Cr <hi
                    rend="subscript"> s</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>, which gives K + (CrO
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + ⅜O) both in the melted and dissolved state, and
                    in that of Na <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> S <hi rend="subscript"> j</hi>, which
                    gives Na + (S, + ⅜S), and also for basic acetate of lead.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n121/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0121-0112"/>
                <p>Faraday’s law receives striking confirmation from the. electrolysis of several
                    solutions arranged in series in contact with each other bv means either of
                    porous septa, asbestos wicks, or siphon tubes. Each liquid then acts as an
                    electrode to the adjacent ones, and so at the junction we have separated the
                    anion of one electrolyte and the cation of the next. These in general unite, and
                    if the resulting compound be insoluble, a precipitate is thrown down. Faraday
                    thus precipitated magnesia from its sulphate by electrolysing a solution of that
                    salt in contact with water, the current passing from the salt solution to the
                    water. Now, in all cases in which the ions unite at the junction, and do not
                    appear free at all, the amount of the cation of one liquid must be chemically
                    equivalent to that of the anion of the succeeding one, and hence obey Faraday’s
                    law. Many of the decompositions and combinations thus effected are very
                    interesting, a list showing in a tabulated form the results of experiments by
                    Hisinger and Berzelius, Davy, Daniell, Miller, and others will be found in
                    Wiedemann {Galv., Bd. i. § 368). We can only mention one example which is of
                    theoretical importance. If the positive electrode be in solution of iodic acid
                    which is in contact with dilute sulphuric acid containing the cathode, then at
                    the surface of separation there will be formed I and SO <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi>, or H and SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, according as the I observed at
                    the negative electrode in the electrolysis of HIO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>
                    solution is an ion or due to secondary action. By the union of the two ions at
                    the junction the latter is shown to be the case; therefore iodic acid is
                    electrolysed as H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + (I <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    O <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> + O).</p>
                <p>We gather at once from the truth of Faraday’s law that we can assign to each ion
                    an electrochemical equivalent (which may be referred to as E.C.E.), which will
                    enable us to determine at once the amount of the ion which will be separated by
                    a given quantity of electricity. With the notation already used the E.C.E. of an
                    ion =⅜ me. The value of ∈—the amount of water decomposed by one C.G.S.
                    electromagnetic unit of electricity—from experiments of Weber, Joule, Bunsen,
                    Casselmann, and. Kohlrausch is •00093 gramme (Wied. Galv., Bd. iii. §
                    1077-1079). The quantity m is one of the chemical equivalents of the ion,
                    usually that deduced from its most stable salts; some metals, indeed, with two
                    series of salts have two E. C. E. s. The following table of the elements gives
                    the values of m and the E.C.E.s in absolute units, as far as they have been
                    experimentally determined. Since m bears a simple ratio to the atomic weight,
                    its value can be corrected by the results of chemical analysis.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="8"><p>Table of Electrochemical Equivalents.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>∞ Oz</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>c s</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>)mic weight.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>îctrochemlca equivalent in <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> ∙drogen
                            unit</p><p>(ml.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>E d</p><p>S∞∏ g.kW &lt;u c <hi rend="superscript"> jo</hi>-⅛ '". £
                            S II w <hi rend="superscript"> ft</hi> s</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>α</p><p>O&gt;</p><p>S</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>tmic weight,</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>E.C.E. in fdrogen unit</p><p>(m).</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>E.C.E. in absolute units</p><p>1</p><p>= 9 <hi rend="superscript">
                            me</hi> ∙</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>s</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>&lt;</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>r5 W</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Q "</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>S</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>M</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Al ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>275</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> l(<hi rend="superscript">
                            2</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00094</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Mo....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>96</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Faraday,
                            Exp. Res., ser. vii.</p></note>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Sb</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>122</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40∙6(<hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00420</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ni</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29∙5(<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Renault (Z.c. infra").</p></note>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>00305</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>As....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>25∙(Z)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00258</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Nb....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>97’5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ua....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>137</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>68∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00708</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>N</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(»)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3i ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>210</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7K <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>)(<hi rend="superscript">
                            2</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ό0733</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Os</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>199</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>109</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8(*&gt;</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00083</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>8r</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>80</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>80(&gt;)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0Ô826</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pd ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>106</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> &gt;</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3d ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>112</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00578</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>P</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>31</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2s. ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>133</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>133(∙ ’)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•01374</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Pt ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>197</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>98∙5(1)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•01018</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ca....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00206</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>K ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>391</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>391 ()</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00404</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>C</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Ro ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>104 3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> &gt;</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ce ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>92</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Rb....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>85</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>85(&lt;)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00878</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cl ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>35 5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>35 5(1)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>00366</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ru....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>104 2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cr ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>52∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>175</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00181</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Se</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>795</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> j</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Co ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>59</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>29∙5(i)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00305</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Si</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Cu ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>63</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>( 3Γ6(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00326 )</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ag....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>108</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>108(i)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•01116</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>(63(*)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00651 f</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Na ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>23(i)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00237</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>n</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>96</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Sf ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>87∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>43 7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>00452</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>F</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19(1)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00196</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>S</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>32</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16(3)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00165</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>G</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>93</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Ta....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>138</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Au....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>196 6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>65∙5(<hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00677</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Te</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>129</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>64∙5(<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Either these elements have not been obtained as ions by electrolytic
                            action, or qualitative experiments are wanting.</p></note>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00666</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>il</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•000103</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'∏</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>204</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>204(2)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>02108</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>In ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>113<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Bunsen.</p></note></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> 1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Th....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>119</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>I</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>127</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>127(∙)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•01312</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sn</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>118</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>f 29 5(<hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00305)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ir ....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>197</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>( 59&gt;(2)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00610)</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fe...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>28(1)(*)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00289</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ti</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>La. ..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>92</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>w....</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>184</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Pb ..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>207</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>103∙5(&gt;)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>01069</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>u</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>120</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(’)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Li ..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00072</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>V</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>137</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mg..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>243</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>12(&gt;)(2)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00124</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Zn...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>65</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>32∙5(i)(2)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00336</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Mn..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>27∙5(1)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•00284</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Zr ...</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>89∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>(<hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>)</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Hg..</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>200</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>J200(&gt;)(*)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>.02066 1</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>(100(2)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•01033 )</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Every complex ion has also a definite electrochemical equivalent, usually
                    coinciding with its chemical equivalent. The E.C.E. of an electrolyte is the sum
                    of the.E.C.E.s of its component ions.</p>
                <p>Renault<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“Vérification
                    expérimentale de la réciproque de la loi de Faraday, sur la décomposition des
                    électrolytes.” Paris, 1867; Ann. de Chirn. [4] xi. 137.</p></note> determined
                    the E.C.E.s by an inverse method. He observed the amount of the metal which,
                    forming the negative pole of a battery with various electrolytes, gave a current
                    equivalent to that produced by the dissolution of a definite amount of zinc in a
                    ZnPt cell, the two currents passing through a differential galvanometer, and
                    thus compared the amounts of elements which generate the same quantity of
                    electricity in combining. It is perhaps necessary to observe that the
                    electrolytic reactions taking place in a galvanic cell which generates a current
                    are in every way identical with those due to a current from an external source
                    sent through the electrolyte. In the former case, the energy of chemical
                    affinity at the electrodes is transformed into the energy of electrical
                    separation, and in the latter the converse is the case.</p>
                <p>The Electrochemical Series.</p>
                <p>It is evident from ∙all the examples we have given that it is' not an accident
                    whether an ion will appear at the anode or cathode; the cations have been all
                    more or less similar in character, and were either metals or more allied to the
                    metals than the corresponding anions, which were bodies like Cl, Br, I, CN, O,
                    &amp;c. Faraday {Exp. Res., 847) was accordingly led to consider that an element
                    or radicle was unalterably either an anion or a cation; this, however, was
                    contradicted by the fact that the same element may act as an anion in one
                    solution and a cation in another, as is the case with iodine, which in KI is an
                    anion, but from a solution of iodine bromide (IBr) appears at the cathode. The
                    electrolysis of alloys<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Alloys of tin and lead, potassium and sodium, sodium amalgam, gold amal gam,
                    and fused cast-iron have all been shown to suffer chemical decomposition on the
                    passage of the electric current (wied. Galv., i. § 328).</p></note> points in
                    the same direction, so that the conclusion is suggested to us that “anion” and
                    “cation” have only relative meanings, and that we might arrange the elements in
                    a series such that, in a compound of an element A with any one of those above
                    it, A would appear as a cation, but in a compound with any of those below, as an
                    anion. To do this by purely electrolytic means is out of the question, as binary
                    electrolytes do not exist for each pair of elements. As far, however, as the
                    series can be thus made out, it is found that, as a rule, if two elements A and
                    B, such that A is above B in the series, be immersed in a simple electrolyte, as
                    dilute II <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, and
                    connected by means of a wire, the current flows from B to A through the liquid.
                    Hence in unknown cases we may observe the direction of the current when the two
                    elements are immersed in an electrolyte, say H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, and determine the relative position in the
                    series.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This is not
                    always conclusive evidence, as the direction of the current for tho same two
                    elements sometimes varies with the electrolyte employed, as will be seen by
                    referring to the list of chemico-electric series in Gore, Electro-metallurgy, p.
                    66. The boraeic acid ∙&lt;∙H"s is peculiarly anomalous.</p></note> With the
                    series thus roughly formed, it is observed that the wider two elements are apart
                    the greater is the chemical affinity between the two, and thus that if we have a
                    compound MR, where M is the electro-positive element, a more electro-positive
                    element M' having a greater affinity for R than M tends to replace M from the
                    compound, and a more electro-negative element R ’ tends to replace R as iron
                    replaces copper from CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, and chlorine iodine from
                    KI. This further assists us in forming an electrochemical series of the
                    elements, but it is still not very strictly arranged, and many of the members of
                    the series are placed by their analogy to elements whose positions are known.
                    Moreover, it is supposed that the relative position of two elements may vary
                    with the temperature. Thus carbon which is used in batteries as the negative
                    element, is at a full red heat electro-positive even to potassium, or at least
                    reduces the carbonate of that element. Jablochkoff {Comptes Rendus, Dec. 3,
                    1877) describes a cell of which the positive element is coke. The electrolyte is
                    fused sodium or potassium nitrate, and the negative element is a cast-iron
                    vessel containing the fused salt. The current is from coke to cast-iron through
                    the nitrate, and the electromotive force 2 to 3 volts.</p>
                <p>Berzelius’s final series stands thus :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Electro-negative.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Oxygen.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Boron.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Mercury.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Thorium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Sulphur.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Carbon.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Silver.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Zirconium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Selenium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Antimony.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Copper.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Aluminium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Nitrogen.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tellurium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Bismuth.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Didymium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Fluorine.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tantalum.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Tin.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Lanthanum.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Chlorine.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Titanium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Lead.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Yttrium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Bromine.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Silicon.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Cadmium.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Glucinum.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Iodine.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hydrogen.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Cobalt.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Magnesium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Phosphorus.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Gold.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Nickel.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Calcium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Arsenic.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Osmium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Iron.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Strontium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Chromium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Indium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Zinc.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Barium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Vanadium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Platinum.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Manganese.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Lithium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Molybdenum.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Rhodium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Uranium.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>Sodium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Tungsten.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Palladium.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Cerium.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>*Potassium.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Electro-positive.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n122/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0122-0113"/>
                <p>Radicles as NH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> and S0 <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    behave as elements, and have each a definite position in the series.</p>
                <p>Theory of Electrolysis.</p>
                <p>Any hypothesis which seeks to account for the phenomena of electrolysis has
                    mainly to deal with the two points—(1) that the ions appear only at the
                    electrodes, and (2) that the electricity at the same time is conducted between
                    the electrodes. From the behaviour of electrolytes iu contact on the passage of
                    the current we conclude that if we had a series of cells consisting alternately
                    of KC1 and NaCl, the result of electrolysis might be represented thus :—</p>
                <p>Before electrolysis,</p>
                <p>KCl,NaCI, KCl,NaCl; after it,</p>
                <p>-K NaCl,KCl,NaCl,Cl-f-.</p>
                <p>Now, we may suppose similar effects to occur if the cells were all identical, and
                    farther we may consider the collection of molecules in any electrolyte as such a
                    series of cells in contact, and argue the electrolytic process to be a series of
                    decompositions and recombinations along a line of molecules resulting finally in
                    the decomposition of molecules at the electrodes alone. The decomposition of any
                    oxygen salt would be similar, with the exception that the one ion is complex.
                    Thus</p>
                <p>— ZnSQ^, ZnSO^~ZnSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> +</p>
                <p>might represent the decomposition of zinc sulphate. This idea of alternate
                    decompositions and recombinations was originally suggested by Grotthuss in 1805,
                    who, however, attributed the separation to attractions, due to the electrodes,
                    varying inversely as the square of the distance. Faraday (Exp. Res., 481 -563,
                    series iv. ) discusses the theory, and, while denying the attractions of the
                    electrodes defends the idea of decomposition and reformation, chiefly against De
                    la Rive and Riflault and Chompré, and considers thatthe effect of the passage of
                    the current is due to a change of the chemical affinities of the components of
                    the electrolyte, and he points out (1343 sqq , ser. viii.) that the
                    decomposition is probably preceded by a polarized state of the particles, as
                    explained by him in his theory of electrostatic induction. This is confirmed by
                    experiments of Tribe (Proc. Roy. Soc., 1875-6), who inserted 198 small strips of
                    silver in rows, parallel to the line joining the electrodes in dilute CuSO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, and observed that copper was deposited on the ends
                    facing the anode, while gas was given off from the other ends; by comparing the
                    amounts of the deposit he explored the electric field, showing that it was
                    roughly similar to the magnetic field due to a north and a south pole.</p>
                <p>Many investigators have suggested additions to Grotthuss's hypothesis (see
                    Wiedemann, i. 421, α.), and in particular Hittorf (Pogg. Ann., lxxxix.) has
                    expanded it to explain the migration of the ions in salt solutions investigated
                    by him. He supposes that the molecules are equal distances apart, and that the
                    ions when separated travel with different velocities to the points of
                    recombination, and consequently those points are not the middle points between
                    pairs of adjacent molecules. He thus considers that the cation travels —th of
                    the distance between molecules while the n anion travels - ~ Jth of the
                    distance.</p>
                <p>If then we suppose the ions separated at the electrodes to be remoyed, we may
                    imagine the positions of the particles in the medium of solution before and
                    after electrolysis to be represented by a a' respectively, thus (where n -4)
                    :—</p>
                <p>the effect will be the same as if (1) the particle nearest the negative electrode
                    were removed, and all the other particles in the line moved towards that
                    electrode —th of the distance between the particles, oras if (2) the particle at
                    the positive electrode were removed, and all the rest shifted ( I - ~ ^th part
                    of the distance between the particles towards it. If we suppose the solvent
                    separated by a porous wall into two portions, we shall have after electrolysis
                    in the portion containing the cathode (cn the first supposition) corresponding
                    to deposition of ono equivalent of hydrogen in the voltameter—</p>
                <p>(1) a gain of one equivalent of cation deposited;</p>
                <p>(2) a loss of one equivalent of salt since the decomposed mole cules are supposed
                    taken from there;</p>
                <p>(3) a gain of — equivalent of salt due to translation.</p>
                <p>Hence the whole increase in the amount of the cation, free and combined, due to
                    electrolysis is -- equivalent.</p>
                <p>In the portion containing the anode we shall have—(1) a gain of one equivalent of
                    anion set free, and (2) a loss of equivalent of electrolyte due to the
                    translation; and hence the whole increase in the amount of anion free and
                    combined round the anode is ∖ 1 — — ∣ ∖ n J equivalent The same results are
                    obtained if the second supposition be made. Hence the n here used is identical
                    with the n used above in the account of the phenomena of migration of the ions.
                    D Almeida considered that the phenomena were due to the fact that round the
                    positive electrode an envelope of free acid was formed by electrolysis, and that
                    this became a second electrolyte in contact with the salt solution. 11 is also
                    evident that by supposing the salt to be electrolysed in a hydrated state, i.e.
                    combined with a number of molecules of water which may travel with either the
                    anion or cation, an explanation of the phenomena may be arrived at (Burgoin,
                    Bull. Soc. Chιm. [2] xviι. 244). Hittorf explained the ιematkable cases of the
                    iodides of zinc and cadmium by a somewhat similar assumption (v. supra, p.
                    110).</p>
                <p>F. Kohlrausch (Nacht, v. d. K. Gcs. d. JVιss., Gottingen, 17 Mai 1876, 4 April
                    1877) has recently pointed out a most reιnaιkable relation between the migration
                    constants and the conductivities of extremely dilute solutions containing
                    electrochemically equivalent amounts of haloid or oxygen salts. Thus if Z <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, Z <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> be the conductivities
                    of such solutions of two salts MR, AIR' containing one component M the same in
                    both, and if τι <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, n <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> be
                    the corresponding migration constants of the ion M, then Kohlrausch shows that
                    the • Λ <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> t equation - <hi rend="subscript">
                    j</hi>- holds with remarkable accuracy for many salts. The quantities 7 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi>, l„ are called the “specific molecular conductivities’’
                    of the solutions, and are defined by the equation l=^ , where jθ7 is the
                    specific conductivity of a very dilute solution at 18" C. referred to mercury,
                    and u is the ratio of the number of grammes of salt per unit of volume of
                    solution to its electrochemical equivalent iu hydrogen units. The results are in
                    accordance with the hypothesis that the conductivity of an electrolyte is
                    proportional to the sum of the oppositely directed velocities of the anion and
                    cation; the velocity of any ion is supposed to depend on the friction of the
                    surrounding fluid, and is accordingly constant for the same ion in different
                    solutions if these are extremely dilute. A table of relative, velocities can be
                    formed from the migration constants of Hittorf, Wiedemann, and Weiske; a
                    multiple of these velocities gives numbers such that the sum of those
                    corresponding to two ions gives a value for the molecular conductivity of a
                    solution of the compound of the two ions agreeing very closely with the
                    experimental determinations of Kohlrausch and Grotrian.</p>
                <p>In order to explain the conduction of electricity during electιolysis several
                    hypotheses have been suggested, which involve the idea of continuity of
                    electricity, even in the molecules. On this view the elementary atoms when
                    recombining carry with them a certain quantity of electricity, which, indeed, by
                    Faraday's law, must be the same for every group of atoms constituting a chemical
                    equivalent. Berzelius, for example, considers that when two atoms, e g., H and
                    Cl, unite to form HC1, electric distribution takes place similar to that of
                    magnetism in a bar magnet, II being the positive pole, Cl the negative. The
                    hypothetical positive pole is then attracted by the negative electrode, and the
                    attraction is so great at the electrode itself as to overcome the chemical
                    affinity of the H for Cl, and separation is the result, while the electricity of
                    the electrode and of the H combine and are neutralized. The liberated chlorine
                    atom then behaves in the same way towards its next neighbour, and so the current
                    of electricity is set up.</p>
                <p>For an account of the allied theories see Wiedemann, l.c., and see also Clerk
                    Maxwell s remarks upon the subject (Elec. Mag., vol. i. § 259 sqq). These
                    hypotheses nearly all involve the idea, more or less defined, of a statical
                    molecule, i.e., a molecule at test relatively to other molecules, and consisting
                    of relatively fixed atoms; but while we regard heat as the energy of molecular
                    motion, this notion of a molecule cannot be sustained, and accordingly the above
                    hypothesis can serve, as Maxwell suggests, merely to give precision to our
                    ideas. Clausius (Poqg. Ann.,ci. 33S), however, has applied the kinetic
                    hypothesis of the constitution of bodies to electrolysis, and from his
                    suggestions we can form some conception of the method of proceeding in
                    electrolytic action. He supposes the molecules in the ordinary state to be in a
                    state of agitation, and the atoms composing the molecules to be also in motion,
                    sometimes separating, sometimes recombining with other separated atoms, so that
                    decomposition and recombinations are continually going on, but in no definite
                    direction. The mean result is an apparent state of equilibrium. When, however,
                    an electromotive force acts upon the electrolyte, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n123/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0123-0114"/> no matter how small it is, it causes the atoms,
                    when liberated as usual, to tend in one direction, viz., along the lines of
                    force. Hence the collection of the ions at the electrodes, where they will
                    separate if the electromotive force be sufficient to prevent them reacting and
                    again recombining,—in other words, sufficient to bear the polarization. This,
                    though by no means a complete theory, is indeed applicable to ultimate atoms,
                    and is the only oue which admits decomposition for all electromotive forces.
                    Clausius shows that the finite electromotive force is necessary to maintain the
                    ions in the tree state, at the electrodes.</p>
                <p>One theory, which we must mention because it accounts at once for conduction, the
                    migration of the ions, and “electric endosmose,” is that due to Quincke (Pogg.
                    Ann., cxni., extended in cxliv ), who con· siders the ions of each molecule
                    charged with quantities of electricity e and e'; then the force K. tending to
                    separate the ions from each dυ dυ</p>
                <p>other = <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi><hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> fo.(Bt-Be),
                    where B and B are constants, and is the electromotive force per unit of length
                    ot the electrolyte, and is consequently = - h , where i is the current
                    intensity, q the sectional area of the electrolyte, and k its specific
                    conductivity; so that K = (Be - B'e'), and electrolysis takes place when this is
                    greater than the force of chemical affinity. This is a weak point of the theory,
                    as a finite electromotive force would be required to produce any decomposition
                    or polarization.</p>
                <p>The forces on the ions when separated, and hence their respective velocities,
                    will,be proportional to c and √. This will account for the migration of the
                    ions, for which e and √ are supposed unequal and of different signs in all cases
                    except Zul and Cdl, &amp;c., for which (1 - is greater than unity; for these t
                    and √ may be ot the same sign. If, on the other hand, e be the amount of free
                    electricity on a molecule of the electrolyte (supposed of high resistance) 111
                    contact do with the glass, then - B^,* will represent the force urging the fluid
                    in the positive direction of the current, and perhaps producing endosmose, since
                    e will be positive except for turpentine oil. So •the motion of particles may be
                    similarly explained by supposing t to be the chaιge on them due to contact with
                    the fluid; this is negative with particles in water, and positive for all
                    particles except sulphur in turpentine oil. The results thus obtained will be
                    found to agree closely with the experiments mentioned above (p. 111); and the
                    quantitative results also agree, since the force on a particle i equals Bp∕, and
                    therefore varies as the current density i, and inversely as the conductivity
                    k.</p>
                <p>An application of electrolysis, which has already proved to be of great value in
                    chemistry, has been introduced of late years by Gladstone and Tn be. In a paper
                    read before the British Association in 1872 (Trans. of Sections, p. 75, see
                    Proc. Roy. Soc., vol. xx. p. 218) they showed that although zinc alone does not
                    decompose distilled <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> water, yet if zinc foil be
                    immersed in dilute solution of cupric sulphate, and be thereby coated with
                    metallic copper, which is thrown down as a black crystalline powder, containing
                    traces of zinc only if the time of immersion be very long (Journal Chem. Soc.,
                    1873, p. 452), and if the zinc copper couple thus produced be immersed in
                    distilled water at ordinary temperature, about 4 cc. of H can be collected per
                    hour. The hydrogen is seen by the microscope to collect upon the copper
                    crystals, while the zinc is oxidized, and forms a hydrate. The rate of evolution
                    of hydrogen varies with the temperature; the relation may be exhibited by a
                    curve very similar to the curve of tension of water vapour, Gladstone and Tribe
                    have found this a powerful method of acting upon many organic bodies,
                    particularly the halogen compounds of the alcohol radicles. In all cases either
                    new reactions were set up, or the temperature at which reaction takes place was
                    very much lower than with ordinary zinc (see the series of papers by Gladstone
                    and Tribe in the Jour. Chem. Soc., 1873-6). To the chemist the ZnCu couple
                    affords an exceedingly convenient way of arranging electrolysis, since the whole
                    may be contained in one vessel. For the copper in the arrangement, gold or
                    platinum may with great advantage be substituted by immersing zinc foil in
                    solutions of the chlorides.</p>
                <p>This easily explains the well-known custom of generating hydrogen from zinc and
                    sulphuric acid, to which a little CuSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> is added;
                    and the “local aetion” in batteries, when currents pass from one part to the
                    other of the same mass of metal and consequently energy is expended for which no
                    external equivalent is obtained, may be similarly referred to the difference of
                    composition of the metals in the two places. It should be remembered that Davy
                    suggested the preservation of the copper sheathing of ships by attaching plates
                    of Zn; the same object is now achieved by using an alloy of the two metals.</p>
                <p>The application of the principle of the conservation of energy to electrolysis
                    has already produced valuable results; research, how ever, in this direction is
                    rendered difficult on account of the great number of circumstances which have to
                    be taken into account, in computing the balance of energy expended and work
                    done; the chemical composition and physical state of the electrolyte, the
                    moleculaι condition of the ions, and the secondary actions at the electrodes
                    have all to be taken into account. For a notice of the present state of this
                    branch ot the subject the reader is referred to the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Electricity.</hi> (W. M.S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
