<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0543-0524-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ERIVAN, or Irwan (9th edition, volume 8, page
                    524)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1143526">Tatars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n543/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ERIVAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Irwan</hi></label>, in
                    Persian <hi rend="smallcaps">Rewan,</hi> a town of Russian Armenia, at the head
                    of a province of the same name, is situated 3430 feet above the level of the
                    Black <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n544/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0544-0525"/> Sea, on the Zengui, Zanga, or Hrastan, an
                    affluent of the Araxes, about 171 miles S.S.W. of Tiflis by road. The old
                    Persian portion of the town consists mainly of narrow crooked lanes inclosed by
                    mud walls, which effectually conceal the houses, and the modern Russian portion
                    is laid out in long ill-paved streets. On a steep rock, rising about 600 feet
                    above the κiver, stands the old Turkish fortress, surrounded by ditches and
                    earthen ramparts, and containing within its area part of the palace of the
                    ancient Persian governors, a handsome but greatly dilapidated mosque, a Greek
                    church of modern erection, a cannon foundry, and barracks. One chamber, called
                    the Hall of the Sardar, bears witness to the former splendour of the palace by
                    its pictorial decorations, which include legendary and historical scenes from
                    the lives of Zal and Rustam, of Abbas-Mirza and Nadir Shah. The finest building
                    in the city is undoubtedly the mosque of Hussein Ali Khan, familiarly known as
                    the Blue Mosque from the colour of the enamelled tiles with which it is richly
                    encased. At the mosque of Zal Khan a yearly passion play is performed
                    illustrative of the assassination of Hussein the son of Ali. Besides the
                    episcopal church of St Sergius <hi rend="italic">(Sourp Sarghis),</hi> the
                    Armenians possess five churches, a monastery, and a seminary. Several hundred
                    travellers can be accommodated in the new caravanserai; and there is a club
                    which in some degree makes up for the absence of hotels. The bazaar, though
                    extensive, is poorly supplied with goods; and the only manufactures of the town
                    are a little cotton cloth, leather, earthenware, and blacksmiths’ work. The
                    fruits of the district are exceedingly cheap, and noted for their
                    excellence—especially the grapes, apples, apricots, and melons. The surrounding
                    country is richly watered by a system of canals connected with the Gokcha or
                    Sevanga Lake and the river Zengui. Armenians, Persians, and Tatars are the main
                    elements in the population, to which is added a certain number of Russians and
                    Greeks—making a total in 1874 of 30,000.</p>
                <p>The origin of Erivan is altogether unknown. One pious Armenian tradition
                    recognizes in the name the joyful exclamation of Noah at the reappearance of the
                    dry ground— <hi rend="italic">Erevan,</hi> it has shown itself; another explains
                    it as equivalent to <hi rend="italic">Erovantavan,</hi> the place of defeat of
                    Erovant II. of Armenia; and a third identifies it with the name of Rewan Kul,
                    who built a castle about 1412 on the spot at the command of Shah Ismail. The
                    present fortress at any rate was erected by the Turks in the 16th century, and
                    since that time the place has been of considerable celebrity. It was taken by
                    the Persians under Shah Abbas in 1604, besieged by the Turks for four months in
                    1615, and reconquered by the Persians under Nadir Shah in the 18th centuιy. In
                    1780 it was successfully defended against Heraclius of Georgia; and in 1804 it
                    resisted the Russians under Prince TsitsianofF. At length in 1827 Paskievitch
                    took the fortress by storm, and in the following year the town and province were
                    ceded to Russia by the peace of Turkmanchai. The successful general was rewarded
                    by the title of Count of Erivan (Erivanski). A Tatar poem in celebration of the
                    event has been preserved by Bodenstedt in his “Thousand and One Days in the
                    East.”</p>
                <p>See Fr. Dubois de Montpéreux, <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >autour du Caucase,</hi> vol. iii., 1839; Baron Thielman, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Travels in the Caucasus,</hi> &lt;tc., 1875; J. B. Telfer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Crimea and Transcaucasia,</hi> 1876; J. Bryce, <hi rend="italic">Transcaucasia
                    and Ararat,</hi> 1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
