<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0550-0531-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ERYSIPELAS (9th edition, volume 8, page 531)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sk85">Throat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:923528">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919522">Face</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150388">Throat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n550/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ERYSIPELAS</label> (a Greek word, <hi rend="italic"
                    >epvσlπeλa&lt;s,</hi> probably derived from <hi rend="italic">ίρυθρός,</hi> and
                    7reλλα, skin)—synonyms, <hi rend="italic">the Pose, St Anthonfs Fire—</hi> a
                    disease characterized by diffuse inflammation of the skin, attended with fever.
                    Two kinds of this disorder are recognized, namely,— <hi rend="italic"
                    >traumatic</hi> erysipelas, which occurs in connexion with some wound or
                    external injury, and may thus affect any part of the body where such lesion may
                    exist; and <hi rend="italic">idiopathic</hi> erysipelas, in which no connexion
                    of this kind can be traced, but which appears to arise spontaneously, and most
                    commonly affects the face and head. They are, however, essentially the same
                    disease, and, as regards the latter variety, it is believed by some authorities
                    that an abrasion of the skin, generally too trifling to attract attention,
                    exists in almost every case as the starting-point of the inflammatory
                    action.</p>
                <p>The question as to whether erysipelas is to be regarded as an eruptive fever
                    allied to scarlet fever, measles, &amp;c., or a local inflammatory disease of
                    the skin, the fever being secondary, has engaged much attention; and while the
                    weight of opinion appears to be in favour of the latter view, the facte of the
                    contagiousness of erysipelas, its occasional appearance in an epidemic form, and
                    the discovery in the inflamed tissues of microscopic organisms <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Bacteria)</hi> point to the existence of a specific poison as giving peculiar
                    characters to this form of cutaneous inflammation. The contagiousness of
                    erysipelas in its traumatic form is often illustrated in the surgical wards of
                    hospitals, where, having once broken out, it is apt to spread with great
                    rapidity, and to produce disastrous results, as well as in lying-in hospitals,
                    where its occurrence gives rise to the spread of a form of puerperal fever of
                    virulent character. It is not so certain that the disease in its idiopathic
                    variety is contagious to persons who have no wound or abrasion, and this form of
                    the complaint is in general excited by exposure to cold, a predisposing cause
                    being some deranged or low condition of the general health.</p>
                <p>When the erysipelas is of moderate character there is simply a rednoss of the
                    integument, which feels somewhat hard and thickened, and upon which there often
                    appear small vésications. This redness, though at first circumscribed, tends to
                    spread and affect the neighbouring sound skin, until an entire limb or a large
                    area of the body may become involved in the inflammatory process. There is
                    usually considerable pain, with heat and tingling in the affected part. As the
                    disease advances the portions of skin first attacked become less inflamed, and
                    exhibit a yellowish appearance, which is followed by slight desquamation of the
                    cuticle. The inflammation in general gradually disappears. Sometimes, however,
                    it breaks out again, and passes over the area originally affected a second time.
                    But besides the skin, the subjacent tissues may become involved in the
                    inflammation, and give rise to the formation of pus. This is termed <hi
                    rend="italic">phlegmonous erysipelas,</hi> and is much more apt to occur in
                    connexion with the traumatic variety of the disease. Occasionally the affected
                    parts become gangrenous. Certain complications are apt to arise in erysipelas
                    affecting the surface of the body, particularly inflammation of serous
                    membranes, such as the pericardium, pleura, and peritoneum.</p>
                <p>Erysipelas of the face, the most common form of the idiopathic variety, usually
                    begins with symptoms of general illness, the patient feeling languid, drowsy,
                    and sick, while frequently there is a distinct rigor followed with fever.
                    According to some observers, the fever is symptomatic of inflammation already
                    begun in the neighbouring lymphatic vessels and glands before the appearance of
                    the disease on the skin. Sore throat is sometimes felt, but in general the first
                    indication of the local affection is a red and painful spot at the side of the
                    nose or on one of the cheeks or ears. Occasionally it would appear that the
                    inflammation begins in the throat, and reaches the face through the nasal
                    fossae. The redness gradually spreads over the whole surface of the face, and is
                    accompanied with swelling, which in the lax tissues of the cheeks and eyelids is
                    so great that the features soon become obliterated and the countenance wears a
                    hideous expression. Advancing over the scalp, the disease may invade the neck
                    and pass on to the trunk, but in general the inflammation remains confined to
                    the face and head. While the disease progresses, besides the pain, tenderness,
                    and heat of the affected parts, the constitutional symptoms are very severe. The
                    temperature rises often to 105° or higher, and there is great gastric
                    disturbance. Delirium is a frequent accompaniment. The attack in general lasts
                    for a week or ten days, during which the inflammation subsides in the parts of
                    the skin first attacked, while it spreads onwards in other directions, and after
                    it has passed away there is, as already observed, some slight disquamation of
                    the cuticle.</p>
                <p>Although in general the termination is favourable, serious and occasionally fatal
                    results follow from inflammation of the membranes of the brain, and in some rare
                    instances sudden death has occurred from suffocation arising from oedema
                    glottidis, the inflammatory action having spread into and extensively involved
                    the throat. One attack of this disease, so far from protecting from, appears
                    rather to predispose to others; and this fact is appealed to by those physicians
                    who deny that erysipelas is merely one of the eruptive fevers—such disorders, as
                    is well known, rarely occurring a second time in the same individual.</p>
                <p>Erysipelas occasionally assumes from the first a violent form, under which the
                    patient sinks rapidly, and instances are on record where such attacks have
                    proved disastrous to several persons who had been exposed to their contagion. It
                    is sometimes a complication in certain forms of exhausting disease, such as
                    consumption or typhoid fever, and is then to be regarded as of serious import. A
                    very fatal form occasionally attacks new-born infants, particularly in the first
                    four weeks of their lives, In epidemics of puerperal fever this form of
                    erysipelas has been specially found to prevail.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n551/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0551-0532"/>
                <p>The treatment of erysipelas is best conducted on the ex pectant system. The
                    disease in most instances tends to a favourable termination; and beyond
                    attention to the condition of the stomach and bowels, which may require the use
                    of some gentle laxative, little is necessary in the way of medicine. The
                    employment of preparations of iron in large doses is strongly recommended by
                    many physicians. But the chief point is the administration of abundant
                    nourishment in a light and digestible form. Of the many local applications which
                    may be employed, hot opiate fomentations, such as a decoction of poppy heads,
                    will be found among the most soothing. Dusting the affected part with flour or
                    powdered starch, and wrapping it in cotton wadding, is also of use; or collodion
                    may be painted over the inflamed surface to act as a protective.</p>
                <p>With the object of preventing the spread of the inflammation, lines drawn with
                    some caustic material (such as common lunar caustic) beyond the circumference of
                    the inflamed part have been supposed to be of use, but this plan often fails. In
                    the case of phlegmonous erysipelas complicating wounds, free incisions into the
                    part are necessary, <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> o. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
