<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0581-0560-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ESTHER (9th edition, volume 8, page 560)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t2w">Feasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084333">Purim</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883769">Critics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205830">Ethiopia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n581/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ESTHER</label>. The Book of Esther relates how a Jewish
                    maiden, Esther, a foster-daughter of Mordecai, was raised to the position of
                    queen by the Persian king Ahasuerus (Xerxes) after he had divorced Vashti; next,
                    how she and her uncle Mordecai frustrated Haman’s resolution to extirpate the
                    Jews out of the Persian empire; how Haman fell, and Mordecai was advanced to his
                    place; how Esther obtained the king’s permission for the Jews to destroy all who
                    might attack them on the day which Haman had appointed by lot for their
                    extirpation; and lastly, how a festival was instituted to commemorate their
                    deliverance. Its main object is to account for the origin of the feast of Purim,
                    which from its cradle in the Persian capital had gradually made its way into
                    other countries (Esth. ix. 19-32). The colouring of the narrative is entirely
                    foreign. Frequent and minute references are made to the usages of the Persian
                    court, while on the other hand the peculiar institutions of the Jews, and even
                    Jerusalem and the temple, and the very name of Israel, are studiously, as it
                    would seem, ignored. The name of God is not mentioned once, a phenomenon
                    entirely unique in the Old Testament writings. From a theological point of view,
                    the book is therefore not of much interest. It attracts the historical critic,
                    however, by the strangeness and difficulty of its statements, while the ordinary
                    reader cannot fail to be struck by the force and dramatic vividness of its
                    literary form. Its early popularity is shown by the interpolated passages (as
                    different as possible from the original) in the Septuagint and old Latin
                    versions.</p>
                <p>It was not until the 18th century that a critical examination of the book was
                    made, with a view to determine its precise historical value, not, however, at
                    first with sufficient impartiality or historical information. Eichhorn, the most
                    moderate of the earlier critics, belongs to the 19th century. He has drawn up a
                    long list of improbabilities of detail, some of which he thinks he cau explain
                    away, while others remain in full force. Subsequent critics have believed
                    themselves to have discovered fresh difficulties, insomuch that Dr Kuenen does
                    not hesitate to say that “impossibilities and improbabilities pervade the whole
                    narrative” <hi rend="italic">{Religion</hi><hi rend="italic">of Israel,</hi>
                    iii. 148). It is impossible to mention more than a few of these as a specimen.
                    The very first verses of the book are great stumbling blocks to a Western
                    reader. We are there told that Ahasuerus, “who reigned from India even unto
                    Ethiopia, over an hundred and seven and twenty provinces,” gave a banquet which
                    lasted 180 days, and at which (if we take the expressions of the narrative
                    literally) the whole official world of the Persian empire was simultaneously
                    present (Esth. i. 3, 4). Further on, we are told that Esther, on her elevation
                    to be queen, kept her Jewish origin secret (ii. 10), although she had been taken
                    from the house of Mordecai, who was known to be a Jew (iii. 4), and had remained
                    in constant intercourse with him (iv. 4-17). W e also learn indirectly that
                    Mordecai, previously to his mourning, was able to pass at pleasure into the
                    harem of the jealous and amatory Xerxes (iv. 2). Further, that Mordecai offered
                    a gross affront to Haman without any evil consequences (iii. 2-6). Lastly,
                    Haman, the cruel grandvizier, takes the trouble to give eleven months notice of
                    his intention to exterminate the Jews (iii. 12-14), which respite is spent by
                    the Jews in fasting (the narrative does not add praying) and lamentation (iv.
                    3), and when the danger has been averted through the patriotism of Esther, the
                    Jews are allowed to put to death 75,000 of their fellow subjects (ix. 16).</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, it must at any rate be admitted that these objections are not all
                    of equal value, and that a comparison of the narrative of Esther with the later
                    additions to the book, and with the stories of Judith and Tobit, is distinctly
                    favourable to its historical verisimilitude. Some amount of exaggeration must be
                    allowed for, as the infirmity of an Oriental race; no exegesis is possible
                    without such a postulate. As for the Persian customs described, they are no
                    doubt singular, but, in the absence of documentary evidence, it is unsafe to
                    give them a positive contradiction. At least one confirmation of some importance
                    has been supplied by Herodotus (iii. 69, <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> Esth. ii.
                    12), and many critics hold that the assembly assigned to the third year of
                    Ahasuerus (Esth. i. 3) is that mentioned by Herodotus (vii. 8) as having been
                    held previously to the expedition against Greece. This, however, is quite
                    uncertain. The reference to the 127 provinces is in itself not improbable, but
                    is only confirmed by the author of the book of Daniel (vi. 1, <hi rend="italic"
                    >cf.</hi> 1 Esd. iii. 3, LXX.), who has been thought by some to have made a
                    confusion between satrapies and sub-satrapies. It is at any rate in perfect
                    harmony with history that the book of Esther includes India among the subject
                    provinces; this is confirmed not only by Herodotus (iii. 94), but by the
                    inscriptions of Darius at Persepolis and Naksh-i-Rustam. The conduct of Mordecai
                    certainly remains mysterious. In our own day, the harem is impenetrable, while
                    “any one declining to stand as the grand-vizier passes is almost beaten to
                    death” (Morier, the English minister to the court of Persia, quoted by Dean
                    Stanley). And if it is perhaps only too probable that a vizier would use his
                    position for the gratification of spite, and if even the bloodthirstiness of
                    Haman is not inconceivable, still the circumstances connected with the decree
                    for the destruction of the Jews are almost more than even “the peculiarly
                    extravagant and capricious character” of Xerxes (Canon Rawlinson) can render
                    easily acceptable.</p>
                <p>The proper names of Esther, at any rate in their present form, do not all of them
                    stand philological tests. Some of them are genuinely Persian, but others wear a
                    somewhat questionable appearance. These may either be corrupt, or, as Noldeke
                    suggests, framed by the author himself on Persian models. Among the most
                    accurate is Ahasuerus or rather Akhashverosh ( = Persian Chshayarsha, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> Xerxes). The character of this king, too, agrees
                    admirably with that given of Xerxes by Herodotus <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi>
                    Herod, iii. 69, ix. 108). But then, it has been replied, it only agrees so well
                    because Xerxes was a typical Oriental despot, magnificent, swayed by favourites,
                    proud, amatory, capricious. Here we must leave this part of our subject—nothing
                    short of a detailed commentary on the book would give the reader a
                    satisfactorily complete view of the facts. It must, however, be observe! that
                    the serious chronological difficulty in Esther ii. 5, 6 (where Mordecai is
                    apparently said to have been carried captive with Jeconiah) can hardly be
                    removed by maintaining with Canon Rawlinson (contrary to Hebrew usage) that
                    Kish, and not Mordecai, is the person referred to. It must, it would seem, be
                    concluded that the theory that the book of Esther is a strictly historical
                    narrative is not proof at all points against objection. The question then
                    arises, is it a work of pure imagination? This was the view of the 18th century
                    rationalistic critics. Semler, for instance, says, “Illud videtur esse certum,
                    confictam esse universam parabolam, fastûs et arrogantiae Judaeorum
                    locupletissimum testimonium” (Sender, <hi rend="italic">Apparatus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ad liberal.</hi><hi rend="italic">Vet. Test, interpr.,</hi> p. 152
                    <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> quoted by Keil). By this theory, we might at once
                    put a happy end to the guerilla warfare of rationalistic objectors. It is very
                    necessary, however, to see how much is involved in accepting it. For the book of
                    Esther expressly appeals to the authority of the royal Persian chronicles (ii.
                    23, x. 2) and of a contemporary memoir (ix. 32). If untrue, remarks Canon
                    Rawlinson, the book might easily have been proved to be so at the time when it
                    was published, by reference to those chronicles <hi rend="italic">{Speakers
                    Commentary,</hi> iii. 472). The only way to turn the point of this objection
                    would be <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n582/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0582-0561"/> to show that the narrative was written
                    subsequently to the fall of the Persian empire, and not earlier than the end of
                    the fourth century, about 150 years after Xerxes. This has been maintained by
                    several eminent critics <hi rend="italic">(e.g,</hi> Zunz, Herzfeld, Ewald,
                    Bertheau, Kuenen) on the following grounds. (1) The absence of any reference to
                    the story in the books (or rather book) of Chronicles, Ezra, and Nehemiah, in
                    Daniel, in Ecclesiasticus (see chaps, xliv.-l.), or in Philo. (2) The way in
                    which the Persian monarchy is described. A book so far from complimentary in
                    some of its details to a great Persian king cannot, it is urged, have been
                    written during the continuance of his dynasty, any more than the so-called song
                    of Solomon can have been written under the rule of the Solomonic family. True,
                    the opening of Esther pourtrays in brilliant hues the outward splendour of
                    Ahasuerus’s empire, but the very brilliance, and still more the particularity,
                    of the description, indicates that that empire was a wonder of the past, already
                    beginning to be invested with the glamour of fairy-land. The necessity for an
                    explanation of Persian customs (i. 13, viii. 8) is thought to point in the same
                    direction. (3) “The absence of the religious spirit in the writer, or rather the
                    absence of its manifestation. Had the writer lived soon after the events
                    narrated, it is improbable that he would have omitted all [direct] mention of
                    divine providence and the name of God, because the religious feeling had not so
                    far degenerated among the Jewish captives who did not return to their own land
                    with Zerubbabel, Ezra, and Nehemiah” (Dr Davidson, <hi rend="italic">The Text of
                    the Old Testament considered,</hi> 1856, p. 609). In the Greek period, on the
                    other hand, we know for certain from Ecclesiastes that the religious spirit was
                    declining, at any rate in some circles, even in Judea. (4) The lateness of the
                    style. This has been carefully investigated by Zunz, who remarks that there are
                    more than fifty expressions which point to a late date, and which include,
                    besides Persisms, three also found (and found only) in Ezra, Nehemiah,
                    Ecclesiastes, one in Nehemiah, Ecclesiastes, and Ps. cxix., one in Chronicles,
                    five in Ecclesiastes, one in Daniel, one in Chronicles and Daniel, one in
                    Nehemiah and Daniel, also six belonging to later Hebrew, two to Aramaic, and
                    four resembling the usage of the Mishna. The value of this argument, however,
                    depends partly on the date which we assign to Chronicles, Ecclesiastes, and
                    Daniel, also on the relation of Ezra and Nehemiah to Chronicles. The weighty
                    reference to the Mishnaic usage remains, however, in full force, however
                    conservative be our decision on the date of Chronicles, &amp;c. We have said
                    nothing at present of the festival of Purim, which, according to Keil, is “the
                    principal evidence of the historical truth of the whole narrative,” and which,
                    even according to the more critical Friedrich Bleek, “undoubtedly presupposes
                    the occurrence of what is narrated in our book.” To many scholars, however, the
                    connexion of the book of Esther with the festival of Purim is rather a
                    difficulty than otherwise. It is hardly necessary to refer to Mr Tylor for
                    evidence of the tendency to invent stories to account for popular festivals. Dr
                    Kuenen, who speaks as the representative of a growing school, maintains that the
                    book of Esther is through and through unhistorical, that “the explanation it
                    offers of the Purim feast is not taken from the reality, but <hi rend="italic"
                    >invented</hi> to make that feast popular. A Persian word <hi rend="italic"
                    >pur</hi> meaning lot is quite unknown” <hi rend="italic">(Religion of
                    Israel,</hi> iii. 148). He then fortifies his position by a reference to the
                    numerous improbabilities which we have already mentioned. According to him,
                    Purim was originally a Persian feast, and was by degrees adopted by the Jews,
                    first in Persia, and then in other countries, and the object of the author of
                    Esther was to make the observance of the feast still more general. He is not,
                    however, prepared with a satisfactory explanation of the word Purim. Von
                    Hammer’s derivation from <hi rend="italic">fur dig an,</hi> the name of a
                    Persian festival, falls through, as Dr Kuenen points out, owing to the fact <hi
                    rend="italic">axsX fnrdigdn</hi> was not a spring feast, and, as Purim was kept
                    on the 14th and 15th of the month Adar, a spring feast is obviously required. A
                    more plausible form of the hypothesis adopted by Dr Kuenen is perhaps that of
                    Zunz. The Jews during and after the exile were much influenced religiously by
                    the nations among -whom they lived (so at least many critics believe, quoting as
                    instances the belief in the seven archangels and in Azazel). It was the policy
                    of the doctors of the law to adopt as many of the new popular usages as they
                    could, without detriment to the purity of their religion. Purim, a joyous,
                    secular festival, enjoyed (as it still does enjoy) a great popularity among the
                    Jews. The religious authorities, desiring to check the exuberance of its
                    celebration, determined to give it a quasi-consecration by connecting it with an
                    event (real or imaginary) in the history of the nation. They omitted the name of
                    God, not from indifference to religion, but to prevent it from being profaned at
                    the secular celebration to which Purim was liable <hi rend="italic">(ef.</hi>
                    Esther ix. 19-22). It must be observed, in conclusion, that while the doctors of
                    the law attached great importance to Purim and to Esther—witness the statement
                    that the men of the Great Assembly “wrote” (? edited) the book of Esther, also
                    the various interpolated passages, and the devotion of an entire Talmudic
                    treatise to the feast of Purim—the sacerdotal authorities (of a more
                    conservative turn) did their utmost to disparage the intrusive festival. No
                    psalms were sung in the temple at the feast of Purim—not even those which were
                    usual at half festivals (see Bloch, <hi rend="italic">Hellenistische</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Bestaηdtheile</hi><hi rend="italic">im biblischen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Schriftthum,</hi> pp. 39-41). The first mention of Purim occurs in
                    2 Macc., xv. 36, where the thirteenth day of Adar is said to have been observed
                    as a festival in memory of the death of Nicanor, “the day before Mardocheus’s
                    day.” Unfortunately the second book of Maccabees was written little, if at all,
                    before the Christian era, while the first book (of much greater authority)
                    simply says (vii. 49) :—“They ordained to keep yearly this day, being the
                    thirteenth of Adar.” Would the Jews, asks Dr Zunz, have made anew festival on
                    the 13th, if the 14th were recognized as the feast of Purim? This, however, may
                    well be called hypercriticism. And we may sum up by the remark that if direct
                    historical evidence is deficient for the traditional view of the book of Esther,
                    it? is equally deficient for the rival critical theory. Probability is our only
                    guide. Yet even if the book contain a larger or smaller romantic element, it is
                    of real historical value as a record of the Jewish spirit in a little known age,
                    and is edifying even to Christians from its powerful though indirect inculcation
                    of the lesson of divine providence.</p>
                <p>See, besides the Introductions to the Old Testament of Keil <hi rend="subscript">
                    r</hi> Bleek, and Davidson, Baumgarten, <hi rend="italic">Be fide</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">libri</hi><hi rend="italic">Estheroe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >commentatio</hi><hi rend="italic">historico-erilica,</hi> Halae, 1839;
                    Bertheau, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Bûcher Bsra,
                    Nechemja,</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">Esther,</hi> Leipzig,
                    1862; Zunz, <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift</hi><hi rend="italic">der deutsch,
                    morgenländ. Gesellschaft,</hi> 1873, p. 684, &amp;c.; Oppert, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentaire historique et philologiqïie du livre</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d'Esther,</hi> Paris, 1864; Herzfeld, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic">Volkes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Jisrael,</hi> Leipzig, 1863, Bd. ii. pp. 1-9, 357-366; Ewald, <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Israel,</hi> Lond. 1874, vol. v., pp. 230-234; Grätz, “Die
                    Kanonicität des Buches Esther,“<hi rend="italic">Monatsschrift,</hi> 1871, pp.
                    502- 511; Bloch, <hi rend="italic">Hellenistische</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Bestandthcile</hi><hi rend="italic">im biblischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Schriftthum,</hi> 1877. (T. K. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
