<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0863-0828-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EZEKIEL (9th edition, volume 8, page 828)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sf6k">Talmud</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n863/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EZEKIEL</label> (⅛ <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> PWζ God will
                    strengthen, or ⅛ pl∏', God will prevail; ’ <hi rend="italic">ieζeκiηλ∙,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ezechiel}</hi> was the son of Buzi a priest, probably of the line
                    of Zadok, who appears to have lived in Jerusalem, and to have held a position of
                    some prominence there. According to an ancient and not impossible interpretation
                    of his own words (chap. i. 1), Ezekiel was born in 624 B.c. This interpretation
                    is at least preferable to that which reckons “the thirtieth year” from a
                    hypothetical era of Nabopolassar; but it is not free from all objection, and if
                    it fail us we have no data for precisely determining the prophet’s age.
                    Notwithstanding the expression made use of by Josephus <hi rend="italic">(πa⅛
                    ωv, Ant.,</hi> x. 7, 3) we may reasonably assume, however, that he had at least
                    attained to early manhood, and already had read and observed much, when, along
                    with King Jehoiachm and many other prisoners of the better class (2 Kings xxiv.
                    12—16; Jer. xxix. 1) he was carried into exile by Nebuchadnezzar in 599 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> With others of his compatriots he was settled at a
                    place called Tel-Abib (“Cornhill”), on the banks of the river Chebar, by which
                    most probably the Nahr-Malcha or “Grand” Canal of Nebuchadnezzar is meant,
                    though some still think of the Chaboras (modern Khabur), an afflueut of the
                    Euphrates more to the north.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Bleek <hi rend="italic">(EM.</hi> § 221, note), is probably
                    wrong in identifying both '√: <hi rend="superscript"> an</hi> *^ Chaboras with
                    the “Ί1ΠΠ of 2 Kings xvii. 6, which is most probably the Khabur, a tributary of
                    the Tigris (Delitzsch, <hi rend="italic">Jesαjα,</hi> p. 16, note).</p></note>
                    We are left almost wholly to precarious inference and conjecture for all further
                    details of his history. We learn incidentally, indeed, from his writings that he
                    was a married man living in a house of his own, and that his wife died in the
                    ninth year of his exile. But of the nature of his ordinary employments, if he
                    had any, we are not informed. His life, as a priest whose heart was thoroughly
                    absorbed in priestly work, could hardly fail to be tinged with sadness,
                    condemned as it was to be spent in an “unclean land” far away from “the
                    inheritance of the Lord.” He seems to have been of a brooding temperament, and
                    to have passed much of his time in silence and solitude. A recent writer (in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Studien</hi><hi rend="italic">u.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Kritiken</hi> for 1877) has ingeniously suggested and endeavoured to show that
                    he was an invalid, suffering much from some chronic nervous malady. In the fifth
                    year of his exile (594 B.c.) he had a remarkable vision, of which he has given a
                    very full description in the opening chapters of his book. On this occasion he
                    was divinely called to the prophetic office. Thenceforward, for a period of at
                    least 22 years, both orally and in writing, he continued to discharge prophetic
                    functions at frequent if somewhat irregular intervals; and whatever may have
                    been the force and bitterness of the opposition he originally had to face, he
                    ultimately, as a “watchman” and acknowledged leader of public opinion, came to
                    exercise an incalculably powerful influence in keeping alive the Jewish national
                    feeling, and also in quickening and purifying the religious hopes and
                    aspirations of his time. The last date mentioned in his writings is the 27th
                    year of his exile (572 B.c.). It is not probable that he lived long after that
                    time. Nothing authentic, however, has been handed down to us as to the time,
                    place, or manner of his death. Several unimportant traditions may be found in
                    the work of the Pseudo-Epiphanius, <hi rend="italic">De vit. et mort.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ρroρh.,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Itinerary</hi> of Benjamin
                    of Tudela, and elsewhere.</p>
                <p>In the present Massoretic canon the book of Ezekiel stands third in order among
                    those of the so-called Nebî’îm Aharônîm (latter prophets), being preceded by
                    those of Isaiah and Jeremiah, and followed by that of the twelve minor prophets.
                    In the list of canonical books given in the Talmud <hi rend="italic">(fjaha
                    bathra,</hi> 14, 2) it is the second of the four, being followed by “Isaiah” and
                    “the twelve.” Its arrangement is unusually simple, the chronological
                    corresponding for the most part with the natural order. Its three divisions date
                    respectively from before, during, and after the siege of Jerusalem.</p>
                <p>1. The first 24 chapters carry the reader from the time of the prophet’s
                    consecration down to the beginning of the siege of Jerusalem, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> from 594 to 590 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> They are made up of
                    some 29 distinct oracles, all of which, with the trifling exception of xxi.
                    33-37 [28-32], have direct reference to the religious and political condition of
                    Ezekiel’s compatriots in Babylonia and in Palestine. First in order stands the
                    famous “chariot” (comp. 1 Ch. xxviii. 18) vision, which has been so variously
                    estimated, both from theaesthetie and from the theological point of view, by
                    different critics. Rightly interpreted, as a mere description, it cannot justly
                    be called vague or obscure, and it is hard to account foi the strange stories
                    told of the difficulties felt by the Jews in expounding it. The prophet sees in
                    a storm-cloud coming out of the north a group of four living creatures
                    (cherubs), each with four wings and four different faces. Together they are
                    borne upon four wheels which are full of eyes. Resting upon their heads is a
                    firmament, supporting a sapphire throne, whereon is seated a man-like figure,
                    which is almost hidden in a blaze of light. Hereupon Ezekiel receives and eats
                    the bitter-sweet roll in which are written “lamentations and mourning and woe;”
                    he is now ready to go forth to his fellow-countrymen fearlessly declaring the
                    truth as it is revealed to him, however unwelcome it may be. The recorded
                    oracles that follow belong to the fifth, sixth, seventh, and ninth years of his
                    exile. They can be understood only when viewed in connexion with tho general
                    history of that period. Soon after his accession to the throne, Zedekiah, the
                    uncle and successor of Jehoiachin, had begun to intrigue against his suzerain
                    the king of Babylon, and had entered into secret relations with tho king of
                    Egypt. Ezekiel, like his older contemporary Jeremiah, had insight and sagacity
                    enough to see the unwisdom of such a policy. By various symbolical actions (iv.
                    1-8; iv. 9-17; V. 1-4; vi. 11; xii. 1-16; xxi. 11 [6]), and also by unequivocal
                    words, he repeatedly declared the certainty of the doom that was impending over
                    Jerusalem, Judah, and all the mountains of Israel; he insisted on the
                    uselessness of any struggle against Babylon, and distinctly predicted Zedekiah’s
                    captivity, blindness, and death. In language of the severest invective he
                    rebuked the sins and idolatries, worse than those of Sodom, which had brought
                    this inevitable ruin upon the land and people of the Lord; at the same time he
                    held forth the hope of ultimate restoration and final happiness for both Judah
                    and Ephraim at the end of “forty years,” under the guidance of the coming prince
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n864/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0864-0829"/><hi rend="superscript"> ,t</hi> whose right it is”
                    (chaps, xi. 14-21; xvii, 22-24; xx. 40-44; xxi. 32 [27]).</p>
                <p>2. The eight chapters which follow (xxv.-xxxii.) belong to the period which
                    elapsed between the beginning of the siege and the announcement of the capture
                    of Jerusalem; xxix. 17-21 is an exception, belonging to the 27 th year of the
                    prophet’s exile, and perhaps also chap, xxv., which has no date. During this
                    period the prophet had no word to speak concerning Judah and Israel.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The language of xxiv. 27,
                    taken along with that of xxxiii. 22, has led many to the conclusion that Ezekiel
                    was literally dumb during this period, and that the oracles belonging to it must
                    necessarily have been written, not spoken. But xxix. 21, dating from a much
                    later period, requires to be also considered in this connexion. He may possibly
                    have been speechless on certain subjects only.</p></note> In these chapters the
                    divine woe is pronounced against the seven neighbouring nations which had shown
                    most hostility to Judah and Israel, namely, Ammon, Moab, Edom, Philistia, Tyre,
                    Sidon, and Egypt. The oracles relating to Tyre and Egypt are of great length.
                    The others are comparatively brief. With regard to Tyre its capture and ruin by
                    Nebuchadnezzar are foretold: and it is predicted that within a very short time
                    Egypt shall be desolate forty years. The addition (xxix. 17-21) made seventeen
                    years afterwards is apparently due to the fact that the earlier prediction
                    regarding Tyre (xxvi. 7-14) had not been literally fulfilled. This section
                    contains several passages that are specially interesting from a literary point
                    of view. The description of the great merchant city in chap, xxvii. is
                    noticeable for the richness of its details, and also for the vigour with which
                    the comparison to a ship is carried out in ver. 5-9, 26-36. Striking also is the
                    dirge (chap, xxviii. 12-19) upon the king: “Thou deftly made signet-ring, full
                    of wisdom, and perfect in beauty— thou hast been in Eden, the garden of God;
                    every precious stone was thy covering, the sardius, the topaz, and the diamond.
                    . . . Beside the overshadowing cherub did I place thee; thou wast upon the holy
                    mountain of God; thou walkedst up and down in the midst of stones of fire. Thou
                    wast perfect in thy ways from the day that thou wast created, till iniquity was
                    found in thee. By the multitude of thy merchandise they have filled the midst of
                    thee with violence, and thou hast sinned; therefore I will cast thee as profane
                    out of the mountain of God, and the overshadowing cherub shall destroy thee from
                    the midst of the stones of fire.” As Tyre had been likened to a ship, so is
                    Egypt with great minuteness of detail likened to a cedar in chap, xxxi. In chap,
                    xxxii. follows a corresponding dirge, in which the assembled nations are
                    represented as mourning women singing their lament over Egypt’s grave.</p>
                <p>3. The remainder of the book (xxxiii.-xlviii.) dates from after the fall of
                    Jerusalem. In chap, xxxiii. we read how the prophet’s dumbness was taken away in
                    the twelfth (more probably the eleventh<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>So the Peshito and a few of the Λ1SS. See Ewald, Hitzig,
                    Bleek.</p></note>) year of his exile, on the day when tidings were brought of
                    the ruin of the city. Thereupon chap, xxxiv. opens with a brief retrospect, in
                    which the former avarice, idleness, and cruelty of Israel’s shepherds which have
                    led to such disaster are exposed and rebuked. But the future—the immediate and
                    the distant—chiefly occupies the prophet’s mind. He tells of a coming shepherd,
                    “David,” under whose rule great and uninterrupted prosperity is to be secured.
                    Edom is to be finally destroyed, but the twelve tribes are to be resuscitated
                    and gathered together in their own land once more. A final battle has yet to be
                    fought with Gog from the land of Magog, who shall come up against the chosen
                    people with a great army, but only to be utterly destroyed, that Israel may
                    thenceforward dwell in safety, wholly secure from any possible repetition of
                    former calamities. Then follow in detail the final arrangements of the
                    reorganized theocracy. The new temple, its dimensions, construction, furniture,
                    are described; new laws as to sacrifice and festival are given for the priests,
                    prince, and people of the new commonwealth. Directions are given for the
                    equitable partition of the Holy Land among the twelve tribes, and for the
                    building of the new city, which is to be called by the new name Jahveh Shammah,
                    “the Lord is there.” In all these regulations a general formal resemblance to
                    the Pentateuchal legislation is abundantly manifest; but the differences of
                    detail are no less striking. The following may be mentioned among others.
                    Ezekiel’s temple is larger, but simpler, than that of Solomon. The distinction
                    between the Holy and the Most Holy Place is much less marked. Both ark and
                    high-priest are passed over in silence. The priesthood is specifically Zadokite.
                    The “prince” has priestly functions assigned him. The morning burnt-offering is
                    brought into special prominence; of the great festivals, the passover and the
                    feast of tabernacles alone are noticed. The feast of pentecυst is omitted, nor
                    is any mention made of the great day of atonement, but an observance unknown in
                    the Pentateuch, on the 1st and 7th of the first month, is proposed instead.</p>
                <p>The genuineness of the book of Ezekiel has seldom been questioned. Some
                    perplexity has been caused by the statement in the Talmud <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Baba bathra</hi> 15, 1) that the men of the great synagogue “wrote” Ezekiel.
                    This obscure expression, by which most probably mere editing was meant, has been
                    deprived of some of its importance by Kuenen’s demonstration of the unhistorical
                    character of the entire tradition regarding the great synagogue. Towards the
                    close of last century some doubts were expressed by Oeder, Vogel, and an
                    anonymous English writer in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine</hi> (1798),
                    with regard to the genuineness of the last nine chapters, which were supposed
                    rather to be of a Samaritan origin, and by Corodi with respect also to chaps,
                    xxxviii. and xxxix.; but these doubts were unanimously set aside by the not too
                    conservative critics of that period. Zunz <hi rend="italic">(Gottesdienstliche
                    Vortrage,</hi> 1832; also <hi rend="italic">Gesammelte Schriften,</hi> i. 217
                    <hi rend="italic">f.,</hi> 1875) was the first to impugn the genuineness of the
                    entire work, his thesis, in its most recent form, being that no such prophet as
                    Ezekiel ever existed, and that the present work bearing that fictitious name was
                    written somewhere between the years 440 and 400 B.c. His arguments are partly of
                    the <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> kind, such as that the special predictions
                    contained in it (xvii. 16, xxiv. 2, 16, &amp;c.) are inconsistent with the
                    genuineness of the book, and that it is inconceivable that in 570 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> any prophet could ever have thought of suggesting a
                    new division of the Holy Land, or of drafting a new law-book, or of sketching
                    the plans of a new temple and city. He argues further from the silence of other
                    scriptures, particularly of Jeremiah and of the book of Ezra, with regard to
                    Ezekiel; from certain allusions in the book itself, such as those to Daniel, to
                    the wine of Halybon, &amp;c.; also from its grammatical and linguistic
                    peculiarities. There is still practical unanimity, nevertheless, among critics
                    of all schools in the opinion that the stamp of Ezekiel’s individuality is
                    unmistakably and even obtrusively visible in every page of the book that bears
                    his name. Keil and Kuenen agree in holding him to have been its author, and its
                    editor as well. He is believed indeed not to have reduced it to its present form
                    till near the close of his life; and many have embraced the opinion of Ewald,
                    that the earlier dates have in some cases been incorrectly given by him. The
                    text, it ought to be remembered, however, has reached us in a somewhat impure
                    state.</p>
                <p>The question principally discussed in recent years, and likely to be discussed
                    for some time to come, in connexion with Ezekiel’s name is not whether he wrote
                    less than tradition has assigned to him, but rather whether he may <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n865/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0865-0830"/> not possibly have written more. In connexion with
                    his theory of the late origin of the priestly legislation in the Pentateuch,
                    Graf, in 1866, arguing from admitted similarities of style, gave it out as his
                    belief that Ezekiel was the author of certain chapters of Leviticus
                    (xviii.-xxiii., xxv., xxvi.). This view, which in substance has subsequently
                    been adopted by Colenso and a few others, is manifestly one which does not admit
                    of anything like demonstration. On the other hand, the larger and more
                    interesting inquiry as to the relative priority of the Levitical and
                    Deuteronomic legislations does not fall to be discussed in this place (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Pentateuch).</hi></p>
                <p>It remains that something should be said of Ezekiel’s place as an author and as a
                    religious teacher. His work may be judged from the purely literary point of view
                    more fairly perhaps than that of any of the earlier prophets,—for, unlike them,
                    he was a writer much more than he was a preacher. His oracles were sometimes
                    written before they were spoken; sometimes he wrote what he had no intention of
                    speaking at all. He may be called one of the first sopherim or scribes, if we
                    use that word in its higher sense as denoting “bookmen,” and not mere readers or
                    copyists. As a leader of public opinion, he bandied a variety of subjects in a
                    corresponding variety of styles, but always with a manner entirely his own. His
                    prose is invariably simple and unaffected; if there be any obscurity at all, it
                    is really caused by his excessive desire to make it impossible for his reader to
                    misunderstand him. His poetry has suffered much at the hands of translators, and
                    the student who is wholly dependent on our Authorized Version will be often at a
                    loss to understand the comparisons to Aeschylus, Dante, or Milton which have
                    occasionally been suggested. More than that of any other prophet, it has been
                    subjected to the extremes of exaggerated praise and undue depreciation by its
                    critics. The sympathetic modern reader, however, will be able to find in it a
                    sublimity, a tenderness, a beauty, a melody, wholly peculiar to itself. Chapter
                    xix., which even Schrader pronounces “masterly,” may be specially referred to;
                    also chapters xxviii. and xxxii.</p>
                <p>As a religious teacher, it is natural to compare Ezekiel with Jeremiah, his older
                    contemporary, on the one hand, and with his immediate successor, the author of
                    Isa. xL-lxvi., on the other. It has frequently been said (most strongly perhaps
                    by Duhm) that the contrast is very great, an^ very much to the disadvantage of
                    Ezekiel. The three men, nevertheless, have much that is common to them all. If
                    Ezekiel sometimes (and especially in his closing chapters) shows a
                    preponderating externalism, a tendency to delight in the fulness and minuteness
                    of his ceremonial details, it must not be forgotten that Jeremiah too looked
                    forward to a restored sanctuary and a reorganized priesthood as essential
                    elements in the perfected theocracy of the future. And if the “Great Unnamed” be
                    justly regarded as one of the loftiest and purest exponents of the spiritual
                    religion of coming days, we must at the same time remember that Ezekiel too had
                    bidden men seek above all things that'city, open only to the pure in heart, of
                    which the glory is that “the Lord is there.”</p>
                <p>Ezekiel is nowhere mentioned by name in the New Testament, and the direct traces
                    of his writings there, apart from those in the Apocalypse, are comparatively
                    few. Matt, viι. 24-27 compared with Ezek. xiii. 10-13, and John X. 16 compared
                    with Ezek. xxxiv. 22, 23, may be referred to Both directly, however, and also
                    through the writer of the Apocalypse, his influence upon Christian thought, and
                    especially upon Christian eschatology, has been considerable.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> For the ancient, mediaeval, and earlier
                    modern commentaries, see Carpzow and other works of introduction. The most
                    important works of recent date are those of Ewald, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Propheten des alten Bundes,</hi> vol. ii. 2nd. ed., 1868, Engl.
                    tr. 1877; Havernick, <hi rend="italic">Commentar</hi><hi rend="italic">u. d.
                    Proph.</hi><hi rend="italic">Ezechiel,</hi> 1843; Hitzig, <hi rend="italic"
                    >D.</hi><hi rend="italic">Proph.</hi><hi rend="italic">Ezechiel,</hi> 1847;
                    Fairbairn, <hi rend="italic">Exposition of the Book of Ezekiel,</hi> 1851;
                    Kliefotb, <hi rend="italic">D.</hi><hi rend="italic">Buch Ezechiels,</hi> 1865;
                    Hengstenberg, <hi rend="italic">D.</hi><hi rend="italic">JVeissagungen d.
                    Pr.</hi><hi rend="italic">Ezechiels,</hi> 1867; Keil, <hi rend="italic">D.
                    Proph. Ezechiel,</hi> 1868; <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Speakers</hi><hi rend="italic">Commentary,</hi> vol. vi., 1876. See also
                    Ewald’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">d.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">V.</hi><hi rend="italic">Isr.,</hi> iv. 18 ff.; Kuenen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Godsdienst</hi><hi rend="italic">ran</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Israel,</hi> vol. ii., and <hi rend="italic">Profeten en Profetie,</hi> 1875,
                    Eng. tr. 1877; Schrader’s article “Ezekiel” in SchenkeΓs <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibel-Lexieon;</hi> Duhm, <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie der Propheten,</hi>
                    1875. On the critical questions see Zunz, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gottesdienstlwhe</hi><hi rend="italic">Vorträge,</hi> p. 157-299, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Gesammelte Schriften,</hi> 1875; Graf, <hi rend="italic"
                    >D.</hi><hi rend="italic">geschichtliche Bucher</hi><hi rend="italic">des A.
                    B.</hi> 1866; Kuenen, in <hi rend="italic">Theol. Tijdschrift</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ioι</hi> 1870; Colenso, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pentateuch</hi><hi rend="italic">and</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Book</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic">Joshua</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">critically examined,</hi> part vi., 1872; Klostermann on “Ezekiel”
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Studien</hi><hi rend="italic">u.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Kritiken</hi> for 1877. The English reader may be referred to <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Holy Bible with various renderings and readings,</hi> London, 1876.
                    Bunsen’s <hi rend="italic">Bibelwerk</hi> will also be found useful by the
                    ordinaιy reader of German. (J. S. BL.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
