<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0551-0532-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ERZEROUM, Erzrum, or sometimes Arzeroum (9th edition,
                    volume 8, page 532)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996964">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3sw75">Rum</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n551/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ERZEROUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Erzrum</hi>, or sometimes <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Arzeroum</hi></label>, an important town of Turkish Armenia, at
                    the head of an extensive vilayet of the same name, the residence of a pasha, and
                    the seat of an Armenian patriarch and a Greek bishop, as well as the centre of
                    the fourth army corps, and one of the main strategical points on the
                    Turko-Russian frontier. It is situated 6200 feet above the level of the sea on
                    the southern edge of a wide valley, surrounded by mountains of considerable
                    elevation, about 4 miles from the Kara-Su or western branch of the Euphrates,
                    140 miles S.S.E. of Trebizond. To the east lies the Devi-Boyun, upwards of 8000
                    feet in height, and to the south-east the Polan·Duken. the latter being the
                    birthplace of a number of small streamlets, which, after meeting in the town,
                    flow N. to the Kara-Su. The streets of the town are for the most part irregular,
                    unpaved, badly drained, filthy, and infested with dogs; and as the building
                    material is mainly a darkgrey volcanic stone cemented with mud, the general
                    appearance is dull and sombre. The roofs, with scarcely an exception, are flat
                    or dome-shaped, and covered with a layer of earth and sward, on which it is no
                    uncommon thing to see a donkey grazing. A considerable proportion, indeed, of
                    the ordinary dwelling-houses are formed by making an extensive quadrangular
                    excavation in the earth, and covering in the whole or a part of the area, so
                    that the roof is almost on a level with the natural surface of the ground. The
                    town is said to contain about thirty khans or caravansaries, about as many
                    mosques, a number of Christian churches, and nineteen public baths; but none of
                    those buildings are of much architectural pretension, except the Armenian
                    cathedral and the Shifteh— two graceful minarets near the citadel, belonging to
                    an ancient and striking edifice, of which a detailed account may be found in
                    Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Researches in Asia,</hi> 1842. A large number of
                    circular towers with conical tops give a certain picturesqueness to the general
                    view; they are popularly reputed to be the tombs of holy men who died in the 14
                    th century. The defences consist of an old brick-built citadel near the centre
                    of the town, an enceinte on Vauban’s principles with dry ditch and dilapidated
                    walls, several detached forts constructed since 1864, and a number of outlying
                    earthworks of no great strength. The outer wall of the citadel having fallen
                    into disrepair has been demolished. An excellent supply of water from
                    Polan-Duken is distributed by wooden pipes to numerous fountains. Situated as it
                    is on the main route between the Black Sea and Persia, Erzeroum has long
                    maintained an extensive trade; and though on account of the unsettled state of
                    the country its commercial prosperity has declined since 1830, Persia, England,
                    Russia, and Germany think it worth while to maintain consular agents in the
                    town. The exports are wheat, goat and sheep skins, mohair, and a lessening
                    quantity of galls; and tobacco from Persia, known as <hi rend="italic"
                    >timbaki,</hi> furs from Russia, and Manchester goods are among the main items
                    of the transit trade. Since 1860 the road from Trebizond has been greatly
                    improved, and four-wheeled fourgons accomplish the distance in eight or nine
                    days. The principal trades are tanning, morocco-dyeing, sheep skin dressing, and
                    the making of horse-shoes, nails, and iron, brass, and copper utensils. In 1873
                    a building was erected by two Armenian Catholics, Shabanian by name, to be used
                    as a distillery, soap-works, and a macaroni manufactory. A considerable number
                    of the townspeople are owners of sheep-farms or flocks in the mountain pastures;
                    and a still greater proportion keep sheep and cattle in the town, sending them
                    out daily under the charge of a common herdsman. To a stranger it is a
                    remarkable sight to watch the regularity with which, as the herdsman passes in
                    the morning, the separate flocks and herds join the main body, and the equal
                    regularity with which in the evening they turn aside to their respective
                    quarters. The climate is exceedingly severe, and snow lies on the ground for
                    about six months in the year. As wood is scarce the usual fuel is tezek or dry
                    cowdung, the preparation of which is one of the most important tasks of the
                    farmer-citizen. In 1854 the population of Erzeroum was estimated at 50,000, of
                    whom 30,000 were Turks, 5000 Orthodox Armenians, 2300 Catholic Armenians,</p>
                <p>1200 Persians, 300 Greeks, 1200 Armenians, Georgians, and Jews claiming to be
                    Russian subjects, and 10,000 soldiers. More recent estimates give 100,000,
                    60,000, and 50,000.</p>
                <p>Erzeroum is a town of great antiquity, and has been identified with the Armenian
                    Garin Khalakh, the Arabic Kalikalah, and the Byzantine Theodosiopolis of the 5th
                    century. Its present name, by some regarded as a corruption of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Arx Romαηorwu</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> the “citadel of the
                    Romans,’’ is more probably derived from Areen-er-Rum, seeing that Arsen is known
                    to have been the name of a town in the immediate vicinity. At the time of its
                    capture by the Seljuks in</p>
                <p>1201 Erzeroum must have been a mighty city, if the statement that it lost 140,000
                    of its inhabitants forms even an approximation to the truth. It came into
                    Turkish possession in 1517. On July 9. 1829, it was captured by the Russian
                    general Paskevitch, and the Russian occupation continued till the peace of
                    Adrianople, 14th September. In 1859 a severe earthquake occurred, by which about
                    4500 houses were destroyed, 9 minarets levelled with the ground, and about 500
                    people killed. After suffering greatly from disease and death, the town
                    capitulated to the Russians in February 1878.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n552/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0552-0533"/>
                <p>See Curzon, <hi rend="italic">Erzeroum and Armenia;</hi> Flandin and Coste, <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi rend="italic">Perse,</hi>
                    Paris, 1851; Monteith, J?rzerou?7i <hi rend="italic">and Kars,</hi> 1856;
                    Williams, <hi rend="italic">War Diary,</hi> 1877; C. B. Norman, <hi
                    rend="italic">Armenia and the Campaign of</hi> 1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
