<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0679-0654-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EUCHRE (9th edition, volume 8, page 654)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr79">Carding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jj4b">Cards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86p9b">Tricks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1939006">Cards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847103">Carding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156642">Tricks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937529">Games</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137633">Suites</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207035">Louisiana</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n679/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EUCHRE</label>, a game at cards, much played in America.
                    Euchre is said to be a corruption of the word écarté; the game is believed to
                    have been first played by the French settlers in Louisiana, but at what date is
                    uncertain. Euchre is played with thirty-two cards, the twos, threes, fours,
                    fives, and sixes being rejected from a complete pack. The players cut for deal,
                    and the lowest deals. The non-dealer then cuts to his opponent, who deals five
                    cards to each, by two at a time and three at a time, or <hi rend="italic">vice
                    versa.</hi> The dealer turns up the top of the undealt cards for trumps. In
                    suits not trumps the cards rank as at whist; in the trump suit the knave (called
                    the <hi rend="italic">right bower)</hi> is the highest trump, and the other
                    knave of the same colour, black or red, as the case may be (called the <hi
                    rend="italic">left bower),</hi> is the next highest, this card being, of course,
                    omitted from the suit to which it would otherwise belong. The other trumps rank
                    as already stated, the queen being next above the ten.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Two-handed Euchre.—</hi> The non-dealer looks at his hand and
                    decides whether he will play it. If content, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> if he
                    thinks he can win three tricks, he says “order it up.” The dealer then puts out
                    from his hand any card he pleases, face downwards, and is entitled to take the
                    trump card into his hand; but the card is generally left on the pack until
                    wanted in the course of play. If the non-dealer is not content, he says “pass.”
                    The dealer then has the option of taking up the trump as before, or of passing
                    also. If the trump is <hi rend="italic">ordered up</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >taken up</hi> the play of the hand commences; if both pass, the dealer places
                    the trump card face upwards under the pack, called <hi rend="italic">turning it
                    down.</hi> The non-dealer has then the option of <hi rend="italic">making it,
                    i.e.,</hi> of naming any suit, except the one turned up, saying, “make it
                    spades,” or any suit he prefers, and that suit becomes trumps, or of passing
                    again, saying, “pass again.” If he makes it, the play begins; if he passes
                    again, the dealer has similarly the option of making it. ∏ both pass a second
                    time the hand is thrown up, and the other player deals When the turn up is red
                    and the trump is made red it is called <hi rend="italic">making it next;</hi>
                    the same if black is made black. If the trump is made of a different colour from
                    the turn up, it is called <hi rend="italic">crossing the suit.</hi> If the hand
                    is played, the non-dealer leads; the dealer plays to the card led. He must
                    follow suit if able, otherwise he may play any card he pleases. If the left
                    bower is led a trump must be played to it. The highest card of the suit led wins
                    the trick; trumps win other suits. The winner of the trick leads to the next. If
                    the player who orders up, takes up, or makes the trump, wins five tricks, he
                    scores two, called a <hi rend="italic">march·,</hi> if he makes three or four
                    tricks he scores one, called the <hi rend="italic">point.</hi> If he fails to
                    make three tricks he is <hi rend="italic">euchred,</hi> and his opponent scores
                    two. The game is five up. By agreement, a player who makes more than five may
                    carry the surplus (called a <hi rend="italic">lap)</hi> to the next game. Also
                    it is sometimes agreed that a love game (or <hi rend="italic">lurch)</hi> shall
                    count double. The game may be reckoned without reference to the adverse score;
                    or it may be played with points, that is, the winner receives from the loser as
                    many points as he wants of game.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Three-handed or Cut-throat Euchre.—</hi> The option of playing
                    or passing goes to each in rotation, beginning with the player to the dealer’s
                    left. Three cards, one from each hand, constitute a trick. The player who
                    orders* up, takes up, or makes the trump plays against the other two, except at
                    <hi rend="italic">independent euchre,</hi> when each plays for himself. If the
                    attacking player is euchred, he is <hi rend="italic">set back</hi> two points.
                    Thus if he is love, and is euchred, he has seven points to make instead of
                    five.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Four-handed Euchre</hi> is generally played with partners, who
                    are cut for and sit opposite each other as at whist. If the first hand passes,
                    the second may say “I assist,” wlιich means that the dealer (his partner) is to
                    take up the trump.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n680/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0680-0655"/>
                <p>The haud is thou played as at whist, four cards constituting a trick. The eldest
                    hand has the next deal. If a player has a very strong hand he may <hi
                    rend="italic">play alone</hi> single-handed against the two adversaries. His
                    partner cannot object. A player can declare to play alone when he or his partner
                    orders up, or when his partner assists, or when he makes the trump, or (if
                    dealer) when he takes up the trump, but not when the adversary orders up,
                    assists, or makes the trump. If the lone player wins a march he scores four, if
                    he wins three or four tricks he scores one; if he fails to win three tricks the
                    opponents score two.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hints.</hi> —1. The chances are that the dealer has one
                    trump in hand; if you order up, you must expect to meet two trumps. Therefore,
                    you should not order up unless your hand gives you a two to one chance of
                    winning three tricks against two trumps, and your cards are such that you would
                    have a worse chance if you made the trump. If strong in trumps and equally
                    strong in another suit, it is always right to pass. Also, if you have the point
                    certain, whether you make the trump or not, you should pass, in hopes the dealer
                    may take up the trump.</p>
                <p>2. If you pass and the dealer turns it down, you should not make the trump unless
                    you have a two to one chance of winning three tricks against one trump.</p>
                <p>3. If you hold good cards in two suits of different colours, and you make the
                    trump, you should make it next. For, the dealer having turned it down in one
                    colour, is less likely to hold a bower of that colour than of the other. At the
                    four-handed game the non dealer and his partner should also avoid crossing the
                    suit. But if the dealer’s partner makes the trump, he should not hesitate to
                    cross the suit, as the dealer, having turned it down, has probably no bower in
                    that suit.</p>
                <p>4. At four-handed euchre, the eldest hand should be very strong to order it up;
                    but the second player should assist if he has something more than one trick, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> an ace and a trump, or two aces. If, however, he is
                    strong in the non-trump suits, he should not assist unless he can be pretty sure
                    of making two tricks. The third hand should be cautious of ordering up, as his
                    partner, having passed, must be weak. This applies with still more force to
                    taking up by the dealer, as his partner, not having assisted, must be very weak.
                    To take up the dealer should be pretty sure of two tricks, aud have a chance of
                    a third.</p>
                <p>5. If the dealer takes up the trump he should keep two. cards of a suit, unless
                    his single card is an ace. Thus, with queen, seven of one suit and king single
                    of another, the king should be discarded.</p>
                <p>6. Lead from a guarded suit unless in fear of losing a march, when lead your
                    highest single card. Lead from a sequence of three trumps. At four-handed euchre
                    always lead a trump with three. Also lead a trump if you have made it next; if
                    your left hand adversary has assisted (unless a bower is turned up); and if
                    your</p>
                <p>I&gt;artner ordersup, assists, takes up, or makes the trump. Further, ea&lt;l a
                    trump if you have lost two tricks and won the third, unless your partner has
                    dealt and still has the turn up in hand.</p>
                <p>7. As a rule make tricks when able. Passing or finessing is seldom good play.</p>
                <p>8. If your partner orders up, assists, takes up, or makes the trump, trump the
                    trick whenever you can.</p>
                <p>9. In discarding during the play, as a rule, keep a guarded card in preference to
                    a single one, except a single ace.</p>
                <p>10. If the adversary is at three do not order up unless you have very good cards.
                    If the adversary is at four take up the trump on a light hand.</p>
                <p>11. At four-handed euchre, if the dealer is one or two, and the eldest hand four,
                    he should order up, unless he has one certain trick, in order to prevent the
                    opponent from playing alone. This position is called <hi rend="italic">the
                    bridge.</hi></p>
                <p>12. At four-all, if the eldest hand or third hand has a trick and the chance of a
                    second, and such cards that he would be no better off if he made the trump, he
                    should order it up.</p>
                <p>13. The eldest hand, and next to him the dealer, may play alone on weaker hands
                    than the other players. The leader, with a lone hand, should lead his winning
                    trumps; if two tricks are thus made, and the leader has a losing trump, he
                    should then lead his best card out of trumps. When playing against a lone hand,
                    lead an ace. If you have not one, lead your highest card out of trumps, except
                    with a guarded king and another suit, when lead the latter. Also, keep cards of
                    the suits your partner discards, but do not throw an ace, even if your partner
                    keeps your ace suit.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Laws of Euchre.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Dealing.—</hi> 1. If
                    the dealer gives too many or too few cards to any player, or if he turns up two
                    cards, it is a misdeal, and the next player deals. 2. If the dealer exposes a
                    card, or if there is a faced card in the pack, there must be a fresh deal. <hi
                    rend="italic">Playing.—</hi> 3. Any one playing with the wrong number of cards
                    can score nothing that hand. The same if, when the trump is ordered up, the
                    dealer omits to discard before he or his partner plays. 4. When more than two
                    play, exposed cards can be called. Also a card led out of turn may be called, or
                    a suit from the side offending at their next lead. 5. A player not following
                    suit when able may correct his mistake before the trick is turned and quitted or
                    he or his partner plays to the next trick, the card played in error being an
                    exposed card. If the error is not corrected a revoke is established. A player
                    revoking is euchred, and cannot score anything that hand. G. A player making the
                    trump must abide by the suit first named. 7. If, after the trump is turned, a
                    player reminds his partner that they are at the point of the bridge, the latter
                    loses the right to order up. 8. Each player has a right to see the last trick.
                    (H. J.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
