<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0167-0158-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EMBALMING (9th edition, volume 8, page 158)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4td9n72j">Abdomen</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44746z94">Pitch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mx40">Viscera</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58ck7s">Annals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794279">Abdomen</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888385">Dead</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n167/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EMBALMING</label> (Greek, βaλσapov, balsam; German,
                    einbalsamiren; French, embaumement), the art of preparing dead bodies, chiefly
                    by the use of medicaments, in order to preserve them from putrefaction and the
                    attacks of insects. The ancient Egyptians carried the art to great perfection,
                    and embalmed not only human beings, but cats, crocodiles, ichneumons, and other
                    sacred animals. It has been suggested that the origin of embalming in Egypt is
                    to be traced to a want of fuel for the purpose of cremation, to the
                    inadvisability or at some times impossibility of burial in a soil annually
                    disturbed by the inundation of the Nile, aud to the necessity, for sanitary
                    reasons, of preventing the decomposition of the bodies of the dead when placed
                    iu open sepulchres. As, however, the corpses of the embalmed must have
                    constituted but a small proportion of the aggregate mass of animal matter daily
                    to be disposed of, the above explanation is far from satisfactory; and it may be
                    questioned whether embalming, together with the greater number of the Egyptian
                    doctrines concerning a future life, may not have entirely originated in
                    superstition or sentiment concerning the dead. According to Prescott, it was a
                    belief in a resurrection of the body that led the ancient Peruvians to preserve
                    the air-dried corpses of their dead with so much solicitude (see Conquest of
                    Peru, bk. i. chap, iii.). Prichard {Egyptian Mythology, p. 200) holds it as
                    probable that the views with which the Egyptians embalmed bodies were “akin to
                    those which rendered the Greeks and Romans so anxious to perform the usual rites
                    of sepulture to their departed warriors, namely, . . . that these solemnities
                    expedited the journey of the soul to the appointed region, where it was to
                    receive judgment for its former deeds, and to have its future doom fixed
                    accordingly.” It has been supposed by some that the discovery of the
                    preservation of bodies interred in saline soils may have been the immediate
                    origin of embalming in Egypt. In that country certain classes of the community
                    were specially appointed for the practice of the art. Joseph, we are told in
                    Gen. 1. 2, “commanded his servants the physicians to embalm his father.”
                    Herodotus (ii. 86) gives an account of three of the methods of embalming
                    followed by the Egyptians. The most expensive of these, which cost a talent of
                    silver (£243, 153), w as as follows. The brains were in part removed through the
                    nostrils by means of a bent iron implement, and in part by the injection of
                    drugs. The intestines having been drawn out through an incision in the left
                    side, the abdomen was cleansed with palm-wine, and filled with myrrh, cassia,
                    and other materials, and the opening was sewed up. This done, the body was
                    steeped seventy days in a solution of litron or natron.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Neutral carbonate of sodium, NaCO, found at
                    the natron lakes in the Libyan desert, and at El Hegs, in Upper
                    Egypt.</p></note> Diodorus (i. 91) relates that the cutter {παpaerχlστ∙tγi)
                    appointed to make the incision in the flank for the removal of the intestines,
                    as soon as he had performed his office, w as pursued with stones and curses by
                    those about him, it being held by the Egyptians a detestable thing to commit any
                    violence or inflict a wound on the body. After the steeping, the body was
                    washed, and handed over to the swathers, a peculiar class of the lowest order of
                    priests, called by Plutarch cholchytoe, by whom it was bandaged in gummed cloth;
                    it was then ready for the coffin. Mummies thus prepared were considered to
                    represent Osiris. In another method of embalming, costing twenty-two minae
                    (about £90), the abdomen was injected with</p>
                <p>“cedar-tree pitch <hi rend="superscript"> ,,</hi> (κeδpια), which, as it would
                    seem from Pliny (A <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> αi. Hist., xvi. 21), was the
                    liquid distillate of the pitch-pine. This is stated by Herodotus to have had a
                    corrosive and solvent action on the viscera. After injection the body was
                    steeped a certain number of days in natron; the contents of the abdomen were
                    allowed to escape; and the process was then complete. The preparation of the
                    bodies of the poorest consisted simply in placing them in natron for seventy
                    days, after a previous rinsing of the abdomen with “syrmaea.” The material
                    principally used in the costlier modes of embalming appears to have been
                    asphalt; wax was more rarely employed. In some cases embalming seems to have
                    been effected by immersing the body in a bath of molten bitumen. Tanning also
                    was resorted to. Occasionally the viscera, after treatment, were in part or
                    wholly replaced in the body, together with wax figures of the four genii of
                    Amenti. More commonly they were embalmed in a mixture of sand and asphalt, and
                    buried in vases, or canοpi, placed near the mummy, the abdomen being filled with
                    chips and sawdust of cedar and a small quantity of natron. In one jar were
                    placed the stomach and large intestine; in another, the small intestines; in a
                    third, the lungs and heart; in a fourth, the gall-bladder and liver. Porphyry
                    {De Abstinentia, iv. 10) mentions a custom of inclosing the intestines in a box,
                    and consigning them to the Nile, after a prayer uttered by one of the embalmers,
                    but his statement is regarded by Sir J. G. Wilkinson as unworthy of belief. The
                    body of Nero’s wife Poppaea, contrary to the usage of the Romans, was not burnt,
                    but, as customary among other nations with the bodies of potentates, was
                    honoured with embalmment (see Tacitus, Annal., xvi. 6). The body of Alexander
                    the Great is said to have been embalmed with honey (Statius, Sylv., iii. 2,
                    117), and the same material was used to preserve the corpse of Agesipolis I.
                    during its conveyance to Sparta for burial. Herodotus states (iii. 24) that the
                    Ethiopians, in embalming, dried the body, rubbed it with gypsum (or chalk), and,
                    having painted it, placed it in a block of some transparent substance. The
                    Guanches, the aborigines of the Canaries, employed a mode of embalming similar
                    to that of the Egyptians, filling the hollow caused by the removal of the
                    viscera with salt and an absorbent vegetable powder (see Bory de Saint Vincent,
                    Essais sur les Iles Fortunées, 1803, p. 495). Embalming was still in vogue among
                    the Egyptians in the time of St Augustine, who says that they termed mummies
                    gabbaroe {Serm. 120, cap. 12). In modern times numerous methods of embalming
                    have been practised. By William Hunter essential oils, alcohol, cinnabar,
                    camphor, saltpetre, aud pitch or rosin were employed, and the final desiccation
                    of the body was effected by means of roasted gypsum placed in its coffin. Boudet
                    embalmed with tan, salt, asphalt, and Peruvian bark, camphor, cinnamon, and
                    other aromatics, and corrosive sublimate. The la3t-mentioned drug, the chloride
                    and sulphate of zinc, the acetate and sulphate of aluminium, and creasote and
                    carbolic, acid have all been recommended by various modern embalmers.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mummy</hi>; Louis Penicher, Traité des Embaumements,
                    Paris, 1669; S. Blancard, Anatomin Reformata, et de Balsamatione nova methodus,
                    Lugd. Bat. 1695; Thomas Greenhill, The Art of Embalming, Loud. 1705; J. N.
                    Marjolin, Manuel d' Anatomie, Paris, 1810; Pettigrew, History of Mummies, Lond.
                    1834; Gannal, Traité d'Embaunwmeηts, Paris, 1838; 2nd ed. 1841; Magnus, Bas
                    Einbalsamiren der Leichen, Brunsw., 1839; Rawlinson’s Herodotus, vol. ii. p.
                    141.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
