<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0908-0159-0150-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ELLIS, William (9th edition, volume 8, page
                    150)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1245821">Polynesia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n159/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ELLIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label> (1794-1872),
                    one of the most devoted and successful of modern missionaries, was born in
                    London on the 29th August 1794. When he was about four years old his father, who
                    was a working man, removed with his family to Wisbeach, where accordingly his
                    boyhood was spent. His school education was even scantier than boys of his class
                    at that time usually received, but being naturally bright and intelligent he did
                    much to supply the deficiency by his own efforts. When about twelve years of age
                    he was put to work with a market gardener. He showed an enthusiastic interest in
                    gardening work, and continued to be engaged in it under various employers until
                    1814. In that year having come under serious religious impressions, he offered
                    himself as a missionary to the London Missionary Society, and after due inquiry
                    the offer was accepted. The year which was allowed him for training was devoted
                    not merely to the study of theology at Homerton, but to the acquisition of
                    various practical arts, such as printing and bookbinding, which proved of the
                    utmost service to him in the mission field. Having been ordained he sailed for
                    the South Sea Islands in January 1816, and reached his destination after a
                    voyage of thirteen months’ duration. He remained in Polynesia, occupying various
                    stations in succession, until 1824, when he was compelled to return home on
                    account of the state of his wife’s health. Though the period of his residence in
                    the islands was thus comparatively short, his labours were very fruitful,
                    contributing perhaps as much as those of any other missionary to bring about the
                    extraordinary improvement in the religious, moral, and social condition of the
                    Southern Archipelago that has taken place during the present century. He was not
                    only unwearied in his efforts to promote the immediate spiritual object of his
                    mission, but he introduced many secondary aids to the improvement of the
                    condition of the people. His gardening experience enabled him successfully to
                    acclimatize many species of tropical fruits and plants, which now form an
                    important source of wealth to the islanders; and he had the distinction of
                    setting up and working the first printing-press in the South Seas. Ellis and his
                    wife availed themselves for their journey home of an American vessel, which
                    landed them free of all charge at New Bedford, Massachusetts, in the spring of
                    1825. They remained for some months in the United States, where they were
                    exceedingly well received, and Ellis excited much interest in the mission with
                    ∙which he was connected by attending numerous public meetings held in support of
                    its claims. For 3everal years after his return to England, he was employed as. a
                    travelling agent of the London Missionary Society, whose schemes he explained
                    and advocated in nearly every important town of the United Kingdom. In the midst
                    of this busy life he found time to publish his Tour through Hawaii (1826), which
                    had been written in the course of his journey home, and his Polynesian
                    Researches (2 vols., 1829), a work which Southey in the Quarterly Revieιv
                    characterized as one of the most interesting he had ever read. In 1832 he was
                    appointed foreign secretary to the London Missionary Society, the state of his
                    wife’s health rendering the long cherished prospect of a return to the South
                    Seas hopeless. He discharged the duties of the office with great efficiency for
                    seven years, when threatened cerebral disease compelled him to resign it. In the
                    interval his first wife had died, and he had married in 1837 Miss Sarah
                    Stickney, authoress of The Poetry of Life, The Women of England, and many other
                    well-known works. Just before resigning the secretaryship he published his
                    History of Madagascar, and thus first established between his name and that
                    island a connection which was destined to be honourable and enduring in no
                    common degree. After a season spent in Pau, of which Mrs Ellis has given a most
                    interesting account in her Summer and Winter in the Pyrenees, Mr Ellis and his
                    wife returned to England in 1841, and took up their residence in a beautiful
                    country house at Rose Hill, Hoddesdon, Hertfordshire. Here he continued to show
                    unabated interest and almost unabated activity in the business of the Society
                    with which he had been in one capacity or another so long connected. By desire
                    of the directors he undertook ahistory of the society, the first volume of which
                    appeared in 1844, though pressure of other work prevented its completion. In
                    1847 he accepted the pastorate of the little congregational church at Hoddesdon,
                    which had been revived and strengthened mainly through his exertions. After a
                    few years his quiet life was interrupted by a call from the London Missionary
                    Society to proceed to Madagascar<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit08newyrich/page/n160/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0908-0160-0151"/> in order to inquire into the prospects for the
                    resumption of the missionary enterprise there, which had been checked for
                    several years owing to the bitter hostility of the reigning queen. Between 1853
                    and 1857 he paid three visits to that island, of which he has given a full
                    account in his Three Visits to Madagascar (1858), one of the most profoundly
                    interesting and romantic narratives in the whole literature of missions. In
                    reading it one scarcely knows whether to admire most the fearlessness, the
                    undeviating regard for principle, or the discretion, with which he discharged a
                    most delicate and difficult negotiation, and won in the end a signal triumph for
                    free Christianity. Though its primary interest is religious, the work contains
                    much valuable scientific information. At the invitation of the directors of the
                    society, Ellis undertook another journey to Madagascar in 1863, when he was
                    close upon seventy years of age. Of this he gave an account in his Madagascar
                    Revisited (1867). He died on the 25th June 1872. In addition to the works
                    already mentioned, Ellis was the author of A Vindication of the South Sea
                    Missions from the Misrepresentations of Otto Von Kotzebue (1831), and Village
                    Lectures on Popery (1851).</p>
                <p>Mrs Ellis survived her husband only a few days. For a considerable number of
                    years she conducted a ladies’ school in Hertfordshire on principles which she
                    had carefully thought out, and which are explained in her Rau&gt;don House
                    (1848). She wrote upwards of thirty works, most of which were very popular.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
