<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0602-0564-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mn08">Jurists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=602" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VATTEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Emmerich de</hi></label>, an
                    eminent jurist, was the son of a protestant minister, and was born at Couret in
                    the principality of Neuchâtel, in the month of April 1714. His academical
                    studies he prosecuted at Basel and Geneva. During his early years, his favourite
                    pursuit was philosophy; and having carefully examined the works of Leibnitz and
                    Wolf, he exhibited a specimen of his talents for metaphysical investigation, by
                    publishing a defence of Leibnitz’s system against Crousaz. It was printed in
                    1741; and in the course of the same year, he repaired to Berlin in the hope of
                    obtaining some public employent from the king; but this hope was so long
                    deferred, that in 1743 he proceeded to Dresden with similar views,' and
                    experienced a very favourable reception from Count Bruhl. Some private affairs
                    required his presence in his native country; but he returned to the court of
                    Saxony in 1746, and obtained from the elector, Augustus the Third, the title of
                    counsellor of embassy, accompanied with a pension. He was sent to Berne in the
                    capacity of the elector’s minister to that republic; and as his diplomatic
                    functions did not require constant re sidence, he passed some portion of his
                    time with his own family. Much of his leisure was devoted to literature and
                    jurisprudence. Among other works, he published “Mélanges de Littérature, de
                    Morale, et de Politique,” and “Loisirs Philosophiques.” But his best efforts
                    were directed to a more elaborate work, on which his reputation is chiefly
                    founded. It appeared under the title of "Droit des Gens; ou, Principes de la Loi
                    Naturelle appliqués à la Conduite et aux Affaires des Nations et des
                    Souverains.” Neuchâtel, 1758, 2 tom. 4to. During the same year, having been
                    recalled from Switzerland, he was employed in the cabinet of Dresden, and was
                    soon afterwards honoured with the title of privy-counsellor. Although his
                    constitution had originally been robust, his labours now became so intense as to
                    exhaust bis strength. Having tried the effects of relaxation and of his native
                    air, he thought himself sufficiently recovered to resume his place in the
                    cabinet. He accordingly returned to Dresden in 1766; but his renewed exertions
                    soon produced a relapse, and he made another excursion to Neuchâtel, where he
                    died on the 20th of December 1767, in the fifty-fourth year of his age. He left
                    a son, who was recently a member of the council of that principality. The last
                    of bis literary labours was a work entitled, “Questions de Droit Naturel; ou,
                    Observations sur le Traité du Droit de la Nature, par Wolf.” Vattel’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Droit des Gens</hi> continues to be studied and quoted as a
                    book of authority. It has passed through many editions, and has been translated
                    into various languages. An English translation was published in the year
                    1760.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
