<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0693-0653-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pp4g">Viola</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn33">Violin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62h1n">Violoncello</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1167119">Viola</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167350">Violin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:2002543">Violin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1135283">String</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167501">Violoncello</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=693" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VIOLA</label>. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Βοτανυ.</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Viola,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Tenor Violin.</hi> A
                    bow-instrument of the violin kind, intermediate in size and pitch between the
                    violin and the violoncello. It has four strings, of which the third and fourth
                    are covered with silvered copper wire. It is tuned C, G, D, A, reckoning
                    upwards, and is an octave higher in pitch than the violoncello, and a fifth
                    lower than the violin. See article Music.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Viola,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Alto Viola,</hi> an
                    instrument of the violin kind, larger than an ordinary violin, and furnished
                    with four gut strings, the third and fourth of these being covered with
                    silver-plated copper wire. It originated from the <hi rend="italic">viola di
                        braccio,</hi> one of the ancient set of viols used in concerts. The English
                    call it the tenor-violin, or simply the tenor. Its name of alto-viola is derived
                    from its music being written in the alto-clef on the third line of the stave. It
                    is tuned C, G, D, A, an octave above the violoncello. For its compass, and use
                    in orchestra, &amp;c., see Music.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Viola d'Amore,</hi> an instrument no longer in use, but of
                    which the tone and effect are said to have been very sweet and singular. It was
                    played with a bow, and seems to have varied in the number of its strings and in
                    its tuning. One species of it is described as having five gut strings, and five
                    metal wires tuned in unison with the strings, but passing under the finger-board
                    and bridge, and thus vibrating only as <hi rend="italic">open</hi> wires, to
                    arpeggios or harmonics, &amp;c., played upon the open gut strings. The principle
                    of this instrument seems to have been revived in the construction of some recent
                    musical instruments.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Viola di Gamba,</hi> a musical instrument no longer in use,
                    but which was the immediate predecessor of the violoncello. A clever musician,
                    C. F. Abel, in the last century, threw away his fine talents upon this nasal and
                    ungrateful instrument. A good <hi rend="italic">viola di gamba</hi> affords
                    excellent wood materials for making a fine tenor-violin.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
