<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0649-0611-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808437">Anatomists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891345">Designers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w05g">Anatomists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=649" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VESALIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Andreas</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated physician and anatomist, was bom at Brussels in the year 1514. He
                    studied physic at Paris under Sylvius, but applied himself chiefly to anatomy,
                    which was then very little known, dissections being esteemed unlawful and
                    impious; and it appears from his work “De Humani Corporis Fabrica,” that he
                    perfected himself in this useful knowledge very early. About the year 1537, the
                    republic of Venice made him professor in the university of Padua, where he
                    taught anatomy for seven years. Charles V. called him to be his physician, as he
                    was afterwards to Philip II., king of Spain. Vesalius was now at the height of
                    his glory, when all of a sudden he formed the design of taking a journey to
                    Palestine; concerning which journey we are told the following story. A young
                    Spanish nobleman whom he had attended was supposed to be dead. Vesalius obtained
                    leave to open him, in order to explore the true cause of his illness; but when
                    he opened the breast, he perceived symptoms of life, and saw the heart beat. The
                    parent, not satisfied with prosecuting him for murder, accused him of impiety to
                    the inquisition, in hopes that tribunal would punish him with greater rigour;
                    but the king interposing, saved him on condition of his making a pilgrimage to
                    the Holy Land. He was ship-wrecked on his return, and thrown upon the island of
                    Zante, where he perished on the 15th of October 1564. He was the author of
                    several works, the principal of which is entitled “De Humani Corporis Fabrica,
                    libri vu.” Basil. 1543, fol. This first edition contains excellent
                    wood-cuts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
