<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0689-0649-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116439">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=689" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VIGO</label>, a sea-port of Spain, in the province of
                    Galicia, more remarkable for the excellence of the bay on which it stands. Vigo
                    bay is entirely enclosed with high mountainous land, broken by cultivated
                    valleys, which form a pleasing landscape. It is entered by a long channel, in
                    which there are from twenty-seven to thirty-two feet of water. The beach is
                    clear, the holding ground good, and there a ship is well sheltered from the sea
                    by the Bayona islands. The town is surrounded by an ancient wall, and is
                    defended by a citadel. The harbour, though so well situated, is little
                    frequented by any but coasting vessels. Vigo contains not more than 2500
                    inhabitants. It is remarkable as the place where a Spanish plate-fleet took
                    refuge in the year 1702, and was attacked by a combined fleet of the British and
                    Dutch ships, then at war with Spain. The victory was complete, but the Spaniards
                    set fire to the richest of the treasure-ships, which were burnt and sunk. It was
                    to this place that General Crawford led the light division of Sir John Moore’s
                    army, on its retreat from Spain, and embarked it with despatch and without loss.
                    The latitude is 42. 13. 20. N. Long. 8. 33. 30. W.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=690"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0690-0650"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
