<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0627-0589-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828821">Bats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163799">Valentinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:868483">Colonization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:868430">Colonate</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44w8x">Colonization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk3c">Colonate</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34ms27">Bats</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=627" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VEGETIUS RENATUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Flavius</hi></label>,
                    a Latin writer, flourished towards the close of the fourth century. His treatise
                    “De Re Militari,” he inscribed to the emperor Valentinian the Second, who was
                    assassinated in the year 393. He appears to have been a man of rank. Raphael
                    Volaterranus styles him “Comes Constantinopolitanus,” and some manuscripts of
                    his own work describe him in a similar manner. In the older editions, his
                    treatise is divided into four books; but Scriverius, on the authority of certain
                    manuscripts, divided it into five. The authors whom Vegetius professes to follow
                    are Cato, Celsus, Frontinus, and Paternus, together with Augustus, Trajan, and
                    Hadrian, in their constitutions, or legal enactments. He has thus collected a
                    valuable mass of materials; but Lipsius has remarked that he confounds the
                    customs and practices of his own with those of former ages.</p>
                <p>An edition of his work, supposed to be the first, appeared under the title of
                    “Epitoma de Re Militari.” It is in folio, without place or date, but, according
                    to conjecture, was printed at Utrecht about the year 1473. There is another
                    undated edition in quarto, and a third in folio. After various intermediate
                    editions appeared that of F. Modius, Colon. 1580, 8vo. It was followed by two
                    editions containing the elaborate commentary of Stewechius, Antverp. 1585, 4to.,
                    Lugd. Bat. 1592, 8vo. His commentary, together with that of Modius, is to be
                    found in the edition of Scriverius, Lugd. Bat. 1607, 4to. These three, like most
                    of the editions, include Frontinus and other ancient writers on military
                    affairs. The text of these authors, with the notes of Scriverius, was reprinted
                    in 12mo. at the same place in 1633 and 1644. An edition of Vegetius, containing
                    select notes of Stewechius and Scriverius, with those of the editor, and a
                    French translation, was published by N. Schwebelius, Norimbergae, 1767, 4to.
                    Another, containing the annotations of various critics, appeared long
                    afterwards, Argent. 1806, 8vo. The work has been translated into several modern
                    languages. There is an early English version by John Sadler, Lond. 1572, 4to.
                    And a more recent translation was published by Lieutenant John Clarke, Lond.
                    1767, 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
