<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0681-0641-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=681" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VIANA</label>, a department or corregimento of the province
                    Entre Duro e Minho in Portugal, extending along the seashore to the northward of
                    the river Minho. It comprehends seven towns, 291 villages or parishes, 30,980
                    dwellings, with about 170,000 inhabitants. The capital is a city of the same
                    name, situated at the mouth of the Minho, a river nearly choked up with sand,
                    and only admitting vessels with a light draught of water to approach the wharfs
                    at the highest tides. From this circumstance the trade of the city has, of late
                    years, been transferred to Oporto. The chief traffic is in fruits and in some
                    light wines. Viana has an extensive sea fishery, which gives occupation to 300
                    boats. The city is surrounded with walls defended by bastions, and the entrance
                    from the sea is protected by two forts, St. Jago and Cao. The public buildings
                    are two parochial churches, or religious houses, an hospital, a poor house, and
                    a military school or college. It contains about 2000 houses and 9500
                    inhabitants. There is a light-house at the entrance of the river Lerna, whose
                    latitude is in 41° 39' north.</p>
                <p>There is another place in Portugal of this name, the town of Viana in the
                    province of Alentejo, which contains 450 houses and 1850 inhabitants.</p>
                <p>In the province of Navarre in Spain, is also a Viana, a city near to Estella. It
                    stands on a hill about three miles from the river Ebro. It is surrounded with
                    walls, and is <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=682"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0682-0642"/>defended by an ancient castle, and contains
                    3,500 inhabitants, who are chiefly employed in rearing black cattle, sheep,
                    horses, and mules.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
