<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0587-0549-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=587" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VALLADOLID</label>, one of the provinces into which the
                    kingdom of Leon in Spain is divided. It extends over 271 square leagues, and has
                    a population of 187,390 souls. It is situated in a country destitute of trees,
                    except an occasional mixture of fir woods in some of the more sandy soils. From
                    being thus denuded of trees. It appears more barren than it in reality is; for
                    it produces good crops of corn, especially of wheat, when the summer is moist,
                    and on all those spots where either natural or artificial irrigation is
                    practised; but like all the plains of Castile and Leon. It suffers most severely
                    in dry seasons. The canal of Castile runs through a portion of this department,
                    and as it is designed for irrigation, as well as for navigation. It is very
                    beneficial as far as it extends; and if ever it should be completed, so as to
                    unite the river Santander with the Ebro and the Douro. It will be of
                    incalculable advantage to the whole of Valladolid.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Valladolid,</hi> a city of Spain in the province of Leon,
                    and the capital of a district of the same name. It is situated on a plain at the
                    spot where the rivers Pisuerga and Esquiva form a junction; and the waters of
                    the latter, divided into two branches, pass through a part of the city. The
                    country around it is not productive, but might be made highly fertile by a small
                    expense in irrigation. The city is large, and contains a population of about
                    30,000 souls. The streets are narrow and crooked, and exhibit signs of decay,
                    but the principal square is very magnificent, and has many remains of that
                    ancient grandeur which belonged to it when this place was a royal residence, and
                    the palace, now hastening to ruin, was occupied by the court of Philip the
                    Third. The convent of the Dominicans is a fine Gothic pile, and some other
                    ecclesiastical edifices are both large and venerable; but the university, which
                    was once flourishing, is hastening to decay, and has very few students, and
                    these are constantly diminishing in number. Valladolid is situated in Lat. 41.
                    42.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
