<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0603-0565-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095153">Research</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=603" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VEDAS</label>, the sacred books of the Hindus believed tn he
                    revealed by God, and called <hi rend="italic">immortal.</hi> They are considered
                    as the fountain of all knowledge human and divine, and are four in number; of
                    which we have the following account in the first volume of the Asiatic
                    Researches. The <hi rend="italic">Rigue-da</hi> consists of five sections; the
                        <hi rend="italic">Yajurveda</hi> of eighty-six; the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sαmaveda</hi> of a thousand; and the <hi rend="italic">Atharvaveda</hi> of
                    nine; with eleven hundred <hi rend="italic">sac'hu's,</hi> or brunches in
                    various divisions and subdivisions. The <hi rend="italic">Vedas</hi> in truth
                    are infinite; but have been long reduced to this number and order; <pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=604"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0604-0566"/> the principal part of them is that which
                    explains the duties of man in a methodical arrangement; and in the fourth is a
                    system of divine ordinances.</p>
                <p>From these are reduced the four <hi rend="italic">Upavedas,</hi> the first of
                    which was delivered to mankind by <hi rend="smallcaps">Brahma, Indra,
                        Dhanwantari,</hi> and five other deities; and it comprises the theory of
                    disorders and medicines, with the practical methods of curing diseases. The
                    second consists of music, invented for the purpose of raising the mind by
                    devotion to the felicity of the Divine nature; the third treats of the
                    fabrication and use of arms; and the fourth of <hi rend="italic">sixty-four</hi>
                    mechanical arts. Of however little value we may esteem the mechanical arts of
                    the Hindus, and however despicable their theological system may really be, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Upaυeda,</hi> which treats of diseases and the method of
                    curing them, surely deserves to be studied by every European physician
                    practising in India. There is indeed a great number of medical books in the
                    Shanscrit language worthy of attention; for though the theories of their authors
                    may be groundless and whimsical, they contain the names and descriptions of many
                    Indian plants and minerals, with their uses, discovered by <hi rend="italic"
                        >experience,</hi> in the cure of diseases.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
