<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0586-0548-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198504">Lava</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7c03z">Lava</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=586" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VALETTA, <hi rend="smallcaps">La</hi></label>, the capital of
                    the island of Malta, is situated on the east side of the island, in 14° 30' E.
                    long., <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=587"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0587-0549"/>and 36° 53' N. lat. It was founded in 1566 by
                    the celebrated grandmaster of the same name, and received munificent
                    contributions from the pope, and from the kings of Spain, France, and Portugal,
                    and it is now one of the finest towns in Europe. It consists of five parts, La
                    Valetta or Citta Nuova, Citta Vittoriosa, Senleya or the isle of St. Michael,
                    Barmola, and Cottonera. The situation of the town is beautiful, the streets are
                    regular, and well paved with lava. The public buildings and private houses are
                    of a very superior order; they are built of stone, with flat or terraced roofs.
                    Water is supplied by means of an aqueduct seventeen thousand yards long,
                    conveying fifty-eight gallons per minute. The city contains above twenty
                    churches, great and small, besides the cathedral. The principal edifices are the
                    cathedral, the palace of the grandmasters, the lodges of the different
                    languages, the conservatory, the university, the treasury, the palace of
                    justice, the hospital, the Monte di Pieta, the barracks, the theatre, and the
                    exchange. These buildings are distinguished by the elegance and chasteness of
                    their architecture. The public library contains about 100,000 volumes, and there
                    is also an extensive museum. The total population of the island in 1836,
                    including the troops, amounted to 106,614, of which about 40,000 resided in the
                    capital.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
