<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0627-0589-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:895648">Ditches</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=627" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VELLORE</label>, a celebrated town and fortress of the south
                    of India, province of the Carnatic, formerly the capital of a small district of
                    the same name. It was once a port of great importance, as it commanded the main
                    road leading to the Upper Carnatic, from the valley of Peniambady, which is the
                    most direct route to and from the Mysore. It is strongly fortified, the walls
                    being built of very large stones, with bastions and round towers at short
                    distances. A fausse bras lines the wall between them, and, with its embattled
                    rampart and small overhanging square towel’s, produces a very handsome effect.
                    The whole fort is surrounded by a deep and wide ditch, cut chiefly out of the
                    solid rock, except atone entrance, where there was a causeway. Besides the usual
                    defence, the ditch contains curiosities of rather an extraordinary character,
                    namely, alligators of a very large size. The fortress, though strong, is
                    commanded by the surrounding hills. It was first taken by the Mahometans in
                    1646, and afterwards by Sevajee in 1677. Subsequently it came into the
                    possession of the nabob of Arcot.∙ and in 1782 was besieged by the whole <pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=628"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0628-0590"/> army of Hyder, when it was relieved by Sir
                    Eyre Coote. After the capture of Seringapatam in 1799. It was fixed upon as the
                    state-prison of Tippoo’s family, consisting, besides his brother, of twelve sons
                    and eight daughters, with a numerous progeny, and an innumerable crowd of women.
                    On the 10th July 1806, a serious mutiny took place among the garrison,
                    principally composed of native troops, who endeavoured to murder all the
                    Europeans they could find. The ostensible cause of the mutiny was a change of
                    dress; but it was strongly suspected that it was instigated by the sons of
                    Tippoo, who were in consequence removed to Bengal, where they remain under a
                    liberal restraint. Since the conquest of Mysore, this fortress has lost much of
                    its consequence, and its fortifications will probably be allowed to fall to
                    decay. The district is included in the collectorship of Arcot. Travelling
                    distance from Madras 88 miles west by south; from Seringapatam 202 miles. Long.
                    79∙ 13. E. Lat. 12. 55. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
