<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0641-0603-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:844698">Camels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844686">Cameleers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837146">Bouquets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955558">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pq59">Camel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=641" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VERMONT</label>, one of the United States of America. It lies
                    between the river Connecticut and the long tapering basin of Lake Champlain;
                    stretching from 42° <hi rend="italic">44' to</hi> 45° north lat., a distance of
                    nearly 160 miles, and from 71° 30' to 73° 20' west long., with a breadth
                    expanding pretty regularly from forty-five miles in the south to ninety in the
                    north. It has an area of 10,200 square miles.</p>
                <p>The most striking natural feature of this tract is the mountainous range called
                    the Green Mountains, which traverse the state from north to south, and, passing
                    into Massachusetts, there take the name of the Hoosic Mountains. In the centre
                    of the state this ridge is divided into two, of which the one called the Height
                    of Land runs north-east to Canada, and the other, taking a north-westerly
                    direction, sinks down in the northern part of the state. The Green Mountains,
                    from whose verdure this state derives its name, are from ten to fifteen miles
                    wide, and are much intersected by valleys; they are watered by numerous springs
                    and brooks, and are covered with evergreen trees and shrubs nearly to their
                    summits. There are many good farms among the mountains, and much of the land
                    upon them is suitable for grazing. The highest points are Mansfield Mountain,
                    rising to 4280 feet; Camel’s Rump, 4190 feet, both in the north-western ridge;
                    and Killington Peak, further south, 3675 feet in height. Ascutney, a detached
                    elevation near Windsor, rises to the height of 3320 feet above the level of the
                    sea.</p>
                <p>The Connecticut forms the eastern boundary of the state. Oniou river passes
                    through Montpellier, the capital, into Lake Champlain at Burlington. Otter creek
                    is a principal branch of Oniou river. Lamoile and Missique are considerable
                    streams north of the Oniou. In the Green Mountains rise many smaller rivers,
                    which at once beautify the country by the picturesque scenery of their banks,
                    and promote its manufactures by the mills which they turn in their course. Those
                    which run towards the east are tributaries to the Connecticut, and those whose
                    course is towards the west discharge their waters into Lake Champlain.</p>
                <p>Lake Champlain, between the west shore of this state and New York, is a beautiful
                    sheet of water, 128 miles long, and from one to twenty wide. It discharges at
                    its northern extremity by the river Sorel into the St. Lawrence, and contains
                    upwards of sixty islands, of which Motte, and North and South Hero, are of
                    considerable size. Besides the rivers which flow into it from the Green
                    Mountains, it receives the Chazy, Saranac, Sable, Bouquet, and Wood rivers, from
                    New York, on the western shore. The Champlain canal connects it with Hudson
                    river and the New York and Erie canal. Lying extremely convenient to facilitate
                    the commerce of the state both with New York and Montreal. It is navigated by a
                    number of steam-boats and lake vessels. Memphremagog is a considerable lake,
                    twenty-five miles long and three broad, lying partly in Vermont and partly in
                    Canada, receiving a number of streams from this state, and communicating by the
                    St. Francis with the St. Lawrence.</p>
                <p>The prevailing rocks belong to the stratified primary group, embracing mica and
                    talcose slates, gneiss, primary limestone, argillite, &amp;c. On the western
                    border there is a narrow strip of transition limestone. These rocks afford good
                    building materials, and marble is quarried and carried out of the state. The
                    magnetic oxide of iron abounds at Somerset, and the brown hematite, associated
                        <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=642"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0642-0604"/>with oxide of manganese, occurs at Bennington,
                    Pittsford, and Manleton. Pyrites, or sulphuret of iron, is found in Strafford
                    and Shrewsbury; and about three million pounds of copperas, of the value of
                    70,000 to 75,000 dollars, are made here annually.</p>
                <p>Vermont was originally covered with a dense forest, a large part of which still
                    remains, although considerable encroachments have been made on it in clearing
                    land for cultivation, and in felling trees for timber. The mountains produce
                    hemlock, spruce, and fir; the lower grounds, various species of oak, pine,
                    maple, elm, hickory, beech, birch, ash, buttonwood or sycamore, and lime or
                    basswood, and the cedar grows in wet places. Ginseng, sarsaparilla, sassafras,
                    snakeroot, lobelias, &amp;c., are also among the products of the forest.
                    Maple-sugar is made in large quantities for domestic use and exportation, and
                    pot and pearl ashes, and lumber, are also exported.</p>
                <p>Vermont is divided into fourteen counties, which are subdivided into townships.
                    There are no large towns in the state, but Vergennes has the name of a city.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population in</hi> 1830.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Counties. </cell>
                        <cell> Population. </cell>
                        <cell> County Towns. </cell>
                        <cell> Population. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Addison, </cell>
                        <cell> 24,940 </cell>
                        <cell> Middleburgh,.. </cell>
                        <cell> 3468 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 17,468 </cell>
                        <cell><p>Bennington,</p><p>Manchester,</p></cell>
                        <cell> 3419 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 1525 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Caledonia, </cell>
                        <cell> 20,967 </cell>
                        <cell> Danville, </cell>
                        <cell> 2631 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Chittenden, </cell>
                        <cell> 21,765 </cell>
                        <cell> Burlington,.... </cell>
                        <cell> 3526 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Essex </cell>
                        <cell> 3981 </cell>
                        <cell> Guildhall, </cell>
                        <cell> 481 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Franklin, </cell>
                        <cell> 24,525 </cell>
                        <cell> St. Albans, </cell>
                        <cell> 2375 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Grand Isle, </cell>
                        <cell> 3696 </cell>
                        <cell> North Hero,... </cell>
                        <cell> 638 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> La Moelle, established in 1837,} </cell>
                        <cell> ... </cell>
                        <cell> Hydepark,...... </cell>
                        <cell> 823 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Orange, </cell>
                        <cell> 27,285 </cell>
                        <cell> Chelsea </cell>
                        <cell> 1958 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Orleans, </cell>
                        <cell> 13,890 </cell>
                        <cell> Irasburgh, </cell>
                        <cell> 860 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Rutland </cell>
                        <cell> 31,294 </cell>
                        <cell> Rutland, </cell>
                        <cell> 2753 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Washington, </cell>
                        <cell> 21,378 </cell>
                        <cell> Montpelier </cell>
                        <cell> 1792 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Windham </cell>
                        <cell> 28,746 </cell>
                        <cell> Newfane, </cell>
                        <cell> 1441 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Windsor, </cell>
                        <cell> 40,625 </cell>
                        <cell><p>Windsor,....</p><p>Woodstock,.</p></cell>
                        <cell> 3134 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 3044 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Vermont is not a slave-holding state. The number of newspapers published in this
                    state in 1839 was thirty-one.</p>
                <p>The senate established in 1836 consists of thirty members, each county being
                    entitled to at least one, and the rest apportioned according to population; and
                    the House of Representatives is composed of one member from each town.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
