<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0743-0703-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=743" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">VOSGES</label>, a department in the north-east of France,
                    formed out of the southern part of the ancient province of Lorraine, and
                    extending in north latitude from 48° 31' to 49° 7', and in east longitude, from
                    5° 30' to 6° 12'. It is bounded on the north by the departments of the Meuse and
                    the Meurthe, on the east by those of the Upper and of the Lower Rhine, on the
                    south by that of the Upper Saone, and on the west by the Upper Marne. It
                    contains 2288 square miles, and returns three members to the Chamber of
                    Representatives. Vosges is divided into five arrondissements, thirty cantons,
                    and 547 communes, and in 1836 had a population of 411,034 souls. They all adhere
                    to the Catholic church, are of German origin, and though active and careful, are
                    for the most part excessively poor. The surface of the department is for the
                    most part mountainous and woody. The Vosges mountains, which are a prolongation
                    of the Jura, stretch in a direction from east to west from Beford to Langres,
                    and in the north join the Hundsruck. In these are vallies of greater or less
                    extent, and capable of cultivation. The highest point of the mountains is the
                    Bolch, whose summit rises to the height of 4320 feet. Considerably more than
                    one-third of the land is covered with woods. The soil in the eastern part is a
                    mixture of sand and stones, and is very unproductive. In the western parts it is
                    calcareous, and covered with a heavy clay, and though difficult to work, is the
                    most productive division; but the whole does not grow sufficient corn for the
                    consumption. As the mountains are covered with snow during the greater part of
                    the year, the climate is raw and cold, but is not deemed unhealthy. The
                    mountains are the sources of several streams. The chief of them is the Moselle,
                    which takes a northerly direction, and soon enters Meurthe, and finally falls
                    into the Rhine. The other rivers are the Meuse, the Meurthe, the Saone, the
                    Breusch, and the Ma-bon; and there is a great number of smaller streams.</p>
                <p>The productions of the land are cattle, chiefly cows and swine, fruit, wax,
                    honey, corn, wine, flax, and hemp; but the most important are from the forests,
                    which supply by means of numerous saw-mills a vast quantity of wood, both for
                    building and for fuel. There are quarries of marble, and mines yielding silver,
                    lead, and copper in small portions; but the iron mines are the most important.
                    Some small articles of manufacture are produced; but the poverty of the
                    inhabitants is such, that they have little power of consuming luxuries of
                    foreign growth, and have no other trade than that of selling the few low-priced
                    commodities which their soil produces.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
