<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0706-0673-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENRY the Lion (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    673)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999328">Lions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1734554">Lion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893284">Diet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120771">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002186">Lombards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669847">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n706/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENRY <hi rend="smallcaps">the Lion</hi></label> (1129-1195),
                    duke of Saxony and Bavaria, son of Henry the Proud, was born in 1129. After the
                    death in 1139 of his father, who had been deprived of his possessions by Conrad
                    III., the bravery and energy of his mother Gertrude and his grandmother Richenza
                    secured to him the duchy of Saxony. Shortly after coming of age he at the diet
                    of Frankfort in 1147 demanded also the restoration of Bavaria, but was refused,
                    upon which, along with his uncle Welf VL, he made an unsuccessful attempt to
                    seize it by force of arms. In 1154 he, however, received from Frederick I. the
                    formal recognition of his claims to its possession, and in 1156 Henry
                    Jasomirgott was compelled to deliver it up to him. Besides distinguishing
                    himself in the wars of Frederick in Italy, Henry now devoted his energies to
                    establishing his power in his own dominions, both by conquest and by encouraging
                    agriculture and trade. He extended the boundaries of Saxony beyond the Elbe by
                    successful battles against the Slavs, founded Munich in Bavaria, colonized
                    Mecklenburg and Holstein, and fostered the growth of Hamburg and Lübeck. His
                    ambitious projects and his arrogant bearing awakened, however, the hostility of
                    several of the secular and ecclesiastical potentates, who in 1166 concluded a
                    league against him at Merseburg, and a stubborn contest of two years’ duration
                    ensued, which was finally ended by Frederick in 1169 deciding at the council of
                    Bamberg in Henry’s favour. In February 1168 Henry, having previously divorced
                    dementia of Zähringen, married Matilda, daughter of Henry II. of England; and,
                    elated by such an influential alliance and by the increasing resources of his
                    dominions, he shortly after his return from a pilgrimage to the Holy Land in
                    1172 began to manifest a tendency to treat the emperor with coldness and to
                    revive the traditional rivalry of his race with the Hohenstaufens. He took no
                    part in the Italian expedition of 1174, and in 1176 his sudden desertion of
                    Frederick in the crisis of his struggle with the Lombard cities resulted in the
                    disaster at Legnano. On Frederick’s return from Italy in 1177 Henry was summoned
                    to appear before him at the diet of Worms, and declining to do so he was placed
                    under the ban of the empire, and his lands were divided among other princes. For
                    more than a year he endeavoured to resist the execution of the imperial decree,
                    but he found it necessary at last, in November 1181, to give in his submission
                    to Frederick, who, on condition that he remained three years in England, agreed
                    to reinstate him in the possession of Brunswick and Lüneburg. Having in 1189
                    refused to accompany Frederick on his crusade, he was again compelled to
                    withdraw to England, but shortly after Frederick’s departure he returned, and,
                    concluding an alliance with the archbishop of Bremen, made a second attempt to
                    recover his territories; but, though at first he gained several important
                    victories, he was ultimately compelled in July 1190 to conclude a peace at
                    Fulda, which secured to him scarcely any advantages from the contest. Emboldened
                    by the hostile alliance formed against the emperor Henry VI. in 1192, he again
                    renewed the struggle; but after Richard of England fell into the hands of the
                    emperor in the following year, he found it necessary again to give in his
                    submission; and shortly afterwards a pledge of amity between the two houses was
                    given through the marriage of the eldest son of Henry the Lion to Agnes, niece
                    of Frederick I., and cousin of the reigning emperor. Henry died 6th August 1195
                    at Brunswick, and was buried in the church of St Blaise. Otto, his seoond son,
                    became emperor under the title of Otto IV. A colossal statue of Henry was
                    unveiled at Brunswick 4th July 1874. Though ambitious, headstrong, and
                    pugnacious, Henry showed that while he possessed no small skill in the art of
                    war he could appreciate the arts of peace, and he gave <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n707/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0707-0674"/> a powerful impetus to the development of many
                    important cities, and furthered with judicious sagacity the material prosperity
                    of his kingdom.</p>
                <p>See Bottiger, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich</hi><hi rend="italic">der Löwe,</hi>
                    Hanover, 1819; Prutz, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich</hi><hi rend="italic">der
                    Löwe,</hi> Leipsic, 1865: Weiland, <hi rend="italic">Das Sachs.
                    Hcrzogthum</hi><hi rend="italic">unter</hi><hi rend="italic">Lothar</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">Heinrich</hi><hi rend="italic">dem
                    Löwen,</hi> Greifswald, 1866; Philippson, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Heinrichs</hi><hi rend="italic">des Löwen,</hi> Leipsic, 2 vols.,
                    1867-8; and the various biographies of Frederick I.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
