<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0879-0840-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HINDÜSTANÎ (9th edition, volume 11, page 840)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067392">Pluralism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:892462">Dialectic</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106878">Scholars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qq9f">Pluralism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25g11">Dialects</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w849">Dialectics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77z92">Brahmanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HINDÜSTANÎ</label>,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Hindustani <hi rend="italic">(lit.</hi> “Of or belonging to
                    Hindustan”) is the English name for the language. The natives generally call it
                    <hi rend="italic">Urdu</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Urdu Zαbαn,</hi> “the camp
                    language” (the word <hi rend="italic">Urdu</hi> meaning, in Turkish, “a camp”),
                    and the poets, <hi rend="italic">Rekhta,</hi> “mixed;” while the phase of the
                    dialect which is peculiar to southern India is termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dakhini,</hi> or “southern.” The term <hi rend="italic">Hindi,</hi> on the
                    other hand, is derived from the Persian <hi rend="italic">Hind,</hi> “India,”
                    and, strictly speaking, is applicable only to the modern language of the Hindus.
                    The old language, prior to the inroads of the Musalmäns, is termed <hi
                    rend="italic">Hindui,</hi> and is derived from Hindti. It may be added that the
                    present article has reference only to the so-called High HindûstânT, which
                    differs considerably from the vulgar speech. This, in some parts of the area
                    mentioned in the text, bears but little resemblance to the cultivated language,
                    except in the possession of a few Persian or Arabic words. The High Hindustani
                    is that which is uniformly employed in literature over the whole of the
                    specified area. It is, moreover, the language in which the proceedings of the
                    various Government courts and offices are carried on, and is spoken in its
                    purity in all the large towns by the educated classes generally, by Hindus as
                    well as Musalmäns.</p></note> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Urdü,</hi> is a dialect of
                    the Hindi, one of the seven languages of Aryan stock spoken at the present day
                    in North India, the others being the Panjabi, Sindhi, Gujarati, Marathi,
                    Bangali, and Oriyä. The area over which it is spoken in North India may be said
                    to be co-extensive with that of the Hindi, which is estimated at about 250,000
                    square miles, extending from the river Gandak in the east to the Sutlej in the
                    west, and from the Himalaya in the north to the Vindhiyâ mountains in the south.
                    It is also extensively used, though in a somewhat different phase, in a great
                    part of the Deccan, and is moreover the <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> of
                    most parts of India.</p>
                <p>• As the Hindi language consists of many dialects, it is necessary to state that
                    it is the Braj Bhäshä, or the dialect that is spoken in the districts of Agra
                    and Mathura, and in the neighbourhood of Dehli, the ancient capital of the
                    Mahometan empire, which is generally regarded as the parent of Hindustani. The
                    grammatical structure and also a vast number of the commonest vocables of the
                    Braj were incorporated in the new dialect, and to these were added a vast number
                    of Persian, Arabic, and even Turkish words. “Such words, however, in no wise
                    altered or influenced the language itself, which, as regards its inflexional or
                    phonetic elements, remains still a pure Aryan dialect, just as pure in the pages
                    of Wall or Saudä, as it is in those of Tulsi Dâs or Bihârï Läl.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Beames, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Comparative Grammar of the Modern Aryan Languages,</hi> vol. i. p.
                    32.</p></note> Peculiarities of composition, such as reversing the positions of
                    the governing and the governed word <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">häp</hi><hi rend="italic">mera</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                    >merä</hi><hi rend="italic">bap),</hi> or of the adjective and the substantive
                    it qualifies, or such as the use of Persian phrases with the preposition <hi
                    rend="italic">ba</hi> instead of the Hindi postposition of the ablative case <hi
                    rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi><hi rend="italic">ba-khushï</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">khushï</hi><hi rend="italic">se,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >ba-hzιkm</hi><hi rend="italic">sarkär-ke,</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic"
                    >sarkar ke hukm se),</hi> are no doubt to be met with in many writings, and
                    these, perhaps, combined with the too free indulgence on the part of some
                    authors in the use of high-flown and pedantic Persian and Arabic words in place
                    of common and yet chaste Hindi words, and the general use of the Persian instead
                    of the Nâgarï character, have induced some to regard Hindustani or Urdu as a
                    language distinct from Hindi. But such a view betrays a radical misunderstanding
                    of the whole question.</p>
                <p>As regards the introduction of foreign words into the various dialects of Hindi,
                    it seems highly probable that it had its origin at an early period, perhaps as
                    early as the 8th or 9th century of our era. But there is good ground for the
                    opinion that, although the Hindi area was overrun as early as the 12th century,
                    the Hindustani was not formed till the 16th century. “For many generations after
                    the victories of Kutbu’d-din Aibak, the first Musalmän sovereign of Dehli,the
                    conquerors retained their own Persian, and the conquered their Hindi. The
                    Musalmäns had long been accustomed to speak pure Hindi,and it was not they who
                    introduced Persian words into the language, but the Hindüs themselves, who at
                    the epoch above mentioned were compelled by Todar MaΓs new revenue system to
                    learn Persian.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Beames,
                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> vol. i. p. 30, note.</p></note> And we learn from
                    Mir Amman of Dehli (whose brief account of the origin of Urdu in the preface to
                    his well-known <hi rend="italic">Bagh-o-Bahär</hi> bears on the face of it every
                    convincing mark of probability, and, scanty as it is, is remarkable a«, perhaps,
                    the only attempt at a critical disquisition in the whole range of Hindustani
                    literature) that at the date of the composition of his work (1802) the Musalmän
                    dynasties had endured for a thousand years, and that as intercourse increased
                    the languages of the Hindus and Musalmäns became to a certain extent mixed. By
                    the arrival and stay of the Amir Tïmür the camp or bäzär of the army was
                    introduced into the city, whence the city bäzär was called Urdu, a Tartar word
                    signi Tying “camp.” “When</p>
                <p>Akbar ascended the throne, various races from all quarters, on hearing the kind
                    patronage and bounty of that incomparable house, came and assembled in the royal
                    presence, but the speech and dialect of each was different. From their being
                    collected together, and owing to the trade, traffic, and intercourse which they
                    carried on with one another, a single language, that of the Urdu (or
                    Hindustani), was established.”</p>
                <p>The epoch of Akbar, which first saw a regular revenue system established, with
                    toleration and the free use of their religion granted to the Hindus, was, there
                    can be little doubt, the period of the formation of the language. But its final
                    consolidation did not take place till the reign of Shah Jahän. After the date of
                    this monarch the changes are comparatively immaterial until we come to the time
                    when European sources began to mingle with those of the East. Of the
                    contributions from these sources there is little to say. Like the greater part
                    of those from the Arabic and Persian, they are chiefly nouns, and may be
                    regarded rather as excrescences which have sprung up casually and have attached
                    themselves to the original trunk than ingredients duly incorporated in the body.
                    In the case of the Persian and Arabic element, indeed, we do find not a few
                    instances in which nouns have been furnished with a Hindi termination, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g., kharldna, bαdαlηa,</hi><hi rend="italic">guzarnä,
                    däghnä,</hi><hi rend="italic">bαkhshna,</hi><hi rend="italic">kamïnapan,</hi>
                    &amp;c. But the European element cannot be said to have at all woven itself into
                    the grammar of the language. It consists, as has been observed, solely of nouns,
                    principally substantive nouns, which on their admission into thelanguage are
                    spelt phonetically, or according to the corrupt pronunciation they receive in
                    the mouths of the natives, and are declined like the indigenous nouns by means
                    of the usual postpositions or case-affixes.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>It is supposed, however, that the strange dialect in which
                    the Lascärs, or “native seamen,” and the Dändls, or “boatmen,” hohl converse,
                    and in which orders are given to a native crew regarding the working of a ship,
                    is compounded of Portuguese words assimilated to Hindustani in their
                    terminations and inflexions. Of this there is no positive proof, and until the
                    matter has been properly and satisfactorily investigated it would be injudicious
                    to pronounce a decided opinion.</p></note> A few examples will suffice. The
                    Portuguese, the first in order of seniority, contributes a few words, as <hi
                    rend="italic">kamαra</hi> or <hi rend="italic">kαmra</hi> (camera), “a room ;”
                    <hi rend="italic">martοl,</hi> “a hammer:” <hi rend="italic">nilam,</hi>
                    “auction” (often corrupted <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n880/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0880-0841"/> into <hi rend="italic">lilam); peril,</hi> “a
                    turkey,” &amp;c. &lt;kc. Of French and Dutch influence scarcely a trace exists.
                    English has contributed a number of words, some of which have even found a place
                    in the literature of the language; <hi rend="italic">e.g., Kammishanar</hi>
                    (commissioner); <hi rend="italic">jaj</hi> (judge) <hi rend="italic">;
                    istant</hi> (assistant); <hi rend="italic">dakfαr</hi> (doctor) <hi
                    rend="italic">; dαkfari,</hi> “the science of medicine,” or “the profession of
                    physicians ;” <hi rend="italic">inspektar</hi> (inspector); <hi rend="italic"
                    >sosayafl</hi> (society); <hi rend="italic">aρll</hi> (appeal); <hi
                    rend="italic">aphl kamιa,</hi> “to appeal;” <hi rend="italic">dikrι</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">digri</hi> (decree); <hi rend="italic">digri</hi> (degree); <hi
                    rend="italic">inch</hi> (inch); <hi rend="italic">fut</hi> (foot); and many
                    more, are words now commonly used. How far the free use of Anglicisms will be
                    adopted as the language progresses is a question upon which it would be
                    hazardous to pronounce an opinion.</p>
                <p>The grammatical structure of the Hindustani differs in no essential particular
                    from that of the Hindi from which it is sprung. . It is therefore of the rise
                    and formation of this language, and of the stage to which it had attained when
                    the new phase of the Hindustani was developed from it, that we shall now
                    speak.</p>
                <p>Of the history and development of the Hindi or Hindùi language previous to the
                    11th century of our era little or nothing is known. It is accepted as a fact by
                    most scholars that Sanskrit ceased to be a vernacιdar in the 6th century B.c.,
                    when the Buddhist religion was founded, which for ten centuries drove Brahmanism
                    into obscurity. From that time the Aryan people of India spoke popular dialects
                    called Prakrits,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Prakrit
                    is derived from the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">prakriti,</hi> “nature,” and
                    signifies “natural,” “not accomplished,” “vulgar.” It is the collective name of
                    those dialects which are immediately derived from, or which stand in an
                    immediate relation to, Sanskrit, or “the polished or accomplished language” of
                    the Hindus.</p></note> and it is from these that the modern Aryan tongues are
                    mainly derived. These Prakrit dialects are generally grouped under five heads,
                    viz., the Maharâshtrï, Sauraseni, Mägadhi, Paisachi, and Apabhransa. Of these
                    the Sauraseni, or dialect of Saurasena, the modern tract of Mathura and the
                    surrounding country, is taken to be the parent of the Hindi, or at any rate of
                    that phase of it with which we have to do. These Prakrits were, like the
                    Sanskrit, synthetical and inflexional in their structure, and certainly
                    continued to be so up to the 1st century of our era, the lowest stage to which
                    in point of development scholars have been able to reach. At what precise period
                    the synthetical structure of the Prakrit began to break up and to give place to
                    the analytical formations of the modern speech it is impossible to tell. The gap
                    of nine centuries has yet to be filled up. And unless future discoveries of
                    Buddhistic literature should shed light on the subject, it is to be feared that
                    the history of this period will ever remain unknown.</p>
                <p>The dawn of modern Hindi may be dated from the 11th century. The earliest known
                    writer in the language was Chand Bardai (c.1200), whose epic is in a dialect
                    rude and half-formed, but as decidedly analytical as the Hindi of the present
                    day.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is this striking
                    change from the synthetical structure of the Prakrit to the analytical of the
                    Hindi, coupled with an accidental resemblance in certain of the case-affixes to
                    those of the Dravidian tongues, that has led some Oriental scholars to claim for
                    Hindi a nonAryan descent. But this view is ably combated by Mr Beames in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Comparative Grammar of the Aryan Languages of India,</hi> and by
                    Professor Rudolf Hoernle, in his <hi rend="italic">Bssays on the Gaurian
                    Languages.</hi></p></note> Much of the old synthetical structure no doubt is
                    still to be found in the work; the particles and the auxiliary verbs are in a
                    very crude and unformed state (as, for example, the use of an obscure <hi
                    rend="italic">ka</hi> for the modern genitive affix <hi rend="italic">ka,</hi>
                    which <hi rend="italic">ka</hi> does not vary with the governed noun, and is
                    frequently left out altogether; the total absence of the ordinary substantive
                    verb <hi rend="italic">hai,</hi> &amp;c.); but these crudities and remnants of
                    old Prakrit forms do not affect the general structure. Indeed, they are to be
                    found in writings of a much later period, in works belonging to the 14th and
                    15th centuries, <hi rend="italic">e.q.,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Adi</hi><hi rend="italic">Grαnth,</hi> the language of which exhibits,
                    according to Trumpp, “grammatical forms not firmly fixed, but rather in a state
                    of transition.” And although the forms assume greater fixity, and marked
                    progress is observable in the works of later writers in the Braj Bhâkhâ dialect,
                    <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in those of Kabir, Sür Das, Nabhä Ji, Kesava Das,
                    and Bihäri Läl (whose poems are, as a rule, composed in very pure and elegant
                    Hindi), we still find certain crudities and traces of Prakrit forms and organic
                    structure, and these continue even in the language of the present day.</p>
                <p>To give a minute account of the grammatical formation, to indicate the various
                    phonetic or glottic laws by the operation of which the vocables and grammatical
                    forms of the Hindi are derived from those of the Prakrit or Sanskrit, is beyond
                    the scope of the present article. We can but notice a few general laws, and
                    exhibit results, so far as they have been ascertained. For closer acquaintance
                    with the subject we must refer the reader to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Präkrit-</hi><hi rend="italic">Prakαsa</hi> of Vararûchi, edited by Professor
                    E. B. Cowell; the <hi rend="italic">Prakrit Grammar</hi> of Hemachandra, edited
                    by Professor Pischel; the <hi rend="italic">Comparative Grammar of the Modern
                    Aryan Languages of India,</hi> by John Beames, B.C.S.; and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essays on the Gaurian Languages,</hi> by Professor Rudolf Hoernle.</p>
                <p>Prakrit tolerates no compound consonant in the beginning and no dissimilar
                    consonant in the middle of a word. Two dissimilar consonants in a Sanskrit word
                    are changed in Prakrit to two similar consonants, and occasionally one of these
                    is elided and the preceding vowel lengthened. In the modern dialects this
                    elision of one consonant and compensatory lengthening of the preceding vowel is
                    the rule. Prakrit either changes a medial surd mute consonant to the
                    corresponding sonant one, or elides it altogether; and it generally changes an
                    aspirate mute consonant to the simple aspirate <hi rend="italic">h.</hi> In fact
                    the modern Aryan tongues stand to the Prakrit and the Sanskrit in a relation
                    very similar to that existing between the Italian, &lt;fcc., and the Romance and
                    Latin languages. Hindi “is not the daughter of Sanskrit, as we find it in the
                    Vedas, or in the later literature of the Brahmans, it is a branch of the living
                    speech of India, springing from the same stem from which Sanskrit sprang when it
                    first assumed its literary independence.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Max Müller, <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Science of
                    Language,</hi> lect. ii.</p></note><hi rend="italic">Vocables.—</hi> The
                    vocables may be classed under three heads :— 1. Words which are pure Sanskrit,
                    as <hi rend="italic">râjâ,</hi> “a king”; <hi rend="italic">pita,</hi> “father”;
                    <hi rend="italic">kaνi, “</hi> a poet”; <hi rend="italic">nagari,</hi> “of or
                    belonging to a city”; <hi rend="italic">karma,</hi><hi rend="italic">kärya,</hi>
                    “work”; <hi rend="italic">krodha</hi> (vulg. <hi rend="italic">krodh),</hi>
                    “anger.” Nota few of this class of words have existed in the language for some
                    centuries; some are to be found even in the oldest specimens of the literature;
                    but by far the larger number have passed into the language during the present
                    century, and the introduction is still progressing. The form in which they
                    appear is that of the Sanskrit nominative singular.</p>
                <p>2. Words which are derived from the Prakrit, and have been considerably changed
                    in the process, though not so much as to obscure their origin, <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g.,</hi><hi rend="italic">käm,</hi> “work,” Prk. <hi rend="italic"
                    >kamma,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">karma;</hi><hi rend="italic">kän,</hi> “ear,”
                    Prk. <hi rend="italic">kanιιa,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">karna; ath,</hi>
                    “eight,” Prk. <hi rend="italic">attlιa,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">ashtha;
                    hath,</hi> “hand,” Prk. <hi rend="italic">haitha,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >hasta</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">äp,</hi> “self,” Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">appâ,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">âtmâ; bât,</hi> “word,” Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">vattä,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">värttä</hi><hi rend="italic">;
                    âj,</hi> “today,” Prk. <hi rend="italic">ajja,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >adya;</hi><hi rend="italic">âge,</hi> “before,” Prk. <hi rend="italic"
                    >agge,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">agre;</hi><hi rend="italic">äg,</hi> “fire,”
                    Prk. <hi rend="italic">aggi,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">agni; dudh,</hi> “milk,”
                    Prk. <hi rend="italic">duddha,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">dugdha;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">phägun,</hi> “Feb.-March,” Prk. <hi rend="italic">phaggun,</hi> S.
                    <hi rend="italic">ρhalgun;</hi><hi rend="italic">budclhä,</hi> “old,” Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">vudclho,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">vriddhah; kalιa,</hi> “said,”
                    (Braj <hi rend="italic">kahyau),</hi> Prk. <hi rend="italic">kahido, kahio,</hi>
                    S. <hi rend="italic">kathitah;</hi><hi rend="italic">rahä,</hi> “remained,”
                    (Braj <hi rend="italic">rahyauh,</hi> Prk. <hi rend="italic">rahido, rahio,</hi>
                    S. <hi rend="italic">rahitah;</hi><hi rend="italic">thä,</hi><hi rend="italic">‘
                    ‘</hi> was,” Prk. <hi rend="italic">thio,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >sthitah.</hi> This is by far the largest class of words in the Hindi. And, as
                    in the case of the first class, they are adopted in the form of the nominative
                    singular of the Prakrit. They are divisible into two classes, the first
                    comprising such as have in their declension preserved traces of the old organic
                    inflexion of the Prakrit declension, and the second those which have preserved
                    no such traces. As regards these it may be observed that the terminations <hi
                    rend="italic">a, e, i, o, u,</hi> of the Prakrit are regularly reduced in the
                    Hindi to their inherent simple vowels, viz., <hi rend="italic">â</hi> to <hi
                    rend="italic">a, e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
                    >i,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">o</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u</hi> to <hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi>; and these short vowels are, as a rule, made quiescent, so
                    that a word ending in reality in a short vowel virtually terminates in a
                    consonant; and, not being pronounced, the final short vowel is frequently
                    suppressed in writing also.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n881/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0881-0842"/>
                <p>3. Words which cannot apparently he traced to any Sanskrit original, and are
                    therefore considered by some scholars as words of non-Aryan origin; <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi><hi rend="italic">pagri,</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ii</hi> turban”; <hi rend="italic">gor,</hi> Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">goram, “</hi> leg.” Such words form but a small proportion; and it
                    is probable that further research and a better acquaintance with the laws of
                    development of the modern Aryan tongues will ultimately enable scholars to very
                    much diminish their number.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Gender.—</hi> The three genders of the Prakrit and Sanskrit
                    are, in Hindi and Hindüstäni, reduced to two, the neuters and masculines of the
                    old tongues generally becoming masculines in the modern language. Instances,
                    however, are not a few in which they are changed to feminines. A striking
                    feature in the modern tongues is the preponderance of masculines ending in <hi
                    rend="italic">d,</hi> with the corresponding feminines in i. Now in the Sanskrit
                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is a typical feminine ending, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >i</hi> is as often a masculine as a feminine termination. Many feminine words
                    ending in ά are no doubt to be found in the Hindi, <hi rend="italic"
                    >aschhimä,</hi> “patience,” = S. <hi rend="italic">kshamâ</hi>; and similarly
                    many masculine words which in the Prakrit and Sanskrit terminate in <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> are also to be met with, as <hi rend="italic">pdni,
                    “water,”≈S.</hi><hi rend="italic">päniyam</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">hâlhï,</hi> “elephant,” = S. <hi rend="italic">hasti
                    (hastin').</hi> But <hi rend="italic">â</hi> is typically a masculine and <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> a feminine termination in the Hindi and Hindüstäni, and
                    this is probably due to the number of sources from which the termination
                    springs; thus we have—(1) α=Prk. <hi rend="italic">o,</hi> =S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >as or ah, e.g., kaisd,</hi> “like what,” “what manner,” “how,” Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">kériso,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">kidri&amp;ah;</hi> (2) d=Prk.
                    αδ, =S. <hi rend="italic">akas</hi> or <hi rend="italic">akah, e.g., ghord,</hi>
                    “horse,” Prk. <hi rend="italic">ghoraö,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic">ghotakah</hi>;
                    (3) α = Prk. <hi rend="italic">a(k)am, aam,≈S. am, e.g., keld, “</hi> plantain,”
                    Prk. <hi rend="italic">kera(k)am, keradm,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >kadaram.</hi> Again, the masculine ending <hi rend="italic">aka</hi> of the old
                    languages has a corresponding feminine in <hi rend="italic">ikd</hi>; and as the
                    Prakrit commonly employs the pleonastic increment <hi rend="italic">k</hi> to
                    raise bases to the form <hi rend="italic">aka,</hi> so it employs the same affix
                    to form the feminine <hi rend="italic">ikd</hi> of these masculines; <hi
                    rend="italic">ikd</hi> becomes <hi rend="italic">iyd,</hi> and more commonly <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> in the modern tongues. The form <hi rend="italic">iyd</hi>
                    is that which is generally used in feminine diminutives; <hi rend="italic">e.g.,
                    dibiyd,</hi> “a tiny box”; but it is also used like <hi rend="italic">i</hi> for
                    a simple feminine; <hi rend="italic">e.g., kuttd,</hi> “dog,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >kutiyd,</hi> “bitch”; <hi rend="italic">bûrhâ,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> old
                    man,” <hi rend="italic">burhiyd,</hi> “old woman.” If to the above class of
                    feminines ending in <hi rend="italic">i</hi> be added the large class which in
                    Prakrit and Sanskrit form the feminine in <hi rend="italic">i (i.e.,</hi> the
                    Prakrit masculines in <hi rend="italic">o,</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">as),</hi>
                    the preponderance of nouns ending in <hi rend="italic">i</hi> seems sufficiently
                    accounted for. It may be added thatα and <hi rend="italic">i</hi> are so
                    universally regarded as masculine and feminine terminations respectively that
                    the natives employ them freely in forming feminines from masculinesand <hi
                    rend="italic">vice versa, e.g., badld, badli,</hi> from the Arabic <hi
                    rend="italic">badak</hi> There are a few other feminine terminations which are
                    worthy of notice, not so much on account of their origin (which presents no
                    difficulty), as on account of the free use which is made of them; these are—(1)
                    <hi rend="italic">ini, in, an,</hi><hi rend="italic">ni,</hi> ==S. <hi
                    rend="italic">ini</hi> (fem. of <hi rend="italic">in, ι);</hi> (2) <hi
                    rend="italic">äni, äni,</hi><hi rend="italic">dln, = S. dnL</hi> These are not
                    only found in words derived from the Prakrit, but are added to Persian and even
                    Arabic words; <hi rend="italic">e.g., hdthini, hdthin, hathni,</hi> “female
                    elephant,” ( = S. <hi rend="italic">hastini); sundrin, sundran,</hi> “a
                    goldsmith’s wife,” (fem. of <hi rend="italic">sonar,</hi> “goldsmith,” = S. <hi
                    rend="italic">suvarnakdra); sherni, “</hi> tigress,” from the Persian <hi
                    rend="italic">sher, “</hi> tiger ’; <hi rend="italic">nasiban,</hi> a proper
                    name, from the Arabic <hi rend="italic">?iasib; panclitdni,</hi> “the wife of a
                    pandit”; <hi rend="italic">chaudhrdin, “</hi> the wife of <hi rend="italic">a
                    chaudhari</hi> or head-man”; <hi rend="italic">méhtrdnï,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >“</hi> the wife of a sweeper, a sweeper-woman,” from the Persian <hi
                    rend="italic">mêhtar,</hi> “a sweeper.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Declension.—</hi> It is here that the most striking contrast
                    between the old and the new languages is found. The synthetical method of the
                    Prakrit and the Sanskrit is, as a whole, rejected, only certain half-effaced
                    traces of declension being retained. The number of cases, as in the Sanskrit, is
                    seven, the nominative, accusative, instrumental, dative, ablative, genitive,
                    locative, and vocative; but the inflexions of the Prakrit have given place to
                    case-affixes or postpositions. F or example, where the Sanskrit has <hi
                    rend="italic">sivdyai</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sivasyai,</hi> the Hindi has
                    <hi rend="italic">siv-ko,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">siv-kd.</hi></p>
                <p>The case-affixes or postpositions are as follow :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Instrumental _</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">ne.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>“by.”</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Dative-Accusative</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">ko.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>“to," “for.”</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ablative</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">se.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>“from.”</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Genitive</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">...</hi><hi rend="italic">kü (ke,
                            kï),</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>“of.”</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Locative</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">....</hi><hi rend="italic">men,</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">par.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>“in," “on.”</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The genitive affix, it may be observed, varies its termination so as to agree
                    with the governing noun. In other words, it is adjectival, and agrees with the
                    governing noun just as an adjective would; <hi rend="italic">e.g., sone·kigharl,
                    “</hi> a gold watch.”</p>
                <p>The case-affixes or postpositions are all, there can be no doubt, remnants of
                    Prakrit nouns which were probably in use at the period when the modern Aιyan
                    languages began to be formed. The majority of these are fairly determined, and
                    it seems probable that the remainder will also be fixed before long. The results
                    of the investigation of scholars, as regards the postpositions noticed above
                    (which are those commonly employed in the declension of Hindi and Hindüstäni
                    nouns), we will here attempt to exhibit.</p>
                <p>The case-affix <hi rend="italic">ne</hi> of the instrumental (or case of the
                    agent) is regarded by Trumpp and others as derived from <hi rend="italic"
                    >ena,</hi> the instrumental case-ending of the Sanskrit. This opinion is,
                    however, combated by Beames <hi rend="italic">(Comp. Gram.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 266
                    <hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.),</hi> who is of opinion that it
                    is an affix of the dative, which was probably transferred to the instrumental as
                    late as the time of Shäh Jahän, in whose reign, as has been shown above, Urdü or
                    Hindüstäni λvas consolidated. Beames shows that the postposition is not used in
                    the old Hindi, and is not to be found in most of the dialects, except as a
                    dative ∙, but he does not, we believe, trace it to any particular original. It
                    is clear, however, that whether this affix is derived from the instrumental
                    case-ending of the Sanskrit or not, it bears a striking resemblance to the
                    latter in its use and the construction it requires; <hi rend="italic">e.g..</hi>
                    the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">tena uktam</hi> is marvellously like the Hindi
                    <hi rend="italic">us-na</hi><hi rend="italic">kahä,</hi> “by him it was said,”
                    or freely “he said.”</p>
                <p>The dative postposition <hi rend="italic">ko</hi> is derived by Dr Trumpp from
                    the Präkrit <hi rend="italic">kito, kio,≈S. kritam.</hi> Dl∙ Hoernle,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Journal of
                    the Asiatic Society of Bengal,</hi> 1872, pt. 1, p. 174 <hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.</hi></p></note> however, would seem to connect it
                    with the Bangäli <hi rend="italic">kächhe</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> near,”
                    and the S. <hi rend="italic">sa-kdsa;</hi> and Beames <hi rend="italic">(Comp.
                    Gram.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 257), accepting this as a right clue, traces the affix
                    to the Präkrit <hi rend="italic">kakkham,</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">kaksham,
                    “</hi> armpit,” “side," the locative of which, <hi rend="italic">kakshe,</hi> he
                    believes to be the source of the Bangäli <hi rend="italic">kächhe.</hi></p>
                <p>The postposition <hi rend="italic">se</hi> of the ablative is traced by Beames
                    <hi rend="italic">(Comp. Gram.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 274) to the Sanskrit <hi
                    rend="italic">samam, “</hi> with,” through an old form <hi rend="italic"
                    >soil</hi> still used in the rustic dialects.</p>
                <p>The genitive case-affix <hi rend="italic">kd</hi> (fem. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ki,</hi> oblique <hi rend="italic">ke)</hi> is derived by Trumpp and others
                    from the Sanskrit affix <hi rend="italic">ka.</hi> But Hoernle<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid,</hi>
                    p. 124.</p></note> shows conclusively (and his derivation is accepted by Beames)
                    that the affixis derived from the Präkrit <hi rend="italic">kariö</hi> ( = S.
                    <hi rend="italic">kritas),</hi> which becomes <hi rend="italic">kero,
                    kera(k)o,</hi> and then <hi rend="italic">keraö</hi><hi rend="italic">;
                    kero</hi> is then shortened to <hi rend="italic">kard,</hi> whence the modern
                    form <hi rend="italic">kd.</hi></p>
                <p>Of the locative case-affixes, <hi rend="italic">meh,</hi> “in,” is derived by
                    scholars from the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">madhye,</hi> the locative of <hi
                    rend="italic">madhya, “</hi> the middle”; while <hi rend="italic">par (pari,
                    orpai)</hi> is obviously traceable to the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">upari,</hi>
                    “upon.”</p>
                <p>The declensions are two in number. In the one the nominative or base is inflected
                    before the case-affixes are added; in the other no change takes place in the
                    nominative form. The first consists solely of masculine nouns ending in α = Prk.
                    o = S. <hi rend="italic">as (e.g., ghord,</hi> “horse,”. = Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">ghoraö,</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">ghotakas)</hi>; the second
                    comprises all other nouns, whether they end in vowels or consonants. The base of
                    the first declension is inflected by changing final <hi rend="italic">d</hi> to
                    <hi rend="italic">e; e.g.,</hi> nom. <hi rend="italic">ghord,</hi> inflect, base
                    <hi rend="italic">ghore,</hi> gen. <hi rend="italic">ghoγe-kd,</hi> dat. <hi
                    rend="italic">ghore-ko.</hi> But in the second declension we find, nom. <hi
                    rend="italic">rdjd,</hi> “king,” gen. <hi rend="italic">räjä-kä,</hi> “of a
                    king,” &amp;c. Dr Hoernle connects the <hi rend="italic">e</hi> of the inflected
                    base -with the <hi rend="italic">yd</hi> of the oblique form in Maräthi, and so
                    traces it to a Präkrit genitive in <hi rend="italic">yassa = iassa=ikassa.</hi>
                    The correctness of this derivation would seem to be established by the analogy
                    of the oblique or inflected base of the plural of nouns, and especially by the
                    inflected base of the pronouns, both these bases being indisputably traceable to
                    the Präkrit genitive. Mr Beames, however, is of opinion that “it is not correct
                    to derive the oblique form from any special case of the Sanskrit ;” he thinks
                    that “it rather results from a general fusion of all the cases” <hi
                    rend="italic">(Comp. Gram.,</hi> vol ii. p. 210). This is the more remarkable as
                    he accepts without demur the fact that the plural oblique base is a corruption
                    of the Präkrit genitive plural.</p>
                <p>The terminations of the nominative plural of nouns (where a plural form is used)
                    are clearly traceable to the Präkrit. Nouns which fall under the first of the
                    declensions noticed above terminate in <hi rend="italic">e</hi> in the nom.
                    plur. <hi rend="italic">(e.g., ghord,</hi> “horse,” nom. plur. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ghore,</hi> “horses,” which is identical in form with the inflected base of the
                    sing.). The termination <hi rend="italic">e=</hi> Prk. <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>
                    = S. <hi rend="italic">ah.</hi> Feminines ending in a consonant (and also fem.
                    Arabic words ending in <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                    >bald),</hi> form the nom. plur. by adding <hi rend="italic">eh</hi> to the
                    sing. nom. This ending, <hi rend="italic">eh,</hi> = Prk. neuter <hi
                    rend="italic">di, din,</hi> = S. neut. <hi rend="italic">äni.</hi> The plur.
                    termination <hi rend="italic">äh</hi> of the nom. of feminines ending in <hi
                    rend="italic">i</hi> (as <hi rend="italic">beti,</hi> “daughter ”) is also to be
                    refeιτed to the Präkrit <hi rend="italic">din</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >äni.</hi> The oblique form of the plural of.all nouns ends in <hi rend="italic"
                    >oh (e.g., ghoroh</hi>; gen. <hi rend="italic">ghoγoh-kd;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >räjä-</hi><hi rend="italic">oh,</hi> dat. <hi rend="italic">räjä-oh-ko).</hi>
                    The termination <hi rend="italic">oh</hi> is derived from the Präkrit <hi
                    rend="italic">dnam</hi> (=S. <hi rend="italic">ähäm),</hi> the termination of
                    the genitive plural.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pronouns.—</hi> The pronouns stand in marked contrast to the
                    nouns in respect of the fidelity with which they have preserved the Präkrit
                    forms. Those of the first and second persons nιn parallel to one another, and
                    have four fundamental forms, namely, the nominatives and the obliques in both
                    numbers. The genitive is a possessive pronoun, and, as in the noun, is
                    adjectival in form. <hi rend="italic">Main,</hi> “I, is derived by Trumpp from
                    the Präkrit <hi rend="italic">mam,</hi> the accusative of <hi rend="italic"
                    >aham;</hi> but it seems more probable that it is, as Beames shows, the
                    instrumental <hi rend="italic">maim</hi> of the Präkrit, and =S. <hi
                    rend="italic">mayd.</hi> In the genitive <hi rend="italic">me-rd,</hi> “my,” the
                    affix <hi rend="italic">rd</hi> added to the Prk. base <hi rend="italic">me</hi>
                    is, there can be little doubt, connected with the affix <hi rend="italic"
                    >kd,</hi> used in forming the genitive of nouns; the form <hi rend="italic"
                    >kard,</hi> by elision of <hi rend="italic">k</hi> would naturally yield <hi
                    rend="italic">rd,</hi> which we may observe is the genitive affix of <hi
                    rend="italic">nouns</hi> also in the Marwäri dialect of Hindi. The oblique form
                    <hi rend="italic">mujh</hi> is derived from the Präkrit <hi rend="italic"
                    >majjha,</hi> one of the forms of the genitive. The dative-acc. <hi
                    rend="italic">rnujhe</hi> of the modern Hindi is formed by adding <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> to <hi rend="italic">mujh,</hi> this <hi rend="italic"
                    >e</hi> being the usual sign of the oblique in nouns. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ham,</hi> “we,” = Prk. <hi rend="italic">amhe</hi> by transposition of <hi
                    rend="italic">h.</hi> This is now commonly used as the oblique form of the
                    plural <hi rend="italic">(e.g., ham-ko, ham-par)</hi>; but the oblique <hi
                    rend="italic"> hamoh,</hi> = Prk. gen, plur. <hi rend="italic"> amhdnam,</hi> is
                    also to be met with.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n882/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0882-0843"/>
                <p>The genitive plural <hi rend="italic">hamärä</hi> is probably from Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">amha + karo,</hi> by elision of <hi rend="italic">lc-.</hi></p>
                <p>The pronoun <hi rend="italic">tü,</hi><hi rend="italic">‘ ‘</hi> thou,” = Prk.
                    <hi rend="italic">tumam,</hi><hi rend="italic">tuäm,</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >tvam.</hi> A form <hi rend="italic">iaih,</hi> parallel to <hi rend="italic"
                    >main,</hi> and similarly derived, is also in use. The oblique <hi rend="italic"
                    >tujh</hi> is from the Prakrit <hi rend="italic">tujjha,</hi> one of the forms
                    of the genitive. The sources from and the processes by which the remaining forms
                    are obtained are precisely parallel to those employed in the pronoun of the
                    first person.</p>
                <p>The pronouns of the third person are identical with the demonstrative pronouns
                    <hi rend="italic">yah</hi> or <hi rend="italic">yih,</hi> “this,” and <hi
                    rend="italic">ιvah</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wzιh,</hi> “that,” of which the
                    older forms are <hi rend="italic">ih</hi> and <hi rend="italic">uh.</hi> The
                    origin of these forms has not yet been discovered. All that can be gathered
                    respecting them is that they are probably connected with one or other of the
                    Prakrit forms <hi rend="italic">aäm, iärn,</hi><hi rend="italic">inam,
                    im,kc.</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">ayam, rn.,iyam, i.,idam,</hi> n.,&amp;c., and
                    are to be referred to primitive bases <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> or <hi rend="italic">u.</hi> The oblique forms of these
                    pronouns, however, point clearly to the Prakrit genitive, <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g., is</hi> =Prk. <hi rend="italic">ossa,</hi> S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >asya.</hi></p>
                <p>The relative pronoun <hi rend="italic">jo,</hi> “he who” = Prk. <hi rend="italic"
                    >jo,</hi> base <hi rend="italic">ja</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">ya.</hi> The
                    other form in use, <hi rend="italic">jaun,</hi> = Prk. <hi rend="italic"
                    >jo-zιna</hi> ( = S. <hi rend="italic">punah).</hi> The singular oblique form
                    <hi rend="italic">jis</hi> = Prk. <hi rend="italic">jissa</hi> (the fem. base
                    <hi rend="italic">ji</hi> being used in place of the masc. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ja),</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">yasya.</hi> The oblique form of the plural,
                    <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> y⅛ = Prk. <hi rend="italic">jänam</hi> (by
                    weakening of the vowel), = S. <hi rend="italic">yänam.</hi></p>
                <p>The correlative <hi rend="italic">so</hi> =Prk. <hi rend="italic">so</hi> = S.
                    <hi rend="italic">sah.</hi> Its remaining forms may be made on the model of <hi
                    rend="italic">jo</hi> by substituting <hi rend="italic">t</hi> for/.</p>
                <p>The interrogative pronoun has <hi rend="italic">k</hi> for its typical letter,
                    just as the relative has <hi rend="italic">j,</hi> and is in all respects as
                    uniform as the relative and correlative. <hi rend="italic">Kaun,</hi> “who” <hi
                    rend="italic">=ko + τma</hi> ( = S. <hi rend="italic">punah)</hi>; the oblique
                    form <hi rend="italic">kis</hi> =Prk. gen. <hi rend="italic">kassa</hi> (with
                    change of base from masc. <hi rend="italic">ka</hi> to fem. <hi rend="italic"
                    >ki),</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">kasya.</hi></p>
                <p>The indefinite pronoun <hi rend="italic">koi,</hi> “some one,” = Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">kobi,</hi> = S <hi rend="italic">ko + api.,</hi> “The oblique form
                    <hi rend="italic">kisl</hi> shows the oblique of the interrogative with the <hi
                    rend="italic">I,</hi> whose origin has been forgotten, so that it is regarded as
                    a mere emphatic particle” (see Beames, <hi rend="italic">Comp. Gram.). Kuchh,
                    “</hi> something” = Prk. <hi rend="italic">kimchi=S. kimchit.</hi></p>
                <p>The reflexive pronoun <hi rend="italic">ap,</hi> “self” = Prk. <hi rend="italic"
                    >apρa,</hi><hi rend="italic">äpä,</hi> = 8. <hi rend="italic">ätrnä.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Verbs and Tenses.</hi> —The verbal stems are, generally speaking,
                    derived from the Prakrit present tense of Sanskrit neuter verbs, or from the
                    Prakrit passive past participle. In the formation of the tenses, as in the
                    declension of nouns, the synthetical or inflexional system of the Prakrit and
                    the Sanskrit has given place to the analytical. Still wrecks of the old
                    inflexions remain.</p>
                <p>The tenses of the modern verb may be naturally classed under three heads—(1) the
                    simple tenses, which are the exact modern equivalents of corresponding tenses in
                    the Prakrit verb, and in which traces of the old synthetic method still linger;
                    (2) tenses formed of a participle, either the imperfect or the perfect
                    participle; (3) tenses formed of a participle and an auxiliary verb.</p>
                <p>The tenses of the first class are two in*number,—the aorist (which corresponds to
                    the present indicative of the old languages), and the imperative, which is
                    derived from the Prakrit imperative.</p>
                <p>The terminations of the aorist are :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Singular.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Plural.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1. fi⅛=Prk∙ <hi rend="italic">âmi</hi> =S. <hi rend="italic"
                            >ami.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1. e⅛=Γrk. <hi rend="italic">âma,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >ama=S.</hi><hi rend="italic">âmah.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2. <hi rend="italic">e</hi> =Prk. <hi rend="italic">asi</hi> =S.
                            <hi rend="italic">asi.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2. <hi rend="italic">o</hi> =Prk. <hi rend="italic">aha</hi> —S.
                            <hi rend="italic">a-tha.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3. <hi rend="italic">e</hi> =Prk. <hi rend="italic">adi, ai=S.
                            ati.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3. e⅞=Prk. <hi rend="italic">anti</hi> — S. <hi rend="italic"
                            >anti.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The imperative closely resembles the aorist or old present. The second person
                    sing, is the bare verbal stem, and the second person plur. is identical with
                    that of tħe aorist.</p>
                <p>From the aorist the Hindustani and the Hindi form the simple future by the
                    addition of <hi rend="italic">gâ</hi><hi rend="italic">(</hi> = Prk. <hi
                    rend="italic">gaö,</hi><hi rend="italic">gado, =</hi> S. <hi rend="italic"
                    >gatah,</hi> perf. part, of the root <hi rend="italic">gam,</hi> “to go”), <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi><hi rend="italic">kahwh-gä,</hi> “I will tell,” &amp;c.
                    The termination <hi rend="italic">gâ</hi> (which is masc. ) becomes <hi
                    rend="italic">gi</hi> for the feminine, and <hi rend="italic">ge</hi> for the
                    plural, after the analogy of nouns of the first declension.</p>
                <p>Of the tenses of the second class little need be said. The participles (which
                    like other vocables are derived from the Prakrit) are the imperfect and the
                    perfect, or what are vulgarly termed the present and the past. An example of
                    each will suffice to show the construction: <hi rend="italic">wah</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">boltâ,</hi> “he says”; <hi rend="italic">main</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">bolâ,</hi> “I said”; <hi rend="italic">wah boll,</hi> “she said”;
                    <hi rend="italic">we bole,</hi> “they said.” Such is the construction in the
                    case of neuter and intransitive verbs. But if the verb be active transitive, the
                    tenses formed of the perfect passive participle are passively constructed; the
                    place of the nominative is taken by the instrumental or case of the agent, and
                    the participle inflects so as to agree with the object, if this be expressed,
                    and appear in the form of the nominative; but if the object is not expressed, or
                    if when expressed it assumes the dative form, the participle is constructed
                    impersonally and appears in the masc. sing, form; <hi rend="italic">e.g.,
                    'maih-ne</hi><hi rend="italic">kahâ,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> by me it was
                    said,” “I said”; <hi rend="italic">us-ne chitthi likhi,</hi> “the letter was
                    written by him,” “he wrote the letter”; <hi rend="italic">räjä-ne</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">shernï-ko mârâ,</hi> “the king killed the tigress”; lit. “as
                    regards the tigress, it was killed by the king.” This construction, as we have
                    already remarked, is commonly employed in the Sanskrit.</p>
                <p>The tenses of the third class are formed by adding to the participles already
                    mentioned the various tenses of certain auxiliary verbs, as <hi rend="italic"
                    >honä,</hi> “tobe”; <hi rend="italic">jânâ,</hi> “togo”; and the fragmentary
                    forms <hi rend="italic">huh</hi> (with its remaining persons) and <hi
                    rend="italic">thä</hi><hi rend="italic">; e.g., main</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >jâiâ</hi><hi rend="italic">huh,</hi> “I am going”; <hi rend="italic">wah parhti
                    hai,</hi> “she is reading <hi rend="italic">; wah</hi><hi rend="italic">bailhä
                    thä,</hi> “he was seated,” “he was sitting”; <hi rend="italic">we chale
                    hoiige,</hi> “they will have started.”</p>
                <p>Of these auxiliaries <hi rend="italic">honâ</hi><hi rend="italic">(ha-</hi> =
                    Prk. <hi rend="italic">ho-,</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">bhu)</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">jänä</hi><hi rend="italic">(jâ</hi> = Prk. <hi rend="italic"
                    >jâ,</hi> = S. <hi rend="italic">yä)</hi> need not detain us. Both verbs are in
                    use in all their tenses in the modem languages, and the preceding remarks on the
                    verbal forms and tenses apply equally to them. <hi rend="italic">Jänä</hi> is
                    that which is employed to form the passive voice, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,
                    wah</hi><hi rend="italic">märä jäegä,</hi><hi rend="italic">“</hi> he will be
                    killed.” It is also used for other purposes, such as intensifying a root to
                    which it is attached, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The auxiliaries <hi rend="italic">huh</hi> (with its other persons) and <hi
                    rend="italic">thä</hi> stand on a different footing. The former is derived from
                    the present indicative of the root <hi rend="italic">as,</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> a</hi> to be,” in the old languages :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Singular.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">Plural.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1. Λωi=Prk. αmΛi=S. <hi rend="italic">asmi.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1. Λαιn=Prk. <hi rend="italic">asma=S. smah.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>2. Λαι=Prk. <hi rend="italic">asi —8. asi.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2. <hi rend="italic">ho</hi> =Prk. <hi rend="italic">attħa=S.
                            stha.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>3. Λαi=Prk. <hi rend="italic">atthi=S. asti.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3. <hi rend="italic">hain—</hi> Prk. <hi rend="italic">santi=S∙
                            santi.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Beames <hi rend="italic">(Comp. Gram.,</hi> vol. iii. p. 171, <hi
                            rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.)</hi> thinks it difficult,
                            if not impossible, to derive these modern forms from the old ones given
                            above, and would postulate the existence of a present tense of the root
                            <hi rend="italic">as</hi> conjugated after the <hi rend="italic"
                            >bηu</hi> type, thus—(sing.) 1. <hi rend="italic">asämi;</hi> 2. <hi
                            rend="italic">asasi;</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">asati:</hi> (plur.) 1.
                            <hi rend="italic">asâmah;</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">asatha,</hi> 3. <hi
                            rend="italic">asanti.</hi> The objection to this, however, is that no
                            such forms have been found to exist.</p></note></p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The latter is derived from the Prakrit <hi rend="italic">thzo, =</hi> Sanskrit
                    <hi rend="italic">sthιtah,</hi> the perfect participle of the root <hi
                    rend="italic">sfhä,</hi> “to stand.” Besides being used as auxiliaries, both are
                    employed to express simple existence, as <hi rend="italic">main</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">hüh,</hi> “I am,” “it is I”; <hi rend="italic">wah hai, “</hi> he
                    or it is”; <hi rend="italic">ιvah</hi><hi rend="italic">thä,</hi> “he was”; <hi
                    rend="italic">wah thi,</hi> “she was.” (J. T. P. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
