<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0528-0497-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HARTLEPOOL (9th edition, volume 11, page 497)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HARTLEPOOL</label>, and <hi rend="smallcaps">West</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Hartlepool,</hi> respectively a municipal borough and a town of
                    England, county of Durham, and included in the parliamentary borough of the
                    Hartlepools, are situated the one on the north and the other on the south side
                    of Hartlepool Bay, about a mile apart, but having connexion by railway, and
                    practically forming portions of one town. By railway Hartlepool is 10 miles and
                    West Hartlepool 12 miles N.N.E. of Stockton-on-Tees. The principal buildings of
                    Hartlepool are the parish church, in the Early English style, dedicated to St
                    Hilda; the borough hall, in the Italian style, erected in 1866, behind which
                    there is a large market; the Durham militia artillery depot, erected in 1861;
                    the temperance hall, the mechanics’ institute, and the theatre. New schools for
                    boys, girls, and infants have been erected by the school board; and Prissick’s
                    schools, founded in 1826, have been constituted elementary schools under the
                    Education Act of 1870. Among the other schools are Crook’s endowed school,
                    founded in 1755, and the school in connexion with Henry Smith’s charity. The
                    town was originally surrounded by walls, of which considerable remains may yet
                    be seen. It is well supplied with water. The principal buildings of West
                    Hartlepool are the athenaeum<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n529/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0529-0498"/>, the town-hall, the exchange, in the Gothic
                    style, erected in 1875 at a cost of £10,000, the mechanics’ institute, and the
                    theatre. A Government school of art was established in 1874. The manufactures of
                    the two towns are very much alike: they possess iron-works, puddling furnaces,
                    brass and iron foundries, engine and boiler works, sawmills, cement works, tile
                    works, and breweriee. With the addition of the new docks, completed in 1879, the
                    dock area between the towns is 86 acres, besides which there are ponds with an
                    area of about 80 acres. Considerable difficulty has been found in maintaining a
                    sufficient depth of water at the harbour bar of Hartlepool, and although the use
                    of a powerful dredge has been so far effectual, it is probable that the only
                    adequate remedy will be the extension of the breakwater. A large lighthouse for
                    guiding the entrance of vessels was erected in 1846-47 at a cost of nearly
                    £6000. In the shipping returns Hartlepool and West Hartlepool are classed
                    together as one port; in 1878 the number of vessels that entered the port,
                    including those in ballast, was 4640, with a tonnage of 885,762; the number that
                    cleared 4662, with a tonnage of 992,370. For the five years ending 1878 the
                    average number of vessels that entered was 5371, with a tonnage of 975,039,
                    while 5447 cleared, with a tonnage of 1,005,740. The principal exports are coal,
                    coke, machines, and cotton, linen and woollen goods, and the principal imports,
                    timber, cattle, corn, provisions, and wool. The fisheries are considerable. The
                    town is much resorted to in summer for sea-bathing. Several caverns, which may
                    be explored for nearly fifty yards, have been excavated by the sea out of the
                    rocks on the shore of the peninsula. The parliamentary borough of the
                    Hartlepools has an area of 7267 acres, and besides Hartlepool includes Stranton
                    (in which parish West Hartlepool is situated), Seaton Carew, and Throston. Its
                    population in 1861 was 27,475, and in 1871, 38,203. The population of the
                    municipal borough of Hartlepool in 1861 was 12,245, and in 1871, 13,166; and the
                    population of Stranton in 1861 was 13,601, and in 1871, 22,166.</p>
                <p>The name Hartlepool means the pool or lake of Hart. The town grew up round a
                    monastery which had St Hilda as its abbess, and the harbour was of some
                    consequence as early as 1171. In the 13th century Hartlepool belonged to the
                    Bruces of Annandale in Scotland, the progenitors of the royal family of that
                    name. The town was erected into a borough about 1200. After Bruce ascended the
                    Scottish throne his English possessions were forfeited, and Hartlepool was
                    granted to the Cliffords. It suffered severely from the Scots in 1312, and again
                    in 1315 after the battle of Bannockburn. During the great northern rebellion in
                    the reign of Elizabeth it was seized by the insurgents. In 1644 it was taken by
                    the Scottish army, and it remained in the possession of Scotland till 1647. West
                    Hartlepool was founded in 1844 by Mr R. W. Jackson, the first M.P. for the
                    borough of the Hartlepools. Its first dock was constructed in 1847, after which
                    it increased with great rapidity.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
