<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0817-0780-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HESSE-DARMSTADT, Grand-Duchy of (9th edition, volume
                    11, page 780)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:831540">Bidens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n817/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HESSE-DARMSTADT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Grand-Duchy
                    of</hi></label>, the actual Hesse of the present day, is a state of Germany
                    situated on the Rhine and Main, between Prussia on the north and Biden on the
                    south. It consists of two large and several small detached portions of
                    territory. The more northerly of the large portions forms the province of
                    Oberhessen, and is completely surrounded by Prussia. The other, divided by the
                    Rhine into the provinces of Starkenburg and Rheinhessen, is bounded on the N. by
                    Hesse-Nassau, on the W. by the Rhine Palatinate and Rhenish Prussia, on the S.
                    by Baden, and on the E. by Baden and Bavaria. The extent of the duchy is about
                    2965 square miles. Oberhessen is mountainous, having the Vogelsberg in the east
                    with Taufstein (2579 feet) as the highest summit in the country, and the
                    Hausberg, a branch of the Taunus, in the south-west. In the south-east of
                    Starkenburg is the Odenwald. Rheinhessen is occupied by fertile hills. The chief
                    rivers are the Rhine, Main, Neckar, Lahn, and Fulda, with their tributaries.
                    There are no lakes, but mineral springs abound in all the provinces. The climate
                    is pleasant and mild in the river valleys and plains, but severe on the heights,
                    especially in Oberhessen. Besides the usual domestic animals, deer of various
                    kinds, wild swine, foxes, martens, and otters are found. Agriculture, including
                    the breeding of horses and cattle, is actively encouraged by Government, and is
                    the principal industry of the people. Forestry and vine-growing are also
                    important, the latter being practised almost exclusively in Rheinhessen. The
                    principal crops are millet, buckwheat, oats, and potatoes; but rape (for oil),
                    hemp, flax, tobacco, and fruit are also cultivated. The manufactures embrace
                    leather (enamelled and coloured), tobacco, cigars, shoes, furniture,
                    pocket-books and similar goods, chemicals, matches, machinery, and various
                    textile fabrics. Mining is carried on chiefly in Oberhessen. Iron, copper,
                    manganese, graphite, lignite, salt, marble, and clay are the principal minerals,
                    which are worked for home consumption. In 1878 there were produced in Hesse
                    45,300 tons of lignite, 91,724 tons of iron ore, and 13,200 tons of salt,
                    representing in value about £62,100. Trade is tolerably important in Hesse. The
                    following numbers of persons engaged in the various industries are taken from
                    the industrial census of 1875 :—Horticulturists, 292; fishermen, 65; miners,
                    1553; workers in stone, clay, glass, 4715; in metals, 8266; in machines,
                    instruments, &amp;c., 7202; in chemical industries, 2153; in lighting materials,
                    soap, resins, &amp;c., 1190; in textile industries, 8274; in paper and leather,
                    7600; in wood, 11,142; in food and drink, 19,923; in dress and washing, 21,629;
                    in building, 1291; iu polygraphic industries, 1291; in artistic industries, 412;
                    in mercantile business, 17,593; in conveyance, 2273; in lodging and boarding,
                    6016— total, 134,383. The people are well educated; of the recruits in 1878-79
                    only ’ 21 per cent, were unable either to read or write. There is a university
                    at Giessen, and the schools, ordinary, technical, and theological, throughout
                    the country are very numerous. The Protestant religion predominates, though the
                    Roman Catholic faith is also recognized by the state. Darmstadt is the capital;
                    Offenbach is the chief manufacturing town; Mainz has perhaps the most active
                    trade. The other chief towns are Alsfeld, Lauterbach, Friedberg, Bingen,
                    Bensheim, and Worms. The population in 1875 was 884,218. The government since
                    1820 has been a constitutional hereditary monarchy, assisted by two chambers,
                    modified iu 1856—the one of life members, mostly from among the nobility, the
                    other of popular representatives, elected indirectly. The chambers must meet at
                    least once every three years. The ministry of three is responsible to the
                    nation. Hesse is represented in the imperial federal council by 3 votes, and in
                    the reichstag by 9. The annual revenue for the finance-period 1876-78 was
                    £872,375, and the expenditure £872,481. The estimated annual revenue for the
                    period 1879-82 is £1,011,762, and the estimated expenditure £857,124. The public
                    debt in 1879 was £2,041,397, chiefly incurred for railways. For additional
                    statistics see <hi rend="smallcaps">Germany.</hi></p>
                <p>George I., youngest son of Philip the Magnanimous, received on his father’s death
                    in 1567 the upper countship of Katzenelnbogen, and, selecting Darmstadt as his
                    residence, became the founder of the Hesse-Darmstadt line. Additions to the
                    territory were made both in his reign and in that of his son, Louis V. The
                    landgraviate, as it was at first styled, suffered severely from war and its
                    attendant famines and plagues. The Thirty Years’ War, a war of succession with
                    Hesse-Cassel, and the Seven Years’ War dealt heavy blows at its prosperity.
                    Louis X, who succeeded his father in 1790, involved it in further contests.
                    Joining at first the allies against France, he was compelled in 1793 by the
                    latter power to sign a treaty of neutrality. By the treaty of Lunéville he gave
                    up his possessions on the left bank of the Rhine, receiving as compensation a
                    very much larger district on the right bank. From 1805 till 1813 he was
                    compelled to supply Napoleon with a contingent of troops against the other
                    Germans. In 1806, as member of the Confederation of the Rhine, he assumed the
                    title of grand-duke Louis I. of Hesse. After the battle of Leipsic in 1813, when
                    Napoleon was defeated, Louis again joined the allies. By the decision of the
                    Vienna congress in 1815 considerable change in his dominions was made; but
                    though he was forced to recognize the independence of Hesse-Homburg, which since
                    the beginning of the century had been incorporated with Hesse-Darmstadt, his
                    title of grand-duke was confirmed. Within his country a growing desire for
                    political liberty had been making itself apparent, and in 1820 the grand-duke
                    promulgated a new constitution. This was rejected by the people, and attempts
                    were made in vain by successive diets to frame a constitution pleasing alike to
                    the ruler and the ruled. Louis II.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n818/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0818-0781"/>
                <p>succeeded his father in 1830. His policy in no degree lessened the popular
                    discontent. His son Louis III., who succeeded in 1848, alarmed by the events in
                    Paris of that year, and by commotions in his own country, gave way a little, but
                    under the reaction of 1850 he again restored matters to their old state. Since
                    that time, although no radical change has been effected, the liberal party in
                    the state has been steadily gaining ground. In 1866 Hesse-Darmstadt supported
                    Austria against Prussia, with the result that it had to pay a heavy indemnity
                    and cede certain provinces, including the lately acquired Hesse-Homburg, to
                    Prussia. In 1867 it entered the North German Confederation, and in 1870 the
                    German Confederation. Louis IV. succeeded his uncle in 1877.</p>
                <p>A list of works on Hesse is to be found in Walther’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Literarisches Handbuch für Geschichte und Landeskunde von Hessen,</hi> 1841.
                    See also Steiner, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Grossherzogthums Hessen,</hi>
                    5 vols., 1833—4; Türckheim, <hi rend="italic">Histoire généalogique de la maison
                    de Hesse,</hi> 1819-20; Heber, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Grossherzogthums</hi><hi rend="italic">Hessen,</hi> 1837;
                    Dieffenbach, <hi rend="italic">Das Grossherzogthum Hessen in Vergangenheit und
                    Gegenwart,</hi> 1875; Voltz, <hi rend="italic">Uebersicht der geologischen
                    Verhältnisse des Grossherzogthums Hessen,</hi> 1852; and works under <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Hesse.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
