<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0849-0812-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HILARIUS, St (9th edition, volume 11, page 812)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68c45">Trinitarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1200824">Liberals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:997183">Liberalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937256">Gallicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814376">Arianism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n849/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HILARIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>, bishop of
                    Pictavium (Poitiers), an eminent “doctor” of the Western Church, sometimes
                    referred to as the “malleus Arianorum” and the “Athanasius of the West,” was
                    born at Poitiers about the end of the 3d century <hi rend="smallcaps">a.u.</hi>
                    His parents, who were pagans of distinction, afforded him every means of
                    acquiring a good education; and to the ordinary accomplishments of an educated
                    gentleman there was added in his case what had even then become somewhat rare in
                    the West, some knowledge of Greek. After he had attained to manhood his
                    attention was directed to the Old and New Testament writings, with the result
                    that he became convinced of the truth of Christianity, and along with his wife
                    and his daughter received the sacrament of baptism. We have no means of knowing
                    the nature or duration of the services which he rendered the church during the
                    period which immediately<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n850/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0850-0813"/> followed his admission within its pale; but he
                    appears to have continued to reside in Poitiers, and so great was the respect in
                    which he came to be held by the citizens there that about 353, although still a
                    married man, he was by the unanimous voice elected bishop. At that time
                    Arianism, which under imperial protection had overspread the Eastern, was now
                    under similar auspices threatening also to overrun the Western Church; to resist
                    and repel the irruption was the great task which Hilary now set himself to
                    achieve. One of his first steps was to secure the excommunication, by those of
                    the Gallican hierarchy who still remained orthodox, of Saturninus, the Arian
                    bishop of Arles, along with Ursacius and Valens, two of the most prominent of
                    the supporters of that prelate. About the same time he wrote to the emperor
                    Constantius a remonstrance against the persecutions by which the Arians had
                    sought to crush their opponents <hi rend="italic">(Ad</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Constantium</hi><hi rend="italic">Augustum Liber Primus,</hi> of which the most
                    probable date is 355). His labours for the triumph of orthodoxy were not in the
                    first instance, however, crowned with success; for at the synod of Biterrae
                    (Beziers), summoned in 356 by Constantius with the professed purpose of settling
                    the long-standing disputes, Hilary was by an imperial rescript banished along
                    with Rhodanus of Toulouse to Phrygia, in which exile he spent nearly four years.
                    From this hostile region, however, he continued to govern his diocese without
                    undue difficulty, no successor having been nominated to the see; while at the
                    same time he found leisure for the preparation of two of the most important of
                    his contributions to dogmatic and polemical theology, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Synodis,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">De Fide</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Orientalium,</hi> an epistle addressed in 358 to the bishops in
                    Gaul, Germany, and Britain, expounding the true views (sometimes veiled in
                    ambiguous words) of the Oriental bishops on the Trinitarian controversy, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Trinitate Libri</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >XII.</hi>, composed in 359 and 360, in which, for the first time, it was
                    successfully attempted to express in the Latin tongue the theological subtleties
                    and refinements which had been elaborated with the aid of the more flexible
                    language of Greece. The former of these works was not entirely approved by some
                    of the.members of his own party, who thought he had shown too great forbearance
                    towards the Arians, and had expressed himself too hopefully as to the
                    possibilities of an ultimate reconciliation of the contending views; to their
                    criticisms he replied in the <hi rend="italic">Apologetica</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Reprehensores Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Synodis Responsa.</hi> In 359 Hilary attended the convocation of
                    bishops at Seleucia in Isauria, where, along with the Egyptian Athanasians, he
                    joined tho Homoiousian majority against the Arianizing party headed by Acacius
                    of Caesarea; thence he betook himself to Constantinople, and, in a petition <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Constantium Augustum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Liber</hi><hi rend="italic">Secundus')</hi> personally presented
                    to the emperor in 360, repudiated the personal calumnies of his enemies and
                    sought to vindicate his Trinitarian principles. His urgent and repeated request
                    to be permitted a public discussion with his opponents, especially with Ursacius
                    and Valens, proved at last so inconvenient that he was sent back to his diocese,
                    which, accordingly, he appears to have reached about 361, within a very short
                    time of the accession of Julian. Though he was received in his diocese with
                    every demonstration of joy, he yet found Arianism strong enough there to demand
                    his best energy and skill for the next two or three years; but in 364, extending
                    his efforts once more beyond Gaul, he impeached Auxentius, bishop of Milan, and
                    a man high in the imperial favour, as heterodox. Summoned to appear before the
                    emperor (Valentinian) at Milan and there maintain his charges in person, Hilary
                    had the mortification of hearing the supposed heretic give answers entirely
                    satisfactory to all the questions which were proposed; nor did his (doubtless
                    sincere) denunciation of the metropolitan as a hypocrite save himself from an
                    ignominious expulsion from Milan as a disturber of the peace of the church. In
                    365 he published the <hi rend="italic">Contra Ariaηos</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >vel</hi><hi rend="italic">Auxentium</hi><hi rend="italic">Mediolanensem</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Liber,</hi> in connexion with the controversy; and also (but
                    perhaps at a somewhat earlier date) the <hi rend="italic">Contra</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Constantium Augustum</hi><hi rend="italic">Liber,</hi> in which he
                    pronounced that lately deceased emperor to have been Antichrist, a rebel against
                    God, “a tyrant whose sole object had been to make a gift to the devil of that
                    world for which Christ had suffered.” The later years of Hilary’s life were
                    spent in comparative quiet and retirement, devoted in part to the preparation of
                    his expositions of the Psalms <hi rend="italic">(Tractatus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >super</hi><hi rend="italic">Psalmos)</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> for which he
                    was largely indebted to Origen; of his <hi rend="italic">Commentarius</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">Evangelium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Matthai,</hi> a work of no exegetical value; and of his no longer extant
                    treatise on the book of Job. He died 13th January 368. His great energy and
                    zeal, courage and perseverance, rendered him a very influential ecclesiastic
                    during his life; while, in virtue at once of the depth and acuteness of his
                    intellect and of the wide extent of his knowledge, he holds the very highest
                    rank among the Latin writers of his century. Designated already by Augustine as
                    “the illustrious doctor of the churches,” he by his works exerted an increasing
                    influence in later centuries; and by Pius IX. he was formally recognized as
                    “universae ecclesiae doctor” at the synod of Bordeaux in 1851. Hilary’s day in
                    the Roman calendar is January 14; the English “Hilary Term” begins on the 11th
                    and ends on the 31st.</p>
                <p>Of Hilary’s works, which include, besides those already mentioned, some minor
                    treatises, there have been several editions, of which the most worthy of mention
                    are that of Erasmus (Basel, 1523, 1526, 1528), the Benedictine by Coûtant
                    (Paris, 1693; reprinted by Maffei, Verona, 1730), and that of Migne in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Patrologiae Cursus</hi><hi rend="italic">Completus.</hi> His
                    biography by Fortunatus probably dates from about the middle of the 6th century;
                    other sources for the facts of the life of Hilary are the numerous incidental
                    notices to be met with in his own writingsand in those of Jerome, Sulpicius
                    Severus, and Gregory of Tours. See Reinkens, <hi rend="italic">Hilarius</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">v. Poictiers</hi> (1864).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
