<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0748-0715-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERBARIUM, or Hortus (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    715)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946934">Gray</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115626">Sheets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208387">Michigan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n748/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERBARIUM, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Hortus</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Siccus,</hi> a collection of plants so dried and preserved as
                    fully to illustrate their several specific characters. Since the same plant,
                    owing to peculiarities of climate, soil, and situation, degree of exposure to
                    light, and other influences, may vary greatly according to the locality in which
                    it occurs, it is only by gathering together for comparison and study a large
                    series of examples of each species illustrative of the flora of different
                    regions that the laws of vegetable morphology, and many more points of
                    scientific interest, can be satisfactorily determined. Thus, from the herbarium
                    may be acquired a knowledge of those details concerning the minuter structure of
                    individual plants which are of necessity omitted in works of systematic botany,
                    as also of the relative taxonomic importance of the characters to be met with in
                    large groups of forms.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n749/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0749-0716"/>
                <p>Commencing with British herbaria, the collection of the Royal Herbarium at Kew,
                    generally acknowledged to be at once the most extensive and the best preserved
                    and most orderly in the world, comprises some 100,000 species, many of them
                    represented by numerous specimens. It is arranged, for easy reference, in cases
                    situate between the windows of the building containing it, the atmosphere of
                    which is kept dry by means of hot-water pipes. In the intervening spaces are
                    tables for the purpose of study, which is further facilitated by the presence in
                    the same building of a large and valuable botanical library. Next in importance
                    is the herbarium of the British Museum, which comprises assemblages of specimens
                    gathered by numerous eminent botanists. The collection of Dillenius is deposited
                    at Oxford, and that of the late Professor Harvey at Trinity College, Dublin. The
                    original herbarium of Linnaeus is in the possession of the Linnean Society of
                    London. With the more important British herbaria are to be ranked also those of
                    Cambridge and Edinburgh. The collections of Jussieu and St Hilaire are included
                    in the large herbarium of the Jardin des Plantes at Paris, and in the same city
                    is the extensive private collection of Dr Cosson. At Geneva are three large
                    collections,—De Candolle’s, containing the typical specimens of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Prodromus,</hi> Delessert’s fine series, and Boissier’s
                    Mediterranean and Oriental plants. The university of Göttingen has had
                    bequeathed to it the largest collection (exceeding 40,000 specimens) ever made
                    by a single individual—that of the late Professor Grisebach. At the herbarium in
                    Brussels are the specimens obtained by the traveller Martius, the majority of
                    which formed the groundwork of his <hi rend="italic">Flora Brasiliensis.</hi>
                    Other national herbaria sufficiently extensive to subserve the requirements of
                    the systematic botanist exist at Berlin, St Petersburg, Vienna, Leyden,
                    Stockholm, Upsala, Copenhagen, and Florence. Of those in the United States of
                    America, the chief, formed by Asa Gray, is the property of Harvard university;
                    others are to be seen at Yale and Columbia colleges and at New York and Michigan
                    universities. The herbarium at Melbourne, Australia, under Baron Müller, has
                    attained large proportions; and that of the Botanical Garden of Calcutta is
                    noteworthy as the repository of numerous specimens described by writers on
                    Indian botany.</p>
                <p>Specimens of flowering plants and vascular cryptogams are, at Kew, generally
                    mounted on sheets of stout smooth paper, of uniform quality, and in most cases
                    17 inches long by 11 inches broad; the palms and their allies, however, and some
                    ferns, require a size of 22 by 14 inches. The tough but flexible coarse grey
                    paper (German, <hi rend="italic">Fliesspapier),</hi> upon which on the Continent
                    specimens are commonly fixed by gummed strips of the same, is less hygroscopic
                    than ordinary cartridge paper, but has the disadvantage of affording harbourage
                    in the inequalities of its surface to a minute insect, <hi rend="italic">Atropos
                    pulsαtoτia,</hi> L., which commits great havoc in damp specimens, and which,
                    even if noticed, cannot be dislodged without difficulty. The majority of plant
                    specimens are most suitably fastened on paper by a mixture of equal parts of gum
                    tragacanth and gum arabic made into a thick paste with water. Rigid leathery
                    leaves are affixed by means of glue, or, if they present too smooth a surface,
                    by stitching at their edges. Where, as in private herbaria, the specimens are
                    not liable to be handled with great frequency, a stitch here and there round the
                    stem, tied at the back of the sheet, or slips of paper passed over the stem
                    through two slits in the sheet and attached with gum to its back, or simply
                    strips of gummed paper lai 1 across the stem, may be resorted to. A new adhesive
                    substance, a kind of fish glue, has lately come into use for this purpose, and
                    is highly spoken of. To preserve from insects, the plants, after mounting, are
                    brushed over with a liquid formed by the solution of { lb each of corrosive
                    sublimate and carbolic acid in 1 gallon of methylated spirits. They are then
                    laid out to dry on shelves made of a network of stout galvanized iron wire.
                    After this are written, usually in the right-hand corner of the sheet, or on a
                    label there affixed, the designation of each species, the date and place of
                    gathering, and the name of the collector. Information as to economical or
                    medicinal properties may either be added thereto, or mentioned on the back of
                    the sheet. It is especially important to attach to the name of the plant the
                    initials or abbreviated name of the author by whom it was first described; <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g,</hi> the words <hi rend="italic">Ulva lactuca</hi> alone,
                    might signify either of two distinct plants, the one described by Linnaeus, the
                    other by Agardh. When the generic name has been altered, but the specific name
                    has been retained, the name of the original describer of the plant is placed in
                    brackets before the name of the later author. Thus the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eηteromorpha Grevillei</hi> of Thuret, having been renamed, has become <hi
                    rend="italic">Ulva Grevillei</hi> (Thur.), Le Jolis. The value of specimens in
                    private herbaria is greatly enhanced by briefly stating on the lower left-hand
                    corner of the sheet the characters that distinguish it from the plants most
                    nearly resembling it. Other particulars as to habit, local abundance, soil, and
                    claim to be indigenous may be written on the back of the sheet, or on a slip of
                    writing paper attached to its edge. It is convenient to place in a small
                    envelope gummed to an upper corner of the sheet any flowers, seeds, or leaves
                    needed for dissection or microscopical examination, especially where from the
                    fixation of the specimen it is impossible to examine the leaves for
                    oilreceptacles, and where seed is apt to escape from ripe capsules and be lost.
                    The addition of a careful dissection of a flower greatly increases the value of
                    the specimen. To ensure that all shall lie evenly in the herbarium the plants
                    should be made to occupy as far as possible alternately the right and left sides
                    of their respective sheets. The species of each genus are then arranged either
                    systematically or alphabetically in separate covers of stout, usually light
                    brown paper, or, if the genus be large, in several covers with the name of the
                    genus clearly indicated in the lower left-hand corner of each, and opposite it
                    the names or reference numbers of the species. Undetermined species are
                    relegated to the end of the genus. Thus prepared, the specimens are placed on
                    shelves or movable trays, at intervals of about 6 inches, in an air-tight
                    cupboard, on the inner side of the door of which, as a special protection
                    against insects, is suspended a muslin bag containing a piece of camphor.</p>
                <p>The systematic arrangement varies in different herbaria. The works usually
                    followed are—for dicotyledons, De Candolle’s <hi rend="italic">Prodromus,</hi>
                    and Endlicher’s or Bentham and Hooker’s <hi rend="italic">Genera Plantarum</hi>;
                    for monocotyledons, Kunth’s <hi rend="italic">Enumeratio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> for ferns, Hooker and Baker’s <hi rend="italic">Synopsis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Filicum·,</hi> for mosses, Muller’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Synojisis</hi><hi rend="italic">Muscorum Frondosorum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> for algae, Kützing’s <hi rend="italic">Phycologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >generalis</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> for hepaticae, Gottschie, Lindenberg,
                    and Nees ab Esenbeck’s <hi rend="italic">Synopsis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Hepaticarum',</hi> and for other groups of cryptogamie plants the treatises of
                    various authors scattered through numerous scientific publications. In certain
                    herbaria, as in those of Boissier and Delessert at Geneva, the authority of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Prodromus</hi> is accepted only in the absence of any more
                    recent treatise, or of a complete monograph on a family. For the members of
                    large genera, <hi rend="italic">e.g., Piper</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ficus,</hi> since the number of cosmopolitan or very widely distributed species
                    is comparatively few, a geographical grouping is found specially convenient by
                    those who are constantly receiving parcels of plants from known foreign sources.
                    The ordinary systematic arrangement possesses the great advantage, in the case
                    of large genera, of readily <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n750/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0750-0717"/> indicating the affinities of any particular
                    specimen with the forms most nearly allied to it in type. In the United States
                    the species in the genera, and the genera in the orders, are usually arranged
                    alphabetically, and the orders serially; sometimes, however, the genera are
                    placed alphabetically throughout without reference to the orders. The
                    alphabetical arrangement, provided works on systematic botany are referred to
                    for the identification of particular plants, possesses the advantage of
                    permitting ready reference to any given species, and also of being independent
                    of changes of classification; but in Europe it is rarely adopted, on account of
                    the counterbalancing practical inconveniences it is considered to present.
                    Instead of keeping a catalogue of the species contained in the herbarium, which,
                    owing to the constant additions, would be almost impossible, such species are
                    usually ticked off with a pencil in the systematic work which is followed in
                    arranging them, so that by reference to this work it is possible to see at a
                    glance whether the specimen sought is in the herbarium, and what species are
                    still wanted. The custom commonly prevalent in Continental, especially German,
                    herbaria of placing the dried specimens loosely between sheets of papers not
                    always of uniform character is liable to lead to the admixture of nearly allied
                    forms in intricate genera, such as <hi rend="italic">Rubus,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Rosa, Hieracium, Salix,</hi><hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> fcc.,
                    unless a label is attached to each specimen, a precaution not always adopted. In
                    Germany Endlicher’s system is much followed for flowering plants, with the
                    exception of palms, for which Martius’s arrangement is preferred. At Geneva De
                    Candolle’s original herbarium is arranged in exact accordance with his <hi
                    rend="italic">Prodromus.</hi> In the other large herbaria in that city, the
                    mounting and arrangement of the specimens are conducted much as in England, with
                    the exception that smaller-sized sheets of paper are used for cryptogams.</p>
                <p>Specimens intended for the herbarium should be collected when possible in dry
                    weather, care being taken to select plants or portions of plants in sufficient
                    number and of a size adequate to illustrate all the characteristic features of
                    the species. When the root-leaves and roots present any peculiarities, they
                    should invariably be collected, but the roots should be dried separately in an
                    oven at a moderate heat. Roots and fruits too bulky to be placed on the sheets
                    of the herbarium may be conveniently arranged in glass-covered boxes contained
                    in drawers. The best and most effective mode of drying specimens is learned only
                    by experience, different species requiring special treatment according to their
                    several peculiarities. The chief points to be attended to are to have a
                    plentiful supply of botanical drying paper, so as to be able to use about six
                    sheets for each specimen; to change the paper at intervals of six to twelve
                    hours; to. avoid contact of one leaf or flower with another; and to increase the
                    pressure applied only in proportion to the dryness of the specimen. To preserve
                    the colour of flowers pledgets of cotton wool, which prevent bruising, should be
                    introduced between them, as also, if the stamens are thick and succulent, as in
                    <hi rend="italic">Digitalis,</hi> between these and the corolla. A flower
                    dissected and gummed on the sheets will often retain the colour which it is
                    impossible to preserve in a crowded inflorescence. Before placing in a
                    screw-press, should that be used, a flat sheet of lead or some other suitable
                    weight should be laid upon the top of the pile of specimens, so as to keep up a
                    continuous pressure. Succulent specimens, as many of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grchidaceoe,</hi> and sedums and various other Crassulaceous plants, require to
                    be killed by immersion in boiling water before being placed in drying paper, or,
                    instead of becoming dry, they will grow between the sheets. W hen, as with some
                    plants like <hi rend="italic">Verbascum,</hi> the thick hard stems are liable to
                    cause the leaves to wrinkle in drying by removing the pressure from them, small
                    pieces of bibulous paper or cotton wool may be placed upon the leaves near their
                    point of attachment to the stem. When a number of specimens have to be submitted
                    to pressure, ventilation is secured by means of frames corresponding in size to
                    the drying paper, and composed of strips of wood or wires laid across each other
                    so as to form a kind of network. Another mode of drying is to keep the specimens
                    in a box of dry sand in a warm place for ten or twelve hours, and then press
                    them in drying paper. A third method consists in placing the specimen within
                    bibulous paper, and enclosing the whole between two plates, of coarsely
                    perforated zinc supported in a wooden frame. The zinc plates are then drawn
                    close together by means of straps, and suspended before a fire until the drying
                    is effected. By the last two methods the colour of the flowers may be well
                    preserved. When the leaves are finely divided, as in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cοnium,</hi> much trouble will be experienced in lifting a half-dried specimen
                    from one paper to another; but the plant may be placed in a sheet of thin
                    blotting paper, and the sheet containing the plant, instead of the plant itself,
                    can then be moved. Thin straw-coloured paper, such as is used for biscuit bags,
                    may be conveniently employed by travellers unable to carry a quantity of
                    bibulous paper. It offers the advantage of fitting closely to thick-stemmed
                    specimens, and of rapidly drying. A light but strong portfolio, to which
                    pressure by means of straps can be applied, and a few quires of this paper, if
                    the paper be changed night and morning, will be usually sufficient to dry all
                    except very succulent plants. When a specimen is too large for one sheet, and it
                    is necessary, in order to show its habit, &amp;c., to dry the whole of it, it
                    may be divided into two or three portions, and each placed on a separate sheet
                    for drying. Specimens may be judged to be dry when they no longer cause a cold
                    sensation when applied to the cheek, or assume a rigidity not evident in the
                    earlier stages of preparation.</p>
                <p>Each class of flowerless or cryptogamie plants requires special treatment for the
                    herbarium.</p>
                <p>Marine algae are usually mounted on tough smooth white cartridge paper in the
                    following manner. Growing specimens of good colour and in fruit are if possible
                    selected, and cleansed as much as practicable from adhering foreign particles,
                    either in the sea or a rocky pool. Some species rapidly change colour, and cause
                    the decay of any others with which they come in contact. This is especially the
                    case with the <hi rend="italic">Ectοcarpi,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dcsmarestiae,</hi> and a few others, which should therefore be brought home in
                    a separate vessel. In mounting, the specimen is floated out in a flat white dish
                    containing sea-water, so that foreign matter may be detected, and a piece of
                    paper of suitable size is placed under it, supported either by the fingers of
                    the left hand or by a palette. It is then pinned, in order clearly to show the
                    mode of branching, and is spread out as naturally as possible with the right
                    hand. For this purpose a bone knitting-needle answers well for the coarse
                    species, and a camel’s-hair pencil for the more delicate ones. The paper with
                    the specimen is then carefully removed from the water by sliding it over the
                    edge of the dish so as to drain it as much as possible. If during this process
                    part of the fronds run together, the beauty of the specimen may be restored by
                    dipping the edge into water, so as to float out the part and allow it to subside
                    naturally on the paper. The paper, with the specimen upwards, is then laid on
                    bibulous paper for a few minutes to absorb as much as possible of the
                    superfluous moisture. When freed from excess of water it is laid on a sheet of
                    thick white blotting-paper, and a piece of smooth washed calico is placed upon
                    it (unwashed calico, on account of its “facing,” adheres to the sea-weed).
                    Another sheet of blotting-paper is then laid over it; and, a number of similar
                    specimens being formed into a pile, the whole is submitted to pressure, the
                    paper being changed every hour or two at first. The pressure is increased, and
                    the papers are changed less frequently as the specimens become dry, which
                    usually takes place in thirty-six hours. Some species, especially those of a
                    thick or leathery texture, contract so much in drying that without strong
                    pressure the edges of the paper become puckered. Other species of a gelatinous
                    nature, like <hi rend="italic">Nemaleon</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dtιdresnaia,</hi> may be allowed to dry on the paper, and need not be submitted
                    to pressure until they no longer present a gelatinous appearance. Large coarse
                    algae, such, for instance, as the <hi rend="italic">Fucaceoe</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Laminariae,</hi> do not readily adhere to paper, and require
                    soaking for some time in fresh water before being pressed. The less robust
                    species, such as <hi rend="italic">Sphacelaria scoparia,</hi> which do not
                    adhere well to paper, may be made to do so by brushing them over either with
                    milk carefully skimmed, or with a liquid formed by placing isinglass (∣ oz. )
                    and water (1⅜ oz.) in a wide-mouthed bottle, and the bottle in a small glue-pot
                    or saucepan containing cold water, heating until solution is effected, and. then
                    adding 1 oz. of rectified spirits of wine; the whole is next stirred together,
                    and when cold is kept in a stoppered bottle. For use, the mixture is warmed to
                    render it fluid, and applied by means of a camel’s-hair brush to the under side
                    of the specimen, which is then laid neatly on paper. For the more delicate
                    species, such as the <hi rend="italic">Callithamnia</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ectocarpi,</hi> it is an excellent plan to place a small fruiting fragment,
                    carefully floated out in water, on a slip of mica of the size of an ordinary
                    microscopical slide, and allow it to dry. The plant can then be at any time
                    examined under the microscope without injuring the mounted specimen. Many of the
                    fresh-water algae which form a mere crust, such as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ρalmella</hi><hi rend="italic">cruenta,</hi> may be placed in a vessel of
                    water, where after a time they float like a scum, the earthy matter settling
                    down to the bottom, and may then be mounted by slipping a piece of mica under
                    them and allowing it to dry. <hi rend="italic">Oscillatorice</hi> may be mounted
                    by laying a portion on a silver coin placed on a piece of paper in a plate, and
                    pouring in water until the edge of the coin is just covered. The alga by its own
                    peculiar movement will soon form a radiating circle, perfectly free from dirt,
                    around the coin, which may then be removed.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n751/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0751-0718"/>
                <p>There is considerable difficulty in removing mounted specimens of algae from
                    paper, and therefore a small portion preserved on mica should accompany each
                    specimen, enclosed for safety in a small envelope fastened at one corner of the
                    sheet of paper. Filamentous diatoms may be mounted like ordinary seaweeds, and,
                    as well as all parasitic algae, should whenever possible be allowed to remain
                    attached to a portion of the alga on which they grow, some species being almost
                    always found parasitical on particular plants. Ordinary diatoms and desmids may
                    be mounted on mica, as above described, by putting a portion in a vessel of
                    water and exposing it to sunlight, when they rise to the surface, and may be
                    thus removed comparatively free from dirt or impurity. Owing to their want of
                    adhesiveness, they arc, however, usually mounted on glass as microscopic slides,
                    either in glycerin jelly, Canada balsam, or some other suitable medium.</p>
                <p>Lichens are generally mounted on sheets of paper of the ordinary size, several
                    specimens from different localities being laid upon one sheet, each specimen
                    having been first placed on a small square of paper which is gummed on the
                    sheet, and which has the locality, date, name of collector, &amp;c., written
                    upon it. This mode has some disadvantages attending it: such sheets are
                    difficult to handle; the crustaceous species are liable to have their surfaces
                    rubbed; the foliaceous species become so compressed as to lose their
                    characteristic appearance; and the spaces between the sheets caused by the
                    thickness of the specimen permit the entrance of dust. A plan which has been
                    found to answer well is to arrange them in cardboard boxes, either with glass
                    tops or in sliding covers, in drawers—the name being placed outside each box,
                    and the specimens gummed into the boxes. Lichens for the herbarium should,
                    whenever possible, be sought for on a slaty or laminated rock, so as to procure
                    them on flat thin pieces of the same, suitable for mounting. Specimens on the
                    bark of trees require pressure until the bark is dry, lest they become curled;
                    and those growing on sand or friable soil, such as <hi rend="italic">Coniocybe
                    furfuracca,</hi> should be laid carefully on a layer of gum in the box in which
                    they are intended to be kept. Many lichens, such as the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Verrucarioe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Collcmaceoe,</hi> are found in the best
                    condition during the winter months. In mounting collemas it is advisable to let
                    the specimen become dry and hard, and then to separate a portion from adherent
                    mosses, earth, &amp;c., and mount it separately so as to show the branching of
                    the thallus. <hi rend="italic">Pcrtusariae</hi> should be represented by both
                    fruiting and sorediate specimens.</p>
                <p>The larger species of fungi, such as the <hi rend="italic">Agaricini</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Polyporei,</hi> &amp;c., are prepared for the herbarium by cutting
                    a slice out of the centre of the plant so as to show the outline of the pileus,
                    the attachment of the gills, and the character of the interior of the stem. The
                    remaining two halves of the pileus are then lightly pressed, as well as the
                    central slices, between bibulous paper until dry, and the whole is then
                    “poisoned,” and gummed on a sheet of paper in such a manner as to show the under
                    surface of the one and the upper surface of the other half of the pileus on the
                    same sheet. As it is impossible to preserve the natural colours of fungi, the
                    specimens should, whenever possible, be accompanied by a coloured drawing of the
                    plant. Microscopic fungi are usually preserved in envelopes, or simply attached
                    to sheets of paper, or mounted as microscopic slides. Those fungi which are of a
                    dusty nature, like the <hi rend="italic">Myxomycètes,</hi> may, like the
                    lichens, be preserved in small boxes, and arranged in drawers. Fungi under any
                    circumstances form the least satisfactory portion of an herbarium.</p>
                <p>Mosses when growing in tufts should be gathered just before the capsules have
                    become brown, divided into small flat portions, and pressed lightly in drying
                    paper. During this process the capsules ripen, and are thus obtained in a
                    perfect state. They are then preserved in envelopes attached to a sheet of paper
                    of the ordinary size, a single perfect specimen being washed, and spread out
                    near the envelope so as to show the habit of the plant. For attaching it to the
                    paper a strong mucilage of gum tragacanth, containing an eighth of its weight of
                    spirit of wine, answers best. If not preserved in an envelope the calyptra and
                    operculum are very apt to fall off and become lost. Scale-mosses are mounted in
                    the same way, or may be floated out in water like sea-weeds, and dried in white
                    blotting paper under strong pressure before gumming on paper, but are best
                    mounted as microscopic slides, care being taken to show the stipules. The
                    specimens should be collected when the capsules are just appearing above or in
                    the colesule or calyx; if kept in a damp saucer they soon arrive at maturity,
                    and can then be mounted in better condition, the frait-stalks being too fragile
                    to bear carriage in a botanical tin case without injury.</p>
                <p>Of the <hi rend="italic">Gharaceae</hi> many are so exceedingly brittle that it
                    is best to float them out like sea-weeds, except the prickly species, which may
                    be carefully laid out on bibulous paper, and when dry fastened on sheets of
                    white paper by means of gummed strips. Care should be taken in collecting charae
                    to secure, in the case of dioecious species, specimens of both forms, and also
                    to get when possible the roots of those species on which, the small granular
                    starchy bodies or gemmae are found, as in <hi rend="italic">C. fragifcra.</hi>
                    Portions of the fructification may be preserved in small envelopes attached to
                    the sheets.</p>
                <p>See Bentham, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Linn. Soc. Bond.,</hi> 1869-70, p. xlvi.;
                    Johann Nave, <hi rend="italic">Handy Book io the Collection and Preparation of
                    FrcshwatcΙ and Marine</hi><hi rend="italic">Algae,</hi> &amp;c., Lond.; G.
                    Kainann, <hi rend="italic">Das Herbarium,</hi> Berlin, and Lasègue’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Musée botanique de Μ. Benjamin Dclcsscrt,</hi> Paris, 1845. (E. Μ.
                    H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
