<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0754-0721-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERBERT, George (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    721)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n3s">Pulleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kw6x">Flowers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s220">Elixirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808921">Anglicans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071809">Porches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n754/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERBERT, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>
                    (1593-1633), one of the best of English religious poets, was born near the town
                    of Montgomery on the 3d of April 1593. He was a brother of Lord Herbert of
                    Cherbury, noticed below. Educated privately till the age of twelve, he was then
                    sent to Westminster School, and in 1608 he became a student at Trinity College,
                    Cambridge, where he was made B.A. in 1611, M.A. and major fellow of the college
                    in 1615, and orator for the university in 1619. In his capacity as orator he was
                    several times brought into contact with King James. About the same time also he
                    appeared as the champion of Anglicanism against Andrew Melville, the famous
                    Scotch Presbyterian. He numbered among his friends Dr Donne, Sir Henry Wotton,
                    Izaak Walton, Bishop Andrewes, and Francis Bacon, who consulted Herbert about
                    several of his works, and dedicated to him his translation of the Psalms. During
                    his youth he was a courtier, dancing attendance on King James, and “enjoying his
                    genteel humour for clothes”; and the king rewarded his attentions by the gift of
                    a sinecure worth £120 a year. The death of his patrons the duke of Richmond, the
                    marquis of Hamilton, and King James, approaching ill-health, and the influence
                    of his mother finally induced him, not without a struggle, to take holy orders.
                    In July 1626 he was appointed prebendary of Layton Ecclesia, in the county of
                    Huntingdon. Shortly before his induction (1630) to the parsonage of Bemerton,
                    near Salisbury, he married Miss Jane Danvers after three days’ acquaintance. Mr
                    Danvers had been set on the marriage for a long time, and had often spoken of
                    his daughter Jane to Herbert, and “so much commended Mr Herbert to her, that
                    Jane became so much a Platonic as to fall in love with Mr Herbert unseen.” The
                    story of the poet’s life at Bemerton, as told by Walton, is one of the most
                    exquisite pictures in literary biography. He devoted much time to explaining the
                    meaning of the various parts of the PrayerBook, and held services twice every
                    day, at which many of the parishioners attended, and some “let their plough rest
                    when Mr Herbert’s saints-bell rung to praise, that they might also offer their
                    devotions to God with him.” Next to Christianity itself he loved the English
                    Church. He was passionately fond of music, and usually went twice a week to
                    attend the cathedral service at Salisbury. Walton illustrates Herbert’s kindness
                    to the poor by many touching anecdotes. He had not been three years in Bemerton
                    when he succumbed to ill-health. He died in 1633.</p>
                <p>Herbert’s works are— <hi rend="italic">The Temple</hi> (1631); a few
                    miscellaneous poems; a collection of proverbs entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Jacula</hi><hi rend="italic">Prudentum</hi> (1640); and <hi rend="italic">The
                    Country Parson,</hi> which did not appear till 1652. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Temple</hi> is a collection of religious poems marked by unity of sentiment and
                    inspiration. The chief faults of the book are obscurity, verbal conceits, and a
                    forced ingenuity which shows itself in grotesque puns, odd metres, and
                    occasional want of taste. In spite of these drawbacks, the quaint beauty of
                    Herbert’s style and his genuine poetical feeling give <hi rend="italic">The
                    Temple</hi> a high place in literature. The following poems are the gems of the
                    collection “The Church Porch,” “The Agony,” “Sin,” “Sunday,” “Virtue,” “Man,”
                    “The British Church,” “The Quip,” “The Collar,” “The Pulley,” “The Flower,”
                    “Aaron,” and “The Elixir.” The finest of all is his poem on “Man,” which is
                    Miltonic in its sublimity of conception, and shows how poets, in their loftier
                    moods, often anticipate the discoveries of science and the most far-reaching
                    speculations of philosophy. Herbert and Kehle are the poets of Anglican
                    theology. No book is fuller of devotion vθ the Church of England than <hi
                    rend="italic">The Temple.</hi> No poem in our language exhibits more of the
                    spirit of true Christianity. Every page is marked by transparent sincerity, and
                    reflects the beautiful character of “holy George Herbert.”</p>
                <p>Among recent editions of Herbert’s works the following may be mentioned :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Works in Prose and Verse,</hi> with life by Izaak Walton, and
                    notes by 8. T. Coleridge, 1846; Gilfillan’s edition, in his “Library of the
                    British Poets,” 1853; Willmott’s edition, 1854; Professor Nichol’s edition,
                    1863; and the Aldine edition by the Rev. Dr A. B. Grosart. For further
                    information consult Walton’s <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >England's Antiphon,</hi> by George Macdonald, 1871.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
