<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0641-0608-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HECATE (9th edition, volume 11, page 608)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819275">Asterias</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:998476">Light</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944180">Goddesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914383">Epithets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n641/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HECATE</label>, a Greek goddess who is never mentioned in
                    Homer, but is of great importance in other parts of the literature as well as in
                    religious observance. The name Hecatos, the masculine corresponding form, is a
                    frequent <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n642/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0642-0609"/> epithet of Apollo; and though the word <hi
                    rend="italic">eκdτη</hi> is never used exactly as an epithet of Artemis, yet
                    this suggests a close relationship between the two goddesses, which an
                    examination of their functions fully confirms. Their character and attributes
                    stamp both as moon-goddesses. In fact, though often distinguished from Artemis,
                    yet at other times Hecate is identified with her. The worship of Hecate seems to
                    have flourished especially among the wilder tribes of Greek nationality, in
                    Samothrace, Thessaly, and elsewhere; she has, however, been received into the
                    Pantheon of the more civilized Greek races, probably on account of her close
                    resemblance to Artemis; and this is doubtless the meaning of Hesiod’s statement
                    <hi rend="italic">lfΓheoa.,</hi> 423) that she alone of all the Titanic powers
                    was left undisturbed in her honours by Zeus. The parentage of Hecate is
                    variously given. Hesiod names her father Perses (a word connected with Perseus,
                    Persephone, &amp;c., all of which denote powers of light) and her mother
                    Asteria, the starry sky of night. Zeus and Demeter, Zeus and Hera, &lt;fcc., are
                    also named as her parents. Her chief prerogatives or functions are the
                    following.</p>
                <p>(1) She is the chief goddess who presides over magic arts and spells, for all
                    incantations naturally were performed by the light of the moon. Medea is in this
                    respect closely associated with her worship. See her prayer in Sophocles, <hi
                    rend="italic">Rhizοt.fr</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> In Theocr., <hi
                    rend="italic">Id.</hi> ii., where a woman’s incantation to bring back her
                    faithless lover is given, Hecate is constantly invoked. (2) She is a Chthonian
                    power, and is worshipped at the Stmothracian mysteries. She is then closely
                    connected with Demeter. Alone of the gods besides Helios, she witnessed the
                    abduction of Persephone, and, torch in hand (a natural symbol for the moon’s
                    light), she assisted Demeter in the search for her daughter <hi rend="italic"
                    >(IIym. Dem.,</hi> 45 <hi rend="italic">ff).</hi> She is obviously a by-forna of
                    Persephone, who as queen of the lower world is also the moon, the bride of the
                    sun, when at setting he has gone to the lower world. She rules as a terrible
                    power, Krataïs, among the shades <hi rend="italic">&lt;f)rph.,</hi> 48,
                    &amp;c.). (3) As δαδούχος,</p>
                <p>φώσφορος, <hi rend="italic">v7roλαp7rτeφα,</hi> she lights wanderers on their way
                    by night, and is therefore, along with Hermes, worshipped as patron of roads
                    under tire name tvoδ'α, At cross-roads she was the director, hence her name
                    τpιoδZτις, and probably also <hi rend="italic">τρίμορφος, τρνπρόσωπος,</hi>
                    &lt;fcc. Pillars called Hecataea, like the Hermae, stood, especially in Athens,
                    at cross-roads and door-ways. (4) She is the goddess of fertility, and, like
                    Artemis, presides especially over the birth and the youth of wild animals. As
                    the moon measures the months, the moon-goddess in all forms, as Artemis, Helena,
                    &lt;fcc., presides over birth. (5) It follows easily from the last that she
                    should be the goddess who gives wealth and power. Thus she is celebrated by
                    Hesiod (Z.c.). On the Acropolis at Athens Hecate Epipyrgidia, as protectress of
                    the citadel, had a shrine beside the temple of Victory. To Hecate dogs were
                    offered, also honey and black she-lambs, as black victims were offered to other
                    Chthonian deities. She was represented generally as a triple form, holding in
                    the six hands torches, with sometimes a snake, a key, a whip, or a dagger, often
                    with dogs standing beside her. The three heads support a basket, “kalathos,”
                    such as often adorns the statues of Artemis and Hera. The Hecataea also
                    generally represent her with three heads; occasionally, however, a single-formed
                    Hecate is found, still with torch or key in hand, and sometimes with crescent
                    moon on head.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
