<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0700-0667-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HENRY IV (9th edition, volume 11, page 667)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4p01z">Spires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130034">Spires</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n700/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HENRY IV</label>. (1050-1106), Holy Roman emperor, son of
                    Henry III., was born in 1050, and crowned German king at the age of four during
                    his father’s lifetime. After the death of Henry III. in 1056, the government was
                    undertaken by the empress Agnes, the young king’s mother. Henry III.’s vigorous
                    rule, while it had secured the prosperity of the nation as a whole, had excited
                    bitter discontent among the great nobles, and immediately after his death they
                    began to make attempts to recover some portion of the independence he had taken
                    from them. Agnes, who was of too refined a temperament to contend with them,
                    sought to win their support by important concessions; and the evil effects of a
                    feeble central authority were soon felt in every part of Germany. At last, in
                    1062, Anno, archbishop of Cologne, succeeded in gaining possession of the king
                    by enticing him on board a boat on the Rhine. Agnes then resigned her position,
                    and Anno ruled in her stead. He was a harsh, bigoted, aud despotic prelate, and
                    excited Henry’s bitter hatred by the sternness of his discipline. In Adalbert,
                    archbishop of Bremen, who was of an exactly opposite disposition,—gay, worldly,
                    and good-humoured,—Anno had an influential rival. This prelate was at first
                    entrusted with some share in the training of Henry, but ultimately completely
                    gained his affections and became his sole guardian. In his fifteenth year Henry
                    was declared, in accordance with the Ripuarian Code, to have reached his
                    majority, but the royal authority was really exercised by Adalbert, who aroused
                    the jealousy of the princes both by his splendid style of living and by his
                    opposition to their usurped powers. At a diet held in Tribur he was compelled to
                    yield the first place once more to Anno. Trained under these diverse influences
                    Henry became passionate and wilful; but he was endowed with considerable
                    intellectual gifts, and when thoroughly aroused could pursue an object with
                    unquenchable ardour. In order, if possible, to check the excesses of his private
                    life Anno caused him to marry Bertha, the daughter of the margrave of Susa, to
                    whom he had for some time been betrothed. At first he regarded her with strong
                    dislike; but after she had borne him a son in 1071 she succeeded in gaining his
                    affections, and was afterwards his most trusted friend and companion.</p>
                <p>Henry’s reign was one of the most troubled in German history. His chief anxieties
                    began in consequence of Otto of Nordheim, duke of Bavaria, being charged with an
                    intention of murdering him. Otto was declared to have forfeited his titles, and
                    his lands were seized and overrun. Supported by Duke Magnus of Saxony he
                    rebelled, but both princes were quickly subdued. A new rebellion was organized
                    by Otto of Nordheim, who suddenly, at the head of 60,000 men, appeared before
                    the Harzburg, a strong Saxon fortress in which Henry resided. He escaped, but he
                    was looked upon so coldly by the princes that he found it expedient to yield
                    nearly all the demands of his enemies.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n701/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0701-0668"/>
                <p>An opportunity of revenge was, however, created for him by the violence of a body
                    of peasants, who destroyed a chapel connected with the Harzburg and violated the
                    graves of the king’s brother and infant son. He had then no difficulty in
                    obtaining an imperial army, and after defeating the rebels at Hohenburg in 1075,
                    he imposed on them his own terms, and seemed to be on the point of asserting the
                    ascendency which had been exercised by Henry III.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile Hildebrand had become pope as Gregory VII., and had already indicated
                    his design of making the papacy supreme over all earthly authorities. Henry
                    appealed to him to degrade those prelates who had associated themselves with the
                    rebels. Instead of responding favourably to the appeal, Gregory called upon the
                    king to answer to certain charges preferred against him by his subjects. Failing
                    to realize how much power the papacy had acquired through the reforms effected
                    by his father, Henry summoned a council of German prelates at Worms in 1076, and
                    declared the pope deposed. The reply was a sentence of excommunication. Henry’s
                    adherents so rapidly fell away that a reconciliation with the pope was soon
                    perceived to be absolutely necessary. Escaping from his enemies he crossed the
                    Alps in the depth of winter, accompanied only by his wife and child and by a few
                    faithful attendants. The nobles of Lombardy were not unwilling to take up his
                    cause, but he preferred to hurry forward to the castle of Canossa, where Gregory
                    was residing with his friend the Countess Matilda. There occurred the famous
                    scene in which Henry, the highest of secular potentates, stood for three days in
                    the courtyard of the castle, clad in the shirt of a penitent, and entreating to
                    be admitted to the pope’s presence. No historical incident has more profoundly
                    impressed the imagination of the Western world. It marked the highest point
                    reached by papal authority, and presents a vivid picture of the awe inspired
                    during the Middle Ages by the supernatural powers supposed to be wielded by the
                    church.</p>
                <p>The bτn was removed; nevertheless the German princes elected Duke Rudolf of
                    Swabia as their king, and they were soon openly supported by the pope, who
                    resented Henry’s persistent opposition to his great scheme for the deliverance
                    of the clergy from the system of feudal investiture. Henry renewed his sentence
                    of deposition against Gregory, and raised Guibert, archbishop of Ravenna, to the
                    papacy as Clement III. After the death of the antiking Rudolf in 1080 he went to
                    uphold his rights in Italy, and in 1084 he gained possession of Rome, where
                    Clement III. crowned him emperor. In Germany Count Hermann of Luxembourg had
                    been chosen as successor to Rudolf, and in 1085 he defeated Henry near Würzburg;
                    but in 1087 he voluntarily resigned his position, and soon afterwards died. A
                    third anti-king, Margrave Eckbert of Meissen, also died in 1089; and had Henry
                    had no enemies outside his native kingdom there would then have been peace. But
                    Victor III. and Urban II., the successors of Gregory VII. (who died in 1085),
                    continued to oppose him, and in 1090 he was obliged to proceed to Italy for the
                    third timeto support Clement III., his own antipope. Whilst engaged in this
                    struggle he learned that his son Conrad had been induced by the papal party to
                    rebel against him. Stunned by this unexpected blow, the tired emperor withdrew
                    in disgust to a remote fortress, where he remained inactive for several years.
                    In 1096 he recovered his energy, returned to Germany, and by timely concessions
                    managed to overcome the opposition of his leading enemies. A diet at Mainz
                    decided that Conrad had forfeited his right to the throne, and his brother Henry
                    was proclaimed the emperor’s successor. Pope Urban II., the antipope Clement HL,
                    and Conrad, all died within two years, and Henry had reason to hope that he
                    would be able to end his life in quiet. But Paschal II., pursuing the policy of
                    his predecessors, once more excommunicated the emperor, who was driven to
                    despair by the fact of his son Henry putting himself at the head of the pope’s
                    supporters. The aged monarch, deceived by false promises, fell into his hands,
                    and was detained as a prisoner. He ultimately fled to Liege, where he might
                    still have been able to bring an army together; but in 1106 he was relieved from
                    his heavy cares by death. The bishop of Liege buried him with a splendour
                    becoming his position; but his enemies carried the body to Spires, where it was
                    laid in an unconsecrated chapel; and it was not properly interred until, after a
                    delay of five years, he was delivered from the ban of excommunication.</p>
                <p>Henry holds an honourable position in history because, notwithstanding many
                    personal faults, he resisted the excessive pretensions both of the papacy and of
                    the ambitious feudal lords of Germany. He was unable, however, to make good his
                    claims. Centuries passed before the secular power of the Romish see was
                    seriously weakened, and amid the confused struggles of the time the princes
                    obtaine 1 secure possession of rights which they had formerly held by an
                    uncertain tenure.</p>
                <p>See Giesebreeht, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Dcτιtschen</hi><hi rend="italic">Kaiserzeit</hi> (3d ed., vol. iii., part 1,
                    Brunswick, 1869); Floto, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >IV.</hi><hi rend="italic">und sein Zeitalter-</hi> (2 vols., Stuttgart, 1855);
                    Minckwitz, <hi rend="italic">Die Busse Kaiser</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Heinrichs</hi><hi rend="italic">IV.</hi><hi rend="italic">zu Canossa vor dem
                    Papste Gregor VII.</hi> (2d ed., Leipsic, 1875). (J. SI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
