<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0396-0377-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAJJI KHALFA (9th edition, volume 11, page 377)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876647">Contentment</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023582">Mirrors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w38446">Contentment</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43r0ps53">Mirrors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n396/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAJJI KHALFA</label>. Mustafa ’bn Abdallah, Kâtib Che-lepi
                    (c. 1600-1658), commonly known as Haji (or Hadji) Khalfa (more properly Hâjji
                    Khalifah), was the author of an encyclopaedia in Arabic of Oriental biography
                    and bibliography. He was born at Constantinople about the beginning of the 17th
                    century of the Christian era, and after passing the earlier part of his life in
                    military service, studied under Cadhizâdeh Effendi, a learned doctor at the
                    Ottoman capital, and made great progress in Arabic literary and linguistic
                    studies. In June 1633 he again accompanied the army to Syria, but while the
                    troops were in winter quarters at Aleppo, he himself performed the pilgrimage to
                    Mecca, whence he took the cognomen of Hajji, “Pilgrim.” Returning in 1635 to
                    Constantinople, he resumed his literary studies, and occupied himself with
                    visiting all the libraries and book shops, and compiling an inventory of their
                    contents, together with notices of the authors of the various works. In 1638 he
                    attended the lectures of Sheikh A’raj Mustafazadah, whom he proposed to himself
                    as an example to imitate in his future literary career. Besides his purely
                    literary studies he also devoted himself assiduously to the sciences, and became
                    well versed in logic, geometry, geography, astronomy, and the like. Nor were
                    medicine and the occult sciences neglected by him, so that there were few of the
                    subjects treated of in the works which he delighted to describe with which he
                    was not more or less technically acquainted. About 1648 he was appointed
                    assessor (khalifa) to the principal of the imperial college, whence he took the
                    title of Khalfa, by which, with the prefix of Hajji (Pilgrim), he is commonly
                    designated. He died in September 1658.</p>
                <p>Besides his great <hi rend="italic">Bibliographical Lexicon,</hi> he composed
                    several other works, chiefly geographical and historical; of these the best
                    known are <hi rend="italic">Τakιcimuιtawdrikh</hi> or “Chronological Tables,”
                    <hi rend="italic">Tuhfat cl KubArfi asf(iri</hi><hi rend="italic">Bahàr,</hi> a
                    work on the science of naval warfare, <hi rend="italic">Jchân Numà</hi> or
                    “Mirror of the World,” and one or two treatises on miscellaneous literary
                    subjects. The language in which he wrote is Arabic, and the style is that which
                    the nature of his studies would <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n397/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0397-0378"/> lead usto expect,—correct and grammatical, fairly
                    classical, and abounding in technical terms and phraseology. Of the amount of
                    his learning and of his indefatigable application to study his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lexicon</hi> is a lasting memorial. There is scarcely a work in the whole range
                    of Arabic, Persian, and Turkish literature, no matter on what subject or
                    science, but it will be found described in this vast encyclopaedia, with every
                    piece of collateral information which it was possible to procure or useful to
                    mention. When we remember that it is the Oriental habit to give fancy titles to
                    books that often in no way indicate the nature of their contents, and that one
                    is often obliged to read through pages of irrelevant matter before arriving
                    either at the author’s name or the subject of the work, the labour expended on
                    the production of Hajji Khalfa’s book appears absolutely incredible. The work
                    has always enjoyed a well-deserved reputation in the East, and has attracted the
                    attention of many European scholars, but we need only mention here the
                    magnificent edition in seven thick 8vo volumes by the eminent Arabic scholar
                    Gustavus Fluegel published at Leipsic in 1835- 1858 for the Oriental Translation
                    Fund of Great Britain and Ireland. This edition is accompanied by a Latin
                    page-for-page translation, indices, and notes, and is an indispensable adjunct
                    to every library in which a collection of Oriental books is found. The Arabic
                    title of the lexicon is <hi rend="italic">Kashfu zzunιin 'an Asdmt 'l Kutub
                    wa</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">lfundn,</hi><hi rend="superscript"> ,f</hi> The
                    removal of doubts concerning the names of books and concerning sciences,” and
                    the Latin title adopted by Fluegel is <hi rend="italic">Lexicon
                    Bibliographicum</hi><hi rend="italic">et Encyclopoedicum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Haji</hi><hi rend="italic">Khalfae.</hi> After a short preface and an
                    introduction of five chapters comes the encyclopaedia proper, the articles in
                    which are arranged in the alphabetical order of the names of the works
                    described. The title of each work is given, a concise account of its contents,
                    the name of the author, and the date, when this could be ascertained; and in
                    many cases the initial phrase is also added to facilitate its identification.
                    Besides the general bibliography, Fluegel’s edition contains several appendices
                    of great value to Oriental scholars and librarians. Copious notes and indices
                    complete this splendid edition, one of the finest monuments of Oriental learning
                    which Europe has produced.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
