<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0712-0679-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HERA (9th edition, volume 11, page 679)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1243607">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dj11">Cow</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40v89h15">Zoology</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882039">Cows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term ref="fast:995592">Legends</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n712/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HERA</label>, a word of which many different derivations have
                    been proposed, is the name of a Greek goddess, corresponding to the Latin Juno,
                    who according to the conventional type is the wife of Zeus and queen among the
                    gods of Olympus. In the literature of the Greeks Hera fills a very conspicuous
                    place—the strong, haughty, and rebellious character, full of intense hatreds and
                    likings, which was associated with her, made her a picturesque and dramatic
                    figure. According to this conception of her, she was daughter of Cronus and
                    Rhea, and at once sister and wife of Zeus. She was always the bitter enemy of
                    all the heroines who were the successive objects of her husband’s love, and her
                    persecution of them and of their children often forms the theme of poets from
                    the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> (xxiii. 119) downwards. This type, which is the
                    familiar one in all literature, bad never any real existence in religion; but
                    had been gradually elaborated by poets fron» the actual deity worshipped in
                    various parts of Greece, and from the legends transmitted to the Greeks from
                    earlier races.</p>
                <p>The most characteristic and fundamental point in the worship of Hera is the iepoς
                    <hi rend="italic">γάμος,</hi> her marriage with Zeus; and from this any
                    explanation of the conception involved in the goddess must start. Again in Greek
                    legend we learn that a close connexion exists between Hera and the cow, and that
                    probably she was originally thought to have the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n713/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0713-0680"/> form of a cow. These facts at once direct us to
                    the ancient Aryan idea, described in detail by Gubernatis <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Zoolog. Mythoi.,</hi> i), that the divine power as the origin of all life is
                    embodied in a pair of gods male and female, whose fertility leads to the
                    conception of them as a bull and a cow. This pair, the bull and the cow, appear
                    in various fantastic developments in Greek legend. For example, Zeus himself in
                    the form of a bull carries off Europa; and we learn from Hesychius that Europia
                    is an epithet of Hera. Looking at the matter from this point of view, we find
                    that the question so much disputed among mythologers, whether the naturalistic
                    conception out of which the Greek goddess has developed be earth or moon, is a
                    mere matter of words, and that there is no real discrepancy between the two
                    views. The free and vague conceptions of primitive men refuse to be shut into
                    the precise circumscribed terminology of modern thought. Ideas which to us are
                    very different were once expressed by the same root (see Curtius, <hi
                    rend="italic">Grunds.,</hi> iii. 284, No. 415). Thus we have in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pig Veda,</hi> vi. 51, 5, a clear trace of the view so common in
                    all mythologies, whether in the theogony of Hesiod or of the New-Zealanders,
                    that Heaven and Earth are the primitive pair of deities, parents of all
                    existence and first of the gods. This view is of peculiar importance in old
                    Roman religion <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> Schwegler, <hi rend="italic">Pom.
                    Gesch.,</hi> i. 328, 422, &lt;fcc.), and also among the older Pelasgic tribes of
                    Greece. But this same divine power the primitive Aryans beheld in all the great
                    operations of nature; in each they saw the prototype of all earthly works, and
                    in seeking here the origin of life, they found it in the same divine pair, the
                    bull and the cow. In particular, the various alternations of light and darkness
                    appealed to their minds most strongly, and occupy great port of their mythology.
                    In the transitions between light and darkness, and especially in the struggle
                    between night and day, the idea of a pair is not so prominent; and in legends
                    the marriage of moon and sun does not figure very conspicuously. Yet we
                    sometimes find the marriage of the moon and sun described exactly in the way of
                    this iepos γάρ,ος. In <hi rend="italic">Pig Veda,</hi> x. 85, it is the type of
                    all earthly marriage (see Weber, <hi rend="italic">Ind. Stud.,</hi> v. 178). A
                    Slavonic story makee the marriage of moon and sun annual: they part every winter
                    and meet again in the first days of spring; and a Lettish song makes the
                    marriage of moon and sun in spring (Mannhardt in <hi rend="italic">Zft. f.
                    Ethnoh,</hi> 1875, p. 316). The moon too is often symbolized as a cow. The
                    mystic union takes place in the spring when life returns to the earth, and the
                    voice of the cuckoo is heard in the land. Hence in the legend Zeus, enamoured of
                    his sister Hera, is said to have flown to her in the form of a cuckoo dripping
                    wet, and to have been in pity received into her bosom. In various parts of
                    Greece where traces of the ruder tribes are strongest, there remains a coarser
                    conception of this union, and in the popular accounts the marriage customs of
                    the country are reflected (see Weicker, <hi rend="italic">Gr. G'otterl.,</hi> i.
                    364∕ ’.). Lectum in the Trojan Ida and Ocha in Euboea, on the summits of which
                    this union is placed by the legends of the countries, received their names from
                    it. As we might expect, this idea is too purely naturalistic to form any part of
                    the moral Olympian religion. Hera appears there as the wife of Zeus, but all
                    deeper meaning has disappeared. The old tale remains in the mythological
                    legends, which always clung as a degrading appendage to this religion, and we
                    find it in Homer <hi rend="italic">(Il.,</hi> xiv. 294) transformed into an
                    incident of the Trojan war. In the popular religion, however, Hera, as first the
                    virgin, then the sacred bride, and finally the lawful wife of Zeus and the
                    patron of all marriage, is a very prominent figure. Every year the festival of
                    Hera was celebrated with special reference to this union in Argos, Samos, Elis,
                    Plataea, and many other parts of Greece. The festival took place in a month
                    named <hi rend="italic">Vαpηλai)v</hi> at Athens, Ήραίοςΐη some other parts of
                    Greece. Hence we have such epithets of Hera as <hi rend="italic">Νύμφη,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">wμ-φeυομevη, τeλPα, γaμηλ</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">a;</hi> and the
                    bridal veil is one of her most frequent attributes. Hera was married to Zeus in
                    early youth, and knew no other marriage. Hence she is the patron goddess of all
                    married women, the protectress of the sanctity of marriage; and she demands the
                    utmost purity from her votaries. In this respect Hera approaches closely to
                    Demeter Thesmophoros. As the winter is a time of barrenness and separation, so
                    we have in Arcadian, Argive, and Samian legend the angry Hera, the widow Hera,
                    separated from her husband.</p>
                <p>Other points in Hera again point directly to the moon. Like all other forms of
                    the moon-goddess (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Hecate),</hi> she presided over
                    child-birth, and under the epithet <hi rend="italic">elλdθvιa</hi> was invoked
                    by women in labour. This idea arises from the moon’s use as measurer of time and
                    numberer of the months. Then the epithet became gradually developed as a
                    daughter, or set of daughters, of Hera, named Eileithyiae. Beauty is another
                    characteristic of all moon-goddesses, and of Hera also. In her festival at
                    Lemnos prizes were assigned after a contest to the most beautiful woman. Large
                    eyes were part of the artistic type, and <hi rend="italic">βοωπιs</hi> is one of
                    her most constant epithets in literature.</p>
                <p>Eubcea, the very word being an epithet of the goddess, was one of the chief seats
                    of the worship of Hera. So in Boeotia, her temples both at Thespiae and at
                    Plataea were famous. In the <hi rend="italic">Iliad,</hi> Argos, Sparta, and
                    Mycenae are the cities which she specially protects and loves. Argos was always
                    one of the chief seats of her worship, and the Heraion there was one of the
                    chief temples of Greece. At Olympia also was a very ancient temple, the Heraion,
                    the ruins of which have been recently brought to view by the German exploring
                    expedition. At the Lacinian promontory Hera was the patroness of the union first
                    of the Achaean cities and afterwards of a wider circle of the Greek colonies.
                    But the Hera of Samos was perhaps the most famous and most characteristic
                    appearance of the goddess. There the Greek goddess was amalgamated with another,
                    who was worshipped by the kindred tribes among whom the Greeks settled, and who
                    is clearly the same as the Artemis of Ephesus or Clazomenae; and so on coins of
                    Samos we find Hera standing with the sun and moon on either side of her head,
                    exactly like Artemis on coins of Ephesus.</p>
                <p>We find such rude images of Hera as a plank at Samos, or a branch at Thespiae. A
                    very ancient statue by Smilis stood in her temple at Samos; the goddess, veiled,
                    stood erect, clad in a long chiton, holding in each of her outstretched hands a
                    <hi rend="italic">φιάλη.</hi> In the earlier vase-paintings she is hardly to be
                    distinguished from Artemis. She appears, just like Artemis, carrying torch and
                    bow, and wearing the kalathos or the Stephanos; and several figures which others
                    consider to be Artemis, are by Overbeck explained as Hera. In representations of
                    the Judgment of Paris there is often nothing to distinguish her from Aphrodite.
                    Her characteristic symbols are the veil or sceptre, and she often carries a
                    fruit. Numerous vase-paintings, representing a bridal procession, which Forster
                    <hi rend="italic">{Ζcτιs</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Hera's</hi><hi rend="italic">Hochzeit)</hi> believes to represent the iepδs <hi
                    rend="italic">yaμos,</hi> are by Jahn and Overbeck shown to be an earthly
                    marriage escorted. by deities. Overbeck <hi rend="italic">{Hera,</hi> p. 174)
                    maintains that only three certain representations of this scene exist. The
                    colossal statue by Polycletus in the Heraion at Argos showed her enthroned,
                    wearing the <hi rend="italic">στΐφάνη,</hi> holding in one hand a pomegranate
                    and in the other a sceptre, on the top of which was a cuckoo. There is no
                    evidence to determine what was the character of the face, nor what share it had
                    in determining the ideal type of Hera (Overbeck, Z.c., p. 51). The Farnese bust
                    at Naples represents a type more antique than the style of Polycletus.
                    Praxiteles made three great statues of Hera, at Megara, Mantinea, and Plataea.
                    The last, which represented Hera Teleia standing, is known to us by many
                    imitations in the Vatican and elsewhere. From the works of these two great
                    artists we may suppose that the highest type of Hera was elaborated in the
                    Athenian school about the middle of the 4th century, and in the famous bust of
                    the Villa Ludovisi it is probable that we have the actual work in which this
                    type was first attained. This bust, which has been often described, and
                    especially by Goethe, was probably once the head of a colossal seated statue.
                    (W. Μ. B A. ) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n714/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0714-0681"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
