<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0555-0524-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAVANA, Havannah, or Habana (9th edition, volume 11,
                    page 524)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205805">Cuba</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr4v">Box</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766779">Boxing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:884834">Cubans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837290">Boxing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837281">Boxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137272">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n555/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAVANA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Havannah</hi>, or <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></label>, more fully San Cristobal de la Havana, the
                    capital of Cuba, and one of the principal seats of commerce in the New World, is
                    situated on the northern coast of the island in 23° 9' 24" N. lat. and 82° 22'
                    35" W. long. From the sea it presents a picturesque appearance. The background
                    is indeed tame; but the long lines of fortifications, the church-towers, and the
                    shipping relieve the somewhat tawdry effect of tho gaily coloured houses. Though
                    the walls, completed in 1702, have been almost entirely demolished since 1863,
                    it is still usual to speak of the intramural and the extramural city. The
                    former, lying close to the harbour, has streets of the narrowest possible
                    description consistent with the existence of wheel traffic. The latter has been
                    laid out on a spacious plan, with wide thoroughfares frequently fringed with
                    trees. Most of the houses are built of solid stone and have flat roofs, after
                    the manner in vogue in southern Spain, and, as the erection of wooden buildings
                    has been illegal since 1772, it is only in the suburban districts that they are
                    at all common. The lavish use of white marble in the decoration both of shops
                    and dwelling-houses is one of the peculiarities of the popular taste; and it is
                    worthy of remark that, though the native quarries would supply what is wanted,
                    the marble is brought from Genoa. Cafés, restaurants, clubs, and casinos are
                    both exceedingly numerous and largely frequented, forming a good indication of
                    that general absence of domestic life among the white population which surprises
                    the European visitant. Havana is still, as of yore, a city of smells and noises.
                    There is no satisfactory cleaning of the streets or draining of the subsoil, and
                    the harbour is visibly rendered foul by the impurities of the town. Λ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> ictorias,—of which it is the Cuban boast that there
                    are 6000,—volantes, and other vehicles are driven through the thoroughfares with
                    the utmost recklessness; and tramways and railways in the American fashion
                    contribute to the confusion.</p>
                <p>The principal defences of Havana are the Castillo de la Punta, to the west of the
                    harbour entrance, the Castillo del Morro and San Carlos de la Cabana to the
                    east, the Santo Domingo de Atares, which lies at the head of the western arm of
                    the bay and commands both the city and the neighbourhood, and the Castillo del
                    Principe, situated on an eminence to the west, and forming the terminus of the
                    great Paseo Militär. El Morro, as it is popularly called, was first erected in
                    1589, but additions have been frequently made. La Punta, a much smaller fort, is
                    of the same period. The castle of Atares dates from about 1763, when the Con le
                    de Ricla was governor of the island. Cabana, which alone has accommodation for
                    4000 men, fronts the bay for a distance of 800 yards, and is defended on the
                    land side by three bastions. To the east there lies a smaller fort, No. 4, or
                    San Diego, on a hill about 100 feet high.</p>
                <p>Of the churches in the city, which number more than a score, the most noteworthy
                    is the cathedral erected in 1724 by the Jesuits. Externally it is plain though
                    symmetrical; but within it has richly frescoed walls, a floor of variegated
                    marble, and costly altars. In the wall of the chancel, a second-rate medallion
                    and a sorrier inscription distinguish the tomb of Columbus, whose remains were
                    removed thither in 1796. It is enough to mention the churches of San Juan de
                    Dios, dating from 1573, Santa Catalina (1658), San Agostino (1608), and San
                    Felipe, which possesses a large library. Of monasteries and nunneries there is
                    of course no lack; and the same may be said of charitable institutions. The most
                    important of the seven hospitals is the Real Casa de Beneficencia, founded about
                    1790, and containing an orphan asylum, a home for vagrants, a lunatic asylum,
                    and an infirmary.</p>
                <p>Besides the university established in 1728, the city possesses a theological
                    seminary, a military school, and a school of art. The governor and the bishop
                    have their respective palaces, the former a large yellow stone building in the
                    Plaza de Armas; a large prison, erected in 1771, capable of receiving 500
                    inmates, and with barracks for a regiment, forms a striking object in the
                    general view of the city; and among the other public buildings are the exchange
                    (El Muelle), the custom-house (formerly the church of San Francisco), and the
                    maestranza or headquarters of the artillery. Of the theatres, which have s’ill
                    to compete with the bull-ring and the cock-pit, the most important is the Tacon,
                    erected in 1838, and capable of accommodating about 3000 persons. The
                    promenades, drives, and public gardens form a notable feature of Havana: it is
                    sufficient to mention the Plaza de Armas, with a statue of Ferdinand VII.; the
                    Prado or Paseo Isabel, a long and handsome boulevard laid out in the 18th
                    century; the Campo del Marte or drill-park; the Parque Isabel, the Paseo Tacon,
                    the botanical gardens, and the gardens of Los Molinos, the suburban residence of
                    the captain-general. The palm-tree avenues of Los Molinos are unusually fine.
                    Along the borders of the bay there are several fine embankments, of which the
                    best is perhaps that called either the Salon O’Donnell or the Alamada de Paula.
                    In the coral rock of the coast sea-baths have been excavated, so that the
                    bathers may run no risk from the sharks; each apartment is about 12 feet square
                    and 6 or 8 feet deep, and the water enters by two port-holes. The city is
                    supplied with water from the river Chorrera by an aqueduct (Canal Isabel II.)
                    constructed by Antonelli under Philip II., and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n556/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0911-0556-0525"/> the number of fountains is considerable. The
                    markets—-of which the most noteworthy are the Mercado de Cristina, erected in
                    1836, and the Mercado de Tacon or Plaza de Vapor—are abundantly stocked with
                    fruits and vegetables. Several of the suburban villages (e.y., Chorrera,
                    Guanaba-conda) are attractive places of resort.</p>
                <p>The bay of Havana makes one of the finest harbours in the world, easy of access,
                    spacious enough to contain about 1000 large vessels, deep enough to allow them
                    to come close up to the wharves, and, except in the case of a hurricane, well
                    protected on all sides. The entrance, encumbered by neither bar nor rock, is 980
                    feet wide and 4200 feet long. Within, the bay breaks up into three distinct
                    arms, named respectively Marimalena or Regia Bay, Guasabacoa Bay, and El Fondo
                    or Bay of Atares. The wharves are well built, and a good floating dock is
                    maintained by a private company. On the left hand of the entrance stands a lofty
                    lighthouse tower.</p>
                <p>In 1865 1950 vessels entered with a burthen of 686,644 tons; in 1873 2194 vessels
                    with a burthen of 921,632 tons; and in the first six months of 1878 741 vessels
                    with a burthen of 449,785 tons. The average number of vessels annually in the
                    ten years from 1864 to 1873 was 1981 (771,196 tons), and of this average 647
                    (324,373 tons) were American, 689 (190,231 tons) Spanish, 384 (131,216 tons)
                    British, 55 (45,218 tons) French, 55 (18,200 tons) Norwegian, and 32 (31,693
                    tons) German.</p>
                <p>In spite of high tariffs and civil wars, and the competition of Matanzas,
                    Cardenas, Cienfuego, and other Cuban ports opened to foreign trade in modern
                    times, the commerce of Havana continues to increase. As indicated by the
                    statistics just quoted, the chief foreign customers are Britain and the United
                    States; but, while the latter are gradually taking a greater proportion of the
                    trade, the British interest is gradually diminishing. The two staple articles of
                    export are sugar and tobacco-wares. While the average export of sugar for the
                    first ten years of the century was only 177,998 boxes (61,199,200 lb), by 1855
                    it had reached 965,677 boxes (386,270,800 lb), and by 1878 145,601 boxes,
                    102,786 hogsheads, and 91,974 tons, or a grand total of nearly 408 millions of
                    lb. In 1867 there were exported 7,716,802 lb of tobacco and 199,027 millions of
                    cigars, and the corresponding numbers for 1878 were 13,864,800 lb and 174,638
                    millions. Other exports of importance are rum, wax, and honey. The nature and
                    quantities of the imports on an average of the ten years 1868 to 1877 are
                    295,202 quintals (100 lb each) of jerked beef, 134,203 quintals of cod-fish
                    (61,576 from Europe, and 41,019 from United States), 359,925 barrels of flour,
                    627,786 quintals of rice (mainly from the East Indies), 143,035 quintals of lard
                    (from the United States), 85,503 pipes of wine, 145,539 tons of coal, 344,095
                    jars of olive oil, and 92,857 quintals of coal-oil.</p>
                <p>The staple manufacturing industry of Havana is that of tobacco. Of the cigar
                    factories, more than a hundred may be reckoned as of the first class. The Royal
                    and Imperial Factory of La Honradez, which occupies a whole square, and is
                    considered one of the great sights of the city, produces daily 2,532,000
                    cigarettes. Besides the making of boxes and barrels, and other articles
                    necessarily involved in its sugar and tobacco trade, Havana also prosecutes to
                    some extent the building of carriages and ships, and the manufacture of iron and
                    machinery; but the weight of taxation is too great to allow the development of
                    any business requiring great capital. There were six banks in the city in 1877,
                    the most important being the Spanish Bank, through which all the Government
                    paper is issued.</p>
                <p>Havana has steam communication several times a week with New York; once a week
                    with Baltimore, Philadelphia, and New Orleans; and about as frequently with
                    several ports in England, Spain, and France. It is the terminus of a railway
                    system which reaches Cardenas, Cienfuego, Matanzas, Batabano, &amp;c.; and short
                    lines run out to the Bay of Havana and Marianas. Telegraphs radiate to all parts
                    of the island; and a submarine cable to Key West forms part of the line of
                    communication between Aspinwall and New York.</p>
                <p>The population of Havana and its suburbs was stated at 139,996 in 1817, at
                    196,994 in 1841, at 203,676 in 1863, and at 169,184 in 1871. Of this last number
                    108,754 were whites, 27,623 free negroes, mulattos, &amp;c., and 22,807 slaves.
                    By 1873 the total had reached, it is said, 230,000. None of these statistics can
                    be received with much confidence as to their accuracy. Among the white
                    population the proportion of males to females is extraordinarily high: according
                    to the. official returns, there die annually 3682 white males to 1204 white
                    females. .The average rate of mortality is 27 per thousand annually. Foreigners
                    are subject to yellow fever, especially from J une to September.</p>
                <p>Havana, originally founded by Diego Velasquez in 1515 on an unhealthy site near
                    the present harbour of Baracon on the south coast, was removed to its actual
                    position about 1519, and soon began to be considered one of the most important
                    places in the New World. In 1528 the buccaneers laid the settlement in ashes,
                    but it was soon after restored by Da Soto, who built the fortress of La Fuerza.
                    The residence of the captain-general was transferred to Havana from Santiago de
                    Cuba in 1551; and in 1589, to protect the city, which had been plundered by the
                    pirate Jacob Sores in 1555 and threatened by Drake in 1585, Philip II. of Spain
                    ordered the erection of the Bateria de la Punta and the castle of El Mono or Los
                    Très Reyes. In the course of the 17th century the port became the great
                    rendezvous for the gold-ships of Spain, and the commercial centre of the Spanish
                    possessions in America. The English under Admiral Pocock and the duke of
                    Albemarle captured Havana in 1762, but it was restored to the Spaniards on 10th
                    Feb. 1763, in exchange for the Floridas. The <hi rend="italic">Gaccta de
                    la</hi><hi rend="italic">Habana,</hi> the first paper published in Cuba,
                    appeared in 1782. In 1771 the port, which had formerly been, like the rest of
                    Cuba, monopolized by Seville and Cadiz, was declared open to all nations in
                    regard to certain articles of trade; and this liberty was extended in 1818 to
                    all goods whatsoever. During the despotico-paternal administration of Tacon many
                    improvements were introduced at Havana: the railway from Havana to Guines was
                    commenced in 1835; a ferry between the city and the suburb of Regia was set on
                    foot in 1837; and night watchmen, a police-force, and a fire-brigade were
                    established. The first line of steamships from Cadiz to Havana dates from 1850.
                    Like the rest of Cuba the city has frequently suffered severely from hurricanes,
                    the most violent being those of 1768 (St Theresa’s), 1810, and 1846.</p>
                <p>See the works referred to under <hi rend="smallcaps">Cuba.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
