<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0911-0890-0851-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HINTON, James (9th edition, volume 11, page
                    851)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p161">Surgeons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44z7b">Gulls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1139336">Surgeons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:949334">Gulls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit11newyrich/page/n890/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HINTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label> (1822-1875),
                    aural surgeon and author, son of John Howard Hinton, Baptist minister and author
                    of the <hi rend="italic">History and Topography of the United States</hi> and
                    other works, was born at Reading in 1822. He was educated at his grandfather’s
                    school near Oxford, and at the Nonconformist school at Harpenden, and in 1838,
                    on his father’s removal to London, was apprenticed to a woollendraper in
                    Whitechapel, where he came into contact with a phase of human life in its
                    miserable and degraded forms which influenced powerfully the whole cast of his
                    after thought. After retaining this situation about a year he became clerk in an
                    insurance office. The most of his evenings were spent by him in intense study,
                    and this, joined to the ardour, amounting to morbidness, of his interest in
                    moral problems, so affected his health that in his nineteenth year he resolved
                    to seek refuge from his own thoughts by running away to sea. His intention
                    having, however, been discovered, he was sent, on the advice of the physician
                    who was consulted regarding his health, to St Bartholomew’s Hospital to study
                    for the medical profession. After receiving his diploma in 1847, he was for some
                    time assistant surgeon at Newport, Essex, but the same year he went out to
                    Sierra Leone to take medical charge of the free labourers on their voyage thence
                    to Jamaica, after which his interest in their welfare prompted him to remain a
                    year on the island. After his return to England in 1850, he entered into
                    partnership with a surgeon in London, where he soon had his interest awakened
                    specially in aural surgery, and gave also much of his attention to physiology
                    and to problems bearing on the relation between mind and body. In his practice
                    he became convinced that in the immense majority of cases of ill-health it was
                    the hope of cure rather than the drug that effected the remedy, a fact which
                    explained to him much of the success of homoeopathy, and induced him to lay the
                    principal stress on moral methods of cure. He made his first appearance as an
                    author in 1856 by contributing a series of papers on physiological and ethical
                    subjects to the <hi rend="italic">Christian Spectator</hi>; and the success of
                    his work <hi rend="italic">Man and his Dwelling Place,</hi> which appeared in
                    1858, determined him, notwithstanding that he had married in 1852, to give up
                    his medical practice in order to devote his whole attention to writing on those
                    practical moral problems which chiefly occupied his thoughts. A series of papers
                    entitled “Physiological Riddles,” which he contributed to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cornhill Magazine,</hi> and afterwards published under the title <hi
                    rend="italic">Life in Nature,</hi> as well as another series entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Thoughts on Health,</hi> written for the same periodical and
                    collected and published separately in 1871, gave evidence of great aptitude in
                    popular scientific exposition; but his interest in speculation was too absorbing
                    to permit him to apply himself with sufficient pertinacity to literary work, and
                    after a year’s trial of it he found it necessary to resume his profession. In
                    1863 he obtained the appointment of aural surgeon to Guy’s Hospital, after which
                    he speedily acquired a lucrative west-end practice, and the reputation of being
                    the most skilful aural surgeon of his day, a reputation fully borne out by his
                    works, <hi rend="italic">An Atlas of Diseases of the Memhrana</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Tympani</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Questions of Aural
                    Surgery,</hi> which are regarded as the chief authorities in this branch of
                    surgery. The skill he had now obtained in his profession seemed to justify him
                    in 1869 in resuming his philosophical studies, but the mental excitement thus
                    produced, added to his professional labours, appears to have inflicted permanent
                    injury on his brain; and, although by giving up his practice in 1874 he obtained
                    partial relief, he began to suffer from sleeplessness and depression, and died
                    of acute inflammation of the brain, 16th December 1875.</p>
                <p>In addition to the works already mentioned, Hinton was the author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mystery of Man,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Place of the
                    Physician.</hi> On account of their fresh and vigorous discussion of many of the
                    important moral and social problems of the time, his writings have had a wide
                    circulation on both sides of the Atlantic. He contributed also several papers to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Review</hi> and other periodicals. His <hi
                    rend="italic">Life and Letters,</hi> edited by Ellice Hopkins, with an
                    introduction by Sir W. W. Gull, appeared in 1878.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
