<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-8777-0736-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NASSAU</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 15, page 736</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:949578">Gymnasiums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1201065">Publications</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211813">Luxembourg</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193828777" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NASSAU</label>, a sovereign dukedom in Germany, the reigning
                    family of which is distinguished by its antiquity, and the number of eminent men
                    it produced at the most interesting period of European history. The founder of
                    the sovereignty of this family was Waltram of Laurenburg, the ruins of whose
                    castle stand on the banks of the Lahn. His sons divided the inheritance among
                    them; but some branches becoming extinct, the whole were united again in the
                    year 1523, under Count Adolph, and continued so till 1605, when, under Louis II.
                    the territories were distributed among three of his sons, who thus became
                    sovereigns with the title of Graffs or Counts. They were, first, Saarbruck,
                    divided in the next generation into two branches, called Saarbruck-Sarbruck and
                    Sarbruck-Usingen, both of which were again united in 1735; but the branch became
                    extinct in 1797, and the land devolved on the present line: Secondly, Idstein, a
                    branch which became extinct in 1721: Thirdly, Weilburg, on which all the states
                    devolved, and since 1816 have formed but one principality. During the French
                    revolution, the city of Saarbruck, with its territory upon the left bank of the
                    Rhine, was seized by the republicans. It then comprehended 430 square miles of
                    land, with 53,000 inhabitants; for which, at the pacification in 1803, it
                    received an indemnification of 750 square miles and 93,000 inhabitants, which
                    were added to the Grafschaft of Usingen. The Count of Weilburg had lost, on the
                    left bank of the Rhine, 170 square miles and 19,000 inhabitants, for which he
                    received on the other side of that stream a territory of 330 square miles, with
                    37,000 inhabitants. At the period when Napoleon instituted the confederation of
                    the Rhine in 1806, the whole of these families had been united in the person of
                    the existing prince, who then received, in addition to the former territories
                    which he possessed, a tract of land of 650 square miles, with 84,500
                    inhabitants, and at the same time the title of duke was conferred upon the
                    reigning prince.</p>
                <p>At the peace which followed the capture of Paris, the territory assigned to the
                    dukedom, as well as the title, were affirmed by the great powers; and by them it
                    was stipulated, that in case of the extinction of that branch of the family of
                    Nassau which filled the throne of the Netherlands, the present ducal family of
                    Nassau should succeed to the inheritance of the duchy of Luxembourg. The
                    stipulations on this subject seem to be at present the principal obstacles to an
                    arrangement between the Dutch and the new kingdom of Belgium.</p>
                <p>The house of Orange-Nassau, which produced a race of distinguished heroes
                    favourable to the reformation, and amongst others our King William III. was a
                    branch, descended from Otho, a younger son of the house separated from the
                    principal one in the year 1292. There were many intermarriages between the
                    families at subsequent periods, and during the long contest in the Netherlands
                    the Prince of Orange drew great aid, both in men and money, from his relations
                    in the then countships of Nassau.</p>
                <p>The dukedom of Nassau in its present state is bounded on the north-west and on
                    the north by the Prussian Rhenish provinces; on the north-east by
                    Hesse-Darmstadt; on the east by Prussia, Hesse-Casel, and Hesse-Homburg; on the
                    south-east by the state of Francfort; and on the south and west by the Prussian
                    territory and Darmstadt. It stands wholly on the right bank of the river Rhine,
                    into which the small but navigable river Lahn falls. The surface, independently
                    of the rivers, extends over 1812 square miles. It is divided into twenty-two
                    ampts or bailiwicks. It contains ten cities, which are mostly small, but retain
                    that denomination from having been once fortified, twenty-five market-towns, and
                    429 villages, with a population in 1834 of 370,374 inhabitants of both sexes.
                    This district in 1817 contained, by the census then taken, only 301,907
                    individuals. In the year 1833 the births were, males 6690, females 6252; the
                    deaths were, males 4557, females 4506; and the marriages were 3367.</p>
                <p>The reigning house adheres to the Protestant religion; and the two sects of
                    Lutherans and Calvinists have been united into one, assuming the title of
                    Evangelical. There are 196,387 Protestants, 167,800 Catholics, 6009 Jews, and
                    184 Menonites. The Protestants of Nassau have a bishop, twenty deans, 178
                    pastors, and a theological seminary. The Catholics have a bishop and a
                    commissary, fifteen deans, and 138 parish priests, and also a seminary for
                    clerical instruction. Education is much extended and well conducted. At Weilburg
                    there is a gymnasium or college; there are also several respectable
                    grammar-schools, and 658 schools for popular instruction, under competent
                    teachers, so that every child is taught reading, writing, and the common rules
                    of arithmetic.</p>
                <p>The government is hereditary in the present family, and, if it become extinct, it
                    devolves on that branch of the Nassau family at the head of which is the king of
                    Holland. By a charter granted in the year 1817, there are two houses of
                    legislature; the upper consisting of hereditary members, of individuals of the
                    royal family, and of a few mediatized princes, being six together; the lower
                    house is elective, and consists of twenty-one members, amongst whom are the
                    Catholic and Protestant bishops, and the director of the gymnasium of Weilburg,
                    by virtue of their offices. These bodies rarely meet, and have little to do when
                    they do assemble, as few alterations are made in the laws, and new taxes are not
                    wanted.</p>
                <p>The income of the state, independently of that of the duke, from which the
                    public, civil, and ecclesiastical institutions are paid, is about L.180,000 per
                    annum; but it has a debt charged on it amounting to near L.500,000, which is
                    yearly diminished by a sinking fund. The personal income of the duke is very
                    large, arising from his estates, houses, and mineral springs; but the amount is
                    unknown, as are also the debts by which they are encumbered. The duke has a most
                    magnificent palace on the right bank of the Rhine at Biberach, another at
                    Wiesbaden, and several<pb break="no" facs="nls:193828790"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-8790-0737"/> hunting seats for pursuing his favourite
                    amusement in other parts of his dominions.</p>
                <p>The military force of the dukedom consists of two regiments of infantry, one
                    battalion of artillery, a company of pioneers, and a reserve corps serving as a
                    kind of police. The contingent of Nassau to the Germanic confederation is fixed
                    at 3026 men.</p>
                <p>The face of the country may be represented as in general mountainous, though
                    there are some rich and beautiful tracts of land near the river, about Hochst.
                    There are two ranges of hills which run through the territory, viz. the
                    Westerwald and the Taunus. The latter is the most picturesque, several of its
                    points rising to 1000 feet above the level of the river; whilst some of the^
                    valleys in these hills contain the mineral springs, and the vast piles of
                    building erected near them for the accommodation of their visitants. As these
                    springs have been made familiar to the English public by the popular work
                    entitled “Bubbles of the Brunnens of Nassau,” we need here do little more than
                    merely notice them. The baths of Ems are on a beautiful stream which runs into
                    the Rhine; and on its banks are a great number of lodging-houses and hotels.
                    Langen Schwallbach, about twelve hilly miles distant, in another valley, with
                    the surrounding hills covered with woods, is pleasantly situated. It too is well
                    provided with hotels and lodging-houses. Schlangenbad consists of but two large
                    buildings, though with sufficient apartments for numerous parties. Wiesbaden is
                    the most frequented, because the water is most highly valued for its curative
                    effects, and has, besides, a greater variety of amusements than either of the
                    other baths, being in contact with the city, which is a well-built place,
                    containing more than 9000 inhabitants. One of these springs is most remarkable
                    for the profit it yields to the duke, who is the proprietor of it, as well as of
                    the others. Nieder-Selters supplies that water which is known in every part of
                    Europe by the name of Seltzer. About one million of large and two millions and a
                    half of small bottles or jugs are filled from the spring and sealed. The profit
                    is stated to be about L.5000 per annum, after clearing all expenses; though it
                    is said to have been purchased by an ancestor of the duke for a single pipe or
                    butt of wine.</p>
                <p>The agriculture of the dukedom produces sufficient corn and cattle for the
                    consumption of the inhabitants, though it is generally conducted in a slovenly
                    way. The vineyards produce sufficient wine of a moderate quality, and fruit of
                    all kinds is plentiful and excellent.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Nassau.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Poggy Isles.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
