<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0239-0198-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRADSHAW, John (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    198)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nj3s">Sealing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198938">Rebellion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n239/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRADSHAW, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, president
                    of the High Court of Justice which tried Charles I., appears to have been born
                    in 1602 at Marple Hill, near Stockport in Cheshire. He was of good family, and
                    is believed to have been connected with Milton, the mother of the latter having
                    married a Bradshaw. At all events, whether connected or not, the two knew and
                    respected each other. Milton gives a highly eulogistic account of Bradshaw’s
                    character in his <hi rend="italic">Defensio Secunda,</hi> and Bradshaw left by
                    will £10 to Milton. His education seems to have been carried on at Stockport
                    free school, and afterwards at Bunbury and Middleton. He was called to the bar
                    at Gray’s Inn in April 1627, and in 1645 became a bencher. For some time
                    he.acted as judge in the Sheriff-Courts of London. As a lawyer he had
                    considerable chamber practice, especially among those whom Clarendon calls the
                        <hi rend="superscript"> ti</hi> factious.” In 1644 he was employed by
                    Parliament as one of the prosecutors of the Irish Lords Macguire and Macmahon.
                    In October 1646 he was voted by the Commons as one of the commissioners of the
                    Great Seal, and in March of the following year he was appointed chief-justice of
                    Cheshire. On October 12, 1648, he was raised to the rank of serjeant. In January
                    1649, when it was found difficult to compose a court of justice for the trial of
                    the king, Bradshaw was proposed as president, and at once elected. His demeanour
                    on the trial is well known, but has been variously judged. He continued to
                    retain the title of Lord President for some time after the trial, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n240/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0240-0199"/> and received large rewards from Parliament
                    for his valuable services. On the formation of a council of state Bradshaw was
                    elected a member, and for three years held office as president. After that time
                    the presidents were elected in rotation, and held their appointment for a month.
                    When, on the 20th April 1653, Cromwell, after dismissing the Parliament, came to
                    dissolve the council, Bradshaw is said to have confronted him boldly, and denied
                    his power to dissolve the Parliament. This story rests on the authority of
                    Ludlow, who was not a witness, and who does not say that Bradshaw was president
                    of the council on that occasion. Bradshaw, an ardent republican, ever afterwards
                    showed himself an uncompromising adversary of Cromwell. He was returned for
                    Cheshire in the Parliament of 1654, and spoke strongly against vesting the power
                    in a single person. He refused to sign the “engagement” drawn up by Cromwell,
                    and in consequence withdrew’ from Parliament. Some time afterwards he was
                    concerned with Harrison and others in one of the numerous republican
                    conspiracies, and it has even been suspected that he was at least cognizant of
                    some of the fifth monarchy men’s desperate plots. He failed to obtain a seat in
                    the Parliament of 1656, and on 1st August of the same year Cromwell ordered him
                    to be dismissed from the chief-justiceship of Chester. It is not quite certain
                    that this order was carried out. After the abdication of Richard Cromwell,
                    Bradshaw again entered Parliament and became a member of the council of state.
                    His health, however, was bad, and his last public effort was a vehement speech
                    on the seizure of Speaker Lenthall, in which he denounced the military despotism
                    of the time. He died on the 22d November 165D, and was buried in Westminster
                    Abbey. His body was disinterred at the Restoration, and exposed on a gibbet
                    along with those of Cromwell and Ireton. Bradshaw’s character will be found very
                    differently drawn by Clarendon <hi rend="italic">(History of the Rebellion,</hi>
                    bk. xi.) and Milton <hi rend="italic">(Defensio Secunda).</hi></p>
                <p>See Foss, <hi rend="italic">Lives of Judges;</hi> Onnerod’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chester,</hi> iii. 408-9! <hi rend="italic">Beauties of England and
                        Wales,</hi> ii. 26 4,' <hi rend="italic">sqq.;</hi> Noble, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lives of the English Regicides,</hi> vol. i.; Caulfield, <hi rend="italic"
                        >High Court of Justice;</hi> Godwin, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                        Commonwealth;</hi> Ludlow’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs;</hi> Forster’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Statesmen of the Commonwealth.</hi> On Bradshaw’s connection
                    with Milton see Masson, <hi rend="italic">Life of Milton,</hi> i.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
