<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0417-0370-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BROOKLYN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 370</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1170170">Walloons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137272">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn40532">Walloons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n417/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BROOKLYN</label>, a city of the United States of North
                    America, capital of King’s County, New York, is situated on the western end of
                    Long Island, immediately opposite the city of New York, from which it is
                    separated by the East River, an arm of the sea, about three-quarters of a mile
                    in breadth. Lat. 40° 4Γ N., long. 73° 59' W. The city now includes not only
                    Brooklyn proper, but also, by a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n418/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0418-0371"/> recent act of the legislature, all the county
                    towns of the western part of the island, so that it now covers a larger area
                    than any other city in the United States. From Hunter’s</p>
                <p>Point to Bay Ridge it has a river frontage of nearly nine miles. The ground on
                    which the city is built exhibits considerable inequalities of surface, and thus
                    increases the picturesqueness of its appearance, while the practical
                    disadvantages of such a site have been overcome by skilful engineering. The
                    streets, with the exception of Fulton Street, the principal thoroughfare, are
                    generally straight, have a width of from GO to 100 feet, and cross each other at
                    right angles. Chief among the public buildings are the city-hall (an edifice of
                    white marble dating from 1845-6), the county courthouse (erected in 1862), the
                    county jail (1837), the peni tentiary, the state arsenal, and the city hospital.
                    Besides the last-mentioned institution the benevolent establishments of Brooklyn
                    include the Long Island College Hospital, St Mary’s and St Peter’s hospital, the
                    female orphan asylum, the marine hospital, the Graham institution for the relief
                    of aged women, and numerous other charities. The churches number between 200 and
                    300, many of them are beautiful buildings, but none claim special notice except
                    the new Roman Catholic Cathedral, which is only rivalled by the corresponding
                    building in New York. Of literary and artistic institutions the most remarkable
                    are the Mercantile Library (dating from 1857), the Brooklyn Institute (founded
                    by Augustus Graham), the Long Island Historical Society, the Art Association,
                    the Academy of Design, the Academy of Music, and the Philharmonic Society. There
                    are three theatres, and an opera house, which dates from 1862. The educational
                    establishments comprise the Packer Collegiate Institute (founded in 1853) for
                    female education, the Polytechnic Institute for boys (started in 1854), the
                    Adelphi Academy for both sexes (founded in 1863), the Roman Catholic College of
                    St John, upwards of fifty public grammar and primary schools, and numerous
                    private institutions. Though Brooklyn in some measure serves as a suburb of
                    residence to New York, and many of its inhabitants carry on their business in
                    the larger city, its own industrial and commercial activity is very great. It
                    has flour-mills, sugar-refineries, lager-beer breweries, distilleries, tobacco
                    factories, and chemical works; and manufactures steel, brass, and copper wares,
                    engines, machinery, and printing-presses. The grain trade is of enormous extent,
                    the warehouses being capable of holding about 12,000,000 bushels; and sugar,
                    coffee, oil, hides, and wool are also largely imported. Most of the river
                    frontage is lined with basins, wharves, and docks, the most important being the
                    Atlantic dock (constructed about 1846) with an area of 40 acres, the Erie basin
                    of 60 acres, the Brooklyn basin of 40 acres, the Wallabout basin, and the United
                    States navy yard. This last occupies a total area of 144 acres, and has
                    extensive wharfage, and a dry dock, built of granite, at a cost upwards of
                    $2,113,000. The city is supplied with water by an elaborate system of
                    reservoirs, of which the most distant is 19 miles away in the vicinity of
                    Hempstead. Its principal pleasure ground is Prospect Park, which embraces more
                    than 600 acres, partly covered with forest trees. A lake of 50 acres is being
                    excavated, and there is a large well 60 feet in diameter, which will furnish the
                    necessary water to keep it fresh. Washington Park, on the site of ancient
                    fortifications, is also a pleasant spot, and there are various other open
                    grounds throughout the city. At the west end is situated the well known
                    Greenwood cemetery, which contains about 520 acres of finely-varied ground, a
                    good part of which is still adorned with natural wood.</p>
                <p>The traffic of the city is facilitated by tramway lines; and its co’nection with
                    New York, which has hitherto been dependent on steam-boat ferries, is to be
                    rendered more convenient by a large bridge in course of construction. This
                    bridge, which crosses the East River near its western extremity, is 85 feet
                    wide, and has a river span of 1596 and a total length of 5989 feet. The total
                    cost is estimated to exceed $13,000,000.</p>
                <p>The first settlement of Brooklyn, or as it was formerly called Breuckelen, dates
                    from 1636, when a few Walloon colonists took up their residence on the spot that
                    still bears the name of Wallabout (Waalbogt or Walloons’ Bay). English and Dutch
                    settlers followed; and in 1667, a patent or charter was granted to the town by
                    Governor Richard Nicolls. The first church had been erected the previous year.
                    In 1698 the population only amounted to 509 persons, of whom sixty-five were
                    slaves. In 1776 the site of the present town was the scene of the battle between
                    the Americans and British, which is usually known as the battle of Long Island.
                    In 1816 Brooklyn was incorporated as a village, and in 1834 it became a
                    chartered city. Williamsburg was founded by Richard W. Woodhull, in the early
                    part of the present century; it attained the rank of a village in 1827, and was
                    recognized as a city in 1851. The population of Brooklyn was in 1800, 3298; in
                    1820, 7175; in 1830, 15,292; in 1840, 36,233; and in 1850, 96,850. In 1855 the
                    number of inhabitants within the new boundaries was 205,250, of λvhom 48,367
                    belonged to Williamsburg; in 1860 this had increased to 266,661, and in 1870 to
                    396,099, and now (1876) it.is estimated at 500,000. (See Stile’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the City of Brooklyn,</hi> 3 vols., 1867-70.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
