<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0638-0577-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUSSORAH, Bassoka, Balsora, or Basra (9th edition,
                    volume 4, page 577)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n638/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUSSORAH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bassoka, Balsora</hi>, or <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">Basra</hi></label>, a celebrated city of Asia, in the
                    government of Baghdad, situated in 47° 34' E. long., 30° 32' N. lat., on the
                    western banks of the Shatt-el-Arab. It is about 70 miles from the mouth of that
                    noble stream, which is navigable to the city for ships of 500 tons burden after
                    passing the bar at its mouth; this, however, they can only conveniently do at
                    spring-tides. Bussorah is surrounded by walls, which are kept in a tolerable
                    state of repair. They have five gates, and are at the low est computation about
                    seven miles in circuit. Two canals, cut from the river, surround the town on
                    either side, and uniting beyond it on the western side, form a complete ditch to
                    the fortifications. The houses are meanly built, partly of sun-dried and partly
                    of burnt bricks, with flat roofs surrounded by a parapet; and the bazaars,
                    though stocked with the richest merchandise, are miserable structures, not
                    arched as in Baghdad and the Persian towns, but covered with mats laid on
                    rafters of date trees, which hardly afford protection from the scorching rays of
                    the sun. The streets are irregular, narrow, and unpaved, and the town itself is
                    disgustingly filthy. Of the vast area within the walls, the greater proportion
                    is occupied with gardens and plantations of palm trees, intersected by a number
                    of little canals, cleansed twice daily by the ebb and flow of the tide, which
                    rises here about 9 feet. The largest of these canals, which approaches the old
                    English factory and the palace of the governor, situated about two miles from
                    the river, is continually crowded with small vessels. The town has scarcely any
                    public buildings that deserve notice. It has khans and coffee-houses without
                    number, a wretched hummam (or bath), and upwards of forty mosques, of which one
                    only is worthy of the name; and this, with the palace of the governor, and the
                    old English factory, which are all contiguous to one another, are the only
                    decent buildings in the place. The old English factory, which was established at
                    Bussorah by the East India Company, about the middle of the last century, ceased
                    to exist with the expiration of the trading privileges of the company. The
                    building has now passed into private hands, and the British vice-consul, who
                    protects our trading interests, resides at the modern village of Maghil, which
                    has been built in a healthy position on the right bank of the river a few miles
                    from the Turkish town. The population of Bussorah is a heterogeneous mixture of
                    all the nations in the East, and consists of Turks, Arabs, Indians, Persians,
                    Armenians, Jacobites, and Jews. The Arabs constitute the principal class; and
                    the Turks, though they are masters of the town, are almost the least
                    numerous.</p>
                <p>Bussorah is a great emporium of Indian commerce. Six or eight English ships
                    arrive in the course of a year from India; but the chief part of the traffic is
                    carried on in Arabian bottoms; and the merchants of Muscat possess some of the
                    finest vessels that navigate the Indian seas. From various parts of Hindustan
                    Bussorah receives silk, muslin, linen, white and blue cloths for the clothing of
                    the Arabians, gold and silver stuffs, various metals, sandalwood, and indigo;
                    pearls from Bahrein, and coffee from Mocha; shawls, fruit, and the precious
                    metals from Persia; spices from Java; and European commodities, which are scarce
                    and dear, from different parts. The trade with the interior is conducted by
                    means of caravans to Aleppo and Baghdad, whence the goods are conveyed to
                    Constantinople. The returns are made in Indian goods, bullion, pearls, dates,
                    copper, raw silk, gall-nuts; and the horses, which are very strong and
                    beautiful, are exported in large numbers by the English.</p>
                <p>The situation of the town is unhealthy, owing to the inundations of the river,
                    from which noxious exhalations arise; and strangers are commonly attacked by
                    fever after a short residence. The adjoining country is fertile, producing,
                    besides rice, wheat, barley, and dates of different species, a variety of fruits
                    and vegetables, such as apricots, apples, figs, olives, pomegranates, and
                    grapes; and cabbages, broccoli, lettuce, onions, pease, beans, and truffles, in
                    vast quantities. There are whole fields of roses, which the inhabitants
                    cultivate for the purpose of making attar. The liquorice plant also grows amidst
                    the palm groves on the borders of the river.</p>
                <p>The city of Bussorah was originally founded by Omar, 636 A.D., on a canal eight
                    miles S.W. from its present site, where the town of Zobeir now stands; and its
                    situation was so favourable for commerce that in a few years it became a large
                    and flourishing city. The canal, however, soon became useless, and the city was
                    abandoned. The present city was conquered by the Turks in 1668, and since that
                    period has been the scene of many revolutions. It was taken in 1777, after a
                    siege of eight months, by the Persians under Sadick Khan. In about a year it
                    fell again into the hands of the Turks, who were again deprived of it by the
                    sheikh of the Montefik Arabs. The town w as in the October following recovered
                    by Soliman Pasha, who encountered the sheikh on the banks of the Euphrates, and
                    put him to flight; and it has since remained in the hands of the Turks.</p>
                <p>Under the government of the Turks Bussorah has dwindled down to a mere
                    second-rate town, the permanent population at present (1876) being certainly
                    under 10,000. In the river there is perhaps a greater show of activity just now
                    than in past times, as the Turks employ a considerable naval force in the
                    Persian Gulf to support their land operations against the Arabs, and the
                    Bussorah roads form the headquarters of the squadron, while tw o or three
                    Turkish steamers also ply upon the river, and have their depots upon its bank.
                    There are two steamers also belonging to the Tigris and Euphrates Navigation
                    Company (besides a war steamer maintained by the British Government in virtue of
                    a special firman), which convey merchandise and passengers between Baghdad and
                    Bu3sorah; and, lastly, the vessels of the British India Steam Navigation Company
                    visit Bussorah every week from Bombay and Bushire; but as the trade fostered by
                    these means is entirely one of transit, it confers little benefit on the town or
                    its inhabitants. The village of Maghil, however, on the banks of the Euphrates,
                    at the <hi rend="superscript"> q</hi> ista ce of three or four miles from
                    Bussorah, where the wharves and s &gt;re-house of the European <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n639/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0639-0578"/> companies are situated, is becoming a
                    considerable place, and may be expected ultimately to supersede the Turkish
                    town. The terminus of the Constantinople line of telegraph, which furnishes an
                    alternative means of communication between England and India, is at Fâo, near
                    the mouth of the Euphrates, and at the distance of about 60 miles below
                    Bussorah. A good deal of attention has of late years been directed to Bussorah
                    in connection with the proposal for a railway to unite the Mediterranean with
                    the Persian Gulf, either by way of the Tigris or Euphrates valley. In no case,
                    however, would it be desirable to establish the terminus of such a railway at
                    Bussorah, where the climate would prove most destructive to European life. The
                    most eligible site for the terminus would be either at Kowait on the sea-coast,
                    50 miles south of Bussorah, or at the Persian town of Mohamreh, where the Karûn
                    River disembogues into the Euphrates. Quite recently the Turkish Government has
                    decided to dissociate the Bussorah district, with its dependencies, from
                    Baghdad, and to attach it to the newly-created province of Arabia, the
                    headquarters of the pashalic being established at El Hassa; but such an
                    arrangement is not likely to be permanent. <hi rend="smallcaps">(h. c.
                    r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
