<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0222-0181-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOWRING, Sir John (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    181)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q43v">Economists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:902277">Economists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n222/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOWRING, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label>, an
                    eminent English linguist, translator, political economist, and miscellaneous
                    writer, was born at Exeter, October 17, 1792. He was a descendant of an old
                    Puritan family; and he became in early life an ardent disciple in the school of
                    utilitarianism and philosophical radicalism, whose prophet was Jeremy Bentham.
                    He did not, however, share his master’s contempt for poetry and the belles
                    lettres, but was a diligent student of literature and foreign languages,
                    especially those of Eastern Europe. His attainments as a linguist were of
                    remarkable extent. He stated that he knew two hundred languages and could speak
                    one hundred. This, of course, does not mean more than that he had some slight
                    acquaintance with them; but it is certain that he had a pretty good knowledge of
                    forty, and these were languages of various classes. This gives him a place, with
                    Mezzofanti and Von Gabelentz, among the greatest linguists of the world. The
                    first fruits of his study of foreign literature appeared in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Specimens of the Russian Poets,</hi> published in two volumes in 1821-23.
                    These were speedily followed by <hi rend="italic">Batavian Anthology</hi>
                    (1824), <hi rend="italic">Ancient Poetry and Romances of Spain</hi> (1824), <hi
                        rend="italic">Specimens of the Polish Poets,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Servian Popular Poetry,</hi> both in 1827. During this period he began to
                    contribute to the newly-founded <hi rend="italic">Westminster Review, of</hi>
                    which he was appointed editor in 1825. By his contributions to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Review</hi> he obtained considerable reputation as political
                    economist and parliamentary reformer. He advocated in its pages the cause of
                    free trade long before it was popularized by the eloquence of Richard Cobden and
                    John Bright. He pleaded earnestly in behalf of parliamentary reform, Catholic
                    emancipation, and popular education. In 1828 he visited Holland, and during his
                    stay there the university of Groningen conferred on him the degree of doctor of
                    laws. In the following year he was in Denmark, occupying himself with
                    preparations for the publication of a collection of Scandinavian poetry.
                    Bowring, who had been the trusted friend of Bentham during his life, was
                    appointed his literary executor, and was charged with the task of preparing a
                    collected edition of his works. This appeared in eleven volumes in the years
                    1838 aud 1839. Meanwhile Bowring had entered Parliament in 1835 as member for
                    Kilmarnock; and in the following year he was appointed head of a Government
                    commission to be sent to France to inquire into the actual state of commerce
                    between the two countries. He was engaged in similar investigations in
                    Switzerland, Italy, Syria, and some of the German States. The results of these
                    missions appeared in a series of reports laid before the House of Commons. After
                    a retirement of four years he sat in Parliament from 1841 till 1849 as member
                    for Bolton. During this busy period he found leisure for literature, and
                    published in 1843 a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Manuscript of the
                        Queen's Court,</hi> a collection of old Bohemian lyrics, &amp;c. In 1849 he
                    was appointed British consul at Hong-Kong, and superintendent of trade iu China,
                    a post which ho held for four years. After his return he distinguished himself
                    as an advocate of the decimal system, and published a work entitled, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Decimal System in Numbers, Coins, and Accounts</hi>
                    (1854). The introduction of the florin as a preparatory step was chiefly due to
                    his efforts. Knighted in 1854, he was again sent the same year to Hong-kong as
                    governor, invested with the supreme military and naval power. It was during his
                    governorship that a dispute broke out with the Chinese; and the irritation
                    caused by his “spirited” or high-handed policy led to the second war with China.
                    In 1855 he visited Siam, and negotiated with the king a treaty of commerce.
                    After the usual five years of service he retired and received a pension. His
                    last employment by the English Government was as a commissioner to Italy in
                    1861, to report on our commercial relations with the new kingdom. Sir John
                    Bowring subsequently accepted the appointment of minister plenipotentiary and
                    envoy extraordinary from the Hawaiian Government to the courts of Europe, and in
                    this capacity negotiated treaties with Belgium, Holland, Italy, Spain, and
                    Switzerland. In addition to the works already named he published— <hi
                        rend="italic">Poetry of the Magyars</hi> (1830); <hi rend="italic">Cheskian
                        Anthology</hi> (1832); <hi rend="italic">The Kingdom and People of Siam</hi>
                    (1859); a translation of <hi rend="italic">Peter Schlemihl;</hi> translations
                    from the Hungarian poet·, Alexander Petöfi (1866); and various pamphlets. He was
                    elected F.R.S. and F.R.G.S., and received the decorations of several foreign
                    orders of knighthood. Bowring was twice married; his second wife survived him,
                    with several sons, who have attained distinction in various fields. He died at
                    Claremont, near Exeter, November 23, 1872.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
