<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0438-0391-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BROWNING, Elizabeth Barrett</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 391</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1175789">Windows</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126608">Sonnet</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126610">Sonnets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3cd37">Windows</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55t8q">Sonnets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n438/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BROWNING, <hi rend="smallcaps">Elizabeth
                    Barrett</hi></label>, the most distinguished poet of her sex that England has
                    produced, was born in London in the year 1809. She was the daughter of Mr
                    Barrett, an English country gentleman. From a very early age, almost before the
                    years of childhood had passed, she exhibited a remarkable preference for the
                    arts, but especially that of the poetic. Previous to attaining her fifteenth
                    year she had written verse upon which was the stamp of true genius—poems
                    eminently worthy of preservation Whatever she wrote, however, was sacred to all
                    eyes save those of her father, to whom she refers in the first collected edition
                    of her poems as <hi rend="italic">“my</hi> public and my critic.” Her physical
                    constitution was most fragile and delicate, but nature seemed to have
                    supplemented her deficiency iu this respect by bestowing upon her an unusually
                    sensitive mental and spiritual organization. One who knew her intimately, Miss
                    Mitford, has described her as a “slight delicate figure, with a shower of dark
                    curls falling on each side of a most expressive face, large tender eyes, richly
                    fringed by dark eye-lashes, and a smile like a sunbeam.” All descriptions of
                    Miss Barrett concur in this, that she possessed a grace and a delicacy which
                    defied representation by the artist. Her studies were early directed to the
                    poets of antiquity, and, under the guidance of her blind tutor, Boyd, whose name
                    she always warmly cherished, she mastered the rich treasures of Aeschylus The
                    sublime Grecian possessed for her a charm which was only equalled by the
                    fascination held over her wondering spirit by our own Shakespeare. Her knowledge
                    of Greek literature was most profound; she was intimately familiar with all the
                    Attic writers in tragedy and comedy. Yet this did not prevent her from drinking
                    at the wells of English undefiled. Her correspondence with eminent
                    contemporaries of both sexes proves, her to have been thoroughly acquainted,
                    with English literature in its progress from Chaucer downwards. The
                    circumstances of her own life, and her lack of robust health, conspired to make
                    her seek, even more than she might have otherwise done, the communion of the
                    great departed in arts and letters. Not being able to pass from place to place
                    without fatigue and danger, the solitude she was compelled to maintain probably
                    threw her still more ardently into those pursuits which, while dear to the mind,
                    were probably injurious to the body. Most frail from her birth, as we have
                    already seen, it was her misfortune further to have her existence endangered in
                    1837 by the bursting of a blood-vessel in the lungs. By the exercise of extreme
                    care her life was preserved, but the incident was succeeded by a long period of
                    weakness and suffering. Some two years after this first severe shock to her
                    system, and before she had quite recovered from its effects, she was again
                    assailed by misfortune, experiencing the keenest anguish on witnessing the death
                    of her favourite brother, who was drowned at Torquay. As might have been
                    expected from one of her clinging and affectionate disposition, a long period of
                    danger followed this catastrophe, and when at length she was able to be removed
                    to her father’s house, it was only to become an invalid, with the prospect of a
                    life couch-ridden to its close. This period of seclusion lasted for seven long
                    years; and the interval was employed by Miss Barrett in eagerly devouring all
                    the books which could be brought within her reach. At this time also she was
                    sedulously cultivating the art that was afterwards to ensure for her
                    immortality. When she was in her thirty-seventh year, that is, in 1846, she was
                    married to Mr Browning, and the union was singularly felicitous. More cannot be
                    said, as the author of <hi rend="italic">The Ring and the Book</hi> still lives.
                    Mr Browning bore his wife to Italy, and for some years the sunny skies of the
                    south were instrumental in giving to Mrs Barrett Browning that health which had
                    so long forsaken her in her native land. The villa of the Brownings in Florence
                    was the resort of many noble spirits, eminent either for patriotism or in the
                    arts. Mrs Browning died at Florence in the year 1861, after testifying in many
                    ways her singular devotion to the country of her adoption.</p>
                <p>The poetry of this writer is distinguished for its emotional spirit; had her
                    imagination equalled her capacity for feeling she might have taken rank with the
                    highest of our poets. Sensibility and intuition, those endowments of supreme
                    importance to writers of genius, whose greatness is to grow in proportion to
                    their understanding and interpretation of human life, were in her united in a
                    degree seldom witnessed. The aspirations she indulged, and the character she
                    doubtless wished to be impressed upon her own works, were well set forth when
                    she observed on one occasion, “we want the touch of Christ’s hand upon our
                    literature as it touched other dead things; we want the sense of the saturation
                    of Christ’s blood upon the souls of our poets, that it may cry through them in
                    answer to the ceaseless wail of the sphinx of our humanity, expounding agony
                    into renovation. Something of this has been perceived in art when its glory was
                    at the fullest. Something of a yearning after this may be seen among the Greek
                    Christian poets, something which would have been much with a stronger faculty.”
                    Imbued fully with this idea of the sacredness of poetry, Mrs Browning went to
                    the deepest fount of all inspiration—the human heart—and endeavoured to read
                    clearly its intimate relations with God. A peculiar tenderness breathes through
                    her writings, whether of the humblest or the most ambitious description. Almost
                    her first work bore upon it the traces of her Greek studies, being an excellent
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Prometheus.</hi> Another very early
                    production, <hi rend="italic">The Drama of Exile,</hi> is unquestionably marked
                    by great sublimity of thought, though the conception may lack the mighty
                    outlines of the majestic Milton. Eloquent and sustained, however, the poem made
                    manifest a pure and original writer. Mrs Browning’s genius had two sides—the
                    lyric and the dramatic. Her lyrical capabilities were of the highest order; she
                    was greater probably in this particular than either Campbell or Tennyson, though
                    on several occasions Campbell touched the loftiest point such a writer can
                    attain. The heart, which has always given our lyric poets their greatest power,
                    was the strength of Mrs Browning; her song was a living <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n439/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0439-0392"/> voice, eloquent with passion. In one of her
                    lyrics she uttered her conclusion upon the human mystery, “knowledge by
                    suffering entereth, and life is perfected by death.” The spirituality of her
                    “Vision of Poets” is a noticeable quality, and it is in a loftier strain than
                    that of “The Two Voices,” though cast iu the same mould. Wandering amongst the
                    minor poems of Mrs Browuing, such for instance as “The Romaunt of Margret,”
                    “IsobeΓs Child,” “Bertha in the Lane,” and “the Swan’s Nest among the Reeds,” is
                    like standing in the forest alone, with the wailing wind and the flying rain as
                    the only assurances of an existence sublimer than our own. Yet she has thereby
                    reached the profoundest depths of the human heart. But even when most depressed
                    she does not lose faith—confidence in the triumph of the good and the right. To
                    her it was not always necessary to understand the wrong which she beheld; she
                    saw it and hated it, and she has helped men by her writings to do something
                    towards making an end of it. “The Cry of the Children” is a striking
                    illustration of her keen feeling and eloquent power as a philanthropist. She
                    felt for all who are in any way crushed or bruised by the pressure of society,
                    and of social distinctions, or of social misfortunes. Her poetry bears the
                    impress of tender aud profound sympathy with human suffering in every form.</p>
                <p>The range of this author’s powers was wide, as may be gathered by a comparison
                    between such poems as “A Child’s Thought of God” and “Casa Guidi Windows.” In
                    the latter she attained her ripest growth and greatest intellectual strength.
                    The poem is as sustained as anything which she ever wrote, and more perfect than
                    the remaining lengthy poems. The “Casa Guidi Windows” had the advantage of a
                    direct and powerful inspiration. From her windows at Florence Mrs Browning
                    looked out upon the Italian people struggling for freedom, and her enthusiasm
                    was enkindled. Her utterances were therefore in accordance with the fulness of
                    her heart, lavish and unrestrained. The extraordinary wealth and strength of
                    imagery which the poem contains must have been noticed by every reader, and it
                    includes doubtless much of her finest writing. In the inditing of the sonnet,
                    always conceded to be a most difficult task, Mrs Browning was very successful.
                    She is the equal of Wordsworth in this respect, and her “Sonnets from the
                    Portuguese” (but thinly disguised, and giving really the history of her own
                    feelings) are a compact and remarkable series of verses. They present us with a
                    complete study of a human heart as it is affected by the passion of love. First,
                    there is the soul expecting death, when suddenly life is revivified by love;
                    then the grave, which had seemed inevitable, is put behind the soul; and finally
                    comes the sequel, the marriage of those whose history has been traced in the
                    Sonnets. The unity and psychological interest of this series of poems are their
                    most prominent features.</p>
                <p>Mrs Browning’s fame chiefly rest3 upon <hi rend="italic">Aurora Leigh,</hi>
                    except with diligent and reverent students of her other works. The longest poem,
                    nevertheless, which came from her hand is the one, to quote her own words, into
                    which her “highest convictions upon life and art have entered.” Yet it has had
                    the result of causing a wide diversity of opinion upon its merits. Extravagant
                    encomiums or unjust aspersions are generally awarded to it. For a poem of such
                    magnitude unity is essential, and this we find to be lacking. It has not the one
                    purpose—never ignored and never forgotten—which runs through <hi rend="italic"
                    >In</hi><hi rend="italic">Memoriam,.</hi> One of its great charms, however,
                    viz., its intense subjectivity, will prevent <hi rend="italic">Aτιrora
                    Leigh</hi> from falling into desuetude. The writer unfolds with great beauty of
                    expression the truth that that is real art which assists in any degree to lead
                    back the soul to contemplate God, the supreme artist of the universe. But
                    notwithstanding its philosophy, as a solution for many of the problems of our
                    social existence, the poem must be pronounced a failure. It is charged with
                    passages of lofty poetry, though occasionally it falls into mediocrity. It is to
                    be regarded rather as an autobiography (which indeed it claims to be) than as a
                    poem characterized by fine conception or perfect execution. The position of Mrs
                    Browning as a poet is now yielded. Her genius was perhaps as great as that of
                    any poet of our generation, but circumstances retarded its highest possible
                    development. In certain intellectual qualities she was inferior to Tennyson and
                    the author of <hi rend="italic">Sordello,</hi> but in others she was their
                    superior. Be her exact niche, however, what it may, she occupies a favoured
                    place in English literature, and is undoubtedly one of the few leading poets of
                    the 19 th century. Her poetry is that which refines, chastens, and elevates.
                    Much of it is imperishable, and although she did not reach the height of the few
                    mighty singers of all time, she has shown us the possibility of the highest
                    forms of the poetic art being within the scope of woman’s genius. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(g. b. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
