<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0673-0602-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUXTORF, or Buxtorff, John (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    602)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048144">Orientalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n673/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUXTORF, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Buxtorff, John</hi></label>
                    (1599-1664), commonly called “junior,” to distinguish him from his father, the
                    subject of the preceding notice. He was born at Basel on the 13th August 1599,
                    and at a very early age displayed remarkable aptitude for the acquisition of
                    languages. When only four years old he was sent to school, at which age he is
                    said to have been able to read Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, in which he had been
                    instructed by his father. At the age of twelve he entered the university, where
                    he speedily distinguished himself above not only his equals, but his seniors in
                    years, to so great a degree that when only sixteen he received the diploma of
                    master of arts from the hands of his own father. From this time he devoted
                    himself to the study of theology, turning his attention especially to the Hebrew
                    language and its cognate dialects, and then proceeding to the study of
                    rabbinical Hebrew, in which he soon attained such proficiency, that he is said,
                    while still a young man, to have read through not only the Mishna, but also the
                    Jerusalem and Babylonian Gemaras, or commentaries upon the text of the Talmud.
                    In conformity with the excellent custom, so long prevalent on the Continent, of
                    visiting several universities before finally settling down to life-long
                    professional work, Buxtorf proceeded to Heidelberg in 1617, where he listened to
                    the prelections of the theologians Pareus, Scultetus, and the elder Alting. In
                    1619 he repaired to Dort, while the famous Synod was still sitting, and there
                    made the acquaintance of many of the divines who took part in its proceedings.
                    At the close of the Synod he made a short journey in company with the deputies
                    from Basel, through the Netherlands and England, and thence through France back
                    to Basel. On his return he found that his father’s great Rabbinical Bible was in
                    course of publication, and as there was no lexicon suitable for the study of the
                    Chaldee Targums, comprised in the work, he undertook the compilation of such a
                    lexicon, which appeared at Basel in 1622 under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lexicon</hi><hi rend="italic">Chaldaicum, et Syriacum,</hi> with a
                    recommendatory preface from his father, detailing the circumstances under which
                    the work had been executed. Still thirsting for knowledge, he repaired in 1623
                    to Geneva, to enjoy the instructions of the elder Turretin, Diodati, and
                    Tronchin; while in return Turretin and Dav. Clericus did not disdain to avail
                    themselves as pupils of his pre-eminent knowledge of Hebrew and of the
                    rabbinical dialect. So great by this time had become his reputation as a
                    scholar, that he was offered by the authorities of the city of Bern the chair of
                    logic at Lausanne, which he declined, preferring to return to Basel, where in
                    1624, he was appointed general deacon to the church of Basel <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Communis</hi><hi rend="italic">Ecclesioe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Basileensis</hi><hi rend="italic">Diaconus'),</hi> and three years later
                    deacon of St Peter’s church. On the death of his father in 1629, Buxtorf was
                    unanimously designated as the fittest person to succeed so distinguished a
                    Hebraist; and by the advice of his physicians, who were of opinion that the
                    labours involved in the discharge of the duties of a public preacher would be
                    injurious to one whose constitution was feeble, he finally accepted the office.
                    From this date until his death he remained at Basel, declining two offers which
                    were made to him from Groningen and Leyden, to accept the Hebrew chair in these
                    two celebrated schools. To mark their appreciation of his patriotic conduct, the
                    governing body of the university founded in 1647, specially for his behoof, a
                    third theological professorship, that of “Commonplaces and Controversies,” the
                    duties of which Buxtorf discharged for seven years along with those of the
                    Hebrew chair. When, however, the professorship of the Old Testament became
                    vacant in 1654 by the death of Theodore Zuinger, Buxtorf resigned the chair of
                    theology, and accepted that of the Old Testament instead, holding both offices,
                    and for some time that also of chief librarian to the university, until his
                    death in 1664. The course of his private life was chequered by many domestic
                    bereavements. He was four times married <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n674/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0674-0603"/> lιis three first wives dying shortly after
                    marriage, and the fourth predeceasing her husband by seven years. His children
                    also all died young, with the exception of two boys, the younger of whom, John
                    James, became first his father’s colleague, and shortly after his successor in
                    the chair of Hebrew.</p>
                <p>A considerable portion of his public life was spent in controversy regarding
                    disputed points in Biblical criticism, in reference to which he had to defend
                    the views advanced by his father. The attitude of the Reformed churches at that
                    time, as opposed to the Church of Rome, led them to take up and maintain many
                    opinions in regard to Biblical questions, which were not only erroneous in point
                    of fact, but which were altogether unnecessary for the stability of their
                    position. Having renounced the dogma of an infallible church, it was deemed
                    necessary to maintain as a counterpoise, not only that of an infallible Bible,
                    but, as the necessary foundation of this, of a Bible which had been handed down
                    from the earliest ages to the present time without the slightest alteration or
                    change in its text. The letters in which the Old Testament was written, were, it
                    was asserted, the same as those in which the two tables of the law had been
                    written; the vowel points and accents which accompanied them had been given by
                    divine inspiration; and the words themselves had not undergone the slightest
                    change from the time they had ilowed from the pens of the respective writers.
                    The Masoretic text of the Old Testament, therefore, as compared either with that
                    of the recently discovered Samaritan Pentateuch, or of the Septuagint, or of the
                    Vulgate, was alone the “Hebrew Verity,” wherein the true words of the sacred
                    writers were to be found. Although many of the Reformers, as well as learned
                    Jews, had long seen that these assertions could not be made good, there had been
                    as yet no formal controversy upon the subject. It was reserved for a learned and
                    acute Frenchman, Ludovicus Cappellus the younger, professor of Hebrew at Saumur,
                    to enter the field, and by a series of controversial writings effectually to
                    dispel the illusions which had long prevailed in many minds As early as 1622 or
                    1623, Cappellus had submitted in manuscript to the elder Buxtorf a work on the
                    modem origin of the vowel points and accents, which he had been led to undertake
                    in consequence of the statements made by the Swiss professor in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Tiberias,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the
                        Masora,</hi> in which he had controverted the views of Elias Levita on the
                        <hi rend="italic">late</hi> origin of the points. Buxtorf saw the force of
                    the arguments employed by Cappellus, but counselled him not to publish his work,
                    pointing out the injury which it would do to the Protestant cause, and the
                    advantage which it would afford to Romish controversialists on the question of
                    the infallible accuracy of the text of Scripture. Cappellus, however, was not to
                    be deterred by fear of consequences. He sent his MS. to Thomas Erpenius of
                    Leyden, the most learned Orientalist of his day, by whom it was published in
                    1624, under the title <hi rend="italic">Arcanum Punctationis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">revelatum,</hi> with a laudatory preface, but without the
                    author’s name In this work Cappellus adduced those arguments and considerations
                    which have satisfied most scholars since his day that the vowels and accents are
                    the invention of the Masoretes, and that they are not older than the fifth
                    century of the Christian era. It is worth noting that although the elder Buxtorf
                    lived five years after the publication of the work, he made no public reply to
                    it, and it was not until 1648, nearly a quarter of a century afterwards, that
                    Buxtorf, junior, published his <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >de</hi><hi rend="italic">punctorum origine, antiquitate,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">authσritate,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >oppositus Arcano punctationis revelato Ludovici Cappelli.</hi> In this
                    treatise he endeavoured to prove by copious citations from the rabbinical
                    writers, and by arguments of various kinds, that the points, if not so ancient
                    as the time of Moses, were at least as old as that of Ezra, and thus possessed
                    the authority of divine inspiration. In the course of the λvork he allowed
                    himself frequently to employ contemptuous epithets towards Cappellus, such as
                    “innovator,” “prophet,” “revealer,” “a seer of visions,” “dreams,” &amp;c.
                    Cappellus was not the man to remain silent in such circumstances. He speedily
                    prepared a second edition of his work, in which, besides replying to the
                    arguments of his opponent, and fortifying his position with new ones, he
                    retorted his contumelious epithets with interest. Owing to various causes,
                    however, among which may be mentioned the distrust with which Cappellus was
                    coming to be regarded on account of his critical opinions among Protestants
                    themselves, this second edition did not see the light until thirty years after
                    his death; when it was published at Amsterdam in 1685, in the edition of his
                    collected works. Besides this controversy, Buxtorf engaged in three others with
                    the same antagonist, on the subject of the integrity of the Masoretic text of
                    the Old Testament, on the antiquity of the present Hebrew characters, and on the
                    Lord’s Supper. Into the details of these, however, our space does not allow us
                    to enter. In the two former Buxtorf supported the untenable position that the
                    text of the Old Testament had been transmitted to us without any errors or
                    alteration, and that the present square or so-called Chaldee characters were
                    coeval with the original composition of the various books. These views were
                    triumphantly refuted by his great oppo nent in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Critica</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacra,</hi> and in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Diatriba</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">veris et
                        antiquis</hi><hi rend="italic">Ebraicorum literis.</hi> Besides the works
                    which have been already mentioned in the course of this article, Buxtorf edited
                    the great <hi rend="italic">Lexicon</hi><hi rend="italic">Chaldaicum,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Talmudicrum,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Rabbinicum,</hi> on which his father had spent the labour of twenty years,
                    and to the completion of which he himself gave ten years of additional study,
                    and the great Hebrew <hi rend="italic">Concordance,</hi> which his father had
                    little more than begun. In addition to these, he published new editions of many
                    of his father’s works, as well as others of his own, complete fists of which may
                    be seen in the <hi rend="italic">Athence</hi><hi rend="italic">Rauricoe,</hi>
                    and other works enumerated at the close of the preceding article. (F. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
