<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0306-0263-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BREVIARY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 263</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1080778">Psalters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:965486">Hymns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n306/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BREVIARY</label> (Lat. <hi rend="italic">breviarium),</hi>
                    the book which contains the offices for the canonical hours. The word first
                    occurs in the 11th century, and is said to denote that the book was an
                    abridgment of several separate ones which had previously been in use. The
                    English equivalent for it is <hi rend="italic">portuary</hi> (from the mediaeval
                    Latin/jorfø/ortem), <hi rend="italic">portesse,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >portuasse,</hi> the name probably indicating the <hi rend="italic"
                    >portability</hi> of the volumes.</p>
                <p>In the earliest times most of the stated public devotions of the faithful grouped
                    themselves round the daily celebration of the eucharistie sacrifice; but by
                    degrees other offices were added, in which the recitation of the Psalter formed
                    the principal part. The rise of monasticism gave a great impulse to the
                    movement, as the monks generally used the whole Psalter every week, and many of
                    them every day. Numerous complications were added by degrees, in the shape of
                    antiphons, responses, &amp;c. Metrical hymns seem to date from St Ambrose in the
                    middle of the 14th century. Select portions of holy Scripture were also read, as
                    well as extracts from works of the Fathers and from lives of the saints.</p>
                <p>The canonical hours are eight in number; the night office of matins (divided into
                    three nocturns) and seven day offices,—lauds, prime (at 7 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.m.),</hi> terce (at the third hour or 9 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.m.),</hi> sext
                    (at the sixth hour, noon), nones (at the ninth hour, 3 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >p.m),,</hi> vespers (at sunset), and compline before retiring to rest.</p>
                <p>From this account it will at once be seen that the Breviary services can only be
                    carried out in a monastic community where all other duties give place to
                    worship. Accordingly, the secular clergy of the Latin churches who are obliged
                    to recite them daily are allowed much latitude in the way of grouping services
                    together, and saying them at any hour that may be convenient, which quite
                    destroys the grand theory of the nightly and seven-fold daily offices of
                    devotion. There were three leading types of this service book in the Western
                    churches :—(1), the Mozarabic Breviary, once in use throughout all Spain, but
                    now confined to a single foundation at Toledo; it is remarkable for the number
                    and length of its hymns, and for the majority of its collects being addressed to
                    God the Son; (2), the Ambrosian, now confined to Milan, where it owes its
                    retention to the attachment of the clergy and people to their traditionary rites
                    which they derive from St Ambrose; and (3), the Roman, which (with many minor
                    variations) forms the ground-work of all others except those just mentioned.</p>
                <p>Till the Council of Trent every bishop had full power to regulate the Breviary of
                    his own diocese; and this was acted upon almost everywhere. Each monastic
                    community, also, had one of its own. Pope Pius V., however, while sanctioning
                    those which could show at least 200 years of existence, made the Roman
                    obligatory in all other places. But the influence of the court of Rome has
                    gradually gone much beyond this, and has superseded almost all the local “uses.”
                    The Roman has thus become nearly universal, with the allowance only of
                    additional offices for saints specially venerated in each particular
                    diocese.</p>
                <p>The Roman Breviary has undergone several revisions. The most remarkable of these
                    is that by Cardinal Quignon (1536), which, though not accepted by Rome, formed
                    the model for the still more thorough reform made in 1549 by the Church of
                    England, whose daily morning and evening services are but a condensation and
                    simplification of the Breviary offices. Some parts of the prefaces at the
                    beginning of the English Prayer-Book are free translations of those of Quignon.
                    At the beginning of last century a movement of revision took place in France,
                    and succeeded in modifying about half the Breviaries of that country.
                    Historically, this proceeded from the labours of Launoius and Tillemont, who had
                    shown the falsity of numerous lives of the saints; while theologically, it was
                    produced by the Port Royal school, which led men to dwell more on communion with
                    God as contrasted with the invocation of the saints. This was mainly carried out
                    by the adoption of a rule that all antiphons and responses should be in the
                    exact words of Scripture, which, of course, cut out the whole class of appeals
                    to created beings. The services were at the same time simplified and shortened,
                    and the use of the whole Psalter every week (which had become a mere theory in
                    the Roman Breviary, owing to its frequent supersession by saints’ day services)
                    was made a reality. These reformed French Breviaries show a deep knowledge of
                    holy Scripture, and much careful adaptation of different texts; but during the
                    pontificate of the present Pope (Pius IX.) a strong Ultramontane movement has
                    arisen against them. It was inaugurated by the Count de Montalembert, but its
                    literary advocates were chiefly the Abbé Gueranger and Μ. Veuillot of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Univers;</hi> and it has succeeded in suppressing them everywhere
                    except at Lyons, where the shadow of St Irenøeus still protects the local
                    rites.</p>
                <p>The beauty and value of many of the Latin Breviaries were brought to the notice
                    of English churchmen by one of the numbers of the Oxford <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tracts for the Times,</hi> since which time they have been much more studied,
                    both for their own sake and for the light they throw upon the English
                    PrayerBook.</p>
                <p>In a bibliographical point of view some of the early printed Breviaries are among
                    the rarest of literary curiosities, being merely local. The copies were not
                    spread far, and were soon worn out by the daily use made of them. Doubtless many
                    editions have perished without leaving a trace of their existence, while others
                    are known by unique copies. In Scotland the only one which has survived the
                    convulsious of the 16th century is that of Aberdeen, revised by Bishop W.
                    Elphinstone, and printed at Edinburgh by Walter Chepman in 1509. Four copies
                    have been preserved of it, of which one only is complete; but it has been
                    sumptuously reprinted in fac-simile for the Maitland Club by the munificence of
                    the Duke of Buccleuch. It is particularly valuable for the notices of the early
                    history of Scotland which are embedded in the lives of the national saints, and
                    which are considered to be very authentic. For the sake of those who are not
                    familiar with Latin typographical contractions, it would be desirable if a more
                    readable edition were printed, with explanatory notes on the many difficult
                    points which occur in the rubrics.</p>
                <p>The Sarum or Salisbury Breviary was much more widely used. The first edition was
                    printed at Venice in 1483, by Raynald de Novimagio in folio; the latest at
                    Paris, 1556, 1557. It may be noticed as a peculiarity that, while modern
                    Breviaries are always printed in four volumes, one for each season of the year,
                    the editions of the Sarum never exceeded two parts.</p>
                <p>Further information on this subject will be found in the writers on the services
                    of the Western churches, such as Maskell and Procter. Seager has printed a small
                    portion of the Sarum Breviary with elaborate notes. The hymns have been printed
                    separately, with more or less completeness, by Daniel, -Newman, and others; and
                    translations 'from them form the ground-work of <hi rend="italic">Hymns Ancient
                    and Modern,</hi> now so extensively used in the Church of England. Foreign
                    writers on this subject may be consulted by those who wish to pursue it further,
                    but they are too numerous to be mentioned here. They will be found enumerated in
                    bibliographical writers like Taccaria. (α. <hi rend="smallcaps">h. f.)</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n307/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0307-0264"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
