<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0241-0200-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRÄHMA SAMÄJ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 200</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k64b29t">Upanishads</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n241/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRÄHMA SAMÄJ</label>, the new theistic church in India, owes
                    its origin to Ràjâ Râm Mohan Râi, one of the leading men whom India has produced
                    in later times. Râm Mohan Râi was born in the district of Bardwân in 1772. He
                    mastered at an early age the Sanskrit, Arabic, and Persian languages. Impressed
                    with the fallacy of the religious ceremonies practised by his countrymen, he
                    impartially investigated the Hindu Shastras, the Koran, and the Bible,
                    repudiated the polytheistic worship of the Shastras as false, and inculcated the
                    reformed principles of monotheism as found in the ancient Upanishads of the
                    Vedas. In 1816 he established a society, consisting only of Hindus, in which
                    texts from the Vedas were recited and theistic hymns chanted. This, however,
                    soon died away on account of the opposition it met from the Hindu community. In
                    1830 the Râjâ organized a Hindu society for prayer-meetings, which may be
                    considered as the foundation of the present Brâhma Samâj. The following extract
                    from the trust-deed of the building dedicated to it will show the religious
                    belief and the purposes of its founder. The building was intended to be “a place
                    of public meeting for all sorts and descriptions of people, without distinction,
                    who shall behave and conduct themselves in an orderly, sober, religious, and
                    devout manner, for the worship and adoration of the eternal, unsearchable, and
                    immutable Being, who is the author and preserver of the universe, but not under
                    and by any other name, designation, or title, peculiarly used for and applied to
                    any particular being or beings by any man or set of men whatsoever; and that no
                    graven image, statue, or sculpture, carving, painting, picture, portrait, or the
                    likeness of anything shall be admitted within the said messuage, building, land,
                    tenements, hereditament, and premises; and that no sacrifice, offering, or
                    oblation of any kind or thing shall ever be permitted therein; and that no
                    animal or living creature shall within or on the said messuage, &lt;fcc., be
                    deprived of life either for religious purposes or food, and that no eating or
                    drinking (except such as shall be necessary by any accident for the preservation
                    of life), feasting, or rioting be permitted <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n242/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0242-0201"/> therein or thereon; and that in conducting the
                    said worship or adoration, no object, animate or inanimate, that has been, or
                    is, or shall hereafter become or be recognized as an object of worship by any
                    man or set of men, shall be reviled or slightingly or contemptuously spoken of
                    or alluded to, either in preaching or in the hymns or other mode of worship that
                    may be delivered or used in the said messuage or building; and that no sermon,
                    preaching, discourse, prayer, or hymns be delivered, made, or used in such
                    worship, but such as have a tendency to the contemplation of the Author and
                    Preserver of the universe, or to the promotion of charity, morality, piety,
                    benevolence, virtue, and the strengthening of the bonds of union between men of
                    all religious persuasions and creeds.” The new faith at this period held to the
                    Vedas as its basis. Râm Mohan Râi soon after left India for England, and took up
                    his residence in Bristol, where he died in 1835. The Brâhma Samâj maintained a
                    bare existence till 1841, when Bâbu Debendra Nâth Tagore, of the Tagore family
                    of Calcutta, devoted himself to it. He gave a printing-press to the Samâj, and
                    established a monthly journal called the <hi rend="italic">Tattwabodhini</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Patrikä</hi> to which the Bengali language now owes much for its
                    strength and elegance. About the year 1850 some of the followers of the new
                    religion discovered that the greater part of the Vedas is polytheistic, and a
                    schism took place,—the advanced party holding that nature and intuition form the
                    basis of faith. Between the years 1847 and 1858 branch societies were formed in
                    different parts of India, especially in Bengal, and the new church made rapid
                    progress, for which it was largely indebted to the spread of English education
                    and the labours of the Christian missionaries.</p>
                <p>The Brâhma creed was definitively formulated as follows. (1.) The book of nature
                    and intuition supplies the basis of religious faith. (2.) Although the Brâhmas
                    do not consider any book written by man the basis of their religion, yet they do
                    accept with respect and pleasure any religious <hi rend="italic">truth</hi>
                    contained in any boôk. (3.) The Brâhmas believe that the religious condition of
                    man is progressive, like the other departments of his condition in this world.
                    (4.) They believe that the fundamental doctrines of their religion are also the
                    basis of every true religion. (5.) They believe in the existence of one Supreme
                    God—a God endowed with a distinct personality, moral attributes worthy of His
                    nature, and an intelligence befitting the Governor of the universe, and they
                    worship Him alone. They do not believe in any of his incarnations. (6.) They
                    believe in the immortality and progressive state of the soul, and declare that
                    there is a state of conscious existence succeeding life in this world and
                    supplementary to it as respects the action of the universal moral government.
                    (7.) They believe that repentance is the only way to salvation. They do not
                    recognize any other mode of reconcilement to the offended but loving father.
                    (8.) They pray for <hi rend="italic">spiritual</hi> welfare, and believe in the
                    <hi rend="italic">efficacy</hi> of such prayers. (9.) They believe in the
                    providential care of the divine Father. (10.) They avow that love towards Him,
                    and the performances of the works which He loves, constitute His worship. ([ 1.)
                    Th?y recognize the necessity of public worship, buc do not believe that
                    communion with the Father depends upon meeting in any fixed place at any fixed
                    time. They maintain that they can adore Him at any time and at any place,
                    provided that the time and the place are calculated to compose and direct the
                    mind towards Him. (12.) They do not believe in pilgrimages, and declare that
                    holiness can only be attained by elevating and purifying the mind. (13.) They
                    put no faith in rites or ceremonies, nor do they believe in penances, as
                    instrumental in obtaining the grace of God. They declare that moral
                    righteousness, the gaining of wisdom, divine contemplation, charity, and the
                    cultivation of devotional feelings are their rites and ceremonies. They further
                    say, Govern and regulate your feelings, discharge your duties to God and to man,
                    and you will gain everlasting blessedness; purify your heart, cultivate
                    devotional feelings, and you will see Him who is unseen. (14.) Theoretically
                    there is no distinction of caste among the Brâhmas. They declare that we are all
                    the children of God, and therefore must consider ourselves as brothers and
                    sisters.</p>
                <p>For long the Brâhmas did not attempt any social reforms. But about 1860 the
                    younger Brâhmas, headed by Bâbu Kesab Chandra Sen, tried to carry their
                    religious theories into practice by excluding all idolatrous rites from their
                    social and domestic ceremonies, and by rejecting the distinction of caste
                    altogether. This, however, the older members opposed, declaring such innovations
                    to be premature. The theoretical schism now widened into a visible separation,
                    and henceforth the two parties of the Brâhmas were known as the Conservatives
                    and the Progressives. The progressive Brâhmas, or, as they call their church,
                    the <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> Brâhma Samâj of India,’’ have made
                    considerable progress. They have built a chapel in Calcutta, which is crowded
                    every Sunday evening; and they encourage the establishment of branch Samâjes in
                    different parts of the country. The number of avowed Brâhmas probably does not
                    exceed 3000, but the greater part of the educated natives of Bengal sympathize
                    more or less with the movement. (w. w. <hi rend="smallcaps">h.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
