<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0598-0537-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURIAL and (9th edition, volume 4, page 537)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37m31m">Payment</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154ds4b">Freehold</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843192">Buzzards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1055703">Payment</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURIAL <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi></label> BURIAL ACTS. The
                    practice of burying in churches or churchyards is said to have been connected
                    with the custom of praying for the dead, and it would appear that the earlier
                    practice was burying in the church itself. “In England, about the year 750,
                    spaces of ground adjoining the churches were carefully enclosed and solemnly
                    consecrated and appropriated to the burial of those who had been entitled to
                    attend divine service in those churches, and who now became entitled to render
                    back into those places their remnants to earth, the common mother of mankind,
                    without payment for the ground which they were to occupy, or for the pious
                    offices which solemnized the act of interment” (Lord, Stowell). The right to
                    burial in the parish churchyard is far from being merely an ecclesiastical
                    privilege, but at the same time it is intimately bound up with the laws of the
                    Church Establishment. It is a common law right, controlled in many points by the
                    provisions of the law ecclesiastical. This double character is sufficient to
                    explain the controversy which has so long raged round the subject of burials in
                    England. Every man, according to the common law, has a right to be buried in his
                    own churchyard, or, as it is sometimes put, in the churchyard of the parish
                    where he dies. But the churchyard, as well as the church itself, is the freehold
                    of the parson, who can in many respects deal with it as if it were a private
                    estate. A statute of Edward I. (35, st. 2) speaks of the churchyard as the soil
                    of the church, and the trees growing in the churchyard “as amongst the goods of
                    the church, the which laymen have no authority to dispose,” and prohibits “the
                    parsons from cutting down such trees unless required for repairs.”
                    Notwithstanding the consecration of the church and churchyard, and the fact that
                    they are the parson’s freehold, a right of way may be claimed through them by
                    prescription. The right to burial may be subject to the payment of a fee to the
                    incumbent, if such has been the immemorial custom of the parish, but not
                    otherwise. The spirit of the ancient canons regarded such burial fees as of a
                    simoniacal complexion, inasmuch as the consecrated grounds were among the <hi
                        rend="italic">res</hi><hi rend="italic">sacrae</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    a feeling which Lord Stowell says disappeared after the Reformation. No person
                    can be buried in a church without the consent of the incumbent, except when the
                    owner of a manor house prescribes for a burying-place within the church as
                    belonging to the manor house. In the case of Rex <hi rend="italic">v.</hi>
                    Taylor it was held that an information was grantable against a parson for
                    opposing the burial of a parishioner; but the court would not interpose as to
                    the parson’s refusal to read the burial service because he never was
                    baptized—that being matter for the ecclesiastical court. Strangers (or persons
                    not dying in the parish) should not be buried, it appears, without the consent
                    of the parishioners or churchwardens, “whose parochial right of burial is
                    invaded thereby.” According to a recent case, a clergyman may be punished for
                    refusing to read the burial service over a person who had ceased to be a
                    parishioner, but was buried in a family vault. While burial is a common-law
                    right, the mode of burial is said to be of ecclesiastical cognizance, and a
                    mandamus to inter a body in an iron coffin was in one case refused. Lord Stowell
                    permitted the use of iron coffins on condition of an increased rate of payment
                    to the parish, observing that the common cemetery is not <hi rend="italic"
                        >res</hi><hi rend="italic">unius aetatis,</hi> the property of one
                    generation now departed, but of the living and of generations yet unborn, and is
                    subject only to temporary appropriation (Gilbert <hi rend="italic">v.</hi>
                    Buzzard, 2 Consistory Reports, 333). One of the canons of 1603 requires the
                    clergyman under penalty of suspension for three months to bury the corpse
                    without refusal or delay, “unless the party deceased were excommunicated <hi
                        rend="italic">majori excommunicatione,</hi> for some grievous and notorious
                    crime, and no man able to testify of his repentance.” It appears that persons
                    dying in a state of intoxication must be buried with the funeral service of the
                    church. On the other hand no service but that of the Church of England may be
                    used, and no layman or unauthorized person can read or assist in reading a
                    burial service over a dead body in consecrated ground. Nor, it seems, does the
                    church recognize “such an indecency” as burial without service. There are
                    probably many questions as to the common right of burial to which the law has as
                    yet provided no specific answer. In the meantime many attempts have been made to
                    pass a Burials Bill, the main feature of which is the permission to use in
                    churchyards religious services other than that of the Church of England.</p>
                <p>The necessity for providing new cemeteries, caused by the natural increase of
                    population, has led to a good deal of legislation, and an Act was passed (10 and
                    11 Vict. c. 65) to consolidate certain provisions usually contained in Acts
                    authorizing the making of cemeteries. Sec. 23 allows the bishop to consecrate a
                    part of any such cemetery “for the burial of the dead according to the rites of
                    the Established Church.” The 15 and 16 Vict. c. 85, for discontinuing burials in
                    the metropolis and opening new burial grounds, was extended to other towns by
                    the 16 and 17 Vict. c. 134. The new burial ground is to be divided into
                    consecrated and unconsecrated portions; and provision is made for building a
                    cemetery chapel for the use of the church, and, if necessary, another for
                    dissenters. By 20 and 21 Vict. c. 81, ground may be consecrated for the burial
                    of poor persons. The same Act allows a burial board to appeal to the archbishop
                    when the ordinary refuses to consecrate a new burial ground, and if after the
                    archbishop confirms the appeal the bishop still refuses to consecrate, the
                    archbishop may licence the grave for interments as if it were consecrated. The
                    30 and 31 Viet, c. 133 (amended in the following year) provided facilities for
                    cheapening the expense of consecration and for allowing limited owners to convey
                    sites of land for churchyards.</p>
                <p>The practice of burying suicides on a public highway, with a stake driven through
                    the body, is prohibited by 4 Geo. IV. c. 52, which requires the coroner to
                    direct their private interment, without religious rites, in the churchyard,
                    within twenty-four hours after the inquest, and between the hours of nine and
                    twelve at night. Bodies may not be removed from burial grounds without licence
                    from a Secretary of State, except when the removal is from one unconsecrated
                    place to another, and is authorized by the ordinary. A coroner may disinter the
                    body in a case of violent death.</p>
                <p>In Scotland the obligation of providing and maintaining the churchyard rests on
                    the heritors of the parish. The guardianship of the churchyard belongs to the
                    heritors and also to the kirk-session, either by delegation from the heritors,
                    or in right of its ecclesiastical character. The right of burial appears to be
                    strictly limited to parishioners, although an opinion has been expressed that
                    any person dying in the parish has a right to be buried in the churchyard. The
                    parishioners have no power of management. The presbytery may interfere to compel
                    the heritors to provide due accommodation, but has no further jurisdiction. It
                    is the duty of the heritors to allocate the churchyard. The Scotch law hesitates
                    to attach the ordinary incidents of real property to the churchyard, while
                    English law treats the ground as the parson’s freehold. It would bo difficult to
                    sav who in Scotland is the legal owner of thç <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0599-0538"/> soil. Various opinions appear to prevail, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> as to grass growing on the surface and minerals
                    found beneath. The difficulty as to religious services does not exist. On the
                    other hand, the religious character of the ground is hostile to many of the
                    legal rights recognized by the English Law.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
