<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0599-0538-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURIATS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 538</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1002014">Logic</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952109">Hay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:990988">Lamas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c0c">Logic</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t316">Hay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nq7b">Ethics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURIATS</label>, a Mongolian race, who dwell in the vicinity
                    of the Baikal Lake, for the most part in the government of Irkutsk and the
                    Trans-Baikal territory. They are divided into various tribes or clans, which
                    generally take their names from the locality they frequent. These tribes are
                    subdivided according to kinship. In 1857 the Buriats numbered 190,000, about
                    two-thirds of whom were in the Trans-Baikal territory. They have high
                    cheek-bones, broad and flat noses, and sparse hair on the chin. The men shave
                    their heads like the Chinese, and leave a tail at the top. In summer they dress
                    in silk and cotton gowns, in winter in furs and sheepskins. Their principal
                    occupation is the rearing of cattle; and some of them possess about 500 oxen and
                    nearly 1000 horses. Some tribes, especially the Idinese, the Kudinese, the
                    Alarese, and the Khorinese, also engage in agriculture,—a department of activity
                    which was totally neglected till 1796, when the last-mentioned tribe first
                    turned its attention to it. As early as 1802 the produce of the Irkutsk
                    government was no less than 9800 quarters of grain; and in 1839 the Buriats had
                    229,500 acres under cultivation. Their soil is generally fertile, and they have
                    an elaborate system of irrigation by canals and trenches. Their only implements
                    are the plough and the harrow. Wheat, rye, spring corn, and oats are their
                    principal crops; and a large quantity of hay is made for their cattle. A good
                    deal of activity is also shown in trapping and fishing. In religion the Buriats
                    are mainly Buddhists; and their head lama (Khambo Lama) lives at the Goose Lake
                    (Gusinoe Ozero). Others are Shamanists, and their most sacred spot is the
                    Shamanic stone at the mouth of the River Angar. A few only, about 9000 or
                    10,000, are Christians. A knowledge of reading and writing is diffused,
                    especially among the Trans-Baikal Buriats, who possess books of their own,
                    chiefly translated from the Thibetan. Their own language is Mongolian, and
                    presents three distinct dialects, of which the Selengese is nearest to the
                    written form. The Russians became acquainted with the Buriats in the beginning
                    of the 16th century. In 1631 there was built in their territory, for the purpose
                    of bringing them into subjection, the Bratski block-house, whence arose the
                    Russian designation of Bratski applied to the Buriats. This building was
                    followed by the Kanski block-house in 1640, the Ver-kholenski in 1641, the
                    Udinski in 1648, the Balaganski in 1654, and finally in 1661 by Irkutsk itself.
                    The Buriats frequently besieged these posts and attacked the Russians, and in
                    1661 they even slew the Russian ambassador, Zabolotski; but in the end of the
                    17th century they were finally subdued. (See Gmelin, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Siberia;</hi> Pallas, <hi rend="italic">Mongol. Volkersch.;</hi> Castren, <hi
                    rend="italic">Versuch einer Burätisch. Sprachlehre.')</hi> BURIDAN", <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Jean,</hi> a celebrated philosopher who flourished in the 14th
                    century, was born at Bethune in Artois, but in what year is not known. He
                    studied at Paris under William of Occam, and became an ardent nominalist. The
                    legend which represents him as having been involved, when a student, in the
                    terrible drama of the Tour de Nesle has no discoverable historical basis. He
                    long held the office of professor of philosophy in the university of Paris; in
                    1327 he was its rector; in 1345 he was deputed to defend its interests before
                    Philip of Valois and at Rome. He was alive in 1358, but the year of his death
                    has not been recorded. The tradition that he was forced to flee from France
                    along with other nominalists, and that be settled in Vienna, and there founded
                    the university in 1356, is unsupported by evidence and in contradiction to the
                    fact that the university of Vienna was founded by Frederick II. in 1237. An
                    ordinance of Louis XI., in 1473, directed against the nominalists, prohibited
                    the reading of his works. These works treat of logic, metaphysics, physics,
                    ethics, and politics; theology is deliberately avoided on the ground that it
                    does not rest on reason alone, and does not proceed exclusively by
                    argumentation. In philosophy Buridan acknowledged no other authority than that
                    of reason. He followed Occam in resolutely denying all objective reality to
                    universals. He held that singulars or individuals alone exist, and that
                    universals are mere words. “Genera et species non sunt nisi termini apud animam
                    existentes vel etiam termini vocales aut scripti, qui non dicuntur genera aut
                    species nisi secundum attributionem ad terminos mentales quos designant.” Occam
                    had not gone so far. The chief aim of his logic is commonly represented as
                    having been the devising of rules for the easy and rapid discovery of
                    syllogistic middle terms,—the construction of a dialectical <hi rend="italic"
                    >pons</hi><hi rend="italic">asinorum,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> but there is
                    nothing in his writings to warrant this representation. The parts of logic which
                    he has treated with most minuteness and subtility are the doctrines of modal
                    propositions and of modal syllogisms. In commenting on Aristotle’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Nicomachean Ethics</hi> he dealt in a very independent and
                    interesting manner with the question of free will. The conclusions at which he
                    arrived are remarkably similar to those long afterwards reached by John Locke.
                    The only liberty which he ascribes to the soul is a certain power of suspending
                    the deliberative process and determining the direction of the intellect.
                    Otherwise the will is entirely dependent on the view of the mind, the last
                    result of examination. The comparison of the will unable to act between two
                    equally balanced motives to a hungry ass unable to eat between two equal and
                    equidistant bundles of hay is not found in any of his works, and may have been
                    invented by his opponents to ridicule his determinism. His works are— <hi
                    rend="italic">Summula</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dialectica,</hi> 1487; <hi rend="italic">Compendium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >logi</hi><hi rend="italic">coe,</hi> 1489; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quoestiones</hi><hi rend="italic">in viii.</hi><hi rend="italic">libros
                    physicorum,</hi> &amp;c., 1516 <hi rend="italic">', In Aristotelis
                    Metaphysica,</hi> 1518; <hi rend="italic">Quoestiones</hi><hi rend="italic">in
                    x. libros ethicorum Aristotelis,</hi> 1489; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quoestiones</hi><hi rend="italic">in viii. libros politicorum Aristotelis,</hi>
                    1500. There may be consulted regarding him, besides the general histories of
                    philosophy, Bayle’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary,</hi> art. “Buridan ”; Prantl’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Logik,</hi> bk. iv. 14-38; and Stöckl’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte der Philosophie des Mittelalters,</hi> Bd. ii. 1023-
                    1028. <hi rend="smallcaps">(r. f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
