<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0634-0573-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURY ST EDMUNDS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 573</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:874681">Confessors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:794221">Abbots</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n634/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURY ST EDMUNDS</label>, a market-town and municipal and
                    parliamentary borough of England, in the county of Suffolk, on the Lark, 26
                    miles N.W. of Ipswich, and 71 miles from London. It is governed by a mayor, six
                    aidermen, and eighteen councillors, and returns two members to Parliament. The
                    town is pleasantly situated on a gentle eminence, in a fertile and richly
                    cultivated district, is clean and well built, and has a good drainage system. It
                    is supposed to be the <hi rend="italic">Villa JVaustini</hi> of the Romans, and
                    numerous Roman remains have been dug up on the spot. It was the Beodericsworth
                    of the Saxons, and by them was made a royal town of East Anglia. Its present
                    name is derived from St Edmund, the king and martyr, who was taken prisoner and
                    put to death by the Danes in 870. In 1020 a monastery was founded there by
                    Canute, which for magnificence and splendour surpassed every other establishment
                    of the kind in Britain, with the exception of that of Glastonbury. It was 505
                    feet long and 212 w ide; and contained twelve chapels. The abbot had a seat in
                    Parliament, with the power to inflict capital punishment, and judged in_all
                    civil causes within the liberty. The privilege of coining was granted to the
                    abbot by Edward the Confessor, and both Edward I. and Edward II. had mints in
                    the town. In 1327 the people of the town and neighbourhood attacked the
                    monastery and reduced a large part of it to ashes. The tower or church-gate, one
                    of the finest specimens of Norman architecture in the kingdom, and the western
                    gate, erected about the middle of the 14th century, with a small portion of the
                    walls, are all that now remains of that magnificent structure. St Mary’s church,
                    a fine Gothic edifice, with a beautifully carved roof, was erected in the
                    earlier part of the 15th century, and contains the tomb of Mary Tudor, Queen of
                    Louis XII. of France. St James’s church is also a very fine building, containing
                    several handsome monuments. The free grammar school, founded by Edward VI., has
                    two scholarships at Cambridge, and six exhibitions to each university. The town
                    has a shire-hall where assizes for the county and liberty are held, a handsome
                    and commodious corn exchange, a guildhall, news and assembly rooms, a theatre, a
                    savings-bank, botanic gardens, a county jail, a general hospital, and about 100
                    almshouses. The market-days are Wednesday and Saturday. Wednesday’s market is
                    very important, both for com and cattle, but particularly for the latter, being
                    second only to that of Norwicn, which is the largest in the Eastern counties.
                    About a mile below the town the river becomes navigable for barges to Lynn,
                    whence coals and other commodities were tormeιly brought, but of late years,
                    since the formation of the railway, the river has been but little used, <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n635/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0635-0574"/> There are four lines of railway,—in connection
                    with London and Cambridgeshire for the north, Thetford to Norwich and West
                    Norfolk, Ipswich and East Suffolk, and Colchester for Essex. In the vicinity is
                    Ickworth, the magnificent seat of the marquis of Bristol. The town was the
                    birthplace of Bishop Gardiner, and gives the title of viscount to the Keppel
                    family (Earls of Albemarle). Population in 1871, 14,928.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
