<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0642-0581-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUTE, John Stuart, third Earl of (9th edition, volume
                    4, page 581)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nk3680j">Eras</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v18f">Princesses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938095">Garters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962162">Households</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1076505">Princesses</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n642/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Stuart, third Earl
                        of</hi></label> (1713-1792), for a brief time prime minister of England, was
                    born in 1713, and was educated at Eton. Horace Walpole, who was one of his
                    contemporaries there, tells us that Bute “studied simples in the hedges about
                    Twickenham.” For many years he resided in the remote island of Bute, where he
                    appears to have diligently studied mathematics, mechanics, and natural science.
                    He married the daughter of Mr and the celebrated Lady Mary Wortley Montagu, an
                    alliance which subsequently brought the large Wortley estates into his family. A
                    mere accident introduced him at court; a shower of rain interrupted a cricket
                    match at Cliefden, and led to his services being required by the Prince of
                    Wales. He received a bedchamber appointment in the household of the prince.
                    Prince Frederick died, however, next year, and Lord Bute lived in retirement. On
                    the formation of a separate household for the princess and the young princes, he
                    received the appointment of groom of the stole, somewhat to the dissatisfaction
                    of the old king, George II., who gave him the gold key of office in an
                    ungracious way. In the household of the Prince of Wales Lord Bute acquired great
                    influence over the mind of the youthful heir of the throne and his mother. The
                    scandal of the last century associated his name most intimately with that of the
                    princess, but for this cruel and persistent rumour there appears to be no
                    foundation either in contemporary literature or in the large inedited Bute
                    MSS.</p>
                <p>Lord Bute does not appear to have had much to do with the education of the future
                    king and his brothers, which was chiefly left in episcopal hands. He took,
                    however, some part in the direction of his studies, and is known to have read
                    Blackstone’s <hi rend="italic">Commentaries,</hi> when still in MS., with him.
                    He seems also to have inculcated him with the writings of Bolingbroke, whose
                    theory was that a king should not only reign but govern, and who had sketched
                    out the ideal of a patriot king. The constant language of the Princess Dowager,
                    re-echoed by the groom of the stole, was “George, be king!” In 1760 George II.
                    died, and the young king proceeded to put in practice the teachings he had
                    received. This marked an important era in constitutional history. Then began the
                    era of the “king’s friends ;” the royal will was to be supreme; the ministers
                    were simply to act ministerially, giving expression to and carrying out the
                    sovereign’s pleasure. It is manifest that this doctrine weakened the
                    responsibility of ministers and the authority of parliament, and invited dangers
                    in the direction both of absolutism and of anarchy. Bute, however, was prepared
                    to carry out a scheme very like Strafford's “Thorough” with zeal and energy. The
                    day after the accession Bute was made a privy councillor. A little later he was
                    made secretary of state. Afterwards he was made Knight of the Garter. The king
                    told the ministers, “Lord Bute is my very good friend ;” and the royal will was
                    expressed through him. The extraordinary spectacle was witnessed, on the meeting
                    of parliament, of a man with no political connection, who had never been in the
                    cabinet, and who had never served in any ministerial office, being practically
                    prime minister. What he was in reality he soon became in name. In the <hi
                        rend="italic">Shelburne Correspondence</hi> we find him asserting that there
                    was nothing which he could not do. The ministers at the time of the accession,
                    who both in the Eastern and the Western World were maintaining the war with
                    France with the greatest glory and success, were William Pitt, the duke of
                    Newcastle, and Mr Legge. The last, Mr Legge, was ignominiously dismissed. Pitt
                    could not carry the support of the cabinet in his proposal to declare war
                    against Spain, and therefore resigned, —a resignation which probably prevented a
                    dismissal. Such insults were heaped upon the duke of Newcastle that, although he
                    long clung to office, he was at last compelled to resign.</p>
                <p>As premier, Bute showed considerable ability. Lord Mansfield said he never knew
                    any man come to business so late who did it so well, and he proved an extremely
                    good speaker. He also gave considerable patronage to literature and art. He had
                    several distinct points of policy. He wished to close the era of war and make
                    peace with France. He wished to sever the political connection between England
                    and Hanover. He wished to humble the dominant Whig families, and to make the
                    king supreme. In all these objects he was to a considerable extent successful.
                    The popular feeling against the peace was intense. Still the minister had
                    secured a large majority in the House of Commons; but although he had spoken
                    much of purity of election, it is not to be denied that there had been extensive
                    bribery in the elections. Confident of the royal support and a parliamentary
                    majority, he seemed secure of a long lease of power.</p>
                <p>After being premier for eleven months, to the astonishment of all, he suddenly
                    resigned. He was unable to face the black tide of personal unpopularity which
                    set in so heavily against him. Wilkes’s publication of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >North Briton</hi> had both expressed and intensified his unpopularity. He
                    was in danger of being impeached; he was in danger of being torn in pieces by
                    the mob. He went about disguised. He attempted to conciliate popularity by
                    recalling Pitt to office; but Pitt would only return with his Whig friends, to
                    which the king would not consent. Then Lord Bute’s courage gave way. His own
                    explanation was, “The ground I stand upon is so hollow that I am afraid, not
                    only of falling myself, but of involving my royal master in my own ruin.” But
                    although he resigned office, his influence with the king was hardly impaired. It
                    was the king’s custom, at least for some time, to write a minute daily journal
                    of <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n643/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0643-0582"/> events and transmit it to Lord Bute. Both
                    Grenville who succeeded him, and Rockingham who succeeded Grenville, regarded
                    him with the utmost jealousy. Grenville made it an absolute condition that Bute
                    should retire from the presence and counsels of the young king. He retired to
                    Luton; he afterwards travelled on the Continent under the name of Sir John
                    Stuart He complained bitterly that he was not allowed <hi rend="italic">“to</hi>
                    enjoy that peace, that liberty, which is the birthright of the meanest Briton,
                    but which has been long denied me.”</p>
                <p>The influence of Lord Bute over the king was great for a time, but it has been
                    much exaggerated. After a few years it seems to have declined altogether. Both
                    the king and Lord Bute soon disclaimed its existence, and there is no lack of
                    corroboratory evidence But it was impossible to eradicate the notion that there
                    was a back-stairs influence personified in Lord Bute. He was denounced in
                    popular addresses before the king himself as a betrayer of the constitution, and
                    mobs regularly broke his windows. Wilkes reviled him; Junius thundered against
                    him. Lord Chatham declaimed against him as one behind the throne greater than
                    the throne itself. For twenty years he was regarded with invincible hostility
                    and suspicion, yet we find him complaining that he had not the influence of an
                    aiderman in obtaining a position for his son. Horace Walpole gives a curious
                    account of an offer being made to Chatham shortly before his death of making him
                    premier with a dukedom, he himself being a secretary of state. The facts are not
                    well ascertained, but Lord Mountstuart, afterwards first marquis of Bute, wrote
                    to assert upon his honour that his father, Lord Bute, assured him that he had
                    not thought of coming into place again.</p>
                <p>Lord Bute had purchased an estate at Luton in Bedfordshire, where Adams, the
                    Scottish architect, had built him a magnificent residence. Here he formed an
                    immense library, a superb collection of astronomical and philosophical
                    instruments, and an admirable gallery of pictures, which are preserved in a
                    large house appropriated to them in Warwick Square, London. On the summit of a
                    plain Tuscan pillar in the grounds is an inscription in honour of his great
                    friend and benefactress the Princess Dowager. Pie took great delight in
                    architecture, and among other edifices built himself a marine villa on the edge
                    of the cliff, in Hampshire, overlooking the Needles and the Isle of Wight. He is
                    said to have been an admirable tutor and father to his children, and to have
                    taken a greater pleasure in simple,· natural delights than he could have found
                    in courts. His death was occasioned through that intense love of natural science
                    which had followed him through life. Seeing a new plant on the cliff he climbed
                    towards it, and received a severe fall, which brought on an illness of which he
                    died.</p>
                <p>The eleven months’ premiership, during which he was mayor of the palace, was a
                    singular episode in his prolonged life,—a remarkable and unconstitutional
                    experiment in politics which has never been repeated. Lord Bute possessed great
                    virtues, great energy and ability, and was as able a premier as Newcastle,
                    Grenville, or Rockingham, But the royal favouritism on which he relied proved
                    the greatest bar to his political success, and has left a slur, exaggerated, but
                    not altogether ill-deserved, on his memory. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f.
                    a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
