<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0064-0055-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BORNEO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 55</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="26" ref="fastgeo:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1138427">Sultans</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1138426">Sultanate</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1104535">Sambas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b07v">Dyak</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n64/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BORNEO</label>, one of the largest islands of the world, is
                    situated about the middle of the East Indian Archipelago, and lies immediately
                    under the equator, between 7° N. and 4° 20' S. lat., and between 109° and 118°
                    E. long. It forms a kind of irregular hexagon, and its area is estimated by
                    Engelhardt at 289,000 Eng. square miles (more than double the area of the United
                    Kingdom). Its coast-line is much less broken than that of most of the
                    neighbouring islands; and though there are some extensive bays, such as Maludu
                    in the north and Sarawak in the west, none of them are so deep as greatly to
                    interfere with the regularity of its côntour. A large proportion of the seaboard
                    is of alluvial formation; and in various districts the deposition of new land is
                    very perceptibly going on. The whole of the ground, for example, to the west of
                    the Kandang Mountains in the kingdom of Landak ha3 been gained from the sea
                    during the last four centuries, and it is evident that many smaller islands
                    which fringed the coast in former times have been incorporated with the
                    mainland. This process of extension goes on all the more rapidly, because the
                    neighbouring sea is very shallow, except on the eastern side.</p>
                <p>Of the interior of the island a considerable part has been only partially
                    explored, so that the physical features can <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n65/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0065-0056"/> hardly be given with sufficient precision and
                    detail. The general character of the country is mountainous, though none of the
                    ranges and few of the individual peaks attain to any great elevation The centre
                    of the island seems to be occupied by a kind of table-land, with which the
                    principal chains connect themselves more or less directly. Of these the most
                    extensive may be traced from Cape Dattb on the west coast, in 2° 5' 24" N. lat.,
                    northwards through the length of the island, which it divides as watershed into
                    two portions, a north-western of comparatively narrow dimensions, and a
                    south-eastern comprising the rest of the island. The different parts of the
                    chain are known by various local names, as the Krimbang or Bayang-Miut, the
                    Batang-Lupar, the Madi, and the Anga-Anga Mountains. Tn the north-west corner of
                    the island it attains its highest elevation in Kini-balu, or St Pietersberg,
                    which is generally supposed to be the highest peak in the whole island.
                    According to the trigonometrical measurement of Capt. Belcher the summit is
                    13,G98 feet above the level of the sea, but this was in 1851 reduced to 9500 by
                    Messrs Low and St John, who were the first to ascend the mountain. A second
                    great chain, known as the Kaminting Mountains, stretches south-west from the
                    Anga-Anga, and fills the south-west corner of the island with numerous offshoots
                    and underfalls; and a third starting from the same quarter strikes first
                    south-east and then south along the southern part of the eastern coast, and is
                    known as the Meratu Mountains. A fourth chain, of which the most important part
                    bears the name of Sakuru, runs almost due east to Cape Kamiungun.</p>
                <p>U alike the most of the larger islands of the archipelago, and in remarkable
                    contrast with Java, Borneo seems to possess no active volcanoes. Many of the
                    peaks, however, bear distinct evidence of former activity in regular craters,
                    now in some cases forming lakes of salt water. The prevailing rocks are
                    limestone, slate, sandstones, conglomerates, and on the mountain tops syenitic
                    granite. The limestone hills are remarkable for the number of their caves, many
                    of which, such as those of Kumbary, are a source of wealth to the natives, as
                    they afford shelter to swallows that build edible nests.</p>
                <p>The island, which is abundantly supplied with rivers and streams, may be
                    hydrographically divided into five principal versants Of these the shortest lies
                    along the northwestern slope of the Krimbang and Kini-balu range, and discharges
                    its waters into the Chinese Sea. The most important of its rivers are the
                    Sarawak, the Batang-Lupar, the Seribas, the Rejang (which is navigable for 140
                    miles), the Baram (about half a mile wide at its mouth), the Limbang or Bruni
                    River, the Tewaran, the Bintulu, and the Tampasuk, the last two having their
                    sources in Mount Kini-balu itself. In the south-western versant the largest
                    river is the Kapuas, which, rising towards the centre of the island, in about
                    114° E. long., falls, after a long and winding course, into the sea between
                    Mempawa and Sukkadana. It has eight navigable mouths, and at Sintang, where it
                    receives the Melawi, its principal tributary, it has a breadth of 1072 feet and
                    a varying depth of 6 to 11 fathoms. The Banjermassin or Barito, which is the
                    master stream of the southern versant, rises in the Kuti-Lama Lake, and reaches
                    the Sea of Java in 114° 30' E. long. Its upper channel is greatly interrupted by
                    rocks and waterfalls, but the lower part of its course is wide and navigable,
                    and traverses a rich alluvial district. Cross branches unite it with two rivers
                    of considerable size towards the west, the Little Dayak or Murung and the Great
                    Dayak or Kahayan, and still further west are the independent rivers Mendawi,
                    Sampit, Pembuang or Surian, and Kota-Waringin. Passing over the south-east
                    corner of the island, which is watered by a large number of short mountain
                    streams, we reach the one great river of the eastern versant, the Kuti (Coti) or
                    Mahakkan, which, rising in Mount Lassan-Tula, flows east, with a rapid and
                    sinuous course, and falls by numerous mouths into the Strait of Macassar. Most
                    of the rivers of the northern versant are comparatively small, as the island
                    narrows iuto a kind of promontory. Besides the Sebuku, which rises in Mount
                    Pentyieangan and falls into the sea at Temelingan, the Berou, the Gunong-Tebur,
                    and the Bulungan arc all worthy of mention.</p>
                <p>Among the lakes of Borneo that of Kini-balu, near the mountain of the same name,
                    is regarded as the largest, but many others are of considerable size. The Danau
                    Sriang, for example, on the Kapuas River, is, according to Dr E. van Martens,
                    larger than the Lake of Constance. In the valley of the Banjermassin are the
                    Babi and the Pamingir (or Telaga) Jakes, the latter of which supplies nearly all
                    the inhabitants of the kiugdom with fish; and in the district of Sintang there
                    is an extensive sheet of water, on the Kapuas-Tawang, which was discovered in
                    1825, and is known by the various names of the Luar, Sumbah, Malayu, or van
                    Capellan Lake.</p>
                <p>In spite of the equatorial position of the island its climate is nowhere
                    oppressive, and in many places might almost be called temperate. At Pontianak,
                    for example, which is almost under the equator, the mean reading of the
                    thermometer is 82°, while it varies from 76° to 79° at sunrise, and hardly ever,
                    even at noon, exceeds 92°. The difference between the rainy season and the dry
                    is not rigidly marked; the atmosphere is moist all the year round, and while, on
                    the one hand, there is hardly a day of continuous downpour, there is hardly, on
                    the other hand, a day without a shower. During the rainy season, which extends
                    from November to May inclusive, the torrents, while they last, are tremendous,
                    and the wind is frequently violent. Over such an extensive area there is, of
                    course, great variety in the climatic character of different districts,
                    especially when viewed in relation to health. Some places, as Bidi, for example,
                    are notoriously unhealthy; but from the statistics of the Dutch Government it
                    appears that the European has in general no more to fear in Borneo than in the
                    island of Java. Among the native races the prevailing diseases are principally
                    those that arise from bad food or want of cleanliness. Scrofula is common
                    throughout the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0066-0057"/> country, and elephantiasis is frequently met with
                    on the coast. Small-pox, dysentery, and fevers are the usual epidemics; and
                    ophthalmia sometimes attacks whole tribes. About a sixth of the native
                    population in some quarters suffer from a kind of ringworm, called kurab, which
                    is identified with <hi rend="italic">herpes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >farinosus.</hi> Consumption is not uncommon.</p>
                <p>The mineral wealth of Borneo is great and varied, including diamonds, gold,
                    platina, quicksilver, cinnabar, copper, iron, tin, antimony, petroleum, sulphur,
                    rock-salt, marble, and coal. Landak and Pontianak arc the best diamond
                    districts, and Sambas, Landak, Montrado, and Borneo Proper furnish the greatest
                    quantity of gold. The annual amount of gold collected in the island cannot be
                    ascertained; but the amount exported from Bruni in 1870 was 5789 dollars. Coal
                    of excellent quality is found in the valleys of the Banjermassin, the Kuti, the
                    Gunong-Tebur, and the Melawi, as well as in Sarawak, and in the island of
                    Labuan. The Kuti deposit was discovered in 1845 or 1846 above Samarinda, and has
                    since been struck in a number of places along the main river and several of the
                    tributaries. A mine was opened at Pelarang, but does not seem to be at present
                    worked. Another, however, at Pengaron, on the Riam Kiva, yields annually about
                    9000 or 10,000 tons. The coal-fields in Borneo Proper were conceded to Sir James
                    Brooke in 1846, and since 1868 have been in the hands of the Oriental Coal
                    Company, which has as yet taken no advantage of its rights. Antimony was
                    discovered to be a Bornean product by Mr J. Craufurd, the well-known geographer,
                    who, in 1825, learned that a quantity had been brought to Singapore by a native
                    trader as ballast. The supply is practically unlimited, and the chief mine is at
                    Bidi in Sarawak.</p>
                <p>The fauna of Borneo comprises a large variety of species, many of which are
                    numerically of great importance. Among the Quadrumana, which are very well
                    represented, the most remarkable is the orang-outan (or <hi rend="italic"
                    >mias,</hi> as it is called by the natives), an animal only to be found
                    elsewhere in the Island of Sumatra. It frequents the low-lying districts,
                    especially in the neighbourhood of the Dyak plantations. The wawah, a kind of
                    gibbon, several <hi rend="italic">Semnopitheci</hi> (as the longnosed ape and
                    the golden-black or chrysomelas), and the large-eyed <hi rend="italic"
                    >Stenops</hi><hi rend="italic">tardigradus</hi> are also worthy of mention. The
                    larger beasts of prey seem to be altogether wanting, so that little check is put
                    on the natural fecundity of the graminivorous species. A small panther and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Felis</hi><hi rend="italic">macrocelis</hi> are the largest
                    animals of the cat-kind known; for though the tiger has sometimes been reported
                    to occur in the mountains, its presence has never been verified. The Malay or
                    honey bear is very common. The rhinoceros is found on the north-west coast, and
                    the elephant, introduced by the Chinese or Portuguese, in the neighbourhood of
                    Cape Unsang. Wild oxen of the Sunda race are not uncommon; and the whole island
                    swarms with droves of wild pigs, which are distinguished by a curious
                    protuberance of hair on each side of the head. These furnish food not only to
                    the Dyaks, who are very fond of the flesh, but also to the crocodiles that
                    abound in the principal rivers. Three or four species of deer are enumerated,
                    one of which, the pelandok of the Malays, is remarkable for its smallness and
                    beauty. Squirrels, porcupines, civet-cats, rats, bats, and lizards are well
                    represented, and snakes of various kinds, from the boa constrictor downwards,
                    are abundant, while the marshy districts swarm with frogs and leeches. The
                    latter attach themselves in a most troublesome manner to the passing traveller.
                    A remarkable flying-frog was discovered by Mr Wallace. Birds are comparatively
                    rare in many quarters; the most important being eagles, vultures, falcons, owls,
                    horn-bills, cranes, pheasants,—notably the Argus-pheasant, —partridges, ravens,
                    crows, parrots,woodpeckers, doves, and swallows. The <hi rend="italic">Cypselus
                    esculentus,</hi> or edible-nest swallow, is very common. Mosquitoes and
                    sandflies are the chief insect pests, and in some districts are very
                    troublesome. There is also a kind of ant called the <hi rend="italic">sumpitrapi
                    or</hi> fire-ant, the sting of which is very painful. The lepidopterous insects
                    are remarkable for their number, variety, beauty, and size. In one favourable
                    situation Mr Wallace caught 120 different species of moths in one night. The
                    Coleoptera are no less numerously represented, as, indeed, might be expected in
                    so richly-wooded a region. The lakes and rivers, as well as the surrounding sea,
                    abound with fish. Dr Bleeker in his “Bijdragen tot de Kennis der Ichthyologische
                    Fauna van Borneo," in the <hi rend="italic">Natuurkundig Tijdschrift van Nederl.
                    Ind.,</hi> describes 176 species which he obtained during his residence in the
                    island.</p>
                <p>The domestic animals of Borneo are few both in number of species and for the most
                    part in number of individuals. The character of the country has prevented the
                    development of pastoral modes of life. In some districts, as in the
                    neighbourhood of Ambong, there are bullocks of the Brahmin breed, about thirteen
                    hands high; the buffalo is sometimes employed in agriculture; and sheep and
                    goats occur. The cat and dog are both domesticated. A few horses, introduced by
                    Europeans, and only possessed by the wealthier classes, are found in
                    Banjermassin and Sarawak.</p>
                <p>The flora of Borneo is very rich, the whole surface of the island being clothed
                    in luxuriant vegetation. The king of the forest is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >tappan,</hi> which, rising to a great height with a single branchless stem, is
                    crowned with a splendid dome of foliage. From the wood of this tree the chiefs
                    construct their official seats. The iron-wood, so remarkable for the durability
                    of its timber, is abundant; it is used by the natives for the pillars of their
                    houses, and forms an article of export to China. It is almost rivalled by the
                    <hi rend="italic">kayu temesu</hi> in hardness. In all about sixty kinds of
                    timber are furnished in more or less profusion. Palm-trees are abundant in great
                    variety, including the <hi rend="italic">nipa,</hi> cabbage, fan, cocoa-nut, and
                    sago palms; the two last afford large supplies of food to the natives.
                    Gutta-percha, camphor, cinnamon, cloves, nutmegs, gambir, and betel-nuts are all
                    produced in the island; most of the tropical fruits flourish, such as the
                    mangosteen, the lansat, rambutan, jack, jambon, and blimbang; nor must the
                    wonderful durian be forgotten, of which Mr Wallace enthusiastically declares
                    that it is worth a voyage from Europe to taste it. It is a large fruit with an
                    exceedingly strong spiked outer covering, and not unfrequently inflicts severe
                    wounds by falling on the passers by. Yams, potatoes (an indigenous sort),
                    melons, pumpkins, cucumbers, pine-apples, and bananas, sugar, pepper, cotton,
                    and tobacco are cultivated, though not as yet on a very extensive scale. In the
                    south-eastern division of the Dutch territory the export of cotton was in 1854
                    1795 picols. The product of the wild plant is very good, and is exported from
                    Borneo Proper. Among the more beautiful of the flowering plants are
                    rhododendrons, orchids, and pitcher-plants,—the last reaching a most
                    extraordinary development, especially in the northern districts about Kini-balu.
                    Epiphytous plants are very common, many that are usually independent assuming
                    here the parasitic character. The <hi rend="italic">Vanda Lowιi,</hi> for
                    example, “grows on the lower branches of trees, and its strange pendent
                    flower-stalks often hang down so as almost to reach the ground.” Ferns are
                    abundant, but are not so varied as in Java; Mr Wallace collected fifty
                    species.</p>
                <p>The population of Borneo consists of a considerable variety of races, of very
                    different-origin, and of different degrees of civilization. The most important
                    numerically are the Dyaks, the Malays, the Chinese, and the Buginese; <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n67/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0067-0058"/> and, from their political influence, the Arabs
                    and the Dutch.</p>
                <p>The Dyaks, Dayaks, or Dayakkers are generally regarded as the most aboriginal.
                    For themselves they have no general designation; but, broken as they are into
                    numerous tribes, they are distinguished by separate tribal names, many of which
                    seem to be merely the names of the rivers on which their settlements are
                    situated. Though regarded by the Malays as aliens, and looked down upon as
                    almost beneath humanity, they belong to the same race. Separation, however, must
                    have taken place at a very early date. Kessel, who has attempted to form a
                    classification of the Dyaks according to their ethnographical affinity, divides
                    them into five principal branches. The first of these, which he calls the
                    north-western, includes the natives of Sadong, Sarawak, Sambas, Landak, Tayan,
                    Melionøw, and Sangow. They all speak the same language, and are remärkable for
                    their dependence on the Malay princes. The second branch, which is called
                    emphatically the Malayan from its greater retention of Malay characteristics,
                    occupies the north coast in Banting, Batang-Lupar, Rejang, and part of the
                    valley of the Kapuas. To the third or Parian branch belong the Dyaks of the
                    rivers Kuti and Passir, who are said to speak a language like that of Macassar.
                    The fourth consists of the Beyadjoes, who are settled in the valley of the
                    Banjermassin; and the fifth and lowest comprises thé Manketans and Punans, who
                    are still nomadic and ignorant of agriculture. In stature the Dyak is rather
                    above the Malay, while still considerably shorter than the average European. He
                    is rather slightly built, but is active and capable of eħduring great fatigue.
                    His features are distinctly marked and often well-formed, though the cheekbones
                    are higher and the nose more <hi rend="italic">retrousse</hi> than agrees with
                    the European standard. The forehead is generally high, and the eyes are dark;
                    the hair is black, and the colour of the skin a pure reddish brown, that
                    frequently, in the female, approaches to a Chinese complexion. In general
                    neither beard nor whiskers are present, but this does not hold of all the
                    tribes. In dress there is considerable variety, great alterations having
                    resulted from foreign influence. The original and still prevailing style is very
                    simple, consisting of a mere <hi rend="italic">chawat</hi> or waistcloth,
                    generally of blue cotton, for the men, and a tight-fitting petticoat for the
                    women, who acquire a peculiar mincing gait from its interference with their
                    walking. The favourite ornaments of both sexes are brass rings for the legs and
                    arms, hoops of rattan decorated in various ways, necklaces of white and black
                    beads, and crescent-shaped ear-rings of a large size. Tattooing is commonly
                    practised by most of the tribes. The men usually go bare-headed, ot wear a
                    bright-coloured kerchief. The custom of betel-chewing being almost universal,
                    the betel-pouch worn at the side is a necessary part of the equipment. The
                    weapons in use are a <hi rend="italic">klewary</hi> or curved sword and a long
                    spear. The bow is unknown, but its place among some tribes is partly supplied by
                    the <hi rend="italic">sumpitan,</hi> or blowpipe, in the boring of which they
                    show great skill. When going to war the Dyak invests himself with a strong
                    padded jacket, which proves no bad defence. Not only is it a custom with many
                    tribes to preserve the skulls of their slaughtered enemies as trophies of their
                    success in war; but, as the possession of a certain number of human heads is
                    necessary before a man can be admitted to some of the most important of his
                    social privileges, it is usual for the young men to go out on private
                    head-hunting excursions. The custom, however, is dying out before the influence
                    of civilization.</p>
                <p>The Dyak is decidedly intelligent; his memory is tenacious, and his powers of
                    observation good. Unacquainted in his natural state with both reading and
                    writing, his aptitude for acquiring these arts is greatly praised by
                    missionaries. In moral character he is far superior to the civilized Malay,
                    being unsuspicious and hospitable, and honest and truthful in a striking degree.
                    The various tribes differ greatly in religious ceremonies and beliefs, and it is
                    hard to give a satisfactory idea of them. They have no temples, priests, or
                    regular recurrence of worship; but the father of each family performs such rites
                    as the exigencies of each day demand. A supreme god seems generally
                    acknowledged, but subordinate deities are supposed to watch over special
                    departments of the world and human affairs. Sacrifices both of animals and
                    fruits—and in some cases even of human beings—are offered to appease or invoke
                    the gods; divination of various kinds is resorted to for the purpose of deciding
                    the course to be pursued in any emergency; and criminals are subjected to the
                    ordeal by poison or otherwise. There is a very strong belief in the existence of
                    evil spirits, and all kinds of calamities and diseases are ascribed to their
                    malignity. Thus almost the whole medical system of the Dyaks consists in the
                    application of appropriate charms or the offering of conciliatory sacrifices.
                    Many of those natives who have had much intercourse with the Malays have adopted
                    a kind of mongrel Mahometanism, with a mixture of Hindu elements. The
                    transmigration of souls seems to be believed in by some tribes; and some have a
                    system of successive heavens rising one above the other very much in the style
                    of the Hindu cosmogony. In the treatment of their dead the same variety prevails
                    as in other things—they are sometimes buried, sometimes burned, and sometimes
                    elevated on lofty framework. The Dyaks have no exact calculation of the year,
                    and simply name the months first month, second month, and so on. They calculate
                    the time of day by the height of the sun, and if asked how far distant a place
                    is can only reply by showing how high the sun would be when you reached it if
                    you set out in the morning. In agriculture, navigation, and manufactures they
                    have made some progress. In a few districts a slight sort of plough is used, but
                    the usual instrument of tillage is a kind of cleaver. Two crops, one of rice and
                    the other of maize or vegetables, arc taken, and then the ground is allowed to
                    fallow for eight or ten years. They spin and weave their own cotton, and dye the
                    cloth with indigo of their own growing. Their iron and steel instruments are
                    excellent, the latter far surpassing European wares in strength and fineness of
                    edge. Their houses are neatly built of bamboos, and raised on piles a
                    considerable height from the ground; but perhaps their most remarkable
                    constructive effort is the erection of suspension bridges and paths over rivers
                    and along the front of precipices, in which they display a boldness and
                    ingenuity that surprise the European traveller.</p>
                <p>The Dyaks speak a variety of dialects, most of which are still very slightly
                    known. The tribes on the coast have adopted a great number of pure Malay words
                    into common use, and it is often hard to ascertain their own proper synonyms.
                    The American missionaries have investigated the dialects of the west coast
                    (Landak, &amp;c.), and their Rhenish brethren have devoted their attention to
                    those of the south, into one of which (that of Pulu Petak) a complete
                    translation of the Bible has been made. Air Hardeland, the translator, has also
                    published a Dyak-German dictionary. (See Vocabularies in St John’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Life in the Forests.)</hi> On the authority of the sultan of
                    Bruni, who in 1824 visited Singapore, Crawfurd asserts that of the forty wild
                    tribes that inhabit Bruni, eight had completely, and five partially, adopted the
                    Malay speech. The dialect of the Kayans seems to be one of the
                    purest,—nine-tenths of its words having no cognates in the other languages of
                    the archipelago.</p>
                <p>For an account of the Malays the reader must be referred to a separate article,
                    but the Chinese require more particular notice. They seem to have been the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n68/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0068-0059"/> first civilized people who had dealings with
                    Borneo: their own annals speak of tribute paid to the pmpire by Pha-la o∏ the
                    north-east coast of the island as early as the 7th century, and later documents
                    mention a Chinese colonization in the 15th. The traditions of the Malays and
                    Dyaks support these statements,—the people of Bruni regarding themselves as
                    partly of Chinese descent, and the annals of Sulu recording an extensive Chinese
                    immigration about 1575. Be this as it may, the flourishing condition of Borneo
                    in the 16 th and 17th centuries was largely due to trade with China. The Chinese
                    founded in the 18th century an important colony in Bruni; but their numbers were
                    lessened by the bad treatment of the princes. The Malay chiefs of other
                    districts invited them to come and develop the mineral wealth of the country,
                    and before long they were to be found in considerable numbers in Saιnbas,
                    Montrado, Pontianak, and elsewhere. They were at first forbidden to engage in
                    commerce or agriculture, and prevented from wearing fire-arms or possessing
                    gunpowder. About i779 the Dutch acquired immediate authority over all strangers,
                    and thus had the means of controlling the new colonists, who soon proved
                    themselves rather troublesome. Their numbers continually increased, and they
                    pushed inland to new mineral districts, forming friendships and contracting
                    marriages with the Dyaks. For the better management of their affairs they
                    entered into extensive associations, which gradually assumed more and more of a
                    political character until they were almost regular confederacies. This rendered
                    them at once more disposed and more able to assert their claims to independence;
                    and it cost both the Dutch Government and the Rajah of Sarawak several severe
                    contests to bring them to terms. They form at the same time one of the most
                    valuable elements in Bornean civilization, and are an industrious, intelligent,
                    and well-educated race, It would be hard to find a man among them who cannot
                    read and write; and their first care in a new settlement is to found a school.
                    The greater part of those on the west coast are emigrants, originally from the
                    northern boundaries of Quang-tung and Quang-si. They are rough, stern, and
                    quarrelsome. A more polished class come from the coast district of Amoy, and
                    look down on their ruder fellow-countrymen, from whom they keep themselves
                    markedly distinct. The former class are called Kehs by the Borneans, and the
                    latter Ollohs.</p>
                <p>In regard to the number of the population of Borneo it is difficult to arrive at
                    anything like a satisfactory estimate. The inland districts seem to be very
                    thinly inhabited; and the Dyaks increase in numbers at a very slow rate, in
                    spite of their being both a healthy and moral people. This is attributed by Mr
                    Wallace mainly to infecundity on the part of the women brought on by the
                    excessive labour to which they are subjected from early girlhood. The population
                    of the Dutch territory was stated in 1871 at 335,677 natives and 131 Europeans
                    in the western division, and at 847,846 natives and 320 Europeans in the
                    south-eastern, making a total of 700,386; but the statements rest on little
                    better than conjecture. If they approximate to the truth, the population of the
                    whole island may be set down at between 1,000,000 and 2,000,000. Earlier
                    estimates carried the total as high as 3,000,000.</p>
                <p>Borneo is politically divided into Borneo Proper or Bruni (inclusive of Sarawak),
                    the territory of the sultan of Sulu, and the Dutch possessions and protectorate.
                    Bruni is an independent cquntry, governed by a sultan, who is nominally
                    absolute; but the real power is distributed among the subordinate chiefs, who
                    act each as much as possible as his own master. The inhabitants are all serfs of
                    the sultan or the chiefs, who may dispose of their property, their wives, or
                    their children in the most arbitrary manner. Mahometanism is the state religion.
                    The capital, also called Bruni, is a large and flourishing city. The estimates
                    of its population have all along greatly varied. Among the mos∣, recent is one
                    which makes it 30,000 or 40,000, while the population of the whole kingdom is
                    given at 225,000. A considerable traffic is carried on with Malacca, Singapore,
                    China, Rio, Sambas, Pontianak, and other places in the Dutch possessions. There
                    is an extensive fishing in the river, the produce of which furnishes the people
                    with a large proportion of their food. The fishermen form a distinct caste, and
                    the same is the case with the workers in brass, the blacksmiths, the goldsmiths,
                    the matmakers, &amp;c. The manufacture of goldlace and silk embroidery is
                    carried to great perfection. For accounts of Sarawak and the Sulu territory the
                    reader is referred to separate articles.</p>
                <p>The Dutch territory forms two great divisions, the western and the south-eastern.
                    The western, governed by a resident, is subdivided into two parts, Pontianak and
                    Sambas, the former administered by the resident himself and the latter by an
                    assistant-resident and the sultan of Sambas. Pontianak includes Landak, Tajan,
                    Mampawa, Sintang, Selimbou, Upper-Kapuas, and Montrado, while to Sambas belong
                    the districts of Pamangkut and Seminis. The south-eastern division is subdivided
                    into an eastern and a southern part. Under the southern are Kota-Waringin,
                    Pembuang, Sampitite, Great and Little Dyak, Bekompai, Duson, Banjermassin, and
                    Tanah-Laut; and under the eastern are Tanah-Bumbu, Kusan, Passir, Kuti,
                    Sambi-liung, Gunong-Tebur, Bulungan (the three last being also known as Berou),
                    and the Tidung lands. The east coast, from Sebamban in Tanah Bumbu to Kaniungan
                    in l <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 3' N. 1st., belongs immediately to the Dutch
                    Government. In the western division several important military roads have been
                    constructed, and the resources of the country are being opened up.</p>
                <p>Borneo has never, as far as we have information, formed a political unity; and
                    even its physical unity as an island is so little known or considered by its
                    native inhabitants that it possesses in their languages no general designation.
                    As a natural consequence Borneo has no proper history. The island was first
                    discovered by European navigators in the beginning of the 16th century,
                    according to one account by Lorenzo de Gomez, a Portuguese, in 1518, and
                    according to another by Don Jorge de Menezes in 1526. Before long commercial
                    relations were formed with the natives by the Portuguese traders, at first in
                    the city of Bruni itself, and then in various other maritime states. In 1573
                    their Spanish rivals tried to open a connection with Bruni, but their attempts
                    were without success till the sultan being dethroned appealed to them for
                    assistance, and was restored in 1580. From that time they kept up intercourse
                    with the country, but it was not unfrequently interrupted by war. In 1645 an
                    expedition was sent to punish the inhabitants of the capital for their piratical
                    excursions. The real influence exerted by the Portuguese and Spaniards on the
                    condition of the country was very slight; and the only effort at proselytizing
                    of which we have record came to an untimely end in the death of the Theatine
                    monk, Antonio Ventimiglia, who had been its originator. Meanwhile the Dutch and
                    English had been gaining a footing in the island. In 1604 Waerwijck began to
                    trade on the west coast, and in 1608 Samuel Blommaert was appointed Dutch
                    resident in Landak and Sukkedana. The English appeared for the first time about
                    1609, and by 1698 had an important settlement at Banjermassin, from which,
                    however, they were expelled by the influence of the Dutch, who about 1733
                    obtained from the sultan a monopoly of the trade. The Dutch, in fact, became
                    paramount all round the west and south coasts, and the king of Bantam ceded his
                    rights <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n69/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0069-0060"/> of suzerainty to the company. The attention of
                    the English was meantime turned to the north of the island, which was subject to
                    the sultan of Sulu, from whom, in 1756, Alexander Dalrymple obtained possession
                    of the island of Balambangan, and all the north-eastern promontory. A military
                    post was established, but in 1775 it was surprised and destroyed by the natives
                    under the <hi rend="italic">dutus</hi> or subordinate chiefs, who were
                    dissatisfied with the cession of their territory. This disaster rendered a
                    treaty, which had just been concluded (in 1774) with the sultan of Bruni, in
                    great measure a dead letter, and before the end of the century English influence
                    in Borneo was practically at an end. The Dutch, too, were overtaken, in spite of
                    apparent success, with a succession of misfortunes, through their own
                    mismanagement; and in 1809 their settlements were all abandoned by order of
                    Marshal Daendels. The natives along the coast, assisted and stimulated by
                    immigrants from the neighbouring islands to the north, gave themselves more and
                    more to piracy, and rendered the trade of civilized nations almost an
                    impossibility.</p>
                <p>In 1811, however, an embassy was sent to the British Government in Java by the
                    sultan of Banjermassin to crave their assistance, and in reply Alexander Hare
                    was despatched as commissioner and resident. He not only formed an advantageous
                    treaty with the sultan, but got for himself a grant of a district of country
                    which he proceeded to colonize and cultivate. An expedition was also sent
                    against Sambas, and a post established at Pontianak. On the restoration of the
                    Dutch possessions in 1818 all these arrangements were cancelled, and a free
                    field was left to the enterprise of the Dutch Government. A succession of active
                    commissioners—Boekholtz, Tobias, Halewijn, &amp;c.— soon laid the foundations of
                    an extensive supremacy. About half of the kingdom of Banjermassin was
                    surrendered by the sultan in 1823, and further concessions were granted by his
                    son in 1825. Meanwhile, George Muller was exploring the east coast, and obtained
                    from the sultan of Kuti an acknowledgment of the Dutch authority—a concession
                    which seems to have been immediately regretted, as the enterprising traveller
                    was shortly afterwards killed. The outbreak of a war in Java turned the
                    attention of the Dutch in some measure from Borneo, and nothing was done by them
                    to check the piracy which was growing more and more unendurable. On the rise of
                    Singapore direct trade had been opened with Sarawak and Bruni, and it was a
                    matter of moment to the English merchants that their traffic should be safe. In
                    1838 Sir James Brooke, an Englishman, whose attention had been turned to the
                    state of affairs in the Eastern Archipelago, set out for Borneo, determined, if
                    possible, to remedy the evil. By 1841 he had obtained from the sultan of Bruni
                    the highest authority in Sarawak, and before many years were over he succeeded
                    in restoring order and peace to the district, and, with the assistance of the
                    English Government, in repressing piracy. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Brooke</hi>
                    and <hi rend="smallcaps">Sarawak.)</hi> In 1847 the sultan of Bruni agreed to
                    make no cession of territory to any nation or individual without the consent of
                    Her British Majesty. The Dutch hopes of gradually incorporating the whole island
                    were thus frustrated, but this served only to increase their activity in other
                    directions. In 1844 the sultan of Kuti had acknowledged their protectorate, and
                    about the same time a treaty of similar character was formed with Passir. Since
                    1834, when Gunong-Tebur, Tanjong, and Bulungan are said to have made a nominal
                    submission, the boundaries of their authority have undergone no change to the
                    north; and in general their political power has been rather rising in level, so
                    to speak, over the southern part of the island than seeking to spread over a
                    wider area,</p>
                <p>Of the works on Borneo, which are very numerous, the following may be named :—
                    Blommaert’s <hi rend="italic">Discours</hi><hi rend="italic">ende</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ghelegentheyt van het eylandt Borneo int Jear</hi> 1609; <hi
                    rend="italic">Hachelyke reystogt van Jacob Jansz. de Roy na Borneo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">en</hi><hi rend="italic">Atchin in het jaar</hi> 1691; Beeckman,
                    <hi rend="italic">Visit</hi><hi rend="italic">to Borneo,</hi> 1718; Valentijn’s
                    description in his great work, 1726; <hi rend="italic">Berigt van een reiziger
                    over Borneo</hi><hi rend="italic">Propre</hi> in P. P. Roorda van Eysinga’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Verschill.</hi><hi rend="italic">reizen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >en</hi><hi rend="italic">lotgevallen,</hi> vol. iv.; G. W. Earl, <hi
                    rend="italic">Eastern Seas,</hi> 1837; W. L. Bitter, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Indische</hi><hi rend="italic">Herinneringen,</hi> &amp;c., 1843; S. Muller,
                    <hi rend="italic">Reizen</hi><hi rend="italic">in den Ind. Archip.;</hi> Keppel,
                    <hi rend="italic">Expedition of the Dido,</hi> 1846; Mundy, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Narrative of events in Borneo and Celebes,</hi> 1848; Belcher, <hi
                    rend="italic">Voy. of the Samarang,</hi> 1840; H. Low, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sarawak,</hi> 1848; F. S. Marryat, <hi rend="italic">Borneo, &amp;c.,</hi>
                    1848; Keppel, <hi rend="italic">Visit to Ind.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Archipel.</hi><hi rend="italic">by the</hi><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ae</hi><hi rend="italic">ander,</hi> 1853; J. C. Temple, <hi
                    rend="italic">Private</hi><hi rend="italic">Letters of Sir J. Brooke,</hi> 1853;
                    H. St John, <hi rend="italic">The Indian Archip.,</hi> 1853; C. A. L. Μ.
                    Schwaner, <hi rend="italic">Borneo, Beschr. van het stromgebied van den Barito,
                    etc., in den jaar</hi><hi rend="italic">en</hi> 1843-47, 1853-4; P. J. Veth, <hi
                    rend="italic">Borneo's Westerafdeeling,</hi> 1854, 1856 (a work which has been
                    largely used in the preparation of the present article); E. Francis, <hi
                    rend="italic">Herinneringen nit het leven van</hi><hi rend="italic">een
                    Indisch.</hi><hi rend="italic">ambtenaar,</hi> 1856; J. J. Rochussen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Toelichting, etc. van eenige daden van mijn bestuur,</hi> 1853; W.
                    A. van Rees, <hi rend="italic">Montrado,</hi> &amp;c., 1858; C. J. Temminck, <hi
                    rend="italic">Coup d'oeil</hi><hi rend="italic">sur les poss.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Neêrland.</hi><hi rend="italic">dans l’</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Inde</hi><hi rend="italic">Archipel.,</hi> 1846-50; Ida Pfeiffer, <hi
                    rend="italic">Zweite Weltreise,</hi> 1856; MacDougall, <hi rend="italic">Letters
                    from Sarawak, addressed to a Child,</hi> 1854; Crawfurd, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Descriptive Dictionary,</hi> art. <hi rend="italic">Borneo;</hi> W. E. Kroesen
                    and F. H. van Vlissingen, <hi rend="italic">Cultuur-</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >en</hi><hi rend="italic">Industrie-ondememingen van Borneo,</hi> 1859; J.
                    Hasselman and F. H. van Vlissingen, <hi rend="italic">Beschouwingen over de
                    exploitatie van Borneo,</hi> 1859; Tracy, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                    American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions,</hi> 1842; Spenser St
                    John, <hi rend="italic">Life in the Forests of the Far East,</hi> 1862; F.
                    Boyle, <hi rend="italic">Adventures among the Dyaks of Borneo,</hi> 1865; A. R.
                    Wallace, <hi rend="italic">The Malay</hi><hi rend="italic">Archipel.,</hi> 1869;
                    P. J. Veth, <hi rend="italic">Woordenboek van Nederl. Indie,</hi> 1869; (in this
                    work the reader will find a long list of articles on Borneo that have appeared
                    in Dutch and other periodicals); “Contribuzioni geografiche italiane a Borneo”
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi> of Guido Cora, 1874. (H. A. W.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
