<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0206-0165-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOTTICELLI, Sandro</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 165</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:817559">Artists</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n206/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOTTICELLI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sandro</hi></label> (for <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Alessandro),</hi> one of the most original and fascinating
                    painters of the school of Florence. Like many Italian artists, he is called not
                    after his father but after the master under whom he learned his first lessons in
                    art. He was the youngest son of a citizen named Mariano Filipepi, and was born
                    at Florence in the year 1447. It is related how as a child, though quick at
                    whatever he chose to do, he was restless and wayward, and would not take kindly
                    to “any sort of schooling in reading, writing, or arithmetic;” so that his
                    father put him, in despair, to learn the goldsmith’s trade with a gossip of his
                    own named Botticello. Thus his first training, like that of Ghirlandaio and many
                    of the best artists of the time, was in jewellery and metal working. He showed
                    talent and fancy, and was presently transferred from the school of Botticello
                    the goldsmith to that of Lippo Lippi the Carmelite brother, then in the height
                    of his practice and reputation as a painter. Under that master Sandro acquired a
                    perfect proficiency, and on his death in 1468 appears to have begun independent
                    practice. The special characteristic of Lippo Lippi’s style had been its union
                    of a buoyant human spirit of life and enjoyment with the utmost simplicity and
                    tenderness of religious feeling. In Botticelli there was more than all the fire
                    of his master, and more than all his delight in beauty, together with a
                    sentiment which was altogether personal to himself. All his creations are
                    coloured with an expression of eager and wistful melancholy, of which it is hard
                    to penetrate the sense and impossible to escape the spell. Whether he paints a
                    Madonna with her child surrounded by angels, or a Venus among her Graces and
                    Cupids, the countenances which he shows us are of a kindred type, and have upon
                    them the. pale cast of the same nameless passion. He was an artist of immense
                    invention and industry, and in the early part of his career painted in oil and
                    tempera a vast number of pictures both in the classical and the Christian vein.
                    No other work expresses the spirit of the time in a more interesting way, or
                    with so much imaginative refinement and technical charm. His dejected types haye
                    an infinite beauty of their own, and though his figures are not designed with
                    perfect science, and have some tendency to attenuation, and to coarseness of the
                    hands and feet, they are nevertheless drawn with a determination and finish in
                    the contours, and modelled with a fulness and delicacy of relief, which belong
                    only to the most accomplished art.</p>
                <p>Of all the Florentine school, Botticelli is the richest and most fanciful
                    colourist,—often using gold to enrich the lights on hair, tissues, and foliage,
                    with a very exquisite effect. That may be the consequence of his early
                    employment upon goldsmith’s work, as is, more certainly, his minute solicitude
                    in all the accessory details and ornaments of his compositions. The patterned
                    and embroidered dresses, the scarves and head-gear of his figures, are often
                    treated with an incomparable invention and delicacy. No artist has ever painted
                    flowers with a more inspired affection, and especially roses, with which he was
                    wont to fill the backgrounds of his pictures. He preferred, it would seem, the
                    circular form for his compositions; and a large number of devotional pieces in
                    this form, by his own hand and that of his scholars, are scattered through the
                    museums and private collections of Europe, and are among the most poetical
                    examples of religious art that Italy has left us. He went even beyond hi3 master
                    Lippo Lippi, and the sculptors Luca della Robbia, Donatello, and Desiderio da
                    Settignano, in the touching and engaging character of the children who minister,
                    in the form of angels, to his sacred personages. He designed choirs of such or
                    of grown-up angels dancing between earth and heaven, or circles of them ranged
                    in the order of the celestial hierarchies, with a variety of grouping and a
                    graceful fire of movement that was a new thing in his art. One of the best
                    examples of this kind of work is a round numbered 33 in the gallery of the
                    Uffizj at Florence. Another very famous example of his devotional art is a
                    picture of the Coronation of the Virgin executed for Matteo Palmieri, a
                    Florentine man of letters and speculative philosopher, with whom the painter was
                    intimate, and who gave suggestions for the design of the picture. It represents
                    the Virgin and Christ surrounded by the celestial hierarchies according to the
                    scheme (with some slight divergencies) of Dionysius the Areopagite,—on the
                    ground beneath, the donor and his wife kneeling at either side of the Virgin’s
                    tomb, the Vai d’Arno and the city of Florence in the distance. This picture is
                    now the property of the duke of Hamilton. But the grandest of all his
                    altar-pieces is that numbered 47 in the Florence Academy, with a group of
                    life-sized saints on the ground and a dance of angels above. In the Uffizj is an
                    Adoration of the Magi, in which Botticelli has introduced the portraits of
                    Cosimo, Giuliano, and Giovanni de’ Medici. By that house he, like all the
                    artists of his time, was much befriended; and for Lorenzo’s villa at Castello he
                    painted the most beautiful of his pictures of classical mythology, the Birth of
                    Venus now at the Uffizj, and the Venus with the Graces now at the Florence
                    Academy. The National Gallery possesses two smaller but adrairable works of the
                    master in the same vein. An allegorical figure of Fortitude, designed for a
                    series of which the rest were painted by the brothers Pollaiuoli, and now in the
                    Uffizj; a picture composed from Lucian’s account of the Calumny of Apelles in
                    the same gallery; a series illustrating Boccaccio’s story of Nastagio degli
                    Onesti, which has passed into private hands in England—these instances will
                    suffice to show the variety of themes upon which Botticelli exercised his
                    genius. A St Augustine, painted by him in rivalry with Ghirlandaio in the church
                    of the Ognissanti, and still existing, is said to have won great praise from his
                    contemporaries for its exhibition, in the head of the saint, of “that profound
                    cogitation and most acute subtlety which we are wont to find in persons who are
                    of thoughtful habit and continually abstracted in the investigation of things
                    the most deep and difficult.”</p>
                <p>In 1478 happened the attempt and failure of the conspirators of the Pazzi family
                    and their followers against the house of Medici. It was the custom in Florence
                    to have the likenesses of such state offenders painted large upon the outside of
                    the Public Palace, and in this case Botticelli was employed upon the task. It
                    will have been soon afterwards<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n207/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0207-0166"/> that he was summoned to Rome by Sixtus IV., to
                    decorate the walls of his. new chapel in the Vatican. Among the great scenes in
                    fresco painted, on those walls by Domenico Ghirlandaio, Cosimo Rosselli,
                    Signorelli, and Perugino, three subjects from the hand of Botticelli hold their
                    place with the n0ble3t. They represent the Life of Moses, the Destruction of
                    Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, and the Temptation of Christ. In 1482, probably after
                    his return from Rome, he received a commission to paint in the Sala dell’
                    Udienza at Florence, together with Domenico Ghirlandaio. Many of the works
                    already mentioned probably fall within the next ten years of Botticelli’s
                    manhood. The Boccaccio series belongs to 1487. In 1491 he was engaged, together
                    with the brothers Ghirlandaio, upon some mosaic decorations in the cathedral of
                    Florence which have unhappily perished. Soon after this time there came into his
                    life a new influence which greatly changed it. It is well known how the genius
                    of the Dominican Savonarola swept like a storm over the affairs of Italy, and
                    what a revolution, after the passage of the French king through Florence, he
                    brought about in the temper and policy of the republic,—driving out the merchant
                    family who had been its untitled masters for half a century, establishing in
                    place of their rule a new theocracy of which he was himself the oracle and
                    minister, turning the hearts of old and young away from the world and from their
                    lusts. Many of the first artists of the city became his most ardent followers,
                    and among them Botticelli. What the actual effect of his conversion was upon him
                    we have scanty means of judging, but it needs must have put an end to his
                    painting of those old mythologies, over which in earlier days his imagination
                    had been used to throw so singular a charm. Vasari, a devoted servant of the
                    later Medici, and therefore a traducer of the greatest enemy that house had ever
                    had, speaks of Savonarola’s influence upon Botticelli as altogether disastrous,
                    saying that he was “obstinate upon that side,” “a partisan of the sect of
                    Savonarola in such a fashion that, abandoning painting and having no income to
                    live upon, he fell into the utmost disorder;” and again how, “playing the
                    Piagnone (the name given to the followers of Savonarola), he fell out of the way
                    of painting, and thereby at last found himself old and poor in such a sort that
                    if Lorenzo Medici, as long as he lived, had not supported him, and afterwards
                    his friends and many worthy men who felt au affection for his virtues, he would,
                    we may say, have died of hunger.” We have few materials by which we can test the
                    accuracy of this account. We know that in 1496 the young Michelangelo sent
                    through his hands a letter addressed to this Lorenzo de’ Medici (Lorenzo the
                    younger, that is,—the son of Giuliano); that in 1498 he was living with a
                    brother in the quarter called Sta Lucia of Ognissanti; that in 1503 he was
                    consulted along with other artists as to the best place for Michelangelo’s
                    colossal statue of David. But of more importance and significance than all this
                    is a beautiful picture of a Nativity with mystical by-scenes, in the possession
                    of Mr Fuller Maitland, which bears an inscription in base Greek by the master
                    himself. The inscription seems to construe thus :—“This picture I, Alessandro,
                    painted at the end of the year 1500, in the troubles of Italy, in the half-time
                    after the time, during the fulfilment of the eleventh of John, in the second woe
                    of the Apocalypse, in the loosing of the devil for three and a half years.
                    Afterwards he shall be chained according to the twelfth of John, and we shall
                    see him trodden down as this picture.” Hence it appears to be established that
                    Botticelli, a year and a half after the downfall and execution of Savonarola,
                    had his mind full of his instructions and prophecies; that he regarded the death
                    of the Dominican reformer and his companions as the fulfilment of the
                    Apocalyptic prophecies about the slaying of the witnesses; that he thought of
                    the tribulations among which he lived as the “second woe” of Rev. xi., and as
                    coincident with the “time, times, and half a time” of that and other prophetic
                    writings; and finally—such is the originality and excellence of the work—that
                    his imagination had at this time lost none of its fire nor his hand of its
                    cunning. We are quite without the means of deciding whether any proportion of
                    the large existing mass of his undated works belong to the years following this;
                    or whether we are really to think of him as failing in his wonted industry in
                    his latter days, from regret and disappointment at his master’s fate and;at
                    public affairs, from pre-occupation over mystical theology (which had always had
                    an attraction for him, and, in the case of the picture painted early in his life
                    for Matteo Palmieri, had brought upon him a charge of heresy), or, lastly, from
                    another cause which Vasari alleges, but which we have designedly passed by till
                    this place.</p>
                <p>In the history of engraving there are no productions more precious, more
                    interesting, or more problematical than a number of plates executed in a
                    primitive style, with severe outlines and straight lines of shading, by artists
                    of the Florentine school towards the close of the 15 th century. The engravings
                    in this manner include some two hundred and fifty pieces, covering the whole
                    range of subjects that interested the mind of Italy at this most active and
                    fanciful moment of the early Renaissance. The best known of these engravings are
                    as follows :—three designs to the earliest book published in Florence with
                    engraved illustrations, called <hi rend="italic">II Monte</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sancto</hi><hi rend="italic">di Dio</hi> (1471); a set of nineteen designs to
                    an edition of the <hi rend="italic">Divina</hi><hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>
                    of Dante (1481); a set of twenty-four Prophets; a set of twelve Sibyls; several
                    subjects of Saints; several of mythology, such as the Death of Paris, Theseus
                    and Ariadne, the Judgment of Paris, Loves in a Vineyard, and the like; a famous
                    series (long falsely ascribed to Mantegna, whose manner in engraving is easily
                    distinguishable from this) of the Ranks and Professions of Men, the Virtues, the
                    Arts and Sciences, the Muses, and the Planets (fifty in all); a series of
                    fifteen setting forth the lives of Mary and of Christ; a subject of the deluge;
                    another of the preaching of the Franciscan Fra Marco, and many more. Between the
                    various examples of this large class there are considerable differences, but
                    they are all unlike the work of any other school, and all manifestly Florentine
                    of the 15th century. Conjectures the most confident and at the same time the
                    most conflicting have been put forward as to their authorship. All such
                    conjectures alike have been based on a few passages in Vasari’s lives of
                    Botticelli and of Marc Antonio. According to Vasari, the first Florentine who
                    took impressions on paper from engravings was Maso Finiguerra, and he, says our
                    author, was “followed by Baccio Baldini, who not having much power of designing,
                    all that he did was with the invention and design of Sandro Botticelli.” And
                    again, Vasari says of Botticelli that, “from being a sophistical <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> thoughtful or ingenious) person, he commented a part
                    of Dante, and made figures for the <hi rend="italic">Inferno,</hi> and put them
                    into print; upon which pursuit he spent a deal of time; so that not working” <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> at painting) “it was a cause of infinite disorders in
                    his life. He put in print many more things of his own from designs which he had
                    made, but in a bad manner.” On the strength of those passages this whole class
                    of early Florentine engravings has generally been put down by connoisseurs, as,
                    for instance, Young Ottley, Bartsch, and Passavant, as the work of Sandro
                    Botticelli and Baccio Baldini, jointly or apart,—each critic attributing
                    separate subjects to the one or the other of the artists according to his
                    private canon of internal evidence. But a scrupulous examination shows this
                    internal evidence to be both very meagre and very contradictory. Nor can much be
                    built upon the external <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0208-0167"/> testimony of Vasari. The phrase “put into print”
                    is ambiguous, and by it Vasari may mean us to understand either that Botticelli
                    engraved the designs himself or else that he merely furnished them to be
                    engraved by another hand. To him the chief part in the invention, to Baldini the
                    chief part in the execution, is usually and with a fair measure of probability
                    assigned. Vasari’s information on the whole subject was evidently loose; a
                    Triumph of Faith of Savonarola, which he extols as Botticelli’s best engraving,
                    does not at present exist at all. None of the designs bear the evidence of
                    Botticelli’s manner in a sufficiently definite form to be undeniable. On the
                    other hand, many of them, by their poetry, their refinement, their singularity,
                    are quite worthy of his hand, nor do they resemble any other contemporary style
                    more than his. If he designed and executed, or in part executed, them, they are
                    no slight addition to his fame, and a noble vindication of his industry during
                    that old age of idleness, decay, and “disorder,” which followed, if we are to
                    believe Vasari, upon the splendid and inspired activity of his youth and
                    manhood. But the question is one which criticism, it is to be feared, will never
                    have the means of fully settling. (Vasari, ed. Lemonnier, vol. v. pp. 110-127;
                    Crowe and Caval-caselie, <hi rend="italic">Hist. of Painting in Italy,</hi> vol.
                    ii. pp. 414-430; W. H. Pater, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History of the
                    Renaissance;</hi> and see also <hi rend="italic">Ariadne</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Florentin,</hi> No. vi, by John Ruskin; art. “Baccio Baldini,” by E. Kolhoff in
                    2d ed. of Nagler’s <hi rend="italic">Künstler-Lexikon</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Academy</hi> for February 1871.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
