<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0627-0566-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURNS, Robert</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 566</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198490">Dreams</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg38">Dreams</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67561">Visions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n627/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURNS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label> (1759-1796).
                    In a company of German critics who were weighing the claims and estimating the
                    rank of the poets, their contemporaries, the leader of their chorus, the genial
                    humorist, Jean Paul Richter, is said to have hushed his audience when the name
                    of Goethe was introduced, exclaiming—“We are not to sit in judgment on that
                    sacred head.” Scotsmen are apt to attach the same half-superstitious reverence
                    to the name which is, more than any other, that of Scotland condensed in a
                    personality, the representative of what is noblest and also of much that is
                    erring in their race.</p>
                <p>Robert Burns was born on the 25th of January 1759, in a cottage about two miles
                    from Ayr, the eldest son of a small farmer, William Burness, of Kincardineshire
                    stock, who wrought hard, practised integrity, wished to bring up his children in
                    the fear of God, but had to fight all his days against the winds and tides of
                    adversity, “The poet,” says Mr Carlyle, his best biographer, “was fortunate in
                    his father—a man of thoughtful intense character, as the best of our peasants
                    are, valuing knowledge, possessing some and open-minded for more, of keen
                    insight and devout heart, friendly and fearless: a fully unfolded man seldom
                    found in any rank in society, and worth descending far in society to seek. . . .
                    Had he been ever so little richer, the whole might have issued otherwise. But
                    poverty sunk the whole family even below the reach of our cheap school system,
                    and Burns remained a hard-worked plough-boy.”</p>
                <p>Through a series of migrations from one unfortunate farm to another; from Alloway
                    (where he was taught to read), to Mt. Oliphant, and then (1777) to Lochlea in
                    Tarbolton (where he learnt the rudiments of geometry), the poet remained in the
                    same condition of straitened circumstances. At the age of thirteen he thrashed
                    the corn with his own hands, at fifteen he was the principal labourer. The
                    family kept no servant, and for several years butchers’ meat was a thing unknown
                    in the house. “This kind of life,” he writes, “the cheerless gloom of a hermit
                    and the unceasing toil of a galley-slave, brought me to my sixteenth year.” His
                    naturally robust frame was overtasked, and his nervous constitution received a
                    fatal strain. His shoulders were bowed, he became liable to headaches,
                    palpitations, and fits of depressing melancholy. From these hard tasks and his
                    fiery temperament, craving in vain for sympathy in a frigid air grew the strong
                    temptations on which Burns was largely wrecked,—the thirst for stimulants and
                    the revolt against restraint which soon made headway and passed all bars. In the
                    earlier portions of his career, a buoyant humour bore him up; and amid
                    thick-coming shapes of ill he bated no jot of heart or hope. He was cheered by
                    vague stirrings of ambition, which he pathetically compares to the “blind
                    groping of Homer’s Cyclops round the walls of his cave.” Sent to school at
                    Kirkoswald, he became, for his scant leisure, a great reader—eating at
                    meal-times with a spoon in one hand and a book in the other,—and carrying a few
                    small volumes in his pocket to study in spare moments in the fields. “The
                    collection of songs,” he tells us, “was my <hi rend="italic">vade mecum.</hi> I
                    pored over them driving my cart or walking to labour, song by song, verse by
                    verse, carefully noting the true, tender, sublime, or fustian.” He lingered over
                    the ballads in his cold room by night; by day, whilst whistling at the plough,
                    he invented new forms and was inspired by fresh ideas, “gathering round him the
                    memories and the traditions of his country till they became a mantle and a
                    crown.” It was among the furrows of his father’s fields that he was inspired
                    with the perpetually quoted wish—</p>
                <p>“That I for poor auld Scotland’s sake Some useful plan or book could make, Or
                    sing a sang at least.”</p>
                <p>Au equally striking illustration of the same feeling is to be found in his summer
                    Sunday’s ramble to the Lcglen <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n628/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0628-0567"/> wood,—the fabled haunt of Wallace,—which the poet
                    confesses to have visited “with as much devout enthusiasm as ever pilgrim did
                    the shrine of Loretto.” In another reference to the same period he refers to the
                    intense susceptibility to the homeliest aspects of Nature which throughout
                    characterized his genius. “Scarcely any object gave me more—I do not know if I
                    should call it pleasure—but something which exalts and enraptures me—than to
                    walk in the sheltered side of a wood or high plantation in a cloudy winter day
                    and hear the stormy wind howling among the trees and raving over the plain. I
                    listened to the birds, and frequently turned out of my path lest I should
                    disturb their little songs or frighten them to another station.” Auroral visions
                    were gilding his horizon as he walked in glory, if not in joy, “behind his
                    plough upon the mountain side;” but the swarm of his many-coloured fancies was
                    again made grey by the <hi rend="italic">atra</hi><hi rend="italic">cura</hi> of
                    unsuccessful toils.</p>
                <p>Burns had written his first verses of note, “Behind yon hills where Stinchar
                    (afterwards Lugar) flows,” when in 1781 he went to Irvine to learn the trade of
                    a flax-dresser. “It was,” he says, “an unlucky affair. As we were giving a
                    welcome carousal to the New Year, the shop took fire and burned to ashes; and I
                    was left, like a true poet, without a sixpence.” His own heart, too, had
                    unfortunately taken fire. He was poring over mathematics till, in his own
                    phraseology,—still affected in its prose by the classical pedantries caught from
                    Pope by Ramsay,—“the sun entered Virgo, when a charming <hi rend="italic"
                    >fillette,</hi> who lived next door, overset my trigonometry, and set me off at
                    a tangent from the scene of my studies.” We need not detail the story, nor the
                    incessant repetitions of it, which marked and sometimes marred his career. The
                    poet was jilted, went through the usual despairs, and resorted to the not
                    unusual sources of consolation. He had found that he was “no enemy to social
                    life,” and his mates had discovered that he was the best of boou companions in
                    the lyric feasts, where his eloquence shed a lustre over wild ways of life, and
                    where he was beginning to be distinguished as a champion of the New Lights and a
                    satirist of the Calvinism whose waters he found like those of Marah.</p>
                <p>In Robert’s 25th year his father died, full of sorrows and apprehensions for the
                    gifted son who wrote for his tomb, in Alloway kirkyard, the fine epitaph ending
                    with the characteristic line—</p>
                <p>“For even his failings leaned to virtue’s side. ’</p>
                <p>For some time longer the poet, with his brother Gilbert, lingered at Lochlea,
                    reading agricultural books, miscalculating crops, attending markets, and in a
                    mood of reformation resolving, “in spite of the world, the flesh, and the devil,
                    to be a wise man.” Affairs, however, went no better with the family; and in 1784
                    they migrated to Mossgiel, where he lived and wrought, during four years, for a
                    return scarce equal to the wage of the commonest labourer in our day. Meanwhile
                    he had become intimate with his future wife, Jean Armour; but the father, a
                    master mason, discountenanced the match, and the girl being disposed to “sigh as
                    a lover,” as a daughter to obey, Burns, in 1786, gave up his suit, resolved to
                    seek refuge in exile, and having accepted a situation as book-keeper, to a slave
                    estate in Jamaica, had taken his passage in a ship for the West Indies. His old
                    associations seemed to be breaking up, men and fortune scowled, and “hungry ruin
                    had himin the wind,” when he wrote the lines ending—</p>
                <p>“Adieu, my native banks of Ayr,”</p>
                <p>and addressed to the most famous of the loves, in which he was as prolific as
                    Catullus or Tibullus, the proposal—</p>
                <p>“Will ye go to the Indies, my Mary.</p>
                <p>He was withheld from his project and, happily or unhappily, the current of his
                    life was turned by the success of his first volume, which was published at
                    Kilmarnock in June 1786. It contained some of his most justly celebrated poems,
                    the results of his scanty leisure at Lochlea and Mossgiel; among others “The Twa
                    dogs,”—a graphic idealization of Aesop,—“The Author’s Prayer,” the “Address to
                    the Deil,” “The Vision” and “The Dream,” “Halloween,” “The Cottar’s Saturday
                    Night,” the lines “To a Mouse” and “To a Daisy,” “Scotch Drink,” “Man .was made
                    to Mourn,” the “Epistle to Davie,” and some of his most popular songs. This
                    epitome of a genius so marvellous and so varied took his audience by storm. “The
                    country murmured of him from sea to sea.” “With his poems,” says Robert Heron,
                    “old and young, grave and gay, learned and ignorant, were alike transported. I
                    was at that time resident in Galloway, and I can well remember how even
                    plough-boys and maid-servants would have gladly bestowed the wages they earned
                    the most hardly, and which they wanted to purchase necessary clothing, if they
                    might but procure the works of Burns. This first edition only brought the author
                    £20 direct return, but it introduced him to the <hi rend="italic">literati</hi>
                    of Edinburgh, whither he was invited, and where he was welcomed, feasted,
                    admired, and patronized. He appeared as a portent among the scholars of the
                    northern capital and its university, and manifested, according to Mr Lockhart,
                    “in the whole strain of his bearing, his belief that in the society of the most
                    eminent men of his nation he was where he was entitled to be, hardly deigning to
                    flatter them by exhibiting a symptom of being flattered.”</p>
                <p>Sir Walter Scott bears a similar testimony to the dignified simplicity and almost
                    exaggerated independence of the poet, during this <hi rend="italic"
                    >annus</hi><hi rend="italic">mirabilis</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi> his
                    success. “As for Burns, <hi rend="italic">Virgilium υidi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >tantum,</hi> I was a lad of fifteen when he came to Edinburgh, but had sense
                    enough to be interested in his poetry, and would have given the world to know
                    him. I saw him one day with several gentlemen of literary reputation, among whom
                    I remember the celebrated Dugald Stewart. Of course we youngsters sat silent,
                    looked, and listened. . . . I remember . . . his shedding tears over a print
                    representing a soldier lying dead in the snow, his dog sitting in misery on one
                    side, on the other his widow with a child in her arms. His person was robust,
                    his manners rustic, not clownish. . . . His countenance was more massive than it
                    looks in any of the portraits. There was a strong expression of shrewdness in
                    his linea ments; the eye alone indicated the poetic character and temperament.
                    It was large and of a dark cast, and literally glowed when he spoke with feeling
                    or interest. I never saw such another eye in a human head. His conversation
                    expressed perfect self-confidence, without the least intrusive forwardness. I
                    thought his acquaintance with English poetry was rather limited; and having
                    twenty times the abilities of Allan Ramsay and of Ferguson he talked of them
                    with too much humility as his models. He was much caressed in Edinburgh, but the
                    efforts made for his relief were extremely trifling.” <hi rend="italic">Laudatur
                    et alget.</hi> Burns went from those meetings, where he had been posing
                    professors (no hard task), and turning the heads of duchesses, to share a bed in
                    the garret of a writer’s apprentice,—they paid together 3s. a week for the room.
                    It was in the house of Mr Carfrae, Baxter’s Close, Lawnmarket, “first scale
                    stair on the left hand in going down, first door in the stair.” During Burns’s
                    life it was reserved for William Pitt to recognize his place as a great poet,
                    the more cautious critics of the North were satisfied to endorse him as a rustic
                    prodigy, and brought upon themselves a share of his satire. Some of the
                    friendships contracted during this period—as for Lord Glencairn and Mrs
                    Dunlop—are among the most pleasing and permanent in literature; for genuine kind
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n629/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0629-0568"/> ness was never wasted on one who, whatever his
                    faults, has never been accused of ingratitude. But in the bard’s city life there
                    was an unnatural element. He stooped to beg for neither smiles nor favour, but
                    the gnarled country oak is cut up into cabinets in artificial prose and verse.
                    In the letters to Mr Graham, the prologue to Mr Wood, and the epistles to
                    Clarinda, he is dancing minuets with hobnailed shoes. When, in 1787, the second
                    edition of the <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> came out, the proceeds of their sale
                    realized for the author £400. On the strength of this sum he gave himself two
                    long rambles, full of poetic material—one through the border towns into England
                    as far as Newcastle, returning by Dumfries to Mauchline, and another a grand
                    tour through the East Highlands, as far as Inverness, returning by Edinburgh,
                    and so home to Ayrshire.</p>
                <p>In 1788 Burns took a new farm at Eilisland on the Nith, settled there, married,
                    lost his little money, and wrote, among other pieces, “Auld Lang Syne” and “Tam
                    O’ Shanter.” In 1789 he obtained, through the good office of Mr Graham of
                    Fintry, an appointment as excise-officer of the district, worth £50 per annum.
                    In 1791 he removed to a similar post at Dumfries worth £70. In the course of the
                    following year he was asked to edit and supply the <hi rend="italic">Melodies of
                    Scotland with Symphonies and Accompaniments for the Pianoforte and Violin: the
                    poetry by Robert Burns.</hi> To this work he contributed about one hundred
                    songs, the best of which are now ringing in the ear of every Scotchman from New
                    Zealand to San Francisco. For these, original and adapted, he received a shawl
                    for his wife, a picture by David Allan representing the “Cottar’s Saturday
                    Night,” and £5! The poet wrote an indignant letter and never afterwards composed
                    for money. Unfortunately the “Rock of Independence” to which he had proudly
                    retired was but a castle of air, over which the meteors of French political
                    enthusiasm cast a lurid gleam. In the last years of his life, exiled from polite
                    society on account of his revolutionary opinions, he became sourer in temper and
                    plunged more deeply into the dissipations of the lower ranks, among whom he
                    found his only companionship and sole, though shallow, sympathy. To have Jacobin
                    tendencies, to rejoice at the downfall of the Bastille, was regarded as the sign
                    of an abandoned character, as it was twelve years ago in Scotland to embrace the
                    cause of the Northern States in the American War.</p>
                <p>Burns began to feel himself prematurely old. Walking with a friend who proposed
                    to him to join a county ball, he shook his head, saying “that’s all over now,”
                    and adding a verse of Lady Grissel Baillie’s ballad—</p>
                <p>“0 were we young as we an ce hae been, We su&lt;l hae been galloping down on yon
                    green, And linking it ower the lily-white lea, But were na my heart light I wad
                    dee.”</p>
                <p>His hand shook; his pulse and appetite failed; his spirits sunk into a uniform
                    gloom. In April 1796 he wrote—“I fear it will be some time before I tune my lyre
                    again. By Babel’s streams I have sat and wept. I have only known existence by
                    the pressure of sickness and counted time by the repercussions of pain. I close
                    my eyes in misery and open them without hope. I look on the vernal day and say
                    with poor Ferguson—</p>
                <p>“Say wherefore has an all-indulgent heaven Life to the comfortless and wτetched
                    given.”</p>
                <p>On the 4th of July he was seen to be dying. On the 12th he wrote to his cousin
                    for the loan of £10 to save him from passing his last days in jail. On the 21st
                    he was no more. On the 25th, when his last son came into the world, he was
                    buried with local honours, the volqjιteers of the company to which he belonged
                    firing three volleys over his grave.</p>
                <p>It has been said that <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> Lowland Scotland as a
                    distinct nationality came in with two warriors and went out with two bards. It
                    came in with William Wallace and Robert Bruce and went out with Robert Burns and
                    Walter Scott. The first two made the history, the last two told the story and
                    sung the song.” But what in the minstrel’s lay was mainly a requiem was in the
                    people’s poet also a prophecy. The position of Burns in the progress of our
                    literature may be shortly defined; he was a link between two eras, like Chaucer,
                    the last of the old and the first of the new—the inheritor of the traditions and
                    the music of the past, in some respects the herald of the future.</p>
                <p>The volumes of our lyrist owe part of their popularity to the fact of their being
                    an epitome of melodies, moods, and memories that had belonged for centuries to
                    the national life, the best inspirations of which have passed into them. But in
                    gathering from his ancestors Burns has exalted their work by asserting a new
                    dignity for their simplest themes. He is the heir of Barbour, distilling the
                    spirit of the old poet’s epic into a battle chant, and of Dunbar, reproducing
                    the various humours of a half-sceptical, half-religious philosophy of life. He
                    is the pupil of Ramsay, but he leaves his master, to make a social protest and
                    to lead a literary revolt. The <hi rend="italic">Gentle Shepherd',</hi> still
                    largely a court pastoral, in which “a man ’s a man” if born a gentleman, may be
                    contrasted with the “Jolly Beggars ”—the one is like a minuet of the ladies of
                    Versailles on the sward of the Swiss village near the Trianon, the other like
                    the march of the maenads with Theroigne de Mericourt. Ramsay adds to the rough
                    tunes and words of the ballads the refinement of the wits who in the “Easy” and
                    “Johnstone” clubs talked over their cups of Prior and Pope, Addison and Gay.
                    Burns inspires them with a fervour that thrills the most wooden of his race. We
                    may clench the contrast by a representative example. This is from Ramsay’s
                    version of perhaps the best known of our songs,—</p>
                <p>“Methinks around us on each bough</p>
                <p>A thousand Cupids play;</p>
                <p>Whilst through the groves I walk with you. Each object makes me gay.</p>
                <p>Since your return—the sun and moon With brighter beams do shine, Streams murmur
                    soft notes while they run As they did lang syne.”</p>
                <p>Compare the verses in Burns—</p>
                <p>“We twa hae run about the braes</p>
                <p>And pou’t the gowans tine;</p>
                <p>But we’ve wandered mony a weary foot Sin auld lang syne.</p>
                <p>We twa hae paidl’d in the burn, Frae morning sun till dine: But seas between us
                    braid hae roar’d Sin auld lang syne.”</p>
                <p>Burns as a poet of the inanimate world doubtless derived hints from Thomson <hi
                    rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> the poet, not his correspondent), but in his power of
                    tuning its manifestations to the moods of the mind he is more properly ranked as
                    a forerunner of Wordsworth. He never follows the fashions of his century, except
                    in his failures—in his efforts at set panegyric or fine letter-writing. His
                    highest work knows nothing of “Damon” or “Musidora.” He leaves the atmosphere of
                    drawing-rooms for the ingle or the ale-house or the mountain breeze.</p>
                <p>The affectations of his style are insignificant and rare. His prevailing
                    characteristic is an absolute sincerity. A love for the lower forms of social
                    life was his besetting sin; Nature was his healing power. Burns compares himself
                    to an Aeolian harp, strung to every wind of heaven. His genius flows over all
                    living and lifeless things with a sympathy that finds nothing mean or
                    insignificant. An uprooted daisy becomes in his pages an enduring emblem of the
                    fate of artless maid and simple bard. He disturbs <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n630/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0630-0569"/> a mouse’s nest and finds in the “tim’rous
                    beastie” a fellowmortal doomed like himself to “thole the winter’s sleety
                    dribble,” and draws his oft-repeated moral. He walks abroad and, in a verse that
                    glints with the light of its own rising sun before the fierce sarcasm of the
                    “Holy Fair,” describes the melodies of a “simmer Sunday morn.” He loiters by
                    Afton Water and “murmurs by the running brook a music sweeter than its own.” He
                    stands by a roofless tower, where “the howlet mourns in her dewy bower,” and
                    “sets the wild echoes flying,” and adds to a perfect picture of the scene his
                    famous vision of “Libertie.” In a single stanza he concentrates the sentiment of
                    many Night Thoughts—</p>
                <p>“The pale moon is setting beyond tho white wave, And Time is setting wi’ me,
                    O.”</p>
                <p>For other examples of the same graphic power we may refer to the course of his
                    stream—</p>
                <p>“Whiles ow’r a linn the bumie plays</p>
                <p>As through the glen it wimpled,” <hi rend="italic">ke.,</hi> or to the “Birks of
                    Aberfeldy” or the “spate” in the dialogue of the “Brigs of Ayr.” The poet is as
                    much at home in the presence of this flood as by his “trottin’ burn’s meander.”
                    Familiar with all the seasons, he represents the phases of a northern winter
                    with a frequency characteristic of his clime and of his fortunes; her tempests
                    become anthems in his verse, and the sounding woods “raise his thoughts to Him
                    that walketh on the wings of the wind;” full of pity for the shelterless poor,
                    the “ourie cattle,” the “silly sheep,” and the “helpless birds,” he yet reflects
                    that the bitter blast is not “so unkind as man’s ingratitude.” This constant
                    tendency to ascend above the fair or wild features of outward things, or to
                    penetrate beneath them, to make them symbols, to endow them with a voice to
                    speak for humanity, distinguishes Burns as a descriptive poet from the rest of
                    his countrymen. As a painter he is rivalled by Dunbar and James I., more rarely
                    by Thomson and Ramsay. The “lilt” of Tannahill’s finest verse is even more
                    charming. But these writers rest in their art; their main care is for their own
                    genius. The same is true in a minor degree of some of his great English
                    successors. Keats has a palette of richer colours, but he seldom condescends to
                    “human nature’s daily food.” Shelley floats in a thin air to stars and
                    mountaintops, and vanishes from our gaze like h⅛ skylark. Byron, in the midst of
                    his revolutionary fervour, never forgets that he himself belongs to the “caste
                    of Vere de Vere.” Wordsworth’s placid affection and magnanimity stretch beyond
                    mankind, and, as in “Hart-leap-well” and the “Cuckoo,” extend to bird and beast;
                    he moralizes grandly on the vicissitudes of common life, but he does not enter
                    into, because by right of superior virtue be places himself above them. “From
                    the Lyrical Ballads,” it has been said, “it does not appear that men cat or
                    drink, marry or are given in marriage.” We revere the monitor who, consciously
                    good and great, gives us the dry light of truth, but we love the bard, <hi
                    rend="italic">nostroe delicioe,</hi> who is all fire— fire from heaven and
                    Ayrshire earth mingling in the outburst of passion and of power, which is his
                    poetry and the inheritance of his race. He had certainly neither culture nor
                    philosophy enough to have written the “Ode on the Recollections of Childhood,”
                    but to appreciate that ode requires an education. The sympathies of Burns, as
                    broad as Wordsworth’s, are more intense; in turning his pages we feel ourselves
                    more decidedly in the presence of one who joys with those who rejoice and mourns
                    with those who mourn. He is never shallow, ever plain, and the expression of his
                    feeling is so terse that it is always memorable. Of the people he speaks more
                    directly for the people than any of our more considerable poets. Chaucer has a
                    perfect hold of the homeliest phases of life, but he wants the lyric element,
                    and the charm of his language has largely faded from untutored ears.
                    Shakespeare, indeed, has at once a loftier vision and a wider grasp; for he
                    sings of “Thebes and Pelops line,” of Agincourt and Philippi, as of Falstaff,
                    and Smug the joiner, and the “meanest flower that blows.” But not even
                    Shakespeare has put more thought into poetry which the most prosaic must
                    appreciate than Burns has done. The latter moves in a narrower sphere and wants
                    the strictly dramatic faculty, but its place is partly supplied by the vividness
                    of his narrative. His realization of incident and character is manifested in the
                    sketches in which the manners and prevailing fancies of his countrymen are
                    immortalized in connection with local scenery. Among those almost every variety
                    of disposition finds its favourite. The quiet households of the kingdom have
                    received a sort of apotheosis in the “Cottar’s Saturday Night.” It has been
                    objected that the subject does not afford scope for the more daring forme of the
                    author’s genius; but had he written no other poem, this heartful rendering of a
                    good week’s close in a God-fearing home, sincerely devout, and yet relieved from
                    all suspicion of sermonizing by its humorous touches, would have secured a
                    permanent place in our literature. It transcends Thomson and Beattie at their
                    best, and will smell sweet like the actions of the just for generations to come.
                    Lovers of rustic festivity may agree with Professor Craik in holding that the
                    poet’s greatest performance is his narrative of “Halloween,” which for easy
                    vigour, fulness of rollicking life, blended truth and fancy, is unsurpassed in
                    its kind. Campbell, Wilson, Hazlitt, Montgomery, Burns himself, and the majority
                    of his critics, have recorded their preference for “Tam Ό Shanter,” where the
                    weird superstitious element that has played so great a part in the imaginative
                    work of this part of our island is brought more prominently forward. Few
                    passages of description are finer than that of the roaring Doon and Alloway Kirk
                    glimmering through the groaning trees; but the unique excellence of the piece
                    consists in its variety, and a perfectly original combination of the terrible
                    and the ludicrous. Like Goethe’s <hi rend="italic">Walpurgis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Nacht,</hi> brought into closer contact with real life, it
                    stretches from the drunken humours of Christopher Sly to a world of fantasies
                    almost as brilliant as those of the <hi rend="italic">Midsummer Night's
                    Dream,</hi> half solemnized by the severer atmosphere of a sterner clime. The
                    contrast between the lines “Kings may be blest,” &amp;c., and those which
                    follow, beginning “But pleasures are like poppies spread,” is typical of the
                    perpetual antithesis of the author’s thought and life, in which, at the back of
                    every revelry, he sees the shadow of a warning hand, and reads on the wall the
                    writing, <hi rend="italic">Omnia</hi><hi rend="italic">mutantur.</hi> With equal
                    or greater confidence other judges have pronounced Burns’s masterpiece to be
                    “The Jolly Beggars.” Certainly no other single production so illustrates his
                    power of exalting what is insignificant, glorifying what is mean, and elevating
                    the lowest details by the force of his genius. “The form of the piece,” says Mr
                    Carlyle, “is a mere cantata, the theme the half-drunken snatches of a joyous
                    band of vagabonds, while the grey leaves are floating on the gusts of the wind
                    in the autumn of the year. But the whole is compacted, refined, and poured forth
                    in one flood of liquid harmony. It is light, airy, and soft of movement, yet
                    sharp and precise in its details; every face is a portrait, and the whole a
                    group in clear photography. The blanket of the night is drawn aside; in full
                    ruddy gleaming light these rough tatterdemalions are seen at their boisterous
                    revel wringing from Fate another hour of wassail and good cheer.” Over the whole
                    is flung a half-humorous, halfsavage satire—aimed, like a two-edged sword, at
                    the laws and the law-breakers, in the acme of which the graceless crew arc
                    raised above the level of ordinary gipsies, footpads, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n631/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0631-0570"/> and rogues, and are made to sit “on the hills
                    like gods together, careless of mankind,” and to launch their Titan thunders of
                    rebellion against the world.</p>
                <p>“A fig for those by law protected; Liberty ’s a glorious feast;</p>
                <p>Courts for cowards were erected, Churches built to please the priest.”</p>
                <p>A similar mixture of drollery and defiance appears in the justly-celebrated
                    “Address to the Deil,” which, mainly whimsical, is relieved by touches of pathos
                    curiously quaint. “The effect of contrast,” it has been observed, “was never
                    more happily displayed than in the conception of such a being straying in lonely
                    places and loitering among trees, or in the familiarity with which the poet
                    lectures so awful a personage,”—we may add, than in the inimitable outbreak,
                    anticipatory of Professor Maurice, at the close—</p>
                <p>“0 would you tak a thought an’ men’.”</p>
                <p>Mr Carlyle, in reference to this passage, cannot resist the suggestion of a
                    parallel from Sterne. “He is the father of curses and lies, said Dr Slop, and is
                    cursed and damned already. I am sorry for it, quoth my Uncle Toby.”</p>
                <p>Burns fared ill at the hands of those who were not sorry for it, and who repeated
                    with glib complacency every terrible belief of the system in which they had been
                    trained. The most scathing of his <hi rend="italic">Satires,</hi> under which
                    head fall many of his minor and frequent passages in his major pieces, are
                    directed .against the false pride of birth, and what he conceived to be the
                    false pretences of religion. . The apologue of “Death and Dr Hornbook,” “The
                    Ordination,” the song “No churchman am I for to rail and to write,” the “Address
                    to the Unco Guid,” “Holy Willie,” and above all “The Holy Fair,” with its savage
                    caricature of an ignorant ranter of the time called Moodie, and others of like
                    stamp, not unnaturally provoked offence. As regards the poet’s attitude towards
                    some phases of Calvinism prevalent during his life, it has to be remarked that
                    from the days of Dunbar till now there has been a degree of antagonism between
                    Scotch verse and the more rigid forms of Scotch theology.</p>
                <p>It must be admitted that in protesting against hypocrisy he has occasionally been
                    led beyond the limits prescribed by good taste. He is at times abusive of those
                    who differ from him. This, with other offences against decorum, which here and
                    there disfigure his pages, can only be condoned by an appeal to the general tone
                    of his writing, which is reverential. Burns had a firm faith in a Supreme Being,
                    not as a vague mysterious Power, but as the Arbiter of human life. Amid the
                    vicissitudes of his career he responds to the cottar’s summons,“Let us worship
                    God.”</p>
                <p>“An atheist’s laugh ’s a poor exchange</p>
                <p>For Deity offended”</p>
                <p>is the moral of all his verse, which treats seriously of religious matters. His
                    prayers in rhyme give him a high place among secular Psalmists.</p>
                <p>Like Chaucer, Burns was a great moralist, though a rough one. In the moments of
                    his most intense revolt against conventional prejudice and sanctimonious
                    affectation, he is faithful to the great laws which underlie change, loyal in
                    his veneration for the cardinal virtues—Truth, Justice, and Charity,—and
                    consistent in the warnings, to which his experience gives an unhappy force,
                    against transgressions of Temperance. In the “Epistle to a Young Friend,” the
                    shrewdest advice is blended with exhortations appealing to the highest motive,
                    that which transcends the calculation of consequences, and bids us walk in the
                    straight path from the feeling of personal honour, and “for the glorious
                    privilege of being independent.” Burns, like Dante, “loved well because he
                    hated, hated wickedness that hinders loving,” and this feeling, as in the
                    lines—“Dweller in yon dungeon dark,” sometimes breaks bounds; but his calmer
                    moods are better represented by the well-known passages in the “Epistle to
                    Davie,” in which he preaches acquiescence in our lot, and a cheerful acceptance
                    of our duties in the sphere where we are placed. This <hi rend="italic"
                    >i)hilosophie douce,</hi> never better sung by Horace, is the prevailing refrain
                    of our author’s <hi rend="italic">Songs.</hi> On these there are few words to
                    add to the acclaim of a century. They have passed into the air we breathe; they
                    are so real that they seem things rather than words, or, nearer still, living
                    beings. They have taken all hearts, because they are the breath of his own; not
                    polished cadences, but utterances as direct as laughter or tears. Since Sappho
                    loved and sung, there has been no such national lyrist as Burns. Fine ballads,
                    mostly anonymous, existed in Scotland previous to his time; and shortly before a
                    few authors had produced a few songs equal to some of his best. Such are
                    Alexander Ross’s “Wooed and married,” Lowe’s “Mary’s Dream,“ “Auld Robin Gray,”
                    “The Land o’ the Leal,” and the two versions of “The Flowers o’ the Forest.”
                    From these and many of the older pieces in Ramsay’s collection, Burns admits to
                    have derived copious suggestions and. impulses. He fed on the past literature of
                    his country as Chaucer on the old fields of English thought, and—</p>
                <p>“Still the elements o’ sang,</p>
                <p>In formless jumble, right and wrang, Went floating in his brain.”</p>
                <p>But he gave more than he received; he brought forth an hundred-fold; he summed up
                    the stray material of the past, and added so much of his own that one of the
                    most conspicuous features of his lyrical genius is its variety in new paths.
                    Between the first of war songs, composed in a storm on a moor, and the pathos of
                    “Mary in Heaven,” he has made every chord in our northern life to vibrate. The
                    distance from “Duncan Gray” to “Auld Lang Syne is nearly as great as that from
                    Falstaff to Ariel. There is the vehemence of battle, the wail of woe, the march
                    ol veterans “red-wat-shod,” the smiles of meeting, the tears of parting friends,
                    the gurgle of brown burns, the roar oi the wind through pines, the rustle of
                    barley rigs, the thunder on the hill—all Scotland is in his verse. Let whe will
                    make her laws, Burns has made the songs, which heι emigrants recall “by the long
                    wash of Australasian seas,’ in which maidens are wooed, by which mothers lull
                    theiι infants, which return “through open casements unto dying ears ”—they are
                    the links, the watchwords, the masonic symbols of our race.</p>
                <p>In his “Vision” the poet imagines his Muse (probably as real to him as to Homer)
                    descending to address her votarj beside the plough. After paying through her
                    lips ε generous tribute to his predecessors, he draws, as usual, <hi
                    rend="italic">ε</hi> lesson from his own career, “by passion driven.” The
                    goddess counsels him to “preserve the dignity of man ’ and “trust the universal
                    plan,” and leaving a wreath ol green holly to deck his brows, passes “in light
                    away.”</p>
                <p>The poet passed away in darkness, but his name will never disappear from our
                    literature. He stands before us as a feature of Nature; and the fact that he
                    cannot be moved from the hearts of his countrymen, that thej recognize and
                    respect a man who has refused to mutilate human nature, and who at once
                    celebrates and strives t&lt; harmonize its ethnical and Christian elements,
                    marks a gull still fixed between Scotland and the Spain with which Mi Buckle has
                    associated it. “The generous verse of Burns,” says Dr Craik, “springs out of the
                    iron-bound Calvinism of the land like flowing water from Horeb’s rock.”</p>
                <p>The first edition of Burns’s <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> was published at
                    Kilmarnock in 1 vol. 8vo, in 1786; the second edition was published in Edinburgh
                    in 1787 (2 vols. 8vo); the third edition appeared at Dumfries in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n632/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0632-0571"/> 1793. After the poet's death Dr Currie of
                    Liverpool issued a collected edition of his works, with a Life, for the benefit
                    of his widow and family (4 vols. 8vo, Lond. 1800). This included letters as well
                    as poems, but was far from being complete. The edition of Allan Cunningham (8
                    vols. 8vo. Lond? 1834) contains a large number of pieces that are not to be
                    found in Currie’s edition. <hi rend="italic">The Life and Works of Burns,</hi>
                    by Dr Robert Chambers (Edin. 1851-2), has the distinctive feature that the poems
                    are arranged in chronological order, and interwoven with the narrative of the
                    poet’s life, which is, perhaps, the fullest and most precise in its details that
                    has appeared. The <hi rend="italic">Kilmarnock Popular Edition</hi> (2 vols.
                    Kilmarnock, 1871) possesses special interest from the fact that the first volume
                    contains an exact reprint, with fac-simile title-page, of the original edition
                    of 1786. It deserves notice that within a year of the publication of the first
                    Edinburgh edition, two separate editions of the poems were issued in America, at
                    New York and Philadelphia, 1788.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Life of Burns,</hi> by J. Gibson Lockhart (1828), has
                    passed through several editions. Among the numerous critical estimates of the
                    poet the foremost place is given by universal consent to the essay of Carlyle,
                    which first appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> (1828), and
                    is reprinted among his miscellaneous essays. (J. N.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
