<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0671-0600-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUXTON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 600</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:828732">Baths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:998853">Limes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:998827">Lime</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1130905">Spring</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1130935">Springs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737509">Medes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n671/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUXTON</label>, a market-town and fashionable watering-place
                    of England, in the county of Derby, 31 miles N.W. of Derby, and 160 from London,
                    connected with Derby by the Buxton and Rowsley extension line, and with
                    Manchester by the Stockport, Disley, and Buxton Railway. It occupies a high
                    position, being 900 feet above the sea-level, in an open hollow, surrounded at a
                    distance by hills of considerable elevation, except on the S. E. side, where
                    the</p>
                <p>Wye, which rises aoout half a mile off, makes its exit. The old town (High
                    Buxton) is rather higher than the new, and consists of one wide street, and a
                    considerable market place with an old cross With the exception of some good inns
                    and lodging-houses, the buildings in this part are commonplace. The new town is
                    of a more elegant character, and has been greatly extended within the last
                    twenty or thirty years. The crescent is a fine range of buildings in the Doric
                    style, erected by the duke of Devonshire in 1779-86, at a cost of £120,000. It
                    contains hotels, a ballroom, a bank, a library, and other establishments, and
                    the surrounding open grounds have been laid out in terraces and gardens under
                    the control of the Buxton Improvements Company. The Old Hall Hotel at the west
                    end of the crescent is remarkable as the site of the mansion built by the earl
                    of Shrewsbury in the reign of Queen Elizabeth, which was the residence of Queen
                    Mary of Scotland when she visited the town. The new church was erected in 1812
                    by the duke of Devonshire; the edifice which it superseded has since been
                    restored. The mineral waters of Buxton, the most noted in England, are
                    particularly efficacious in cases of rheumatism and gout. There are numerous
                    public and private baths, the most important of which are those in the new and
                    spacious establishment at the eastern end of the crescent. The springs supply
                    hot and cold water at a very short distance of each other, flowing at the rate
                    of 60 gallons a minute. The former possesses a uniform temperature of 82° Fahr.,
                    and the principal substances in solution are, according to the analysis of Dr
                    Muspratt in 1860—carbonate of lime, carbonate of magnesia, chloride of sodium,
                    chloride of calcium, and silica. There is also a chalybeate spring known as St
                    Anne’s well, situated at the S.W. corner of the crescent, the water of which
                    when mixed with that of the other springs proves purgative. The Devonshire
                    Hospital, formerly known as the Bath Charity, is a benevolent institution,
                    supported entirely by voluntary subscriptions, for the reception and free
                    treatment of poor patients from any part of the country. About 900 or 1000
                    persons are annually indebted to its founders. The Buxton season extends from
                    June to October, and during that period the town is visited by thousands
                    annually. The public walks are tastefully laid out. The Cavendish Terrace, 500
                    yards long, forms a fine promenade; there are excellent drives in the park,
                    which occupies more than 100 acres, and the neighbourhood of the town is rich in
                    objects of interest. Of these the chief are—Poole’s Hole, a vast stalactite
                    cave, about half a mile distant, now lighted with gas for the convenience of
                    visitors; Diamond Hill, which owes its name to the quartz crystals which are not
                    unfrequent in its rocks; and Chee Tor, a remarkable cliff, on the banks of the
                    Wye, 300 feet high. Ornaments are manufactured by the inhabitants from alabaster
                    and spar; and excellent lime is burned at the quarries near Poole’s Hole. Other
                    places of interest, but more distant, are the caverns and mines of Castleton,
                    Haddon Hall, and Chatsworth, the seat of the duke of Devonshire. The population
                    in 1871 within the jurisdiction of the Local Board of Health was 3717; but the
                    fluctuating population during summer varies from 4000 to 5000 at a time.</p>
                <p>To judge from the remains of baths and other structures which have at various
                    times been discovered, and the fact that they are situated near the crossing of
                    two military roads, it seems almost certain that the mineral springs of Buxton
                    were known to the Bomans; but by what name they were then designated has not
                    been ascertained. We find them a favourite resort in the period before the
                    Reformation, when the patients were in the habit of offering their cratches or
                    articles of attire to the image of St Anne, the tutelar saint, in token of their
                    gratitude for benefit derived from the springs. Sir William Basset, at the
                    command of Henry V11I., destroyed the “tabernacle” and prohibited the practice;
                    but the wells seem to have lost none of their reputation by the loss of their
                    saint, and continued to be a favourite resort in the last part of the century.
                    Their praises were sounded in 1572 by John Jones, “Phisition at the King’s Mede,
                    near Darby,” in <hi rend="italic">The Benefits of the Ancient Baths of
                    Buckstones,</hi> and at a later period they were celebrated by Hobbes and Cotton
                    in their respective accounts of the wonders of the Peak. See also Thomas Brown’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Tour in Derbyshire,</hi> and among modern works, Sir Charles
                    Scudamore’s <hi rend="italic">Tepid Springs of Buxton,</hi> 1839; Robertson’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Mineral Waters,</hi> 1854; L. Jewitt’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Buxton.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n672/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0672-0601"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
