<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0255-0214-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRAMBANAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 214</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bz6186h">Cells</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r330">Jainas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41v6k">Mir</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1065224">Planning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:828054">Basements</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:850250">Cells</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:840025">Buddhas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n255/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRAMBANAN</label>, a village in Java, notable for extensive
                    and remarkable ruins of Hindu character. The place lies directly south of the
                    great volcanic cone of Mir-Api (8640 feet) in the territory of the sultan of
                    Yugya-karta (written by the Dutch Djokjo-karta), and 10 miles east of the
                    capital, just on the border of the other native state called Surakarta or
                    Solo.</p>
                <p>The remains embrace six groups of temples, besides two buildings intended for
                    residence, perhaps monastic. The most remarkable of the former is that called
                    <hi rend="italic">Chandi Sewu,</hi> or “The Thousand Pagodas.” The centre of the
                    group is a large temple of cruciform plan, standing on a terraced basement, and
                    surrounded by four (originally, perhaps, by five) concentric squares, formed by
                    rows of small detached cells or temples, the whole area forming a square of
                    upwards of 500 feet to the side. Statements differ as to the exact number of
                    these cells, but a plan given by Raffles shows 238 as now standing. They are
                    sculptured externally with mythological reliefs, each is crowned with a small
                    <hi rend="italic">dagoba</hi> of the usual Buddhistic pattern (z'.e., very like
                    the minor domes over the -west portico of St Paul’s), and probably all
                    originally contained images of Buddha in the usual cross-legged attitude (of
                    which a few still remain), whilst the central shrine contained, no doubt, a
                    great image or images of Buddha also. Mr Fergusson thinks the group to be Jaina
                    rather than Buddhist; and this a closer examination of the images and their
                    symbols alone can decide. But similar series of shrines, clustered round a
                    central pagoda, are found in Buddhist Pegu. There is a professed restoration of
                    the central temple of Chaiιdi Sewu in Raffles’s <hi rend="italic">History;</hi>
                    but the details of this plate (pl. 40) are not to be relied on.</p>
                <p>Another Buddhist edifice, single but more perfect, is known by the name of Chandi
                    Kali Baneng. This also is cruciform; it stands on a boldly moulded basement, and
                    the external decoration exhibits pilasters richly carved in scroll-work, and
                    massive double cornices. Small Buddhas in niches remain, but the great figure
                    which must have occupied the interior has disappeared.</p>
                <p>A · third group of temples, once, probably, the most important, is known as <hi
                    rend="italic">Lara Jongran.</hi> These are so ruined that at a short distance
                    they present the aspect of vast and shapeless cairns of stone. One of them
                    contains in three upper cells fine figures of purely Hindu and Brahmanical
                    character. To the north is Durga (here in the character of a strong but
                    beneficent power) slaying the demon Mahishâsura,—precisely the same subject that
                    is to be found in Moor’s <hi rend="italic">Hindu Pantheon,</hi> pl. 35. This is
                    the <hi rend="italic">Lara</hi> or Virgin, who gives the popular name to the
                    group of temples. To the west is the elephant-headed Ganesha, and to the south a
                    fine Jove-like Siva, bearded and trident-bearing. Offerings are sometimes made
                    to these images by the peasantry, in spite of the universal Mahometan
                    profession.</p>
                <p>The name of the place is said by Friedrich to be properly <hi rend="italic"
                    >Parambdnan,</hi> and to mean probably “the Place of Teachers.” The whole of the
                    temples are alleged, in traditional rhymes, to have been erected between 1266
                    and 1296 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> But the chronology and history of the
                    older Javanese remains is still very obscure, and probably the date of some of
                    the Bramb4nan temples must be carried much farther back. The destruction of the
                    last-described group must have been the work of earthquake, and we must suppose
                    the date of the other buildings to be subsequent to the destruction. Some
                    general points worthy of note in regard to these buildings are the following
                    :—</p>
                <p>(1.) They are all built of hewn stones without the use of any cement.</p>
                <p>(2.) There are distinct traces showing that the exterior and interior of the
                    buildings were once covered with a fine coat of stucco, not excepting the most
                    elaborate sculpture in scroll-work, &amp;c. We know that the sculptured
                    cave-walls of Ellora, the great idols at Bamian, and the Doric order at Selinus
                    were similarly coated; and probably in all these cases the stucco was intended
                    to bear colour or gilding.</p>
                <p>(3.) No real arch exists in these buildings. The vaults and doorways are covered
                    by the corbelling, or stepped projection, of the horizontal courses. Mr Crawfurd
                    makes a contrary statement, but that historian, usually so trustworthy, was
                    certainly mistaken on this point.</p>
                <p>(4.) Many of the peculiarities of this architecture, both in general plan and in
                    ornamental details, indicate a close relation to the mediaeval styles of Burmah
                    and Camboja; and points almost necessarily to an original common type in India,
                    a type which as yet we cannot trace satisfactorily. In this lies a problem of
                    interest, which the accumulation of photographs will perhaps allow of being
                    worked out. It is notable, however, that i⅛the Burmese mediaeval brick buildings
                    of analogous character the true arch is used profusely.— <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Chiefly from the notes of a visit to</hi><hi rend="italic">Brambânan</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">by the writer.}</hi> (H. Y.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
