<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0086-0077-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">BOSWELL, James</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 77</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:880392">Corsicans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n86/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BOSWELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label>, the
                    biographer of Johnson, was born at Edinburgh on the 29th October 1740. His
                    father was one of the lords of Session, or judges of the supreme court in
                    Scotland, and took his title, Lord Auchinleck, from the name of his property in
                    Ayrshire. The family was of old and honourable descent, a fact of which both
                    father and son were not only proud but vain. James, the eldest son, was educated
                    at Edinburgh and Glasgow Universities, and during his student days contracted a
                    close and life-long friendship with William Johnson Temple, afterwards vicar of
                    St Gluvias and rector of Mamhead. His unrestrained correspondence with Temple,
                    extending with occasional breaks from 1758 to the last year of his life, affords
                    us the best materials for a knowledge of his career and an estimate of his
                    character. At the age of eighteen he was busily engaged in the study of the law
                    at Edinburgh, not entirely in accordance with his own inclination, but in
                    obedience to the desire of his father. Already, however, he had begun to take a
                    pride in being associated with men of distinction, and tells his friend, with
                    some exultation, that he had accompanied Sir David Dalrymple (afterward Lord
                    Hailes) on the Northern Circuit, and had kept a journal of what was said by the
                    great man on the way. Some other peculiarities of his character also became
                    manifest even at this early period of his life. He was evidently unsettled and
                    unstable, “constitutionally unfit,” as he afterwards said, “for any employment;”
                    he disliked the Scottish style of life, and longed for the elegance, refinement,
                    and liberality of London society. In 1760 this wish was so far gratified; he
                    tasted some of the delights of the capital, and indulged in magnificent dreams
                    of entering the Guards and spending his time about the court. Such a fancy,
                    however, came to nothing; for as he has narrated with some pride, the duke of
                    Argyll told his father that “this boy must not be shot at for three and sixpence
                    a day.” A military life, indeed, would hardly have suited him, for, as he
                    frankly confesses, his personal courage was but small.</p>
                <p>Boswell’s taste3 were always literary; he had contributed some slight tilings to
                    the current magazines; and in 1762 he published a rather humorous little poem,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Cub at Neτvmarket.</hi> In the following year appeared a
                    collection of <hi rend="italic">Letters between the Hon. Andrew Erskine and
                    James Boswell, Esq.,</hi> which the vanity of the youthful authors induced them
                    to think would be received with pleasure and profit by the world. The only
                    prominent characteristic of these epistles is an overstrained attempt at
                    liveliness and wit.</p>
                <p>On Monday, 16th May 1763, Boswell, then on a second visit to London, had thé
                    supreme happiness to make the acquaintance of the object of his almost
                    idolatrous admiration,—Dr Johnson. Their first interview in the back parlour of
                    Mr Davies’s shop in Russell Street was characteristic of both; the calm strength
                    and ponderous wit of the one, the fluttering folly and childish servility of the
                    other, are portrayed .to the life in Boswell’s own narrative. Few things are
                    more singular than the intimacy which sprang up between two men so differently
                    constituted. Boswell might indeed congratulate himself that he had something
                    about him that interested most people at first sight in his favour. He was then
                    about to proceed to Utrecht in order <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n87/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0087-0078"/> to prosecute his studies; and the great Dr
                    Johnson actually accompanied him to Harwich and saw him off, with many
                    protestations of affection.</p>
                <p>At Utrecht Boswell was as unsettled and dissipated as before. He had a fair
                    allowance from his father—£240 a year; but he was determined “not to be
                    straitened nor to encourage the least narrowness of disposition as to saving
                    money.’’ To what extent this virtuous resolution was carried out is unknown; but
                    after leaving the university, he determined, sorely against his father’s
                    inclination, to prolong his residence abroad. He travelled through various parts
                    of the Continent, visited Voltaire and Rousseau, and was finally attracted to
                    Corsica, where he speedily attached himself to and became the intimate friend of
                    the patriot Paoli. He did not return to England till 1766, but he had not
                    neglected his note-book, and in 1768 published his <hi rend="italic">Account of
                    Corsica, Journal of a Tour to that Island, and Memoirs of Pascal Paoli.</hi> The
                    book had a very considerable success, not on account of the merits of its
                    lιistorical or descriptive passages, but from the liveliness and truth of the
                    journal, and from the numerous anecdotes and sayings, which brought the Corsican
                    patriot vividly before the English imagination. Johnson’s estimate of the work
                    was discriminating and just; and other good judges, though they could not avoid
                    noticing and ridiculing Boswell’s extravagances and follies, appreciated at its
                    true value his unrivalled power of biographical narration. The book did much for
                    Paoli, and secured for him sympathy and assistance in England when he was
                    compelled to fly from his native island. The author was for a time intoxicated
                    with his success; he pestered every one with Corsica, introduced himself to Pitt
                    in Corsican dress, and not only appeared at the Shakespeare Jubilee arrayed in
                    the costume of an armed Corsican chief, with “Viva la Liberia” inscribed on his
                    hat, but wrote a full description of his appearance to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >London Magazine.</hi> He certainly gained notoriety, if not fame.</p>
                <p>His restless spirit next found occupation in the great Douglas peerage case. He
                    took an intense interest in this affair, acted as an unattached counsel, and
                    published on it a novel and a pamphlet. The often repeated story, that he
                    resented the judgment given by his father in the case to such an extent that he
                    headed the rioters who broke the old judge’s windows, is not inconsistent with
                    his character, but as the father’s judgment virtually coincided with the son’s
                    opinion, it really has no foundation in fact.</p>
                <p>In 1769, after numerous love affairs, which are told to his friend Temple with
                    more freedom than decency, he married Miss Montgomerie. Not much is known of
                    this lady, except that she was a relation of the earl of Eglinton, as Boswell
                    took care to inform the people of Scotland in his <hi rend="italic">Letter
                    to</hi> them in 1785. Johnson’s opinion of her qualities was very low; but she
                    probably concurred with old Lord Auchinleck in thinking the great lexicographer
                    “a brute.” She seems also to have had rather a contempt for some aspects of Mr
                    Boswell’s character, whatever that might “comprehend in his own imagination, and
                    in that of a wonderful number of mankind.”</p>
                <p>In 1773, though against his father’s will, Boswell came to London. He was
                    admitted a member of the Literary Club, and soon after set out with his great
                    friend on the immortal tour to the Hebrides. It was not till many years
                    afterwards that the famous <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> was given to the
                    world,—not till after the death of Johnson. Some years after the death of his
                    father in 1782 he had joined the English bar, but he never succeeded in gaining
                    any practice. In 1785 the <hi rend="italic">Journal of a Tour to the
                    Hebrides</hi> was published, and preparations set on foot for an extended <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Johnson.</hi> The collection of materials and careful
                    revision occupied several years, and though Eoswell sometimes was despondent,
                    yet on the whole he looked with well-grounded confidence for success. He was
                    absolutely certain that his “mode of biography, which gives not only a <hi
                    rend="italic">history</hi> of Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">visible</hi> progress
                    through the world, and of his publications, but a view of his mind in his
                    letters and conversations, is the most perfect that can be conceived, and will
                    be more of a life than any work that has ever yet appeared.” His expectations
                    were not deceived. The book, which appeared in 1791, was received with the
                    greatest eagerness and delight; and in 1793 a second edition was published. The
                    author’s triumph and selfsatisfaction were complete; but meantime the evil
                    habits he had contracted during a dissipated life were ruining his health, both
                    of mind and body. He was in his later years an habitual drunkard, and the
                    hypochondria, from which he had always suffered at intervals, terribly
                    increased. He died after a short illness on the 19th May 1795, at the age of
                    55.</p>
                <p>Boswell’s character is curious and somewhat contradictory. He was vain of his
                    birth, and of his own talents, sensual and self-indulgent, inquisitive and
                    undignified; and all these faults he parades with a perfectly childish
                    naïveté;—not certainly without consciousness that they were faults, for he is
                    constantly repenting of his sins and framing the best of resolutions, swearing
                    “like an ancient Pythagorean to observe silence, to be grave and reserved though
                    cheerful and communicative.” “One great fault of mine,” he says, “is talking at
                    random. I will guard against it.” But he was, as he has himself admitted,
                    “utterly wanting in solidity and force of mind.” His egotism and vanity were
                    excessive, and he exposes these qualities with the greatest frankness to his
                    friend Temple. “I, James Boswell, Esq.,” he writes on one occasion,—“you know
                    what vanity that name includes.’’ And again with reference to one of his rivals
                    in Johnsonian literature, he writes; “Hawkins is, no doubt, very malevolent;
                    observe how he talks of me as quite unknown.” The peculiar weakness of his
                    intellect and exuberance of his spirits hurried him into absurdities and
                    follies, and made him the butt of the society in which he moved. Yet he was far
                    from having no redeeming qualities. He was genial and friendly, of cultured
                    literary taste, and of no mean powers of mind. It was not a mere frivolous,
                    foolish, prating sot who could appreciate the great qualities of Johnson, and
                    devote himself to a friendship from which he derived no profit and little
                    praise. And assuredly it was not by his unrivalled powers as a fool that Boswell
                    has produced the best biography the world has yet seen. He was not only, as
                    Macaulay admits, a man of quick observation and retentive memory, but he had
                    also grasped with complete consciousness the true idea of biography, which he
                    had learned from his great teacher. Johnson valued biography, because it gives
                    us what comes home to ourselves; he thought that no one could write a real life
                    unless he had lived in social intercourse with the man of whom he wrote, and
                    laid it down as the duty of a biographer to give a full account of the person
                    whose life he is writing, and to discriminate him from all other persons, by any
                    peculiarities of character or sentiment he may happen to have. All these hints
                    were taken hold of and assimilated by Boswell, and the result was a biography
                    which has no equal in our own or in any other literature, which, so far from
                    losing its popularity, is as much esteemed now as when first given to the world,
                    and on which it seems superfluous even to bestow laudation. Johnson was
                    undoubtedly a great man, but he would never have been to us more than a mere
                    name had it not been for Boswell’s life. Through that life he is known to us as
                    no other English writer is; his faults and weaknesses, his grand powers of mind
                    and rugged moral strength,—his whole personality is revived for <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n88/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0088-0079"/> us. We know him as he actually lived and moved
                    among his fellow-men. The very lights and shades thrown on his character by the
                    narrative give it additional force, for they convince us of its intense truth
                    and reality. Nor is it only as a life of Johnson that Boswell’s book has value
                    for us; it is the most important contribution yet made to a knowledge of actual
                    living and thinking in the 18th century. “It is not speaking with exaggeration,”
                    says Carlyle, “but with strict measured sobriety, to say that this book of
                    Boswell’s will give us more real insight into the history of England, during
                    those days, than twenty other books, falsely entitled ‘ Histories,’ which take
                    to themselves that special aim.”</p>
                <p>A short memoir of Boswell was written by Malone and will be found in Nichol’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Literary Anecdotes.</hi> It is also reprinted, with some extracts
                    from Boswell’s letters to Malone, in the edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Life</hi> published by Bohn, 1859. The <hi rend="italic">Letters to JV. J.
                    Temple and Andrew Erskine</hi> were printed in 1857; in the introduction will be
                    found a pretty complete notice of Boswell’s minor writings. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eos-wdliana</hi> have been published in the second volume of the Philobiblon
                    Society Miscellanies, 1855-6, and by Dr Charles Rogers, 1874. Editions of
                    Boswell’s great work are very numerous; perhaps the amended form of Croker’s
                    first edition, by Wright (Bohn, 10 vols., 1859), is the most helpful. The famous
                    essays on Boswell by Macaulay and Carlyle may be taken as mutually corrective
                    and supplementary.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
