<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0039-0030-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BONAVENTURA (9th edition, volume 4, page 30)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n39/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BONAVENTURA</label>. <hi rend="smallcaps">John of</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Fidanza,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Fidenza,</hi> more
                    commonly known as St Bonaventura, was born at Bagnarea in the Papal States, in
                    the year 1221. He was at an early age destined by his mother for the church, and
                    is said to have received his cognomen of Bonaventura from St Francis of Assisi,
                    who performed on him a miraculous cure. He entered the Franciscan order in his
                    twenty-second year, and is said to have studied at Paris under Alexander of
                    Hales. This does not seem very probable, but he certainly studied under
                    Alexander’s successor, John of Rochelle, to whose chair he succeeded in 1253.
                    Three years before that period his fame had gained for him permission to read
                    upon the <hi rend="italic">Sentences,</hi> and in 1255 he received the degree of
                    doctor. So high was his reputation both for brilliancy of intellect and purity
                    of mind that, in the following year, he was elected general of his order. He at
                    once set himself to work to introduce better discipline, and by his mild
                    regulations succeeded in effecting much good. He was an advocate of asceticism,
                    and looked upon the monastic life as the surest means of grace. It is worthy of
                    notice tlιat by his orders Roger Bacon was interdicted from lecturing at Oxford,
                    and compelled to put himself under the surveillance of the order at Paris.
                    Bonaventura was instrumental in procuring the election of Gregory X., who
                    rewarded him with the titles of cardinal and bishop of Albano, and insisted on
                    his presence at the great Council of Lyons in the year 1274. At this meeting he
                    died. Bonaventura’s character seems not unworthy of the eulogistic title,
                    “Doctor Seraphicus,” bestowed on him by his contemporaries, nor of the place
                    assigned to him by Dante in his <hi rend="italic">Paradiso.</hi> He was formally
                    canonized in 1482 by Sixtus IV.</p>
                <p>His works, as arranged in the Lyons editon (7 vole., folio), consist of
                    expositions and sermons, filling the first three volumes; of a commentary on the
                        <hi rend="italic">Sentences</hi> of Lombardus, in two volumes, celebrated
                    among mediaeval theologians as incomparably the best exposition of the third
                    part; and of minor treatises filling the remaining two volumes, and including a
                    life of St Francis. The smaller works are the most important, and of them the
                    best are the famous <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium</hi><hi rend="italic">Mentis
                        ad Deum, Βreviloquium, De</hi><hi rend="italic">Reductione Artium</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Theologiam, Soliloquium,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">De septem itineribus</hi><hi rend="italic">oeternitatis,</hi>
                    in which most of what is individual in his teaching is contained. In philosophy
                    Bonaventura presents a marked contrast to his great contemporaries, Thomas
                    Aquinas and Roger Bacon. While these may be taken as representing respectively
                    physical science yet in its infancy, and Aristotelian scholasticism in its most
                    perfect form, he brings before us the mystical and Flatonizing mode of
                    speculation which had already to some extent found expression in Hugo and
                    Richard of St Victor, and in Bernard of Clairvaux. To him the purely
                    intellectual element, though never absent, is of inferior interest when compared
                    with the living power of the affections or the heart. He rejects the authority
                    of Aristotle, to whose influence he ascribes much of the heretical tendency of
                    the age, and some of whose cardinal doctrines—such as the eternity of the
                    world—he combats vigorously. But the Platonism he received was Plato as
                    understood by St Augustine, and as lie had been handed down by the Alexandrian
                    school and the authors of the mystical works passing under the name of Dionysius
                    the Areopagite. Bonaventura accepts as Platonic the theory that ideas do not
                    exist <hi rend="italic">in rerum</hi><hi rend="italic">natura,</hi> but as
                    thoughts of the divine mind, according to which actual things were formed; and
                    this conception has no slight influence upon his philosophy. Like all the great
                    scholastic doctors he starts with the discussion of the relations between reason
                    and faith. All the sciences are but the handmaids of theology; reason can
                    discover some of the moral truths which form the groundwork of the Christian
                    system, but others it can only receive and apprehend through divine
                    illumination. In order to obtain this illumination the soul must employ the
                    proper means, which are prayer, the exercise of the virtues, whereby it is
                    rendered fit to accept the divine light, and meditation which may rise even to
                    ecstatic union with God. The supreme end of life is such union, union in
                    contemplation or intellect <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n40/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0040-0031"/> and in intense absorbing love; but it cannot
                    be entirely reached in this life, and remains as a hope for futurity. The mind
                    in contemplating Qod has three distinct aspects, stages, or grades,—the senses,
                    giving empirical knowledge of what is without and discerning the traces <hi
                        rend="italic">{vestigia)</hi> of the divine in the world; the reason, which
                    examines the soul itself, the image of the divine Being; and lastly, pure
                    intellect <hi rend="italic">{intelligβntia)</hi> which, in a transcendent act,
                    grasps the Being of the divine cause. To these three correspond the three kinds
                    of theology,— <hi rend="italic">theologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >symbolica,</hi><hi rend="italic">theologia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >propria,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">theologia mystica.</hi> Each stage is
                    subdivided, for in contemplating the outer world we may use the senses or the
                    imagination; <hi rend="italic">we</hi> may rise to a knowledge of God <hi
                        rend="italic">per vestigia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">in vestigiis.</hi> In
                    the first case the three great properties of physical bodies—weight, number,
                    measure,— in the second the division of created things into the classes of those
                    that have merely physical existence, those that have life, and those that have
                    thought, irresistibly lead us to conclude the power, wisdom, and goodness of the
                    Triune God. So in the second stage, we may ascend to the knowledge of God, <hi
                        rend="italic">per</hi><hi rend="italic">imaginem,</hi> by reason, or <hi
                        rend="italic">in imagine,</hi> by the pure understanding <hi rend="italic"
                        >{intellectus)</hi>; in the one case the triple division—memory,
                    understanding, and will,—in the other the Christian virtues—faith, hope, and
                    charity— leading again to the conception of a Trinity of divine
                    qualities—eternity, truth, and goodness. In the last stage we have first <hi
                        rend="italic">intelligentia,</hi> pure intellect, contemplating the
                    essential being of God, and finding itself compelled by necessity of thought to
                    hold absolute being as the first notion, for non-being cannot be conceived apart
                    from being, of which it is but the privation. To this notion of absolute being,
                    which is perfect and the greatest of all, objective existence must be ascribed.
                    In its last and highest form of activity the mind rests in the contemplation of
                    the infinite goodness of God, which is apprehended by means of the highest
                    faculty, the <hi rend="italic">apex mentis,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >synderesis.</hi> Thiβ spark of the divine illumination is common to all
                    forms of mysticism, but Bonaventura adds to it peculiarly Christian elements.
                    The complete yielding up of mind and heart to God is unattainable without divine
                    grace, and nothing renders us so fit to receive this gift as the meditative and
                    ascetic life of the cloister. The monastic life is the best means of grace.</p>
                <p>Bonaventura, however, is not merely a meditative thinker, whose works may form
                    good manuals of devotion; he is a dogmatic theologian of high rank, and on all
                    the disputed questions of scholastic thought, such as universals, matter, the
                    principle of individualism, or the <hi rend="italic">intellectus agens,</hi> he
                    gives weighty and well-reasoned decisions. He agrees with Albert in regarding
                    theology as a practical science; its truths, according to his view, are
                    peculiarly adapted to influence the affections. He discusses very carefully the
                    nature and meaning of the divine attributes; considers universals to be the
                    ideal forms pre-existing in the divine mind according to which things were
                    shaped; holds matter to be pure potentiality which receives individual being and
                    determinateness from the formative power of God, acting according to the ideas;
                    and finally maintains that the <hi rend="italic">intellectus agens</hi> has no
                    separate existence. On these and on many other points of scholastic philosophy
                    the Seraphic Doctor exhibits a combination of subtilty and moderation which
                    makes his works peculiarly valuable.</p>
                <p>Editions of Bonaventura’s works are numerous. The most complete early edition was
                    that in 7 vols, fo., Rome, 1588-96. They nave also been published at Lyons, 7
                    vols., 1668, and at Venice, 14 vois., 1751, <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi> The best
                    edition is that by A. C. Peltier, begun in 1863. Of detached works the editions
                    and translations are very numerous. The following are perhaps the most important
                    :— <hi rend="italic">Brcviloquiuτn</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Itinerarium</hi><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >entis ad Deum,</hi> ed. Hefele, 3d ed., 1862; <hi rend="italic">Théologie
                        Séraphique, extraite et traduite des oeuvres de St B.,</hi> by Alix, 2
                    vols., 1853-56. For Bonaventura’s philosophy, see Erdmann, Hauréau, Stöckl; the
                    works on the history of mysticism by Schmid, Görres, HelfΓerich, Noack, and
                    Preger; and Ozanam, <hi rend="italic">Dante</hi><hi rend="italic">et la
                        Philosophie Catholique au</hi><hi rend="italic">X∏pne</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Siècle.</hi> There are two monographs on him,—Margerie (A. de), <hi
                        rend="italic">Essai sur la philosophie de St</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Bonaventure, 1855,</hi> and Hollenberg, <hi rend="italic">Studien zu
                        Bonaventura,</hi> 1862. Notices of his life are given in the Venice edition,
                    and in that of Peltier; also in the <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Litt, de la France,</hi> vol. xix. (R. AD.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
