<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0728-0672-05" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">SCANDINAVIA</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 672</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51q1n">Fear</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204556">Norway</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210572">Iceland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:922034">Fear</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039481">Norwegians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=728" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">SCANDINAVIA</label>, a general name for the countries of
                    Norway, Sweden, and Denmark, anciently under the dominion of one prince. The
                    inhabitants of these countries, in former times, were excessively addicted to
                    war. From their earliest years they applied themselves to the military art, and
                    accustomed themselves to cold, fatigue, and hunger. Even the very sports of
                    youth and childhood were dangerous. They consisted in taking frightful leaps,
                    climbing up the steepest rocks, fighting naked with offensive weapons, and
                    wrestling with the utmost fury; so that it was usual to see them grown up to be
                    robust men. and terrible in the combat, at the age of fifteen. At this early age
                    the young men became their own masters, which they did by receiving a sword, a
                    buckler, and a lance. The ceremony<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=729" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0729-0673"/>
                    was performed at some public meeting. One of the principal men of the assembly
                    named the youth in public; after which he was obliged to provide for his own
                    subsistence, and was either now to live by hunting, or by joining in some
                    incursion against the enemy. Great care was taken to prevent the young men from
                    too early connexions with the female sex; and indeed they could have no hope to
                    gain the affection of the fair, but in proportion to the courage and address
                    they had shown in their military exercises. Accordingly, in an ancient song, we
                    find Bartholin, king of Norway, extremely surprised that his mistress should
                    prove unkind, as he could perform eight different exercises. The children were
                    generally born in camps; and being inured from their infancy to behold nothing
                    but arms, effusion of blood, and slaughter, they imbibed the cruel disposition
                    of their fathers, and when they broke forth upon other nations, behaved rather
                    like furies than like human creatures.</p><p>The laws of this people, in some measure, resembled those of the ancient
                    Lacedaemonians. They knew no virtue but bravery, and no vice but cowardice. The
                    greatest penalties were inflicted on such as fled from battle. The laws of the
                    ancient Danes declared such persons infamous, and excluded them from society.
                    Among the Germans, cowards were sometimes suffocated in mud; after which they
                    were covered over with hurdles, to show, says Tacitus, that though the
                    punishment of crimes should be public, there are certain degrees of cowardice
                    and infamy which ought to be buried in oblivion. Frotho king of Denmark enacted
                    by law, that whoever solicited an eminent post ought upon all occasions to
                    attack one enemy, to face two, to retire only one step back from three, and
                    never to make an actual retreat till assaulted by four. The rules of justice
                    were themselves adapted and warped to these prejudices. War was looked upon as a
                    real act of justice, and force was thought to be an incontestable title over the
                    weak, a visible mark that God had intended them to be subject to the strong.
                    They had no doubt but that the intentions of the Deity had been to establish the
                    same dependence among men that takes place among inferior creatures; and,
                    setting out from this principle of the natural inequality among men, they had
                    from thence inferred that the weak had no right to what they could not defend.
                    This maxim was adopted with such rigour, that the name of divine judgment was
                    given not only to the judicial combat, but to conflicts and battles of all
                    sorts; victory being, in their opinion, the only certain mark by which
                    Providence enables us to distinguish those whom it has appointed to command
                    others.</p><p>Lastly, their religion, by annexing eternal happiness to the military virtues,
                    gave the utmost possible degree of vigour to that propensity which these people
                    had for war, and to their contempt of death, of which we shall now give some
                    instances. We are informed that Harold, surnamed Blaatand, or Blue-tooth, a king
                    of Denmark, who lived in the beginning of the ninth century, had founded on the
                    coast of Pomerania a city named Julin or Jomsburg. To this place he sent a
                    colony of young Danes, bestowing the government on a celebrated warrior called
                    Palnatoko. In this colony it was forbidden to mention the word fear, even in the
                    most imminent dangers. No citizen of Jomsburg was to yield to any number of
                    enemies, however great. The sight of inevitable death was not to be taken as an
                    excuse for showing the smallest apprehension. And this legislator really appears
                    to have eradicated from the minds of most of the youths bred up under him all
                    traces of that sentiment so natural and so universal, which makes men think on
                    their destruction with horror. Nothing can show this better than a single fact
                    in their history, which deserves to have a place here for its singularity. Some
                    of them having made an irruption into the territories of a powerful</p><p>Norwegian lord, named Haquin, were overcome in spite of the obstinacy of their
                    resistance, and the most distinguished among them being made prisoners, were,
                    according to the custom of those times, condemned to death. The news of this,
                    far from afflicting them, was on the contrary received with joy. The first who
                    was led to punishment was content to say, without changing countenance, and
                    without expressing the least sign of fear, “Why should not the same happen to me
                    as did to my father? He died, and so must I.” A warrior named Thorchill, who was
                    to cut off the head of the second, having asked him what he felt at the sight of
                    death, he answered, “that he remembered too well the laws of Jomsburg, to utter
                    any words that denoted fear.” The third, in reply to the same question, said,
                    “he rejoiced to die with glory, and that he preferred such a death to an
                    infamous life like that of Thorchill’s.” The fourth made an answer much longer
                    and more extraordinary. “I suffer with a good heart, and the present hour is to
                    me very agreeable. I only beg of you,” added he, addressing himself to
                    Thorchill, “to be very quick in cutting off my head; for it is a question often
                    debated by us at Jomsburg, whether one retains any sense after being beheaded. I
                    will therefore grasp this knife in my hand; if, after my head is cut off, I
                    strike it towards you, it will show I have not lost all sense; if I let it drop,
                    it will be a proof of the contrary. Make haste, therefore, and decide the
                    dispute.” Thorchill, adds the historian, cut off his head in a most expeditious
                    manner; but the knife, as might be expected, dropt from his hand. The fifth
                    showed the same tranquillity, and died rallying and jeering his enemies. The
                    sixth begged of Thorchill that he might not be led to punishment like a sheep:
                    “Strike the blow in my face,” said he; “I will sit still without shrinking; and
                    take notice whether I once wink my eyes, or betray one sign of fear in my
                    countenance; for we inhabitants of Jomsburg are used to exercise ourselves in
                    trials of this sort, so as to meet the stroke of death without once moving.” He
                    kept his promise before all the spectators, and received the blow without
                    betraying the least sign of fear, or so much as winking with his eyes. The
                    seventh, says the historian, was a very beautiful young man, in the flower of
                    his age. His long hair, as fine as silk, floated in curls and in ringlets on his
                    shoulders. Thorchill asked him what he thought of death. “I receive it
                    willingly,” said he, “since I have fulfilled the greatest duty of life, and have
                    seen all those put to death whom I would not survive. I only beg of you one
                    favour, not to let my hair be touched by a slave, or stained with my blood.”</p><p>Neither was this intrepidity peculiar to the inhabitants of Jomsburg. It was the
                    general character of all the Scandinavians, of which we shall only give this
                    further instance. A warrior, having been thrown upon his back in wrestling with
                    his enemy, and the latter finding himself without his arms, the vanquished
                    person promised to wait, without changing his posture, till his antagonist
                    fetched a sword to kill him; and he faithfully kept his word. To die with arms
                    in his hand was the ardent wish of every free man; and the pleasing idea which
                    they had of this kind of death led them to dread such as proceeded from old age
                    and disease. The history of ancient Scandinavia is full of instances of this way
                    of thinking. The warriors who found themselves lingering in disease often
                    availed themselves of their few remaining moments to shake off life, by a way
                    that they supposed to be more glorious. Some of them would be carried into a
                    field of battle, that they might die in the engagement. Others slew themselves.
                    Many got this melancholy service performed by their friends, who considered it
                    as a most sacred duty. “There is, on a mountain of Iceland,” says the author of
                    an old Iceland romance, “a rock so high that no animal can fall from the top of
                    it and live. Here men betake themselves when they are afflicted<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=730" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0730-0674"/>
                    and unhappy. From this place all our ancestors, even without waiting for
                    sickness, have departed into Eden. It is useless, therefore, to give ourselves
                    up to groans and complaints, or to put our relations to needless expenses, since
                    we can easily follow the example of our fathers, who have all gone by the way of
                    this rock.” When all these methods failed, and at last when Christianity had
                    banished such barbarous practices, the disconsolate heroes consoled themselves
                    by putting on complete armour as soon as they found their end approaching.</p></div></body></text></TEI>