<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0747-0691-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SCIO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 691</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:938081">Garrisons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1054286">Pashas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=747" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SCIO</label>, an island of the Mediterranean, not far from
                    the coast of Smyrna, and one of those classed as the Sporades. It was known to
                    the ancients by the name of Chios, and by the Turks is now called Sakez-Adassi.
                    It is situated between the parallels of 38° 8' and 38° 30', and between the
                    meridians 25° 50' and 26° 11', thus being in length twenty-two and in breadth
                    twenty-one geographical miles. It is separated from the shore of Anatolia by a
                    strait, called sometimes the Strait of Bianca, and sometimes that of Scio, which
                    is seven leagues long, and has a depth of water of twenty fathoms. The road, or,
                    as it is called, the Great Port, has depth for ships of the greatest draught of
                    water; and near to it is the harbour of Fin or Delfyn. To the south of this last
                    port, at about two leagues distance, is the capital of the island, the city of
                    Scio, which, in spite of the dreadful disasters which it has endured, still
                    exists. It was built by the Genoese when they possessed the island. It is wholly
                    constructed of stone or brick, and was till recently much cleaner in its
                    appearance than most towns in this part of the world. Mr Galt, who visited it in
                    1810, says, that “the houses are built in the Italian style, with lofty
                    pyramidal roofs. Except in the particular of dress, and with the exception of
                    the streets where the shops are situated, every thing about Scio has the
                    appearance of a town in Christendom. The shops are well filled, many of them
                    with those gorgeous stuffs of woven gold and silver which are but rarely to be
                    seen even in London. This was one of the principal manufacturing seats of the
                    Turkish empire; and silks, which rival in beauty and elegance the richest of
                    France and ltaly, are produced in the looms of Scio. In the town are about
                    ninety places of worship belonging to the Greek and Roman persuasions. There is
                    a cathedral, a respectable building, adorned with modern paintings. Almost the
                    whole of the lower class are silk weavers and embroiderers. Many of the villas
                    in the neighbourhood of the town are large buildings, with attached
                    pleasure-grounds and beautiful gardens.”</p>
                <p>At a later period the city contained about 5000 houses, and the inhabitants were
                    estimated at 25,000 persons. Besides the city, there were on the island
                    seventy-six large villages, containing Armenians, Turks, and Greeks. The latter
                    were calculated by none below eighty, but by some at a hundred thousand.</p>
                <p>A traveller, Mr Laurent, who visited the island in 1818, says, “All the ideas
                    which fancy can form of an earthly paradise seem realized here; the face of the
                    country, itself most fruitful, is cultivated with the greatest assiduity, and
                    every part presents rich vineyards intermingled with fruitful trees. The valleys
                    are intersected with paths shaded by trees, spreading over the traveller’s head
                    their luxuriant branches, bending in the seasons under the weight of lemons,
                    oranges, and pomegranates. The inhabitants seem willing to join their efforts to
                    add to the charms of their island; by all the foreigner is welcomed, and the
                    traveller hears the salute of the peasant, <hi rend="italic">kale emera, kalé
                    espera,</hi> good day, or good evening, as he passes along.”</p>
                <p>Among the productions of the island, wine is one of much celebrity when drank on
                    the spot; but, from the delicacy of its flavour, it suffers by removal. The corn
                    produced is not equal to more than two months’consumption; the fruits, which are
                    the chief means of subsistence, are the finest in the Levant; the figs are of an
                    incredible size, and the lemons and oranges exported are said to have risen to
                    the value of L.25,000. Mastic gum is an article of great importance, and the
                    shrub from which it exudes was very extensively cultivated. The other articles
                    of export were cotton wool, silk, terebinth, wrought silks, and tanned
                    hides.</p>
                <p>Literature was more cultivated in Scio than in any other of the Greek islands;
                    and no priest officiated there who had not been a member of the college.</p>
                <p>The richest of the inhabitants were merchants at the head of considerable houses,
                    with commercial establishments under the management of partners in Odessa,
                    Venice, Fiume, Trieste, Leghorn, Genoa, Marseilles, Vienna, and London. They
                    lived here in elegantly-furnished houses, were hospitable to strangers, and in
                    the enjoyment of a degree of ease and freedom which was nowhere else to be
                    witnessed within the other territories under the dominion of the Turks.</p>
                <p>The favourable circumstances in which the people lived was in a great part owing
                    to the power over the island having been granted to a sultana, a sister of the
                    sultan, who, satisfied with a sum of money annually collected by the people
                    among themselves, left them almost to their own religion, laws, manners, and
                    occupations; but she is said to have prided herself on the superiority of those
                    under her sway to any other Turkish subjects.<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=748" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0748-0692"/>
                    It was owing to this state of things that, when the revolutionary movements
                    among the other Greeks in the Turkish dominions were commenced, no disposition
                    was felt in Scio to embark in the same course. There was a small Turkish
                    garrison in a fortress under an aga, to whom the people gave assurance that no
                    disposition to revolt existed among them; and some of the most respectable heads
                    of families gave themselves as hostages for the pacific and tranquil conduct of
                    their countrymen. The Turkish fleets never molested them, but passed by to
                    subdue the other islands then in a state of insurrection. One of the insurgent
                    Greek leaders, however, with a fleet entered the harbour, and landed a body of
                    troops to attack the arsenal, in which the small garrison of the Turks was
                    collected. In the attack on the fort, the Sciotes of the lowest classes, in
                    spite of the remonstrances of their primates, joined their fellow-Christians.
                    The fort was taken, and the garrison, as well as all the Turks in the city, were
                    put to the sword.</p>
                <p>Soon afterwards, in 1822, whilst the island was under the dominion of the rabble
                    and the small body of insurgent Greeks, the Turkish fleet entered the harbour,
                    upon which the invaders escaped from the superior force. As the populace had
                    joined them in spite of the remonstrances of the principal inhabitants, the
                    latter, in number above two hundred, repaired on board the ship of the Capitan
                    Pasha, with the most solemn assurance of their innocence, and the most
                    unqualified submission to the Porte. The admiral received them with great
                    civility, expressed himself willing to forget all that had passed, and ordered
                    coffee and a variety of refreshments. He soon landed, taking with him a force of
                    10,000 men, a few of whom were regular troops, but the far greater number were
                    volunteers, under no control, who had been induced to embark from the capital by
                    the promise of plunder. Then consequently began a general massacre of the men,
                    with the plunder of the houses, and the capture of the women, girls, and boys,
                    as slaves, to be sold by the captors to the harems for the gratification of the
                    natural and the unnatural vices of the Turks. The details given by eye-witnesses
                    who escaped were such as to harrow up the soul. Every house and every garden
                    were strewed with corpses; beneath the orange-trees, on the sides of the
                    fountains, on the rich carpet, and on the marble pavement, lay the young, the
                    beautiful, and the aged, in the midst of their loved and luxurious retreats. Day
                    after day passed, and, lying as they fell, alone or in groups, no hand bore them
                    to their graves, while survivors yet remained to perish. At last, when all was
                    over, they were thrown in promiscuous heaps into large pits.</p>
                <p>Twenty thousand persons are computed to have thus perished during the few days
                    the massacre lasted. A few were happy enough to escape and pass the barrier of
                    rocky mountains, and thus for a time were secure; and a few were received into
                    boats or vessels on the coast, and thus were rescued from immediate destruction.
                    The greater number, especially the younger women and boys, were made objects of
                    plunder by the volunteers; they were mingled together as indiscriminately as a
                    flock of sheep, were driven into the ships, and were thus transported to the
                    capital, where they were exposed to sale like cattle, and a very few were
                    redeemed by their friends, who, privately, it being unlawful for a Greek to buy
                    a Greek, purchased them through Turkish agents.</p>
                <p>Those who had delivered themselves up to the Capitan Pasha were removed to a
                    solitary prison, and there, in spite of Lord Strangford’s intercession, were,
                    after he had thought their lives secure, all decapitated. Even the Sciotes in
                    Constantinople were not spared, but in a short time were plundered and put to
                    death. The English ambassador exerted himself in the cause of humanity, but no
                    diplomatic personage of the other states of Europe interfered in behalf of these
                    wretched sufferers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
