<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0685-0631-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAMARITANS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 631</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109953">Scythians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=685" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAMARITANS</label>. The Samaritans are the people of the city
                    of Samaria, and the inhabitants of the province of which Samaria was the capital
                    city. In this sense, it should seem that we might give the name of Samaritans to
                    the Israelites of the ten tribes, who lived in the city and territory of
                    Samaria. However, the sacred authors commonly apply the name of Samaritans only
                    to those strange people whom the kings of Assyria sent from beyond the Euphrates
                    to inhabit the kingdom of Samaria, when they took captive the Israelites that
                    were there before. Thus we may fix the epoch of the Samaritans at the taking of
                    Samaria by Salmaneser, in the year of the world 3283. This prince carried away
                    captive the Israelites that he found in the country, and assigned them dwellings
                    beyond the Euphrates, and in Assyria. He sent other inhabitants in their stead,
                    of which the most considerable were the Cuthites, a people descended from Cush,
                    and who are probably of the number of those whom the ancients knew by the name
                    of Scythians.</p>
                <p>After Salmaneser, his successor Esarhaddon was informed that the people who had
                    been sent to Samaria were infested by lions that devoured them. This he imputed
                    to the ignorance of the people in the manner of worshipping the god of the
                    country. Esarhaddon therefore sent a priest of the God of Israel, that he might
                    teach them the religion of the Hebrews. But they thought they might blend this
                    religion with that which they had previously professed; so they continued to
                    worship their idols as before, in conjunction with the God of Israel, not
                    perceiving how absurd and incompatible these two religions were.</p>
                <p>It is not known how long they continued in this state; but at the return from the
                    captivity of Babylon, it appears they had entirely quitted the worship of their
                    idols; and when they asked permission of the Israelites that they might labour
                    with them at the rebuilding of the temple of Jerusalem, they affirmed, that from
                    the. time when Esarhaddon had brought them into this country they had always
                    worshipped the Lord. And indeed, after the return from the captivity, the
                    Scripture does not anywhere reproach them with idolatrous worship, though it
                    does not dissemble either their jealousy against the Jews, or the ill offices
                    they had done them at the court of Persia by their slanders and calumnies, or
                    the stratagems they contrived to hinder the repairing of the walls of
                    Jerusalem.</p>
                <p>It does not appear that there was any temple in Samaria, in common to all these
                    people who came thither from beyond the Euphrates, before the arrival of
                    Alexander the Great into Judaea. Before that time, every one was left to his own
                    discretion, and worshipped the Lord wherever he thought fit. But they presently
                    comprehended, from the books of Moses which they had in their hands, and from
                    the example of the Jews their neighbours, that God was to be worshipped in that
                    place only which he had chosen; so that since they could not go to the temple of
                    Jerusalem, which the Jews would not allow of, they bethought themselves of
                    building a temple of their own upon Mount Gerizim, near the city of Shechem,
                    which was then their capital. Sanballat, governor of the Samaritans, therefore
                    applied himself to Alexander, and told him he had a son-in-law, called Manasses,
                    son of Jaddus the high priest of the Jews, who had retired to Samaria with a
                    great number of other persons of his own nation; that he desired to build a
                    temple in this province, where he might exercise the high priesthood; and that
                    this undertaking would be to the advantage of the king’s affairs, because in
                    building a temple in the province of Samaria, the nation of the Jews would be
                    divided, who are a turbulent and seditious people, and by such a division would
                    be made weaker, and less in a condition to undertake new enterprises. Alexander
                    readily consented to what Sanballat desired, and the Samaritans presently began
                    building the temple of Gerizim, which from that time they have always
                    frequented, and still frequent to this day, as the place where the Lord intended
                    to receive the adoration of his people. It is of this mountain and of this
                    temple that the Samaritan woman of Sychar spoke to our Saviour.</p>
                <p>But the Samaritans did not long continue under the obedience of Alexander. They
                    revolted from him the very next year, and Alexander drove them out of Samaria,
                    put Macedonians in their place, and gave the province of Samaria to the Jews.
                    This preference which Alexander gave to the Israelites contributed not a little
                    to increase that hatred and animosity that had already obtained between these
                    two people. When any Israelite had deserved punishment for the violation of some
                    important point of the law, he presently took refuge in Samaria or Shechem, and
                    embraced the method of worship according to the temple of Gerizim. When the Jews
                    were in a prosperous condition, and affairs were favourable to them, the
                    Samaritans did not fail to call themselves Hebrews, and pretended to be of the
                    race of Abraham. But no sooner were the Jews fallen into discredit or
                    persecution, than the Samaritans immediately disowned them, would have nothing
                    in common with them, and acknowledged themselves to have been originally
                    Phoenicians, or that they were descended from Joseph and Manassch his son. This
                    was their practice in the time of Antiochus Epiphanes.</p>
                <p>The Samaritans, having received the Pentateuch, or the five books of Moses, from
                    the priest that was sent by Esarhaddon, continued to preserve it in the old
                    Hebrew or Phoenician character, which we now call the Samaritan, to distinguish
                    it from the modern Hebrew character, which we find in the books of the Jews.
                    These last, after their captivity, changed their old characters, and took up
                    those of the Chaldaic, which they had been used to at Babylon, and which they
                    continue still to use. It is wrong, says Calmet, to give this the name of the
                    Hebrew character, for that can be said properly to belong to the Samaritan text.
                    The critics have taken notice of some variations between the Pentateuch of the
                    Jews and that of the Samaritans; but these varieties of reading chiefly regard
                    the word Gerizim, which the Samaritans seem to have purposely introduced to
                    favour their pretensions that Mount Gerizim was the place in which the Lord was
                    to be adored. The other various readings are of little importance.</p>
                <p>As to their belief, it is objected to them, that they receive only the
                    Pentateuch, and reject all the other books of Scripture, chiefly the prophets,
                    who have more expressly declared the coming of the Messiah. They have also been
                    ac-<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=686"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0686-0632"/> cused of believing God to be corporeal, and of
                    denying the Holy Ghost, and the resurrection of the dead.</p>
                <p>Joseph Scaliger, with the view of informing himself respecting their usages and
                    opinions, wrote to the Samaritans of Egypt, and to the high priest of the whole
                    sect, who resided at Neapolis in Syria. They returned two answers to Scaliger,
                    dated in the year of the Hejira 998. These were preserved in the French king’s
                    library, translated into Latin by Father Morin, and printed in England in the
                    collection of that father’s letters, in 1682, under the title of <hi
                    rend="italic">Antiquitates Ecclesiae Orientalis.</hi></p>
                <p>There are still some Samaritans at Shechem, which is otherwise called Naplous;
                    and they have priests there, who say they are of the family of Aaron. They have
                    a high priest, who resides at Shechem, or at Gerizim, who offers sacrifices
                    there, and who declares the feast of the passover, and all the other feasts, to
                    all the dispersed Samaritans. Some of them are to be found at Gaza, others at
                    Damascus, and others at Grand Cairo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
