<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0711-0657-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SAUSSURE, Horace Benedict de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 657</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1034543">Naturalists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1095153">Research</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827573">Bark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96096v">Bark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=711" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">SAUSSURE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Horace Benedict
                    de</hi></label>, a celebrated naturalist, was a native of Geneva, and born in
                    the year 1740. His father was an intelligent farmer, who lived at Conches, about
                    half a league from Geneva, which no doubt contributed, in addition to his active
                    education, to increase the physical strength of young Saussure, so requisite for
                    a naturalist who intends to travel. He went daily to town for public
                    instruction; and as he lived at the foot of a mountain, he frequently amused
                    himself in ascending its steep and rugged sides. Thus environed by the phenomena
                    of nature, and assisted by study, it was to be expected that he would soon
                    conceive a predilection for natural history. Botany was his most early and
                    favourite study, a taste which was powerfully encouraged by his local situation,
                    and was the means of introducing him to the acquaintance of the great Haller, to
                    whom he paid a visit in 1764, and who was astonished at his intimate
                    acquaintance with every branch of the natural sciences.</p>
                <p>His attachment to the study of the vegetable kingdom was also increased by his
                    connection with Bonnet, who had married his aunt, and who put a proper estimate
                    on the talents of his nephew. He was at that time engaged in the examination of
                    the leaves of plants, to which Saussure was also induced to turn his attention,
                    and published the result of his researches under the title of Observations on
                    the Bark of Leaves. About this time the philosophical chair at Geneva became
                    vacant, and was given to Saussure at the age of twenty-one. Rewards conferred so
                    early have been thought to extinguish in some a zeal for the increase of
                    knowledge; but this was not the case with De Saussure, who taught physics and
                    logic alternately with equal success. For physics, however, he had the greatest
                    taste, as affording the means of prosecuting the study of chemistry, mineralogy,
                    and other kindred sciences.</p>
                <p>He now began his travels through the mountains, not for the purpose of studying,
                    as formerly, their flowery decorations, but their constituent parts, and the
                    disposition of their masses. During the first fifteen years of his
                    professorship, he was alternately engaged in discharging the duties of his
                    office, and in traversing the mountains in the vicinity of Geneva; and in this
                    period his talents as a great philosopher were fully displayed. He extended his
                    researches on one side to the banks of the Rhine, and on the other to the
                    country of Piedmont. He travelled to Auvergne to examine the extinguished
                    volcanoes, going afterwards to Paris, England, Holland, Italy, and Sicily. It is
                    proper to remark, that these were not mere journeys, but were undertaken purely
                    with the view of studying nature; and in all his journeys he was surrounded with
                    such instruments as would be of service to him, together with plans previously
                    arranged of his whole procedure.</p>
                <p>The first volume of his travels through the Alps, which was published in 1779,
                    contains a circumstantial description of the environs of Geneva, and an
                    excursion as far as Chamouni, a village at the foot of Mont Blanc. It contains a
                    description of his <hi rend="italic">magnetometer.</hi> In proportion as he
                    examined the mountains, the more was he persuaded of the importance of
                    mineralogy; and that he might study it with advantage, he acquired a knowledge
                    of the German language. In the last volumes of his travels, the reader will
                    perceive how much new mineralogical knowledge he had acquired.</p>
                <p>During the troubles which agitated Geneva in 1782, he made his beautiful and
                    interesting experiments on hygrometry, which he published in 1783. This has been
                    pronounced the best work that ever came from his pen, and completely established
                    his reputation as a philosopher. De Saussure resigned his chair to his pupil and
                    fellow-labourer, Pictet, who discharged the duties of his office with
                    reputation, although rendered difficult to him by succeeding so great a man. He
                    projected a plan of reform in the education of Geneva, the design of which was
                    to make young people acquainted with the natural sciences and mathematics at an
                    early period; and wished that their physical education should not be neglected,
                    for which purpose he proposed gymnastic exercises. This plan found admirers in
                    the city, but the poverty of its funds was an obstacle in the way of any
                    important innovation. It was dreaded, too, that if established forms were
                    changed, they might be altered for the worse.</p>
                <p>The attention of De Saussure was not wholly confined to public education, for he
                    superintended the education of his own two sons and a daughter, who have since
                    proved themselves worthy of such a father and preceptor. In 1786, he published
                    his second volume of travels, containing a description of the Alps around Mont
                    Blanc, the whole having been examined with the eye of a mineralogist, geologist,
                    and philosopher. It contains some valuable experiments on electricity, and a
                    description of his own electrometer, said to be the most perfect we have. To him
                    we are indebted for his <hi rend="italic">cyanometer,</hi> for measuring the
                    degree of blueness of the heavens, which is found to vary according to the
                    height of the observer; his <hi rend="italic">diaphanometer,</hi> for measuring
                    the transparency of the atmosphere; and his <hi rend="italic">anemometer,</hi>
                    for ascertaining the force of the winds. He founded the Society of Arts, to the
                    operations of which Geneva is indebted for the state of prosperity which it has
                    reached within the last thirty years. Over that society he presided to the day
                    of his death; and the preservation of it in prosperity constituted one of his
                    fondest wishes.</p>
                <p>In 1794, the health of this eminent man began rapidly to decline, and a severe
                    stroke of the palsy almost deprived him of the use of his limbs. Such a
                    condition was no doubt painful; but his intellects still preserved their
                    original activity, and he prepared for the press the last two volumes of his
                    travels, which appeared in 1796. They contain a great mass of new facts and
                    observations, of the last importance to physical science. During his illness he
                    published Observations on the Fusibility of Stones by means of the Blow-pipe. He
                    was in general a Neptunian, ascribing the revolutions of our globe to water, and
                    admitting the possibility of mountains having been thrown up by elastic fluids
                    disengaged from the cavities of the earth. <hi rend="smallcaps">Id</hi> the
                    midst of his rapid decline he cherished the hopes of re<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=712" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0712-0658"/>
                    covery; but his strength was exhausted. A languor succeeded the vigour which he
                    had formerly enjoyed; his slow pronunciation did not correspond with the
                    vivacity of his mind, and formed a melancholy contrast to the pleasantness which
                    he had formerly exhibited. He tried in vain to procure the re-establishment of
                    his health; for all the remedies prescribed by the ablest physicians were wholly
                    ineffectual. His mind afterwards lost its activity; and on the 22d of March
                    1799, he finished his mortal career, in the fifty-ninth year of his age,
                    lamented by a family to whom he was dear, by a country to which he had done
                    great honour, and by Europe, the knowledge of which he had extended.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
