<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0678-0624-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">SALT</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 624</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term><term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term><term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dq72">Salt</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term><term n="35" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6487x">Liquors</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="35" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104215">Salt</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104337">Salts</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:999743">Liquors</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=678" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">SALT</label>, one of the great divisions of natural bodies.
                    The characteristic marks of salt have usually been reckoned its power of
                    affecting the organs of taste, and its being soluble in water. But this will not
                    distinguish salt from quicklime, which also affects the sense of taste, and
                    dissolves in water; yet quicklime has been universally reckoned an earth, and
                    not a salt. The only distinguishing property of salts, therefore, is their
                    crystallization in water. But this does not belong to all salts; for the nitrous
                    and marine acids, though allowed on all hands to be salts, are yet incapable of
                    crystallization, at least by any method hitherto known. Several <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the imperfect neutral salts, such as combinations of the
                    nitrous, muriatic, and vegetable acids, with some kinds of earths, also
                    crystallize with very great difficulty. However, by the addition of spirit of
                    wine, or some other substances which absorb part of the water, and keeping the
                    liquor in a warm place, all of them may be reduced to crystals of one kind or
                    other. Salt, therefore, may be defined a substance affecting the organs of
                    taste, soluble in water, and capable of crystallization, either by itself or in
                    conjunction with some other body; and, universally, every salt capable of being
                    reduced into a solid form is also capable of crystallization <hi rend="italic">per se.</hi> Thus the class of saline bodies will be sufficiently distinguished
                    from all others; for quicklime, though soluble in water, cannot be crystallized
                    without addition either of fixed air or of some other acid; yet it is most
                    commonly found in a solid state. The precious stones, though supposed to be
                    formed by crystallization, are nevertheless distinguished from salts by their
                    insipidity and insolubility in water.</p><p>But acids and alkalis, and combinations of both, when in a concrete form, are
                    salts, and of the purest form. Hence we conclude, that the bodies to which the
                    name of salts more properly belongs are the concretions of those substances,
                    which are accordingly called acid salts, alkaline salts, and neutral salts.
                    These last are combinations of acid and alkaline salts, in such proportion as to
                    render the compounds neither sour nor alkaline to the taste. This proportional
                    combination is called saturation. Thus common kitchen salt is a neutral salt,
                    composed of muriatic acid and soda combined together to the point of saturation.
                    The appellation of neutral salts is also extended to denote all those
                    combinations of acids, and any other substance with which they can unite, so as
                    to lose, wholly or in a great measure, their acid properties.</p><p>But although this general definition of salts is commonly received, yet there are
                    many writers, especially mineralogists, who confine the denomination of salts in
                    the manner we first mentioned, viz. to those substances only which, besides the
                    general properties of salts, have the power of crystallizing, that is, of
                    arranging their particles so as to form regularly-shaped bodies, called
                    crystals, when the water superfluous to their concrete existence has been
                    evaporated.</p><p><hi rend="italic">common</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Salt,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sea-Salt,</hi> the name of that salt extracted from the waters of
                    the ocean, which is used in greater quantities for preserving provisions, and
                    other domestic purposes.</p><p>It is a perfect neutral salt, composed of marine or muriatic acid, saturated with
                    mineral alkali. It has a saline but agreeable flavour. It requires about four
                    times its weight of cold water to be dissolved, and nearly the same quantity of
                    boiling water, according to Macquer; but according to Kirwan, it only’ requires
                    2·5 its weight of water to be dissolved in the temperature of sixty degrees of
                    Fahrenheit. This salt always contains some part formed with a calcareous base;
                    and, in order to have it pure, it must be dissolved in distilled water. Then a
                    solution of mineral alkali is to be poured into it until no white precipitation
                    appears; and by filtrating and evaporating the solution, a pure common salt is
                    produced. Its figure is perfectly cubic, and those hollow pyramids, as well as
                    the parallelopipeds formed sometimes in its crystallization, consist all of a
                    quantity of small cubes, disposed in those forms. Its decrepitation on the fire,
                    which has been reckoned by some as a characteristic of this salt, although the
                    vitriolated tartar, nitrous lead, and other salts, have the same property, is
                    owing chiefly to the water, and perhaps also to the air of its
                    crystallization.</p><p>Its specific gravity is 2·120 according to Kirwan. The acid of tartar
                    precipitates nothing from it. One hundred parts of common salt contain
                    thirty-three of real acid, fifty of mineral alkali, and seventeen of water. It
                    is commonly found in salt water and salt springs, in the proportion of even
                    thirty-six per cent. It is found also in coals, and in beds of gypsum. This salt
                    is unalterable by fire, though it fuses and becomes more opaque. Nevertheless a
                    violent fire, with the free access of air, causes it to evaporate in white
                    flowers, which adhere to the neighbouring bodies. It is only decomposed, as
                    Macquer affirms, by the sulphuric and nitric acids, and also by the boracic or
                    sedative salt. But although nitre is very easily decomposed by arsenic, this
                    neutral marine salt is nowise decomposed by it. According to Monge, the fixed
                    vegetable alkali, when caustic, decomposes all this marine salt. It preserves
                    from corruption almost all sorts of animal food much better for use than any
                    other salt, as it does so without destroying their taste and qualities; but when
                    applied in too small a quantity, it then promotes putrefaction.</p><p>Of this most useful commodity there are ample stores on land as well as in the
                    ocean. There are few countries indeed which do not afford vast quantities of
                    rock or fossil salt. Mines of it have long been discovered and wrought in
                    England, Spain, Italy, Germany, Hungary, Poland, and other countries of Europe.
                    In several parts of the world there are huge mountains which wholly consist of
                    fossil salt. Of this kind are two mountains in Russia, near Astracan; several in
                    the kingdoms of Tunis and Algiers, in Africa; some also in Asia; and the whole
                    island of Ormus, in the<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=679" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0679-0625"/>
                    Persian Gulf, almost entirely consists of fossil salt. The new world is likewise
                    stored with treasures of this useful mineral, as well as with all other kinds of
                    subterranean productions. Moreover, the sea affords such abundance of common
                    salt, that all mankind might thence be supplied with quantities sufficient for
                    their occasions. There are also innumerable springs, ponds, lakes, and rivers,
                    impregnated with common salt, from which the inhabitants of many countries are
                    plentifully supplied. In some countries which are remote from the sea, and have
                    little commerce, and which are not blessed with mines of salt or salt-waters,
                    the necessities of the inhabitants have forced them to invent a method of
                    extracting common salt from the ashes of vegetables. The muriatic salt of
                    vegetables was described by Dr Grew under the title of lixiviated marine salt.
                    Lecuwenhoeck obtained cubical crystals of this salt from a lixivium of soda or
                    kelp, and also from a solution of the lixivial salt of <hi rend="italic">carduus
                    benedictus;</hi> of which he gave an account in a letter to the Royal Society,
                    published in their Transactions.</p><p>The muriatic salt which Mr Boyle extracted from san-diver, and supposed to be
                    produced from the materials used in making glass, was doubtless separated from
                    the kelp made use of in that process. Kunckel also informs us, that he took an
                    alkaline salt, and after calcining it with a moderate fire, dissolved it in pure
                    water, and placing the solution in a cool cellar, obtained from it many crystals
                    of a neutral salt. He supposes that the alkaline salt was by the process
                    converted into this neutral salt. But it is more reasonable to believe that the
                    alkaline salt which he applied was not pure, but mixed with the muriatic salt of
                    vegetables, which by this process was only separated from it.</p><p>Naturalists, observing the great variety of forms under which this salt appears,
                    have thought fit to rank the several kinds of it under certain general classes;
                    distinguishing it most usually into rock or fossil salt, sea-salt, and brine or
                    fountain salt. To these classes others might be added, particularly those
                    muriatic salts which are found in vegetable and animal substances. These several
                    kinds of common salt often differ from each other in their outward form and
                    appearance, or in such accidental properties as they derive from the
                    heterogeneous substances with which they are mixed. But when perfectly pure,
                    they have all the same qualities; so that chemists have not been able to
                    discover any essential difference between them. For this reason we shall
                    distinguish common salt after a different manner, into the three following
                    kinds, viz. into rock or native salt, bay-salt, and white salt. By <hi rend="italic">rock</hi> or <hi rend="italic">native salt</hi> is understood all
                    salt dug out of the earth, which has not undergone any artificial preparation.
                    Under the title of <hi rend="italic">bay-salt</hi> may be ranked all kinds of
                    common salt extracted from the water in which it is dissolved, by means of the
                    sun’s heat, and the operation of the air, whether the water from which it is
                    extracted be sea-water or natural brine drawn from wells and springs, or salt
                    water stagnating in ponds and lakes. Under the title of <hi rend="italic">white</hi> or <hi rend="italic">boiled salt</hi> may be included all kinds of
                    common salt extracted by coction from the water in which it is dissolved.</p><p>The first of these kinds of salt is, in several countries, found so pure that it
                    serves for most domestic uses, without any previous preparation, triture
                    excepted; for, of all natural salts, rock-salt is the most abundantly furnished
                    by nature in various parts of the world, being found in large masses occupying
                    vast tracts of land.</p><p>The English fossil salt is unfit for the uses of the kitchen, until by solution
                    and coction it is freed from several impurities, and reduced into white salt.
                    The British white salt also is not so proper as several kinds of bay-salt for
                    curing fish and such meats as are intended for nautical provisions, or for
                    exportation into hot countries. For these purposes, therefore, we are obliged,
                    either wholly or in part, to use bay-salt, which is purchased in France, Spain,
                    and other foreign countries.</p><p>However, it does not appear that there is any other thing requisite in the
                    formation of bay-salt than to evaporate the sea-water with an exceedingly gentle
                    heat; and it is even very probable, that our common sea-salt, by a second
                    solution and crystallization, might attain the requisite degree of purity.
                    Without entering into any particular detail of the processes used for the
                    preparation of bay-salt in different parts of the world, we shall content
                    ourselves with giving a brief account of the best methods of preparing common
                    salt.</p><p>At some convenient place near the sea-shore is erected the saltern. This is a
                    long, low building, consisting of two parts; one of which is called the
                    fore-house, and the other the pan-house or boiling-house. The fore-house serves
                    to receive the fuel and cover the workmen, and in the boiling-house are placed
                    the furnace, and pan in which the salt is made. Sometimes they have two pans,
                    one at each end of the saltern; and the part appropriated for the fuel and
                    workmen is in the middle.</p><p>The furnace opens into the fore-house by two mouths, beneath each of which is a
                    mouth to the ash-pits. To the mouths of the furnace, doors are fitted; and over
                    them a wall is carried up to the roof, which divides the fore-house from the
                    boiling-house, and prevents the dust of the coal and the ashes and smoke of the
                    furnace from falling into the salt-pan. The fore-house communicates with the
                    boiling-house by a door placed in the wall which divides them.</p><p>The body of the furnace consists of two chambers, divided from each other by a
                    brick partition called the midfeather, which from a broad base terminates in a
                    narrow edge near the top of the furnace, and, by means of short pillars of cast
                    iron erected upon it, supports the bottom of the salt-pan. It also fills up a
                    considerable part of the furnace, which otherwise would be too large, and would
                    consume more coals than, by the help of this contrivance, are required. To each
                    chamber of the furnace is fitted a grate, through which the ashes fall into the
                    ash-pits. The grates arc made of long bars of iron, supported underneath by
                    strong cross bars of the same metal. They are not continued to the farthest part
                    of the furnace, it being unnecessary to throw in the fuel so far. For the flame
                    is driven from the fire on the grate to the farthest part of the furnace, and
                    thence passes, together with the smoke, through two flues into the chimney; and
                    thus the bottom of the saltpan is everywhere equally heated.</p><p>The salt-pans are made of an oblong form, flat at the bottom, with the sides
                    erected at right angles. The length of some of these pans is fifteen feet, the
                    breadth twelve feet, and the depth sixteen inches; but at different works they
                    are of different dimensions. They are commonly made of plates of iron, joined
                    together with nails, and the joints are tilled with a strong cement. Within the
                    pan five or six strong beams of iron are fixed to its opposite sides, at equal
                    distances, parallel to each other and to the bottom of the pan, from which they
                    are distant about eight inches. From the beams hang down strong iron hooks,
                    which are linked to other hooks or clasps of iron firmly nailed to the bottom of
                    the pan; and thus the bottom of the pan is supported, and prevented from bending
                    down or changing its figure. The plates most commonly used are of malleable
                    iron, about four feet and a half long, a foot broad, and the third of an inch in
                    thickness. The Scotch commonly prefer smaller plates fourteen or fifteen inches
                    square. Several make the sides of the pan, where they are not exposed to the
                    fire, of lead; those parts, when made of iron, being found to consume fast in
                    rust from the steam of the pan. Some have used plates of cast iron five or six
                    feet square, and an inch in thickness; but they are very subject to break when
                    unequally heated, and shaken, as they frequently are, by the violent boiling of
                    the liquor. The cement most commonly used to fill the joints is plaster made of
                    lime.<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=680" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0680-0626"/> The pan, thus formed, is placed over the furnace,
                    being supported at the four corners by brick-work, but along the middle, and at
                    the sides and ends, by round pillars of cast iron called taplins, which are
                    placed at three feet distance from each other, being about eight inches in
                    height, and at the top, where smallest, four inches in diameter. By means of
                    these pillars the heat of the fire penetrates equally to all parts of the bottom
                    of the pan, its four corners only excepted. Care is also taken to prevent the
                    smoke of the furnace from passing into the boiling-house, by bricks and strong
                    cement, which are closely applied to every part of the salt-pan. In some places,
                    besides the common saltpans here described, they have a preparing pan placed
                    between two salt-pans, in the middle part of the building, which in other works
                    is the fore-house. The sea-water being received into this preparing pan, is
                    there heated and in part evaporated by the flame and heat conveyed under it
                    through flues from the two furnaces of the salt-pans. And the hot water, as
                    occasion requires, is conveyed through troughs from the preparing pan into the
                    salt-pans. Various other contrivances have been invented to lessen the expense
                    of fuel, and several patents have been obtained for that purpose; but the
                    salt-boilers have found the old methods the most convenient.</p><p>Between the sides of the pan and walls of the boiling-house there runs a walk
                    five or six feet broad, where the workmen stand when they draw the salt, or have
                    any other business in the boiling-house. The same walk is continued at the end
                    of the pan, next to the chimney; but the pan is placed close to the wall at the
                    end adjoining to the forehouse.</p><p>The roof of the boiling-house is covered with boards fastened with nails of wood,
                    iron nails quickly mouldering into rust. In the roofs are several openings, to
                    convey off the watery vapours; and on each side of it a window or two, which the
                    workmen open when they look into the pan whilst it is boiling.</p><p>Not far distant from the saltern, on the sea-shore, between full sea and
                    low-water marks, they also make a little pond in the rocks, or with stones on
                    the sand, which they call their <hi rend="italic">sump.</hi> From this pond they
                    lay a pipe, through which, when the tide is in, the sea-water runs into a well
                    adjoining to the saltern; and from this well it is pumped into troughs, by which
                    it is conveyed into the ship or cistern, where it is stored up until they have
                    occasion to use it.</p><p>The cistern is built close to the saltern, and may be placed most conveniently
                    between the two boiling-houses, on the back of the fore-house; it is made either
                    of wood or of brick and clay. It sometimes wants a cover, but ought to be
                    covered with a shed, that the salt water contained therein may not be weakened
                    by rains, nor mixed with soot and other impurities. It should be placed so high
                    that the water may conveniently run out of it, through a trough, into the
                    salt-pans.</p><p>Besides the buildings already mentioned, several others are required; as
                    storehouses for the salt, cisterns for the bittern, an office for his majesty’s
                    salt-officers, and a dwelling-house for the salt-boilers.</p><p>All things being thus prepared, and the sea-water having stood in the cistern
                    till the mud and the sand are settled to the bottom, it is drawn off into the
                    salt-pan. And at the four corners of the salt-pan, where the flame does not
                    touch its bottom, are placed four small lead pans, called scratch-pans, which,
                    for a salt-pan of the size above mentioned, are usually about a foot and a half
                    long, a foot broad, and three inches deep, and have a bow or circular handle of
                    iron, by which they may be drawn out with a hook when the liquor in the pan is
                    boiling.</p><p>The salt-pan being filled with sea-water, a strong fire of pit-coal is lighted in
                    the furnace; and then, for a pan which contains about four hundred gallons, the
                    salt-boiler takes the whites of three eggs, and incorporates them well with two
                    or three gallons of sea-water, which he pours into the salt-pan whilst the water
                    contained therein is only lukewarm, and immediately stirs it about with a rake,
                    that the whites of the eggs may everywhere be equally mixed with the salt
                    water.</p><p>Instead of whites of eggs, at many salterns, as at most of those near Newcastle,
                    they use blood from the butchers, either of sheep or black cattle, to clarify
                    the sea-water; and at many of the Scotch salterns they do not give themselves
                    the trouble of clarifying it. As the water grows hot, the whites of eggs
                    separate from it a black frothy scum, which rises to the surface of the water,
                    and covers it all over. As soon as the pan begins to boil, this scum is all
                    risen, and it is then time to skim it off.</p><p>The most convenient instruments for this purpose are skimmers of thin ash boards,
                    six or eight inches broad, and so long that they may reach above half way over
                    the saltpan. These skimmers have handles fitted to them; and the salt-boiler and
                    his assistant, each holding one of them on the opposite sides of the pan, apply
                    them so to each other that they overlap in the middle, and beginning at one end
                    of the pan, carry them gently forward together, along the surface of the boiling
                    liquor, to the other end; and thus, without breaking the scum, they collect it
                    all to one end of the pan, whence they easily take it out.</p><p>After the water is skimmed, it appears perfectly clear and transparent; and they
                    continue boiling it briskly till so much of the fresh or aqueous part is
                    evaporated, that what remains in the pan is a strong brine almost fully
                    saturated with salt, so that small saline crystals begin to form on its surface;
                    and this operation, in a pan filled fifteen inches deep with water, is usually
                    performed in five hours.</p><p>The pan is then filled up a second time with clear seawater drawn from the
                    cistern; and about the time when it is half filled, the scratch-pans are taken
                    out, and being emptied of the scratch found in them, are again placed in the
                    corners of the salt-pan. The scratch taken out of these pans is a fine white
                    calcareous earth found in the form of powder, which separates from the sea-water
                    during its coction, before the salt begins to form into grains. This subtile
                    powder is violently agitated by the boiling liquor, until it is driven to the
                    corners of the pan, where the motion of the liquor being more gentle, it
                    subsides into the scratch-pans placed there to receive it; in them it remains
                    undisturbed, and thus the greatest part of it is separated from the brine.</p><p>After the pan has again been filled up with sea-water, three w hites of eggs are
                    mixed with the liquor, by which it is clarified a second time, in the manner
                    before described; and it is afterwards boiled down to a strong brine as at
                    first, which second boiling may take up about four hours. The pan is then filled
                    up a third time with clear sea-water; and after that a fourth time, the liquor
                    being each time clarified and boiled down to a strong brine, as before related,
                    and the scratch-pans being taken out and emptied every time that the pan is
                    filled up. Then, at the fourth boiling, as soon as the crystals begin to form on
                    the surface of the brine, they slacken the fire, and only suffer the brine to
                    simmer, or boil very gently. In this heat they constantly endeavour to keep it
                    all the time that the salt corns or granulates, which may be nine or ten hours.
                    The salt is said to granulate when its minute crystals cohere together into
                    little masses or gains, which sink down in the brine, and lie at the bottom of
                    the salt-pan.</p><p>When most of the liquor is evaporated, and the salt thus lies in the pan almost
                    dry on its surface, it is then time to draw it out. This part of the process is
                    performed by raking the salt to one side of the pan into a long heap, where it
                    drains a while from the brine, and is then filled out into barrows or other
                    proper vessels, and carried into the store<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.28490931&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=681" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0681-0627"/>
                    house, and delivered into the custody of his majesty’s officers. And in this
                    manner the whole process is performed in twenty-four hours, the salt being
                    usually drawn every morning.</p><p>In the storehouse the salt is put hot into drabs, which are partitions like
                    stalls for horses, lined on three sides and at the bottom with boards, and
                    having a sliding-board on the foreside to put in or draw out as occasion
                    requires. The bottoms are made shelving, being highest behind, and gradually
                    inclining forwards, by which means the saline liquor, which remains mixed with
                    the salt, easily drains from it; and the salt, in three or four days, becomes
                    sufficiently dry, and is then taken out of the drabs, and laid up in large
                    heaps, where it is ready for sale.</p><p>The saline liquor which drains from the salt is not a pure brine of common salt,
                    but has a sharp and bitter taste, and is therefore called bittern. This liquor,
                    at some works, is saved for particular uses, and at others is thrown away. A
                    considerable quantity of this bittern is left at the bottom of the pan after the
                    process is finished; and as it contains much salt, it is suffered to remain in
                    the pan when it is filled up with sea-water. But at each process this liquor
                    becomes sharper and more bitter, and also increases in quantity. Thus, after the
                    third or fourth process is finished, they are obliged to take it out of the pan,
                    otherwise it mixes in such quantities with the salt as to give it a bitter
                    taste, disposes it to grow soft and run in the open air, and renders it unfit
                    for domestic uses.</p><p>After each process there also adheres to the bottom and sides of the pan a white
                    stony crust, of the same calcareous substance with that before collected from
                    the boiling liquor. This the operators call stone-scratch, distinguishing the
                    other found in the lead pans by the name of powder-scratch. Once in eight or ten
                    days they separate the stone-scratch from their pans with iron picks, and in
                    several places find it a quarter of an inch in thickness. If this stony crust be
                    suffered to adhere to the pan much longer, it grows so thick that the pan is
                    burned by the fire, and quickly wears away.</p><p>The consumption of salt in this country is immense. Neckar estimated the
                    consumption, in those provinces of France which had purchased an exemption from
                    the <hi rend="italic">gabelle,</hi> at 19 ½ lbs. English for each individual.
                    But we believe that the people in this country may be estimated a little higher,
                    or at <hi rend="italic">22</hi> lbs.; and, on this supposition, taking the
                    population at 16,500,000, the entire consumption will amount to 363,000,000 lbs.
                    or 161,000 tons. Exclusively of this immense home consumption, we annually
                    export about 10,000,000 bushels, which, at 56 lbs. a bushel, are equivalent to
                    250,000 tons. The cheapness of this important necessary of life is therefore not
                    less remarkable than its diffusion.</p><p>In this country duties upon salt were imposed in the reign of William III. In the
                    year 1798, they amounted to five shillings a bushel, but were subsequently
                    increased to fifteen shillings, or about forty times the cost of the salt. So
                    exorbitant a duty was productive of the worst effects, and by its magnitude, as
                    well as by the regulations allowing salt duty-free to the fisheries, occasioned
                    a great deal of smuggling. For this reason, the opinion of the public and the
                    House of Commons having been strongly expressed against the tax, it was finally
                    repealed in the year 1823. (M'Culloch’s Commercial Dictionary, art. <hi rend="italic">Salt.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Salt</hi><hi rend="italic">Springs. Of</hi> these there are great numbers in different parts of the world,
                    which undoubtedly have their origin from some of the large collections of fossil
                    salt mentioned under the article <hi rend="italic">common</hi><hi rend="italic                     smallcaps"> Salt.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Salt,</hi><hi rend="italic">Valley
                    of,</hi> in Syria. It is a lake in winter; but in summer the moisture is
                    evaporated by the heat of the sun, when the salt is left in beds of about half
                    an inch thick, and is afterwards purified for use. It is about eighteen miles to
                    the east of Aleppo.</p></div></body></text></TEI>