<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0090-0079-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KINDERGARTEN (9th edition, volume 14, page 79)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tq9k">Kindergarten</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937529">Games</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987552">Kindergarten</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n90/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KINDERGARTEN</label>, a German word meaning “garden of
                    children,” is the name, given by Friedrich Froebel (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Feoebel)</hi> to a kind of “play-school” invented by him for furthering the
                    physical, moral, and intellectual growth of children between the ages of three
                    and seven. Froebel’s observation of the development of organisms and his
                    fondness for analogies drawn from trees and plants made him attach especial
                    importance to our earliest years, years in which, as he said, lies the tap-root
                    of much of the thought and feeling of after life. Although the analogies of
                    nature had constantly been referred to before Froebel’s days (“First the blade,
                    then the ear, then the full corn in ear ”), and Bacon, speaking of education,
                    had said that the gardener bestows the greatest care on the young plants, the
                    Renaissance left the imparting theory of education so firmly fixed on the mind
                    of Europe that for two hundred years the developing theory could hardly get a
                    hearing, and little was done to reduce it to practice before the attempt of
                    Pestalozzi. Pestalozzi and other great thinkers (notably Comenius), who attached
                    much importance to the first years of life, looked to the mother as the sole
                    educator. But in the case of the poor the mother might not have time to attend
                    to her children; so towards the end of the last century Pestalozzi planned and
                    Oberlin formed day-asylums for young children, the benefit of which was intended
                    no less for the mother than the child. Schools of this kind took in the
                    Netherlands the name of “play school,” and in England, where they have
                    especially thriven, of “infant schools.” But Froebel’s idea of the
                    “Kindergarten” differed essentially from that of the infant schools. He
                    maintained that there was something to do for young children which even the
                    ideal mother in the ideal family could not do. The child required to be prepared
                    for society by being early associated with its equals; and young children thus
                    brought together might have their employments, especially their chief
                    employment, play, so organized for them as to draw out their capacities <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n91/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0091-0080"/> of feeling and thinking, and even of inventing
                    and creating.</p>
                <p>According to the development theory all education must be based on study of the
                    nature to be developed. Froebel’s study of the nature of children showed him
                    that their great characteristic was restlessness. This was, first, restlessness
                    of body, delight in mere motion of the limbs; and, secondly, restlessness of
                    mind, a constant curiosity about whatever came within the range of the senses,
                    and especially a desire to examine with the hand every unknown object within
                    reach. Children’s fondness for using their hands was specially noted by Froebel,
                    and he found that they delighted, not merely in examining by touch, but also in
                    altering whatever they could alter, and further that they endeavoured to imitate
                    known forms whether by drawing or by modelling in putty or clay. Besides
                    remarking in them these various activities, he saw that children were sociable
                    and needed the sympathy of companions. There was, too, in them a growing moral
                    nature, passions, affections, and conscience, which needed to be controlled,
                    responded to, cultivated. Both the restraints and the opportunities incident to
                    a well-organized community would be beneficial to their moral nature, and prove
                    a cure for selfishness.</p>
                <p>Froebel held that the essence of all education was to be found in rightly
                    directed but spontaneous action. So the children must be employed; and at that
                    age their most natural employment is play, especially, as Wordsworth has pointed
                    out, games in which they imitate and “con the parts” they themselves will have
                    to fill in after years. Froebel agreed with Montaigne that the games of children
                    were “their most serious occupations,” and with Locke that “all the plays and
                    diversions of children should be directed towards good and useful habits, or
                    else they will introduce ill ones” <hi rend="italic">{Thoughts concerning
                    Education,</hi> § 130). So he invented a course of occupations, most of which
                    are social games. Many of the games are connected with the “gifts,” as he called
                    the series of simple playthings provided for the children, the first being the
                    ball, “the type of unity.” The “gifts” are chiefly not mere playthings but
                    materials which the children work up in their own way, thus gaining scope for
                    their power of doing and inventing and creating. The artistic faculty was much
                    thought of by Froebel, and, as in the education of the ancients, the sense of
                    rhythm in sound and motion was cultivated by music and poetry introduced in the
                    games. Much care was to be given to the training of the senses, especially those
                    of sight, sound, and touch. Intuition or first-hand experience <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Anschauung)</hi> was to be recognized as the true basis of knowledge, and
                    though stories were to be told, and there was to be much intercourse in the way
                    of social chat, instruction of the imparting and “learning-up” kind was to be
                    excluded. Froebel sought to teach the children not what to think but how to
                    think, in this following in the steps of Pestalozzi, who had done for the child
                    what Bacon nearly two hundred years before had done for the philosopher. Where
                    possible the children were to be much in the open air, and were each to
                    cultivate a little garden.</p>
                <p>To judge by. all appearances at the present date (1881), the kindergarten will be
                    an important institution in the education of the future. The first kindergarten
                    was opened at Blankenburg, near Rudolstadt, in 1840, but after a needy existence
                    of eight years was closed for want of funds. In 1851 the Prussian Government
                    declared that “schools founded on Froebel’s principles or principles like them
                    could not be allowed.” But the idea had far too much vitality to be starved or
                    frowned down. Although its progress has not been rapid, it has been constant. As
                    early as 1854 it was introduced into England by the then famous Ronges, and
                    Henry Barnard reported on it that is was ‘ ‘ by far the most original,
                    attractive, and philosophical form of infant development the world has yet seen”
                    <hi rend="italic">(Report to Governor of Connecticut,</hi> 1854). But the
                    attempt failed, and though there are now a Froebel Society, an institution for
                    training young women to conduct kindergartens, and also some good kindergartens,
                    Froebel’s idea has hardly yet found a home in Britain. The great propagandist of
                    Froebelism, the Baroness Marenholtz-Bülow, drew the attention of the French to
                    the kindergarten from the year 1855, and Michelet declared that Froebel had
                    “solved the problem of human education.” In the department of the Seine the
                    “Salles d’asile” now consist of a class for children from two to four years old,
                    and a “Froebel class” of children from four to six. In Italy the kindergarten
                    has been introduced by Madame Salis-Schwabe, and is used in the education of the
                    poor. In Austria it is recognized and regulated by the government, though the
                    Volks-Kindergiirten are not numerous. But by far the greatest developments of
                    the kindergarten system are in the United States and in Belgium. Dr William T.
                    Harris, assisted by Miss Blow, tried the experiment of making the kindergarten a
                    part of the public education in St Louis eight years ago, and there are now no
                    less than 8000 children, all over five years of age, in the St Louis public
                    kindergartens. In Belgium the mistresses of the “Écoles gardiennes” have for
                    some time been instructed in the “idea of the kindergarten” and “Froebel’s
                    method,” and in 1880 the minister of public instruction, Van Humbeeck, issued a
                    programme for the “Écoles Gardiennes Communales,” which is both in fact and in
                    profession a kindergarten manual. This programme attributes the improvement in
                    infant schools to “le souffle puissant de Froebel”; and, after explaining that
                    the method to be adopted is based on the laws which govern the development of
                    the child, the minister continues: “In its great principles as well as in its
                    main applications this method is that created by the genius of Froebel.” This
                    estimate of Froebel’s principles contrasts strangely with the Prussian
                    minister’s thirty years earlier.</p>
                <p>Literature.—Henry Barnard’s volume, Froebel" s Kindergarten, Hartford, U.S.A.,
                    1881, contains a large collection of papers on the subject, original and
                    translated; W. T. Harris's Reports give full accounts of the adaptation of the
                    Kindergarten to public education at St Louis. Kindergartens in Germany are
                    described in Joseph Payne’s Visit to German Schools, 1876. Practical guides
                    published in England are J. and B. Ronge’s, 3d ed., 1855; E. wiebe’s Paradise of
                    Children; and Miss Lyschinska's, 1880. Other literature is cited in Steiger’s
                    Cyclopaedia of Education; and in L. waiter’s Die Fröbelliteratur, 1881. (R, H.
                    Q.) '</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
