<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0085-0074-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KILKENNY (9th edition, volume 14, page 74)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914304">Episcopalians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n85/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KILKENNY</label>, an inland county of Ireland, in the
                    province of Leinster, is situated between 52° 14' and 52° 52' N. lat., and
                    between 6° 56' and 7° 38' W. long. It is bounded on the N. by Queen’s county, E.
                    by Carlow and Wexford, S. by Waterford, and W. by Waterford and Tipperary. Its
                    greatest length from north to south is about 45 miles, and its greatest breadth
                    from east to west about 25 miles. The area is 507,254 acres, or about 793 square
                    miles.</p>
                <p>The greater part of Kilkenny is a continuation forming the south-eastern
                    extremity of the Carboniferous Limestone plain of Ireland, but in the south-east
                    this is bounded partly by the Cambro-Silurian rocks which run into the county
                    from Wexford, and partly by a continuation of the granite mountains of Wicklow
                    and Carlow, and it is interrupted in the north by an extensive hilly region
                    forming part of the Castlecomer coal-field, which extends also into Queen’s
                    county and Tipperary. The field lies in the form of a broad basin, and rests on
                    flagstone and black shale. The coal is anthracite, and the most productive
                    portions of the bed are in the centre of the basin at Castlecomer. Besides a
                    large number of fossil plants, crustaceans of a rare species and also several
                    peculiar reptilian remains have been found in the measures. The field is
                    believed to contain nearly 80,000,000 tons of workable coal, and at present the
                    annual yield is about 80,000 tons,—the annual yield of Ireland being only about
                    130,000 tons. On the granite the limestone has the form of a bedded dolomite,
                    and this is also principally the form of the central division to the north-west
                    of Kilkenny. In other places the limestones are bluish or black, the latter
                    being the best quality for burning, and are often associated with shales of a
                    considerable thickness. Cherty beds frequently occur between the limestone and
                    the Coal-measures. Hematitic iron of a rich quality is found in the
                    Cambro-Silurian rocks at several places. Tradition has it that silver shields
                    were made about 850 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> at Argetros or Silverwood on
                    the Nore, and at Ballygunnion there were very ancient mines associated with the
                    lead. The shelly black marble obtained near the town of Kilkenny has gained wide
                    fame, and is used for tombstones, chimney-pieces, and picture frames. Manganese
                    is obtained in some of the limestone quarries, and also near the Barrow. Marl is
                    abundant in various districts. Pipeclay and potter’s clay are found, and also
                    yellow ochre. Copper occurs near Knocktopher.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rivers.—</hi> The principal rivers, the Suir, the Barrow, and
                    the Nore, have all their origin in the Slieve Bloom mountains, and after a
                    widely divergent course southwards discharge their waters into Waterford
                    Harbour. The Suir forms the boundary of the county with Waterford, and is
                    navigable for sloops to Carrick. The Nore, which is navigable to Innistioge,
                    enters the county at its northwestern boundary, and flows by Kilkenny to the
                    Barrow, 9 miles above Ross, having received in its course the King’s river at
                    Jerpoint and the Argula near Innistioge. The Barrow, which is navigable beyond
                    the limits of Kilkenny into Kildare, forms the eastern boundary of the county
                    from near New Bridge. There are no lakes of any extent, but turloughs are
                    occasionally formed by the bursting up of underground streams.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate and Agriculture.—</hi> On account of the slope of the
                    country and the nature of the soil, the surface occupied by bog or wet land is
                    very small, and the air is dry and very salubrious. So temperate is it in winter
                    that the myrtle and arbutus grow in the open air. There is less rain than at
                    Dublin, and vegetation is earlier than in the adjacent counties. Along the banks
                    of the Suir, Nore, and Barrow a very rich soil has been formed by alluvial
                    deposits. Above the Coal-measures in the northern part of the county there is a
                    moorish tract devoted chiefly to pasturage. The soil above the limestone is for
                    the most part a deep and rich loam admirably adapted for the growth of wheat.
                    The heath-covered hills afford honey with a flavour of peculiar excellence.</p>
                <p>The following table gives a classification of holdings according to size in 1850
                    and in 1880, as contained in the agricultural returns :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>1 Acre.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1 and under 5.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5 and under 15.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>15 and under 30.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>SO and ∣ upwards.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1850</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,932</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,583</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4,109</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3,802</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,206</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>18,632</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1880</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,734</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1,816</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,508</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2,662</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5,325</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>14,045</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The total area under crops in 1881 was 159,304 acres, a percentage of 31 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 4 of the whole acreage of the country. In 1880,
                    293,252 acres, a percentage of 57 ’ 8, were under grass,*2196 fallow, 10,799
                    wood, 10,746 bog, 13,515 mountain, and 21,661 water, roads, aud fences. The area
                    under crops in 1850 was 195,923. The area under cereals declined from 112,220
                    acres in 1850 to 65,232 in 1881, wheat decreasing from 47,343 acres to 11,843,
                    and oats from 52,236 to 35,878, while in other cereals, of which the chief is
                    barley, there has been an increase from 12,641 acres to 17,511. Between 1851 and
                    1880 the area under grass increased by 40,530 acres. Almost nothing has been
                    done to improve the pasturage of the hilly districts, which are still largely
                    covered with heath. The area under meadow and clover, which includes a large
                    portion of rich soil on the banks of the Nore and Suir, increased from 42,482
                    acres in 1850 to 62,079 in 1881. Green crops diminished in area from 41,189
                    acres in 1850 to 31,993 in 1881, potatoes from 26,321 acres to 18,269, and
                    turnips from 11,613 to 9929. Horses since 1850 declined from 17,161 to 16,933.
                    The number in 1881 used for agricultural purposes was 11,606. Mules since 1850
                    have increased from 687 to 1054, and asses from 3355 to 5345. Cattle in 1850
                    numbered 72,998, and in 1881 had increased to 120,594. Cows numbered 37,695, or
                    about a third of the total number of cattle, dairy-farming being largely
                    followed, especially in the hilly districts to the south. The most common
                    species of cattle is a cross between the old Irish breed and the longhorn, but
                    Kerry cows are considerably in demand for dairies. For winter-feeding pounded
                    furze tops are frequently used, but in many cases the cattle graze outside in
                    winter. Sheep, the breed of which has been much improved by crossing, increased
                    from 40,450 in 1850 to 85,393 in 1881. Pigs have declined in numbers from 45,763
                    to 39,777, while goats have increased from 5958 to 6376, and poultry from
                    197,955 to 410,524.</p>
                <p>According to the corrected summary of owners of land, 1878, the land in 1873,
                    exclusive of the county of the city of Kilkenny, was divided among 1150
                    proprietors, of whom 827 possessed less than 1 acre. The annual rateable
                    valuation is stated in the return of 1876 as £340,696, giving an average value
                    of 13s. 9d. per acre. There were forty-seven owners who possessed upwards of
                    2000 acres, twelve who possessed upwards of 5000 acres, and six upwards of
                    10,000 acres, viz., Viscount Clifden, 35,288; Earl of Bessborough, 23,967;
                    Charles Wandesforde, 22,232; Col. W. F. Tighe, 11,970; Marquis of Ormonde,
                    11,960; and Viscount Mountgarret, 11,919.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures.—</hi> The linen manufacture introduced into the
                    county in the 17th century by the duke of Ormonde to supersede the woollen
                    manufacture gradually became extinct, aħd the woollen manufacture now carried on
                    is also very small. There are, however, breweries, distilleries, tanneries, aud
                    flour-mills, as well as marble polishing works.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Railways.—</hi> The county is intersected from north to south
                    by the Maryborough and Waterford line, which is joined near Kilkenny by the
                    South-Eastern Railway from Carlow. The Great Southern and Western Railway skirts
                    the south-western boundary of the county.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration.—</hi> The county comprises 10 baronies, 124
                    civil parishes and 15 parts of parishes, and 1601 town-lands. The county of the
                    city contains one parish and four parts of parishes. There are three poor-law
                    unions wholly within the county, viz., Castlecomer, Kilkenny, and Thomastown,
                    and portions of five, viz., Callan, Carrick-on-Suir, New Ross, Urlingford, and
                    Waterford. The county includes the parliamentary borough of Kilkenny, part of
                    that of New Ross, and the township of Callan. There are in the county and city
                    sixteen petty sessions districts. Assizes are held at Kilkenny, and quarter
                    sessions at Kilkenny, Pilltown, Urlingford, Castlecomer, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n86/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0914-0086-0075"/> Grace’s Old Castle, Callan, and Thomastown. The
                    county is within the Cork military district, and there are barrack stations at
                    Kilkenny and Castlecomer. Previous to the Union Kilkenny returned sixteen
                    members to Parliament, two representing the county. Since that period two
                    members have been returned for the county, one for the city of Kilkenny, and one
                    for New Ross, which, however, is situated chiefly in Wexford.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population.—</hi> According to the census of 1659, the total
                    population of the county was 18,427, of whom 1442 were English and 16,985 Irish.
                    In 1760 it was estimated at 62,832. In 1821 it had increased to 158,716, and in
                    1841 to 202,746, butin 1851 it had diminished to 159,514, in 1871 to 109,379,
                    and in 1881 to 99,064, of whom 48,682 were males and 50,382 females. The total
                    number of emigrants from 1st May 1851 to 31st December 1880 was 55,402, or 44 ’
                    5 per cent, of ths population in 1861. The marriage rate in 1880 to every
                    1000.of the population was 3‘2, the birth-rate 22‘1, and the death rate 20'0. In
                    1881 the Roman Catholics numbered 93,699; Protestant Episcopalians, 4963;
                    Presbyterians, 197; Methodists, 131; and all other denominations, 74. There were
                    resident in 1871 in the county 805 natives of England and 160 of Scotland. In
                    1871 the number of persons who spoke Irish only was 316, while 6424 could speak
                    Irish and English. 44,779 could read and write, 15 369 could read but could not
                    write, and 36,521 could neither read nor write.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Kilkenny received its name from St Cannechor
                    Canice, abbot of Aghaboe in Queen’s county, who died in 598, and w hose see was
                    removed to Kilkenny in the beginning of the 11th century. In the time of Ptolemy
                    the county was inhabited by the Brigantes and the Cauci. Afterwards it formed
                    part of the kingdom of Uisrai-gagh, modernized into Ossory, which was tributary
                    sometimes to Leinster and sometimes to Munster. In 1210 Kilkenny was formed into
                    a county by King John. During the Revolution it was held by the Irish, and it
                    also strongly adhered to the cause of James II. against William III.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Antiquities.—</hi> Circular groups of stones of very ancient
                    origin are to be seen on the summits of Slieve Grian and the hill of
                    Clogh-manta. There is a remarkable cromlech at Kilmogue and a large number of
                    cromlechs as well as raths in various parts of the county. Besides numerous
                    forts and mounds there are five round towers, one adjoining the cathedral of
                    Kilkenny, and others at Tulloherin, Kilree, Fertagh, and Aghaviller
                    respectively. The monastic remains in the city of Kilkenny are mentioned under
                    the notice of the town. There are interesting remains of a Cistercian monastery
                    at Jerpoint, said to have been founded by Dunnough, king of Ossory, and of
                    another belonging to the same order at Graig, founded by the earl of Pembroke in
                    1212. The Dominicans had an abbey at Rosbercon founded in 1267, and another at
                    Thomastown, of which there are still some remains. The Carmelites had a
                    monastery at Knocktopher. There was an Augustinian monastery at Innistioge, and
                    priories at Callan and Kells, of all of which there are still some remains. Of
                    the old castles the most remarkable is Graney or Grandison Castle in Iverk,
                    which is supposed to have been founded by the eighth earl of Ormonde in 1521,
                    and of which three towers and the walls still remain. See Robertson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Antiquities and Scenery of the County of Kilkenny,</hi> 1851.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Kilkenny,</hi> the chief town of the above county, a
                    market-town, county of a city, and parliamentary borough, is finely situated on
                    the Nore, and on the Great Southern and Western Railway, 73 miles south-west of
                    Dublin and 32 north of Waterford. It consists of two distinct portions,
                    Englishtown or Kilkenny proper and Irishtown, separated from each other by a
                    small rivulet, but although Irishtown still retains its name it is now included
                    in the corporation of Kilkenny. The city is irregularly built, but possesses
                    several spacious streets with many good houses, while its beautiful environs and
                    several imposing ancient structures give it an unusually interesting and
                    picturesque appearance. The Nore is crossed by two handsome bridges erected
                    towards the close of last century. The old cathedral of St Canice, from whom the
                    town takes its name, dates from 1052, and with the exception of the cathedral of
                    St Patrick in Dublin is the largest ecclesiastical building in Ireland, having a
                    length from east to west of 226 feet, and a breadth along the transepts from
                    north to south of 123 feet. It occupies a commanding position on an eminence at
                    the western extremity of Irishtown. It is a cruciform structure in the Early
                    English style, with a low massive tower supported on clustered columns of the
                    black marble peculiar to the district. The building was lately restored at a
                    cost of £15,000. It contains a large number of old sepulchral monuments. On the
                    eastern side of the north transept is the parish church, and a short distance
                    from the south transept are the remains of a round tower, rising to the height
                    of 100 feet. The episcopal palace near the east end of the cathedral was erected
                    in the time of Edward III. and enlarged in 1735. Besides the old cathedral, the
                    principal other churches are the Episcopal church of St Mary, a plain cruciform
                    structure; that of St John, containing a portion of the old abbey of St John;
                    and the Roman Catholic cathedral, erected in 1857 at a cost of £30,000, a
                    cruciform structure in the late First Pointed style, with a massive central
                    tower 186 feet in height. There are important remains of three old
                    monasteries—the preceptory of St John’s, founded in 1211; the Dominican abbey,
                    founded in 1225, and now used as a Roman Catholic church; and the Franciscan
                    abbey on the banks of the Nore, founded about 1230. But, among the ancient
                    buildings, that next in importance and interest to the cathedral is the castle,
                    occupying a commanding position on the summit of a precipice above the river
                    Nore. It was originally built by Strongbow, but rebuilt by William le Mareschal
                    in 1175, and again restored in the present century, and transformed into the
                    princely residence of the marquis of Ormonde. The grammar school or college,
                    which was originally founded by Pierce, earl of Ormonde, and re-endowed in 1684
                    by the duke of Ormonde, stands on the banks of the river opposite the castle. In
                    it Swift, Farquhar, Congreve, and Bishop Berkeley received part of their
                    education. Adjoining the city is the Roman Catholic college of St Kyran, a
                    Gothic building completed about 1840 at a cost of £20,000. The other principal
                    public buildings are the new court-house, the tholsel or city court, the city
                    and county prison, the barracks, and the county infirmary. There is still a
                    small manufacture of coarse woollens and linens. In the neighbourhood there are
                    large collieries, as well as quarries for marble, the manufactures connected
                    with which are an important industry of the town. It also possesses corn-mills,
                    breweries, and a tannery. The population of the county of the city of Kilkenny
                    in 1851 was 19,973, of the town proper 15,808; in 1871 the numbers were 15,748
                    and 12,710; and in 1881 they were 14,964 and 12,182.</p>
                <p>The town of Kilkenny proper owes its origin to an English settlement which took
                    place in the time of Strougbow, and it received a charter from William le
                    Mareschal, who married Strongbow’s daughter. This charter was confirmed by
                    Edward III., and from Edward IV. Irishtown received the privilege of choosing a
                    portrieve independent of Kilkenny. By Elizabeth the boroughs, while retaining
                    their distinct rights, were constituted one corporation, which in 1608 was made
                    a free borough by James I., and in the following year a free city. From James
                    II. the citizens received a new charter, constituting the city and liberties a
                    distinct county, to be styled the county of the city of Kilkenny, the burgesses
                    of Irishtown continuing, however, to elect a portrieve until the passing of the
                    Municipal Reform Act. Frequent parliaments were held at Kilkenny in the 14th
                    century, and so late as the reign of Henry VIII. it was the occasional residence
                    of the lord-lientenant. In 1642 it was the meeting-place of the assembly of
                    confederate Catholics. In 1648 Cromwell in the hope, by means of a plot, of
                    obtaining possession of the town, advanced towards it, but before his arrival
                    the plot was discovered. In 1650 it was, however, compelled to surrender after a
                    long and resolute defence. At a very early period Kilkenny and Irishtown
                    returned each two members to parliament, but since the Union one member only has
                    been returned for the city of Kilkenny.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
