<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0914-0087-0076-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KILLDEER (9th edition, volume 14, page 76)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6497c">Wings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45z7r">Plovers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rb9k">Snipes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw3f">Hawking</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qj2t">Hawks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987500">Killdeer</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176014">Wings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205585">Panama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit14newyrich/page/n87/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">KILLDEER</label>, a common and well-known American Plover, so
                    called in imitation of its whistling cry, the <hi rend="italic">Charadrius
                    vociferιisoi</hi> Linnaeus, and the <hi rend="italic">Aegialitis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vocifera</hi> of modern ornithologists. About the size of a Snipe,
                    it is mostly sooty-brown above, but showing a bright buff on the tail coverts,
                    and in flight a white bar on the wings; beneath it is pure white except two
                    pectoral bands of deep black. It is one of the finest as well as the largest of
                    the group commonly known as Ringed Plovers or Ring Doterels,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The word Doterel seems
                    properly applicable to a single species only, the <hi rend="italic">Charadrius
                    rnorinellus</hi> of Linnaeus, which, from some of its osteological characters,
                    may be fitly regarded as the type of a distinct genus, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eudrornias.</hi> Whether any other species agree with it in the peculiarity
                    alluded to is at present uncertain.</p></note> forming the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Aegialitis</hi> of Boie. Mostly wintering in the south or only on
                    the sea-shore of the more northern States, in spring it spreads widely over the
                    interior, breeding on the newly-ploughed lands or on open grass-fields. The nest
                    is made in a slight hollow of the ground, and is often surrounded with small
                    pebbles and fragments of shells. Here the hen lays her pear-shaped,
                    stone-coloured eggs, four in number, and always arranged with their pointed ends
                    touching each other, as is indeed the custom of most Limicoline birds. The
                    parents exhibit the greatest anxiety for their offspring on the approach of an
                    intruder: the lien runs off with drooping wings and plaintive cries, while the
                    cock sweeps around, gesticulating with loud and angry vociferations. It is the
                    best-known bird of its Family in the United States, throughout which it is found
                    in all suitable districts, but less abundantly in the north-east than further
                    south or west. In Canada it does not range further to the northward than 56° N.
                    lat., and it is not known to occur in Greenland, or hardly in Labrador, though
                    it is a passenger in Newfoundland every spring and autumn.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A single example is said to have been shot
                    rear Christchurch, in Hampshire, in April 1857 <hi rend="italic">ll'&gt;is,</hi>
                    1862, p. 276).</p></note> In winter it finds its way to Bermuda and to some of
                    the Antilles, but it is not recorded from any of the islands to the windward of
                    Porto Rico. However, in the other direction it goes very much further south,
                    travelling down the Isthmus of Panama and the west coast of South America to
                    Peru. The Killdeer has several other congeners in America, among which may be
                    noticed <hi rend="italic">Ae.</hi><hi rend="italic">semipalmata,</hi> so
                    curiously resembling the ordinary Ringed Plover of the Old World, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ae.</hi><hi rend="italic">hiaticula,</hi> except that it has its
                    toes connected by a web at the base; and <hi rend="italic">Ae.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">nivosa,</hi> a bird inhabiting the western parts of both the
                    American continents, which in the opinion of some authors is only a local form
                    of the widely-spread <hi rend="italic">Ae.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >alexandrνna</hi> or <hi rend="italic">cantiana,</hi> best known by its English
                    name of Kentish Plover, from its discovery near Sandwich towards the end of the
                    last century, though it is far more abundant in many other parts of the Old
                    World. The common Ringed Plover, <hi rend="italic">Ae.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >hiaticula,</hi> has many of the habits of the Killdeer, but is much less often
                    found away from the sea-shore, though a few colonies may be found in dry warrens
                    in certain parts of England many miles from the coast, and in Lapland at a still
                    greater distance. In such localities it has the curious habit of paving its nest
                    with small stones (whence it is locally known by the name of “Stone-hatch”), a
                    habit almost unaccountable unless regarded as an inherited instinct from
                    shingle-haunting ancestors.</p>
                <p>About thirty species all apparently referable with propriety to the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Aegialitis</hi> have been described, but probably so many do not
                    exist. Some, as the Kentish Plover above named, have a very extended
                    distribution, for that, letting alone its supposed American habitat, certainly
                    occurs in greater or less numbers on the coasts of China, India, and Africa
                    generally. On the other hand there is one, the <hi rend="italic">Ae.
                    sanctae-helenae,</hi> which seems to be restricted to the island whence it takes
                    its scientific name, and where it is called the “Wire-bird” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Ibis,</hi> 1873, p. 260). Nearly allied to <hi rend="italic">Aegialitis</hi>
                    are two genera peculiar to the New Zealand subregion— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thinornis,</hi> which does not call for any particular remark, ànd the
                    extraordinary <hi rend="italic">Anarhynchus,</hi> which deserves a few words. Of
                    this there is but one species, <hi rend="italic">Ae.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >frontalis,</hi> the Wrybill, so called from its bill being congenitally bent in
                    the middle and diverted to the right side—a formation supposed to give the bird
                    greater facility in seeking its food, chiefly arthropods that lurk under stones,
                    round which it may be seen running from left to right. Mr Buller <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ji. Hew Zealand,</hi> p. 219) connects with this habit the
                    curious fact that the black pectoral band worn by the bird is “narrower and of a
                    less decided colour on the left side of the breast,” whence he infers that “the
                    law of natural selection has operated to lessen the colouring on the side of the
                    bird more exposed to Hawks and other enemies while the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anarhyηchus</hi> is hunting for its daily food.” Be that as it may, it does not
                    detract from the wonderful nature of this asymmetry of the bill, which is
                    comparable indeed with that found in so large a number of Cetaceans among
                    mammals, but with nothing known among birds, for in the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Crossbills</hi> (g ’.v.) the bones of the mandibles are not affected, and in
                    certain Owls <hi rend="italic">(Hyctala)</hi> the distortion of the ear-bones is
                    not externally visible. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n. )</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
