<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-7159-0791-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PANTHEON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 791</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34n208">Vandals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wv7t">Paganism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jr08">Roofing</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4rn30745">Roofs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g11r">Top</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1164062">Vandals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1164055">Vandalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1100272">Roofing</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1100315">Roofs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1072090">Porticoes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1152704">Tops</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194567159" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PANTHEON</label>, a beautiful edifice at Rome, anciently a
                    temple, dedicated to all the gods, but now converted into a church, and
                    dedicated to the Virgin and all the martyrs. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Rome.)</hi></p>
                <p>This edifice is generally thought to have been built by Agrippa, son-in-law to
                    Augustus, from an inscription on the frieze of the portico Several antiquaries
                    and artists, however, have supposed that the Pantheon existed in the times of
                    the commonwealth, and that it was only embellished by Agrippa, who added the
                    portico But be this as it may, the Pantheon, when perfected by Agrippa, was an
                    exceedingly magnificent building; the form of the body being round or
                    cylindrical, and its roof or dome spherical. Within, it is 144 feet in diameter;
                    and the height from the pavement to the grand aperture on the top, through which
                    it re ceives the light, is just as much. It is of the Corinthian order. The
                    inner circumference is divided into seven grand niches, wrought in the thickness
                    of the wall, six of which are flat at the top; but the seventh, opposite to the
                    entrance, is arched. Before each niche are two columns of antique yellow marble,
                    fluted, and of one entire block, making in all fourteen, the finest in Rome. The
                    whole wall <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the temple, as high as the grand cornice
                    inclusive, is cased with different sorts of precious marble in compartments; and
                    the frieze is entirely of porphyry. Above the grand cornice arises an attic, in
                    which were wrought, at equal distances, fourteen oblong square niches; between
                    each niche there were four marble pilasters, and between the pilasters marble
                    tables of various kinds. This attic had a complete entablature; but the cornice
                    projected less than that of the grand order below. Immediately from the cornice
                    springs the spherical roof, divided by bands which cross each other like the
                    meridians and parallels of an artificial terrestrial globe. The spaces between
                    the bands decrease in size as they approach the top of the roof; to which,
                    however, they do not reach, there being a considerable plain space between them
                    and the great opening. That so bold a roof might be as light as possible, the
                    architect formed the substance of the spaces between the bands of nothing but
                    lime and pumice-stones. The walls below were decorated with lead and brass, and
                    works of carved silver; and the roof was covered on the outside with plates of
                    gilded bronze. There was an ascent from the springing of the roof to the very
                    summit, by a flight of seven stairs; and, if certaina uthors may be credited,
                    these stairs were ornamented with pedestrian statues ranged as an amphitheatre.
                    This notion was founded on a passage of Pliny, who says that Diogenes the
                    sculptor decorated the Pantheon of Agrippa with elegant statues, yet that it was
                    difficult to judge of their merit, upon account of their elevated situation. The
                    porticois composed of sixteen columns of granite, four feet in diameter, eight
                    of which stand in front, with an equal intercolumniation all along, contrary to
                    the rule of Vitruvius, who is for having the space answering to the door of a
                    temple wider than the rest. On these columns there is a pediment, the tympanum
                    of which was ornamented with bas-reliefs in brass; and the cross beams which
                    formed the ceiling of the porticowere covered with the same metal, as were also
                    the doors. The ascent up to the portico was by eight or nine steps.</p>
                <p>In the reign of Tiberius, the Pantheon was considerably damaged; but it was
                    repaired by Domitian, from which circumstance some writers consider him as the
                    founder of the building. The Emperor Hadrian also did something to the edifice.
                    But the Pantheon was more indebted to Septimius Severus, than to any one
                    besides. The most, perhaps, that any of his predecessors had done, was adding
                    some ornament to it; Septimius bestowed upon it essential reparations.</p>
                <p>This temple subsisted in all its grandeur till the incursion of Alaric in the
                    time of Honorius. Zozymus relates, that the Romans having engaged to furnish
                    this barbarian prince with three thousand pounds weight of gold and five
                    thousand pounds weight of silver, upon condition that he should depart from
                    their walls; and having found it impossible to raise those sums either out of
                    the public treasury or by private contribution, they were obliged to strip the
                    temples of their statues and ornaments of gold and silver. It is probable that
                    the Pantheon supplied a good part, as that of Jupiter Capitolinus was the only
                    one in Rome that could vie with it in riches. Alaric carried off nothing from
                    the Romans besides their precious metals. But, thirty-nine years thereafter,
                    Genseric king of the Vandals took away part of the marbles; and whether from
                    greed of plunder, or from a relish for the productions of art, he loaded <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194567172" xml:id="kp-eb0716-7172-0792"/> one of his ships
                    with statues. It cannot be questioned that on this occasion the Pantheon was
                    stripped of more of its ornaments, and that the inestimable works of Diogenes
                    became the prey of this barbarian.</p>
                <p>Before these predatory visits of the Goths and Vandals, the Christian emperors
                    had issued edicts for demolishing the Pagan temples. But the Romans, whatever
                    were their motives, spared the Pantheon, which is known to have suffered no
                    damage from the zeal of the pontiffs, or the indignation of the saints, before
                    the first siege of Rome by Alarie. It continued so rich till about the year 655,
                    as to excite the avarice of Constantius II., who came from Constantinople to
                    pillage the Pantheon, and executed his purpose so far as to strip it both of its
                    interior and exterior coverings of bronze, which he transported to Syracuse,
                    where they soon afterwards fell into the hands of the Saracens.</p>
                <p>About fifty years before this, Boniface IV. had obtained the Pantheon of the
                    Emperor Phocas, in order to convert it[into a church. The artists of those days
                    were totally ignorant of the excellence of the Greek and Roman architecture, and
                    spoiled every thing they laid their hands upon. To this period are to be
                    referred certain alterations, of which we shall immediately have occasion to
                    speak.</p>
                <p>After the devastations of the barbarians, Rome was contracted within a narrow
                    compass. The seven hills were abandoned; and the Campus Martius, being an even
                    plain, and near the Tiber, became the ground-plat of the whole city. The
                    Pantheon happening to stand at the entrance of the Campus Martius, was presently
                    surrounded with houses, which spoiled the fine prospect; and it was still more
                    deplorably disgraced by some of them which stood close to its walls.</p>
                <p>From the time when Constantius carried off the brass plating of the exterior
                    roof, that part was exposed to the injuries of the weather, or at best was but
                    slightly tiled in, till Benedict II. covered it with lead, which Nicholas V.
                    renewed in a better style. It does not appear that from this time till that of
                    Urban VIII. any thing remarkable was done for the Pantheon.</p>
                <p>Raffaelle, who had no equal as a painter, and who was also an architect, left a
                    considerable sum by his will for the reparation of the Pantheon, where his tomb
                    is placed; and Perino de la Vagua, Jacomo Udino, Annibale Caracci, Flamingo
                    Vacca, and the celebrated Corelli, did the same. All the ornaments within which
                    have any claim to be called good, are of later times. The paintings merit
                    esteem; and the statues, although not masterpieces, do honour to sculpture,
                    which alone is a proof that they are posterior to the fifteenth century.</p>
                <p>But, with all the respect due to a pontiff who was otherwise a protector and
                    friend of the arts, it were much to be wished that Urban VIII. had never known
                    that the Pantheon existed. The inscriptions cut at the side of the door inform
                    us that he repaired it; yet, whilst he built up with one hand, he pulled down
                    with the other. He caused two belfries constructed in a wretched taste to be
                    erected on the ancient front-work, and he divested the porticoof all the remains
                    of its ancient grandeur, namely, the brazen covering of the cross beams, which
                    amounted to such a prodigious quantity, that not only the vast canopy of the
                    confessional of St Peter’s was cast out of it, but likewise a great number of
                    cannon for the castle of St Angelo.</p>
                <p>Alexander VII. did what Urban VIII. had neglected to do. Whilst Bernini was
                    constructing the colonnade of St Peter, this pontiff ordered search to be made
                    for pillars to match those of the porticoof the Pantheon; and some were found
                    not far from the French church of St Louis, which were of the very same model.
                    They were granite of the isle of Ilva or Elba, and those of the porticowere
                    Egyptian granite; the colour, however, was the same, so that the effect was
                    equal. Nor did the pontiff’s zeal stop here. He caused all the old houses before
                    the porticoto be pulled down, and the soil and rubbish which covered the steps,
                    and even the bases of some of the pillars, to be cleared away. He began covering
                    the roof with marble, and raised a lantern ;over the aperture, to keep out rain;
                    but death removed him before his project was completed. Clement IX. his
                    successor, enclosed the porticowithin iron rails. Several Jater popes have added
                    to its decorations, which were all in the taste of the times when they were
                    executed; and the body of the edifice and its architecture gained nothing by
                    them. The main object of the liberality of the pontiffs was the embellishment of
                    the grand altar. One sent purple curtains, another bestowed silver tabernacles,
                    and others gave vases and superb dresses, suited to the solemn ceremonies of
                    religion. All these might be called rich; but they had in no sense a tendency to
                    retrieve the ancient majesty or original splendour of the temple. The true gusto
                    of the ornaments was a little imitated at the revival of the arts. Good statues
                    replaced the skeletons and squat figures which had disgraced the altars for the
                    space of eight centuries. The paintings of Perugino and others covered the dull
                    mosaics with which the Greeks of Constantinople had loaded the walls of most of
                    the churches in Rome. The porphyry and the green and yellow antique found
                    amongst the old ruins were likewise employed to much advantage.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
