<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-6753-0760-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PALEY, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 760</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194566753" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PALEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>, D. D., was
                    born at Peterborough in July 1743, where his father was then minor canon of the
                    cathedral church. His father afterwards removed to Giggleswick, being appointed
                    head master of the school at that place. Here his son was trained under his
                    immediate inspection, and discovered a solidity of understanding, and a
                    studiousness of disposition, which gave a fair earnest of his future
                    eminence.</p>
                <p>In November 1758, at the age of fifteen, he was admitted a sizar of Christ’s
                    College, Cambridge, and in October 1759 he became a resident member. When he
                    left home his father could not refrain from expressing to his friends the
                    anticipations he entertained of the figure which his son was destined to make:
                    “He’ll turn out a great man; very great. He has by far the clearest head I ever
                    met with.”</p>
                <p>Shortly after his removal to Cambridge he obtained three scholarships. He was not
                    at this time a close or laborious student; he spent much time in company, and
                    improved himself rather by observation and reflection than by reading. When he
                    appeared in the public school to make his first <hi rend="italic">act,</hi> the
                    spruceness of his dress, presenting a striking contrast to the habitual
                    carelessness of his appearance, attracted very particular notice, and, aided by
                    a singularity in his gestures and manner, occasioned much mirth amongst the
                    spectators; but the uncommon success with which he acquitted himself had the
                    effect of drawing crowds on all future occasions when he was expected to
                    dispute. His eminent abilities created upon one occasion some degree of
                    apprehension, when he proposed to argue against the eternity of future
                    punishments. One of the heads of the college insisted on his relinquishing that
                    question. Dr Watson, then moderator, and afterwards the celebrated Bishop of
                    Llandaff, protected on this occasion Paley’s independence. The latter, however,
                    was averse to give offence; and at the suggestion of Dr watson he retained the
                    subject, but took the opposite side. He came off with much eelat, his talents
                    having received the best scope for display from the high ability of his
                    opponent, Mr Freie.</p>
                <p>After obtaining with great honour his bachelor’s degree in January 1763, he
                    accepted of the situation of second assistant and Latin teacher in an academy at
                    Greenwich, chiefly resorted to by young men intended for the army and navy.</p>
                <p>In 1765 Mr Paley gained the first senior bachelor’s prize by a Latin dissertation
                    on “a Comparison between the Stoic and Epicurean Philosophy in their influence
                    on Morals;” taking the side of the Epicureans, as a sect friendly to rational
                    pleasures, and not, as their enemies supposed, indulgent to vicious excesses;
                    whilst he condemned the affected austerity of the followers of Zeno, and showed
                    from facts that it was compatible with the most flagitious crimes. It is a
                    remarkable circumstance, as illustrative of the formality which often presides
                    in university matters, that this dissertation narrowly escaped rejection,
                    because the Latin text was accompanied by <hi rend="italic">English notes,</hi>
                    for the purpose of aiding philosophical accuracy where the Latin appeared liable
                    to ambiguity.</p>
                <p>Being ordained deacon at the proper age, he officiated as curate to Dr
                    Hinehcliffe, vicar of Greenwich, where he continued to reside, though he gave up
                    his situation in the academy.</p>
                <p>Mr Paley was elected a fellow upon the foundation of Christ’s College in June
                    1766; returned to reside in the university; took the degree of master of arts,
                    and engaged in the business of private tuition. He took priest’s orders in
                    December 1767, and in 1768 he was appointed tutor of Christ’s College, along
                    with his friend Mr Law, already a distinguished scholar. The talents and
                    assiduity of these two quickly raised the celebrity of their college to an
                    unprecedented height. Paley’s intimacy with Law was productive of much mutual
                    improvement, and introduced the former to the acquaintance of his friend’s
                    father, the eminent Dr Edmund Law, who was soon after Bishop of Carlisle, but
                    continued to reside in the university as master of Peterhouse. Mr Paley was at
                    this time held in the highest esteem; and amongst his particular friends were
                    numbered Dr Plumptre, professor of casuistry; Dr Waring, Lucanian professor of
                    mathematics, who was in his department eminent beyond his contemporaries; and
                    the accomplished Mr Jebb. He figured as a lecturer on mathematics, morals, and
                    the Greek Testament, and afterwards on divinity. His method of lecturing was
                    singularly happy, the result of a diligent study of the art of teaching. He soon
                    discovered that, in moral disquisitions, more pains are required to make young
                    minds perceive the difficulty than to make them understand the solution, and
                    that some curiosity must be raised before an attempt is made to satisfy it. The
                    discourses which he delivered at this time contained the germ of the principal
                    works which he afterwards published on morals and theology.</p>
                <p>The controversy on the propriety of requiring a subscription to articles of
                    faith, as practised by the Church of England, was at this time much agitated at
                    the two universities. At Oxford the High Church party was triumphant, and
                    scarcely any individual ventured a whisper of opposition; but at Cambridge,
                    talents and ingenuity were exercised upon both sides of the question. Paley
                    favoured the claims of the reforming party; but, from motives of prudence,
                    declined signing a petition for relief at that time drawn up, not entertaining
                    such expectations of ultimate success as to be induced to take a public step so
                    obnoxious to those on whom his future prospects depended. He told one of his
                    friends in jest, that “he could not afford to keep a conscience ;” a confession
                    which will, no doubt, lay him open to the animadversions of those who reserve
                    their censures for the subdued struggles of a mind of limited moral strength,
                    whilst they excuse or applaud the oppressive system by which its efforts are
                    overawed. Paley, however, soon after wielded his pen in a decided tone in the
                    cause of freedom. Dr Law, the bishop of Carlisle, published an able and moderate
                    pamphlet against the imposition of the church test. An answer appeared at Oxford
                    from the pen of Dr Randolph. To this Paley published, anonymously, a reply,
                    entitled A Defence of the Considerations on the Propriety of the Church
                    Test.</p>
                <p>His well-merited reputation induced that great constitutional lawyer, the Earl of
                    Camden, to offer him the situation of tutor to his son; but his other
                    engagements led him to decline the offer.</p>
                <p>In 1775, he was inducted to the rectory of Musgrove in Westmoreland, worth about
                    eighty pounds a year, presented to him by the Bishop of Carlisle. He now married
                    Miss Hewit of Carlisle, and took a small farm to improve his income; a
                    speculation which he soon after gave up as unproductive. Next year, he was
                    inducted to the vicarage of Dalston in Cumberland.</p>
                <p>In 1777, he was inducted to the vicarage of Appleby, worth about L.200 a year;
                    and whilst in this situation he published a small volume, entitled The
                    Clergyman’s Companion in Visiting the Siek; in which he both evinced his
                    personal attention to the spiritual wants of his own flock, and conferred an
                    obligation on his brethren, which has been acknowledged by the numerous and
                    large editions which it has undergone. In June 1780, he was installed a
                    prebendary<pb break="no" facs="nls:194566766" xml:id="kp-eb0716-6766-0761"/> of
                    the fourth stall, in the Cathedral of Carlisle, worth about L.400 a year; and in
                    August 1782, on the promotion of his friend Mr Law to the see of Clonfert, he
                    was raised to the dignity of archdeacon of the diocese.</p>
                <p>A report was long in circulation, that Mr Paley, being appointed to preach before
                    the University of Cambridge when Mr Pitt made his first appearance at St Mary’s
                    after his elevation to the premiership, chose the following passage for his
                    text: “There is a lad here who hath five barley loaves and two fishes; but what
                    are they among so many ?” That was not the fact; but the joke originated with
                    Paley, who said to a friend that, had he been asked to preach on the occasion,
                    he would have chosen this text.</p>
                <p>Now in possession of a competent income, and sufficient leisure, he prepared for
                    the press his great work On the Principles of Moral and Political Philosophy,
                    which first appeared in 1785. In consequence of the well-known merit of his
                    lectures on the subject of that work, high expectations were formed of it; and
                    his admirers were not disappointed. Its most obvious feature was that of being
                    all directed to the practice of life in cases which hourly claim the attention
                    of well-meaning minds. Most other scientific works on morals were mere
                    speculative treatises, which pleased the reader by unfolding the principles of
                    right and wrong, in cases in which he has been previously satisfied about the
                    practical rule and its application; whilst they embarrassed conscientious
                    inquirers with hair-breadth distinctions, instead of conveying satisfactory
                    principles. Dr Paley’s work happily unites a due regard for practical duty with
                    rational information on those points on which the mind is most anxious to obtain
                    satisfaction. It soon established the reputation of its author. Some of his
                    doctrines met with opposition, but he never was provoked to write any reply; and
                    it is further remarked by his biographer, Mr Meadley, that, in the subsequent
                    editions, he made no alterations materially affecting the sense. Had there been
                    a few such alterations, however, he would have more fully merited the character
                    of a liberal inquirer. Amongst his elucidations of the foundations of virtue, he
                    certainly fails in his definition of “the nature of obligation.” He acknowledges
                    that the subject had embarrassed his own mind; yet he ultimately reposes in a
                    solution founded on a confusion of terms, which laid him fully open to the
                    animadversions of the Reverend Mr Pearson, who published An Examination of his
                    Theory. Dr Paley’s doctrine is, that “a man is under moral obligation when he is
                    urged by a violent motive resulting from the command of another.” He thus
                    resolves obligation into an effectual inducement. According to this statement, a
                    man is under no moral obligation unless he feels, acknowledges, and acts upon
                    it. Had such a hypothesis occurred in the writings of an author who made the
                    purity of practice to depend on the reception of peculiar theories, it might
                    have created great laxity of principle in the minds of some persons, and
                    distress in those of others. But his masterly elucidation of the rule of morals,
                    and the paternal benignity with which his efforts are uniformly accompanied, set
                    his reader at rest from all hurtful anxiety on practical topics.</p>
                <p>His exposition of the rule of morals, as founded in utility, is ably managed. He
                    demonstrates the superiority of this rule to every other, and the subordinate
                    rank of all those mental suggestions and impressions which some moralists have
                    represented as essential parts of the foundation of morality. Many such feelings
                    are valuable provisions of the Author of our Nature, but they do not deserve the
                    authority of guides. Their whole claim to our obedience is derived either from
                    their coincidence with some express command of the Deity, or their conduciveness
                    to utility. The difficulties attending inquiries into this conduciveness in
                    particular instances do not generate uncertainties so great as those attached to
                    the other supposed natural tests of moral truth. A man may be mistaken
                    respecting the useful or hurtful <hi rend="italic">tendency</hi> of a particular
                    line of conduct; but he is equally liable to be led astray by feelings venerated
                    as moral suggestions; and, under that influence, he is deprived of an equal
                    possibility of correcting himself by subsequent reflection. When authors declaim
                    on the danger attached to the doctrine of utility, they borrow their arguments
                    from that doctrine itself. They merely set up utility in its extensive
                    application against such utilities as are partial and delusive. Dr Paley,
                    therefore, dwells strongly on the necessity and importance of <hi rend="italic"
                    >general rules;</hi> and, by taking them for his guides, obviates all the
                    serious objections brought against this leading theorem, “that the method of
                    coming at the will of God concerning any action, by the light of nature, is to
                    inquire into the tendency of that action to promote or diminish the general
                    happiness.”</p>
                <p>On our duties to ourselves his observations are short, at which we cannot be
                    surprised when we find that in his definition of virtue these duties are
                    excluded. In the excellent casuistical Observations on Self-Defence,
                    Drunkenness, and Suicide, of which this portion of his work entirely consists,
                    he regards the tendency of personal conduct and habits only as they affect
                    society around us. But if he had paid more respect to the maxims of the stoical
                    authors, and studied them in their most favourable meaning, he would have been
                    more disposed to point out the importance of maintaining mental composure as an
                    ultimate object of individual efforts. On our duties towards God he also treats
                    briefly. The simplicity attached to our knowledge of their great object divests
                    them of variety as a separate subject, without detracting from their
                    sublimity.</p>
                <p>In the political part of this work, we find the exertions of a manly
                    understanding employed with some success in exposing the dark bigotry and the
                    gratuitous king-worship by which political knowledge had in past ages been
                    disgraced. His efforts, however, are exempt from those headstrong tendencies
                    which minds liberated from unfair control sometimes betray, and thus run into
                    schemes incapable of being applied without compromising the happiness of
                    society. That happiness he keeps steadily in view, as the only legitimate object
                    of all government, as well as the only legitimate object of opposition to
                    existing practices and institutions. Some of his admirers consider him as going
                    too far in vindicating the exaction of a subscription to the Thirty-nine
                    Articles. His chapter on subscription has been assailed with equal asperity by
                    the strenuous adherents of the established church, and by the scrupulous
                    advocates of Protestant freedom. His biographer, Mr Meadley, calls it “the last
                    effort of an ingenious mind to soften, by interpretation, the rigour of a
                    practice of which he could not seriously approve, and so to enlarge the pale of
                    conformity to liberal and conscientious men.”</p>
                <p>The answer which he gives to the arguments for passive obedience as founded in
                    Scripture, is particularly worthy of attention. Throughout the whole he displays
                    a candour of the most conciliating kind. None of his strictures on existing
                    systems had the slightest tendency to give offence to any, except to persons
                    actuated by downright prejudice, or the most corrupt motives.</p>
                <p>On the death of Dr Law, bishop of Carlisle, which happened in 1787, Mr Paley
                    published a short Memoir of the life of that venerable prelate. Soon afterwards
                    he wrote two tracts in favour of“the abolition of the slave-trade;” a subject on
                    which he had expressed his sentiments with decision in his Principles of Moral
                    and Political Philosophy, before it began to excite general interest.</p>
                <p>In 1790 he published his <hi rend="italic">ílorae Paulinae,</hi> or the Truth of
                    the Scripture History of St Paul evinced, by a comparison of the Epistles which
                    bear his name, with the Acts of the Apostles, and with one another. The object
                    was to show, by a copious selection of references and reciprocal <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194566779" xml:id="kp-eb0716-6779-0762"/>allusions, the strong
                    evidence of their genuineness derived from their undesigned coincidence. This
                    able treatise possesses more novelty of interest, and greater originality of
                    idea, than any of his other works.</p>
                <p>During the violent political ferment which led to the French Revolution, Dr Paley
                    published a short tract, entitled Reasons for Contentment, addressed to the
                    Labouring Classes; and he republished, in a separate form, his chapter on the
                    British Constitution, from his Principles of Moral and Political Philosophy. He
                    was censured by the violent partisans on both sides, as he went the full length
                    of neither; but his style of reasoning had the best tendency to guide and
                    satisfy those minds which were not obstinately and unreasonably
                    prepossessed.</p>
                <p>In May 1791, Mrs Paley died, leaving him a family of four sons and four
                    daughters.</p>
                <p>Early in 1794 he published his View of the Evidences of Christianity. This work,
                    with regard to manner and effect, follows a happy medium between that learned
                    prolixity which deters the reader, or tires out his patience, and that abrupt
                    brevity which is apt, with some minds, to beget an unfortunate impression of
                    some imperfection in the argument. He contends for the substantial truth of the
                    history connected with the Christian revelation; and, not undervaluing, as some
                    have injudiciously done, the internal evidences, he exhibits, in primitive
                    simplicity, and without the least oratorical exaggeration, the superlative value
                    of those doctrines in which all Christians are agreed, and gives an animated
                    view of the morality of the gospel. The work, considered as addressed to
                    doubting minds, was well fitted to interest the attention of all who are duly
                    impressed with the importance of the question at issue.</p>
                <p>Hitherto his preferment in the church had been slender, considering his singular
                    merit and the opulence of the ecclesiastical establishment. But the boldness of
                    his reasonings on political subjects had given deep dissatisfaction. To the
                    favourers of power it was not welcome doctrine, that “governments may be too
                    secure. ;” that “the obligations of subjects and sovereigns are reciprocal ;”
                    and “that the divine right of kings rests on the same foundation with the divine
                    right of constables.” But when he stood forth as the successful defender of the
                    Christian revelation, at a time when the interests of the church were supposed
                    to be in danger, his services met with more marked attention. Dr Porteous,
                    bishop of London, conferred on him the desirable situation of prebend of St
                    Paneras in the Cathedral of St Paul’s, to which he was instituted in August
                    1794. He was in a few months afterwards promoted to the subdeanery of Lincoln by
                    Dr Prettyman, bishop of that diocese, and took his degree of D. D. at
                    Cambridge.</p>
                <p>Before leaving this place, he had the agreeable surprise of a letter from Dr
                    Barrington, bishop of Durham, offering him the valuable rectory of
                    Bishop-Wearmouth, worth about L.1200 a year, into which he was soon inducted. A
                    few months afterwards he married Miss Dobinson of Carlisle; and, from this
                    period to his death, divided his time between Bish op-Wearmouth and Lincoln,
                    being obliged to reside three months in the year at the latter place. Now that
                    he enjoyed a handsome independence, we find his company courted by many
                    distinguished characters, and his life spent in a series of the most useful
                    labours, whilst all his secular transactions were so well conducted, as to shed
                    a lustre on his character, and to exhibit a most instructive example to all
                    around him. Both his parents lived to witness his high reputation and success in
                    life. His mother died in 1796, and his father in 1799.</p>
                <p>In 1800, Dr Paley was attacked by a disease in the kidneys, accompanied with a
                    species of melaena, which obliged him to suspend the discharge of his
                    professional duties.</p>
                <p>He had a second attack in the following spring, and a third about the end of
                    1802.</p>
                <p>During the progress of this fatal disease, he was engaged in preparing for the
                    press his last important work, On Natural Theology. His literary labours were
                    frequently interrupted by severe paroxysms of pain, but on the first respite he
                    always resumed them with cheerfulness. Under these circumstances, he wrote his
                    excellent remarks on the alleviations of pain, in his chapter on the Goodness of
                    the Deity. This work had been undertaken at the suggestion of the Bishop of
                    Durham, that he might, by theological exertions in his closet, make up for the
                    unavoidable suspension of his public ecclesiastical labours. In none of his
                    writings does his candour appear to such incontestible advantage as in this. We
                    never find him browbeating the adversary, or attempting to push his conclusions
                    a single step farther than his premises evidently warrant We do not find him,
                    like many others, advancing the metaphysical position “that every thing which
                    exists must have a cause,” so glaringly open to the query, “why should the world
                    have a cause more than its Creator?” Mere existence cannot authorize the
                    inference of owing that existence to a higher source. He rests his argument on
                    far better ground; the <hi rend="italic">character</hi> of the fabric of nature,
                    or rather of various objects in it which offer themselves to our observation.
                    Nor does he, with some, assume the doctrine, that matter is essentially inert,
                    and that, therefore, its motions must be induced by an extraneous and spiritual
                    cause. He more wisely turns his attention to the proofs of <hi rend="italic"
                    >design</hi> which so many objects in the world exhibit. These are so selected
                    and arranged as to appear in the most interesting and satisfactory point of
                    view. Where the phenomena are apparently inconsistent, we find no straining to
                    reconcile them; no reluctance to take a full view of unfavourable appearances;
                    no inclination to draw the same inferences from opposite facts. His argument is
                    not suspended on a chain of metaphysical reasoning, which would have subjected
                    it to the risk of destruction as soon as one of the links gave way. He directs
                    the attention of his reader to numerous columnar supports of the existence of a
                    God, each of which is adequate to the whole office. Each instance produced is
                    decisive of the point at issue; and though his instances are numerous as well as
                    beautiful, they are evidently only partial exemplifications of a species of
                    evidence which is boundless in extent.</p>
                <p>In the present state of the learned world, this is perhaps the most important of
                    Dr Paley’s works; as possessing the best tendency to reclaim persons wandering
                    in the mazes of scepticism, to that state of thought which is most favourable to
                    the true improvement of the human character; and to the establishment of that
                    state of mental peace after which a sense of our weakness naturally leads us to
                    aspire.</p>
                <p>After its publication, Dr Paley continued to take a lively interest in the
                    literary and scientific discussions of the day, especially such as bore directly
                    on the great interests of society; but in May 1805, he was subjected to a
                    violent attack of his complaint, in which all remedies proved ineffectual; and,
                    with great tranquillity, he breathed his last at Bishop-Wearmouth, leaving a
                    family of four sons and four daughters in possession of a competent fortune,
                    saved by a systematic though by no means a niggardly economy.</p>
                <p>He wrote several sermons and other minor productions, less known than those above
                    enumerated. They are all collected in a uniform edition of his works, and will
                    be found, on examination, worthy of his fame, and successfully directed to the
                    same valuable ends with his more celebrated productions. (p. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">p. p. p.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
