<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0716-6358-0730-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">HOUSE-PAINTINGPAINTING, HOUSE-</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 730</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="97" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term><term n="68" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term><term n="63" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="20" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="74" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term><term n="68" ref="fasttopic:1050530">Painters</term><term n="63" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="30" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194566358" type="entry"><p><label type="entry"><choice><orig>HOUSE-PAINTING</orig><reg instant="false">PAINTING, HOUSE-</reg></choice></label>.—In a country with a climate like that of Great Britain,
                    house-painting is an art of much importance, as being conducive to the
                    durability and comfort of our dwelling-houses; and in every country it is an
                    art, which, though somewhat mechanical, may be made to approximate to those of a
                    higher and more intellectual nature. The house-painter, therefore, ought to make
                    himself thoroughly acquainted, not only with the mechanical department of his
                    business, but likewise with the rules by which high art is governed, especially
                    those of harmonious colouring. By such means he will, in the first place,
                    understand the best methods of rendering his work capable of resisting for many
                    years the effects of a changeable climate and humid atmosphere; and, secondly,
                    he will be enabled to render even his plainest work pleasing to the eye of the
                    intelligent and tasteful. It is further necessary that he should make himself
                    acquainted with the various styles of ornament, not only in painting, but in
                    architecture, and also with such of the ornamental works of the great masters of
                    antiquity as are still in existence.</p><p>For nearly a century house-painting in this country was in the most degraded
                    state; so much so, that when any thing beyond the plainest style of work was
                    required, artists were brought from France to execute it; and specimens of their
                    skill may still be found in many of the mansions of our nobility and gentry.
                    Within these fifteen or twenty years, however, great improvements have been
                    made. The handicraft department has not only become equal, but it is believed,
                    superior to that of any other country, especially in the imitations of the finer
                    kinds of woods and marbles; whilst attention to the scientific part of the art,
                    if it may be so called, is rapidly becoming more general in practice.</p><p>We shall, in the first place, give a short account of the plainest branch of
                    house-painting.</p><p>It is well known that the ceilings and walls of apartments in dwelling-houses and
                    other buildings of this country are now almost uniformly finished in plaster;
                    and the nature and properties of this composition are also well known. One of
                    these properties is its power of absorbing moisture; consequently, when an
                    apartment is left for any length of time without the benefit of a fire, or
                    heated air supplied by other means, the plaster will continue to absorb a
                    portion of the humidity with which the atmosphere is generally loaded; and this
                    absorption will not only render the room unwholesome, but will tend to impair
                    the durability of the plaster itself. The first object, therefore, in painting a
                    house, is to render the interior walls impervious to this absorption; and for
                    this purpose the house-painter provides various materials.</p><p>These are, white lead, ground in refined oil to the consistency of a thick paste,
                    which operation is now performed by machinery on the premises of the original
                    manufacturer, instead of being done by a clumsy hand-mill as formerly in the
                    painter’s shop; linseed oil, spirits of turpentine, litharge, sugar of lead,
                    japanners’ gold size, ochre, venetian red, lamp black, indian red, Turkey and
                    English umber, terra de Sienna, red lead, Prussian blue, orange lead, chrome
                    yellow, vermillion, lake, and other pigments. But white lead is the material of
                    the greatest importance, as it is the principal ingredient in all ordinary
                    colours used in house-painting; indeed, it generally constitutes nine-tenths of
                    the composition, and consequently forms the main body of the paint. The quality
                    of this article is therefore of the greatest importance, as upon it depends
                    almost entirely the durability of the work; yet it is of all the painter’s
                    materials the most difficult to get free of adulteration. There are three
                    qualities of this article manufactured, the prices of which vary, according to
                    that of pig lead, from about 27s. to 40s. per cwt. But this difference in the
                    price of white lead is trivial in comparison with the mode in which it is
                    sometimes adulterated. This is done by the introduction of fine whiting ground
                    in oil, in the same manner as the white lead. The cost of this is about 5s. per
                    cwt., and, as detection is very difficult, the temptation to adulterate is
                    proportionally great. But how much greater must it be to the needy tradesman,
                    who can employ it alone instead of white lead in the two first coats of his
                    work, with scarcely a possibility of his employers knowing any thing of the
                    matter? This in some measure accounts for the great difference that exists in
                    the prices of painters’ work. The injury done to paint by the admixture of
                    whiting is, that it not only renders it of a much less compact body, but,
                    causing it to be more easily acted upon by the atmosphere, renders it much more
                    liable to be blanched and destroyed by repeated washings.</p><p>Linseed oil being the principal diluent, stands next in importance. It varies but
                    little in quality, and is seldom adulterated; the superiority of one kind over
                    another consisting entirely in its clearness, and being of a moderate age. It is
                    sometimes boiled, which gives it great facility in drying, but renders it so
                    thick and unctuous that it is only fit for out-door work.</p><p>Spirits of turpentine, of which a great deal is now used in house-painting, is
                    also rather uniform in quality; but varies greatly in price according to the
                    state of the market. Perhaps the only difference in its quality, consists in the
                    manner in which it is distilled; and it is easy to distinguish what has been
                    properly done by the absence of the resinous matter which is generally to be
                    found in that which has been distilled with less care.</p><p>Litharge and sugar of lead are purchased by the painter in a dry state, ground in
                    oil into a paste of a thick consistency, and used to dry and harden paint. They
                    do not vary much in point of quality. Japanners’ gold size is a liquid of which
                    there are various qualities, the price being from lθs. to 18s. per gallon. It is
                    used for the same purpose.</p><p>Several of the colouring pigments are equally various in quality, and the
                    house-painter, in laying in his stock, can suit it exactly to the rates of
                    prices at which he works; some of them varying from 9d. to 3s. per lb. according
                    to the quality, and others, such as ochre, from 2d. to ls. per lb. These are the
                    principal materials employed by the housepainter in the plain department of his
                    work; and it will now be necessary to give some account of their
                    application.</p><p>To paint plaster properly, five coats are generally requisite; but where it is
                    not of a very absorbent nature, four <pb break="no" facs="nls:194566371" xml:id="kp-eb0716-6371-0731"/>are found to answer. The first is composed of
                    white lead, diluted with linseed oil, to rather a thin consistency, in order
                    that the plaster may be well saturated; and into this is put a small quantity of
                    litharge to insure its drying. In quick plaster, which is the best for painting,
                    the oil in this coat is entirely absorbed, thereby hardening the plaster to the
                    extent of about the eighth of an inch inwards from the surface. When this is
                    found to be the case, the second coat should also be thin that the plaster may
                    be thoroughly saturated; and it will be found necessary after this to give other
                    three coats, making in all five. The second coat will be found to be but
                    partially absorbed, and it is therefore requisite to make the third coat a good
                    deal thicker, and to introduce into it a little spirits of turpentine, and such
                    of the colouring pigments already enumerated, as may bring it somewhat near to
                    the tint of which the apartment is to be finished. The fourth coat should be as
                    thick as it can be well used, and should be diluted with equal parts of oil and
                    spirits of turpentine. The colour of it ought to be several shades darker than
                    that which is intended for the finishing coat, and the drying ingredient, sugar
                    of lead instead of litharge. These coats ought all to be laid on with much care,
                    both as to smoothness and equality, and each lightly rubbed with sand-paper
                    before the application of the other. The finishing or flatting coat, as it is
                    termed from its drying without any gloss, is next applied. It ought, like the
                    others, to be composed of pure white lead, ground as already described, and
                    diluted entirely with spirits of turpentine; and it should appear, when mixed, a
                    few shades lighter than the pattern chosen for the wall, as it darkens in the
                    drying. The drying ingredient should be a small portion of japanners’ gold size.
                    This coat must be applied with great care and dispatch, as the spirits of
                    turpentine evaporate very rapidly, and if touched with the brush after that
                    takes place, which is in little more than a minute after its application, an
                    indelible glossy mark will be left on the surface. Nothing has been said of the
                    time that each of the coats will take to dry sufficiently to receive the next;
                    as that depends much on the state of the weather, the quantity of dryer
                    employed, and the atmosphere kept up in the apartment. It may be observed,
                    however, that under any circumstances the first coat ought to stand a few days
                    before the application of the second; the second a little longer before the
                    application of the third; and the third, unless in four coat work, should have
                    still longer time to harden. But the coat immediately before the flatting or
                    finishing coat ought not to stand above two days, as much of the beauty and
                    solidity of the work will depend on the latter dying into and uniting with the
                    former.</p><p>The description of this process might be sufficient to convince every one, that
                    there could be no better mode of rendering the plaster of which the walls of our
                    apartments are composed, impervious to the effects of our changeable and humid
                    climate. In the first place, it hardens the surface, and then forms a compact,
                    and smooth incrustation, upon which the dampness of the atmosphere can only
                    condense when any sudden change takes place in the temperature. This is often
                    exemplified in staircases, where the wall gets so low in temperature during a
                    continuance of cold weather, that when a change takes place the condensation is
                    so great, that the water runs in streams upon the steps. How then, we may ask,
                    can any one employ paper-hanging, or any other absorbent mode of finishing in
                    such apartments? It ought to be well known, that in such cases the moisture
                    instead of being condensed and rendered easily removable, is absorbed and
                    gradually given out in connexion with the natural effluvia of glue, rotten
                    paste, and other noxious materials.</p><p>In many cases it has been found that this substantial style of painting is too
                    heavy in its effect for ceilings, which require a degree of aerial lightness,
                    especially in drawingrooms, boudoirs, and such like apartments. In these cases,
                    therefore, the absorption is stopped by two coats of paint, and when these are
                    quite dry and hard, a coat of what is called distemper colour is applied; that
                    is, white lead ground in water, and diluted with size made from the parings of
                    white leather and parchment skins. In ordinary apartments, fine whiting may be
                    substituted in distemper work for white lead.</p><p>The painting of the woodwork of such apartments as are not fitted up with oak or
                    other hard woods, is a process very similar to that employed upon plaster, not
                    only when it is to be finished plain, but also as a ground-work for imitations
                    of the foreign woods now in use; only each of the coats should be thicker and
                    applied with still more attention to smoothness. The imitating of woods and
                    marbles may be termed, in house-painting, a link between that which has been
                    already explained and is essentially simple, and that which is really
                    ornamental. It has of late been brought to such perfection, that in some cases
                    where the real and the imitation oak are brought into juxtaposition, as at
                    Abbotsford, it is scarcely possible, even after examination, to distinguish the
                    imitation from the reality. Imitations of marble have in some cases been brought
                    to equally great perfection, but this is far from being so general.</p><p>The process of painting imitations of woods, is in the first instance, as already
                    observed, to lay a ground-work of four or five coats of paint, taking the
                    greatest care that no brush marks remain. This requires much more time than
                    applying the same number of coats for plain finishing; and the last coat instead
                    of being flatted, is composed of equal portions of oil and spirits of
                    turpentine. The shades and grain of the wood are given by thin glazings of
                    Vandyke brown, terra de sienna, or umber, according to the kind of wood to be
                    imitated; which colours are ground in water and mixed with small beer, the
                    tenacity of which is sufficient to prevent it rubbing off by the application of
                    the varnish which immediately follows. All imitations of woods are painted in
                    this way, except wainscot, for which a thick substance is requisite, in order
                    that it may receive the impression of an ivory or horn comb, by which the
                    peculiar grain of that wood is imitated. The varnish employed upon work of this
                    kind is copal, which of all the materials used by the painter is that in which
                    he has most latitude. The price of copal varnish is from 10s. to 42s. per
                    gallon; so here again he can suit his materials to the price which he receives
                    for his work.</p><p>The imitation of marbles has nothing very peculiar in its mode of execution,
                    being more like actual painting than that employed in imitating wood; and on
                    this account it depends more on natural taste, than on mechanical skill.</p><p>The ornamental department is likewise making great strides towards its ancient
                    excellence, and owing to the improved taste of the present age, is beginning to
                    be somewhat in demand. What is meant by the ornamental department, is the
                    decorating of the walls of apartments either by original designs of pannelling
                    and borders, or by careful imitations of Raffaelle’s arabesques, Watteau’s
                    grotesque pannellings, and the Pompeian frescos; as well as decorations in
                    imitation of basso relievo, in white and gold, polychrome and various other
                    styles.</p><p>The want of general instruction in art, and the prevalence of the use of paper
                    hanging, have tended to retard the progress of ornamental painting; but the
                    former cause, through the patriotism of an individual,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Mr. Ewart, formerly Μ. P. for
                    Liverpool.</p></note> backed by a government that has the interest of all
                    classes in view, is, by the establishment of schools for ornamental design, in a
                    fair way of being removed; and the latter will soon give <pb break="no" facs="nls:194566384" xml:id="kp-eb0716-6384-0732"/>way to the rapid improvement
                    which is taking place in public taste.</p><p>It now only remains to notice what we term the scientific department of
                    house-painting, or more properly (from the improved practice of die profession)
                    interior decoration. The fact is now no longer disputed that the rules of the
                    highest science and art can be made available in improving our most ordinary
                    occupations; and in no case has this fact been made more apparent than in the
                    application of the science of chromatics or the laws of harmonious colouring to
                    the interior decoration of our dwelling-houses. Much attention is, however,
                    requisite on the part of the housepainter, to the <hi rend="italic">proper</hi>
                    application of these laws in his practice. Every practitioner in the higher
                    walks of art, has only such a style of colouring to study, as may be suited to
                    the general character of his subjects; but the housepainter must vary <hi rend="italic">his</hi> style, not only according to the uses of the apartments
                    which he decorates, but the tastes of his employers, the style of the
                    architecture, the situation of the house, and the quarter from which each
                    apartment is lighted. He must confine himself to neither a vivid, sombre, warm,
                    nor cold style; all must be equally at his command. Besides, an artist has the
                    advantage of light and shadow in toning the colours in a picture; whilst those
                    employed in decorative painting, are all liable to be placed in full light, and
                    must necessarily be in themselves toned to prevent that unnatural crudeness so
                    annoying to the eye. A picture may have many excellencies to compensate for
                    defective colouring; it may excel in one or other or all of the qualities of
                    drawing, expression, and composition; but beyond the mere handicraft department,
                    the works of the decorator must depend solely for their effect upon harmonious
                    colouring.</p><p>It would exceed our limits to give even an outline of the laws of harmonious
                    colouring, as applied to house-painting, and shall, therefore, refer the reader
                    to the only work which has yet been written on the subject,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hay’s <hi rend="italic">Laws of Harmonious
                    Colouring adapted to Interior Decoration,</hi> Edinburgh, 1836, in 8vo, 3d
                    ed.</p></note> and from which we make the following extract, relative to the
                    tone and characteristic style of colouring peculiar to the various apartments of
                    a dwelling-house.</p><p>“The tone or key is the first point to be fixed, and its degree of warmth or
                    coldness will be regulated by the use, situation, and light of the apartment.
                    The next point is the style of colouring, whether gay, sombre, or otherwise.
                    This is more particularly regulated by the use of the apartment, and the
                    sentiments which it ought to inspire; for, as Sir Joshua Reynolds says in regard
                    to colouring, ‘what may heighten the elegant may degrade the sublime.’ Unison,
                    or a proper combination of parts, is the next consideration.</p><p>“The tone or key is generally fixed by the choice of the furniture; for as the
                    furniture of a room may be considered, in regard to colouring, in the same light
                    as the principal figures in a picture, the general tone must depend upon the
                    colours of which it is composed: for instance, if the prevailing colour be blue,
                    grey, cool green, or lilac, the general tone must be cool; but if, on the other
                    hand, it be red, orange, brown, yellow, or a warm tint of green, the tone must
                    be warm. But, as stated before, there can be no pleasing combination of colours
                    without variety. This, by judicious management, may be given without in the
                    least interfering with the tone, for it is merely the general colour of the
                    furniture which ought to fix the tone; and there may be the most decided
                    contrasts in its parts, which, by the introduction of proper medial hues
                    throughout the room, can be reconciled and united. Apartments lighted from the
                    south and west, particularly in a summer residence, should be cool in their
                    colouring; but the apartments of a town house ought all to approach towards a
                    warm tone; as also such apartments as are lighted from the north and east of a
                    country residence.</p><p>“When the tone of an apartment is therefore fixed by the choice of the furniture,
                    it is the business of the house-painter to introduce such tints upon the
                    ceiling, walls, and wood work, as will unite the whole in perfect harmony. This
                    is a difficult task. The colours of the furniture may be arranged by a general
                    knowledge of’ the laws of harmony, but the painter’s part cannot be properly
                    added without the closest attention to the principles of art.</p><p>“The style of colouring is the next point to be fixed, and will depend entirely
                    on the use of the apartment. In a drawing-room, vivacity, gaiety, and light
                    cheerfulness should characterise the colouring. This is produced by the
                    introduction of light tints of brilliant colours, with a considerable degree of
                    contrast and gilding; but the brightest colours and strongest contrasts should
                    be upon the furniture, the effect of which will derive additional value and
                    brilliancy from the walls being kept in due subordination, although at the same
                    time partaking of the general liveliness.</p><p>“The characteristic colouring of a dining-room should be warm, rich, and
                    substantial; and where contrasts are introduced, they should not be vivid. This
                    style of colouring will be found to correspond best with the massive description
                    of the furniture; and gilding, unless in very small quantities for the sake of
                    relief, should be avoided.</p><p>“Parlours ought to be painted in a medium style, between that of a drawing-room
                    and dining-room.</p><p>“The most appropriate style of colouring for libraries is solemn and grave, and
                    no richer colouring should be employed than is necessary to give the effect of
                    grandeur, which can scarcely be done where one monotonous tint prevails; but
                    care should be taken not to disturb the quiet and solemn tone which ought to
                    characterise the colouring of all apartments of this description.</p><p>“In bed-rooms, a light, cleanly, and cheerful style of colouring is the most
                    appropriate. A greater degree of contrast may here be admitted between the room
                    and its furniture than in any other apartment, as the bed and window curtains
                    form a sufficient mass to balance a tint of equal intensity upon the walls.
                    There may also, for the same reason, be admitted gayer and brighter colours upon
                    the carpet.</p><p>“Stair-cases, lobbies, and vestibules, should all be rather of a cool tone, and
                    the style of the colour should be simple and free of contrast. The effect to be
                    produced is that of architectural grandeur, which owes its beauty more to the
                    effect of light and shadow than to any arrangement of colours; yet they ought
                    not to be so entirely free from colour as the exterior of a mansion, but should
                    be in colouring what they are in use, a link between exterior simplicity and
                    interior richness.</p><p>“Stair-cases and lobbies being cool in tone, and simple in the style of their
                    colouring, will much improve the effect of the apartments which enter from
                    them.” </p></div></body></text></TEI>