<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-3453-0182-12" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PEMBROKESHIRE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 182</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90257q">Servants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g11r">Top</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj77x65">Sound</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1152704">Tops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1127099">Sounds</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193493453" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PEMBROKESHIRE</label> is a maritime county of South Wales. It
                    forms a peninsula at the south-west corner of the principality, and is
                    surrounded by the sea everywhere except on the eastern side, where it is bounded
                    by Carmarthenshire and by Cardiganshire. Its shape is very irregular, which
                    makes it difficult to ascertain its exact extent. Its extreme length is thirty,
                    and its extreme breadth twenty-seven miles. Its area is estimated, but with no
                    decided accuracy, at 575 square miles.</p>
                <p>It is generally an undulating county, composed of plains, with, hills of no great
                    elevation, except in the northern part, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193493466"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0717-3466-0183"/>where a range of mountains is stretched out to the
                    extent of nine or ten miles. The loftiest points of this group are Precelly Top,
                    1754 feet, and Brennin-Vaur, 1285 feet above the level of the sea. Few of the
                    hills in the other parts of the county attain a greater height than 290 feet. As
                    the greater part of the country is destitute of woods, it has a bare and bleak
                    appearance, except in the valleys, where the numerous brooks which flow through
                    them impart a pleasing verdure to the bordering meadows.</p>
                <p>The most considerable rivers are the Eastern Cleddaus, which forms at first the
                    dividing line between this county and Carmarthenshire; and the Western Cleddaus,
                    which traverses a considerable portion of Pembrokeshire. These two rivers unite,
                    and form the admirable estuary of Milford Haven, which is considered as the best
                    harbour in the British islands. It is sufficiently capacious to contain the
                    whole navy of England, is so completely sheltered as to be secure from all
                    winds, and has good holding ground, with competent depth of water. During the
                    war these advantages induced the lords of the admiralty to establish a
                    dock-yard, chiefly with the view of building ships. It is situated on the
                    southern shore of Milford Haven, about two miles from the town of Pembroke. It
                    includes an area of about sixty acres, its surface descending in a gradual slope
                    to the water’s edge, along the shore of which there is ample space for a couple
                    of dry docks, and at least twelve building slips. The work has been executed
                    with care and accuracy; but, owing to the state of general tranquillity which
                    has prevailed for more than twenty years, it is not of the vast importance that
                    it may become in case of another extended naval war. When at its greatest
                    height, this establishment had about five hundred men. The town of Huberstone,
                    on this bay, is now the resort of the packet for the south of Ireland, and is
                    thus a place of much activity, as far as regards the number of passengers to and
                    fro. The entrance to this important estuary is almost free from danger; the
                    principal difficulty is a sunken rock called the Chapel Rock, but it may easily
                    be avoided, and has at low tide seventeen feet of water on it. This rock, as
                    well as the shoals near it, is well buoyed. There are several bays on this
                    coast, in which are good anchorage and safe riding for ships. The most important
                    of these are St Bride’s Bay, Ramsey Sound, and Nayland Road.</p>
                <p>The rivers of this county are but of short course, and, with the exception of
                    those two which empty themselves into Milford Haven, discharge but little water.
                    The names of these rivers are the Newgall, the Solva, the Alan, the Gwayn, the
                    Nevern, the Cuch, and the Tivy.</p>
                <p>The soil of the county is generally a red loam, in many parts resting on a
                    calcareous subsoil, and admirably adapted for the growth of corn. In some places
                    the surface is covered with porous stones, which are supposed to imbibe and
                    retain the salt from the saline air, and to render the land highly prolific. The
                    principal grain consists of wheat, barley, and oats; but in some parts of the
                    county rye is extensively cultivated. The modes of cultivation are commonly the
                    same as those which prevailed in remote ages, that is, growing wheat, barley,
                    and oats in succession, till the land was so exhausted as to yield no increase,
                    when it was suffered to return to its natural state, under the idea of
                    recovering itself by rest. Very little attention is paid to the preservation of
                    manure; the barns and farming erections are very badly constructed; and the
                    agricultural implements, especially the ploughs, are of a rude and antique form.
                    Such is the description of the greater part of the agricultural state of the
                    country; but there are splendid exceptions. The size of the farms varies from
                    fifty to a hundred acres; but the average extent of them is estimated to be
                    about two hundred. Some of the occupiers are annual tenants, but many hold from
                    the lords of manors by leases for three lives at an agreed rent, though without
                    any fine on the renewal of a life, as is customary in England, and on the lands
                    in Pembrokeshire belonging to the church.</p>
                <p>The black cattle of this county are of an excellent race, and are annually
                    distributed over the south of England in droves, which travel from fair to fair
                    till the whole are sold. They are commonly sent to market when they are in calf
                    for the first time. Some valuable horses are bred here. The sheep are small, and
                    yield little wool, but the mutton is very highly esteemed.</p>
                <p>At no very remote period silver was found in the parish of St Elwys, or St
                    Bride’s Bay. The mine, which was discontinued in the reign of Queen Elizabeth,
                    was resumed some years ago, but not with such success as to induce perseverance.
                    Some excellent lead ore is found upon the banks of the Tivy, but the mines are
                    not worked with any degree of spirit. The most important production of the mines
                    is coal. It is confined to a district of narrow extent on the southern side of
                    the county. The strata lie near the surface, and the quality is not very good.
                    The inhabitants use the small coal mixed with clay and formed into balls; it is
                    sulphureous, and highly offensive to strangers.</p>
                <p>The manufactures of this county are exceedingly few, but the building of ships
                    and boats gives employment to about 400 persons. There are about 130 weavers of
                    woollen cloth and flannels; but they are so much scattered about the county,
                    that the largest number in any one place is no more than seventeen at St
                    David’s. Attempts have been made to introduce cotton-spinning, but without
                    success. The chief trade now consists in the conveyance of coals from Tenby to
                    the opposite shore of Devon, Cornwall, and Somerset, where they are found fitter
                    for limeburners and maltsters than for fuel in dwellings. The great travelling
                    causes the circulation of much money, and some is derived from the company that
                    in the summer frequent Tenby for the purpose of sea-bathing.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants are of two distinct races. If a line be drawn through the whole
                    county, bisecting the town of Haverford West, it will be found that on one side
                    of the line nothing but English is spoken, and on the other side only Welsh.
                    This is so definite, that in the town of Haverford West the one language is
                    spoken in the upper, and the other in the lower part of it; and there are two
                    markets, one frequented by the English, the other by the Welsh peasantry. The
                    part where the English live, commonly called Little England beyond Wales, was
                    originally peopled by a colony of Flemings, who have kept themselves distinct
                    since the first colonization. It is admitted that they speak the English
                    language with more purity than the lower classes in any other part of the
                    island.</p>
                <p>One member of parliament is chosen by the freeholders for the county, and the
                    polling-places are Haverford West, Pembroke, Narberth, Fishguard, Newport,
                    Tenby, and Mathry. The towns of Milford, Pembroke, Tenby, and the ancient
                    borough of Wiston, elect one member amongst them.</p>
                <p>St David’s, the see of a bishop, is a miserable collection of cottages, in the
                    midst of traces of ancient, extensive, and numerous buildings. The object
                    deserving of most notice is the cathedral, the antiquity of which is very great,
                    having been originally built about the year 1180, and enlarged in 1280 and 1328.
                    The bishop’s palace is a magnificent pile, not far from the cathedral, on the
                    opposite side of the river Alan. It was originally a quadrangular building of
                    great extent, of which at present only one side remains entire.</p>
                <p>Amongst the ancient buildings in this county, the most remarkable are Carew
                    Castle, on a creek of Milford Haven; Manorbeer, the mansion of the Barry family,
                    of which Giraldus Cambrensis was a member; and Killgarran, on <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193493479" xml:id="kp-eb0717-3479-0184"/>the river Tivy, the massy
                    towers and fragmented bastions of which present a most imposing spectacle.</p>
                <p>The picturesque beauties of this county, the mildness of the air, and the
                    abundance of every thing, have induced many gentlemen to select it as the place
                    of their residence. The houses of this description are therefore too numerous to
                    be mentioned; but amongst the more ancient proprietors who have splendid seats
                    are, Lord Milford, Sir John Owen, Lord Kensington, Lord Cawdor, and several
                    others.</p>
                <p>The population of the county amounted in 1801 to 56,280, in 1811 to 60,615, in
                    1821 to 74,009, and in 1831 to 80,900. The annual value of the real property, as
                    assessed in 1815 for the property tax, was L.219,589.</p>
                <p>According to the returns of the year 1831, the families chiefly employed in
                    agriculture were 7974; those chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and
                    handicraft, were 4510; and those comprised in neither of the preceding classes
                    were 4102. The number of males under twenty years of age was 18,356. The
                    occupiers employing labourers were 1842, and the occupiers not employing
                    labourers were 1864. The labourers employed in agriculture were 6075. Persons
                    employed in manufactures or manufacturing machinery were 131; those employed in
                    retail trade, or in handicraft, or masters, or as workmen, 4785; capitalists,
                    bankers, professional and other educated men, 605; labourers employed in labour
                    not agricultural, 1599; other males under twenty years of age (except servants),
                    1124; male servants, twenty years of age, 331; male servants under twenty years
                    of age, 219; female servants under twenty years of age, 4929. The towns and
                    their population which exceed 2000 persons are, Pembroke, 6511; Haverford West,
                    3915; Narberth, 2589; St David’s (city), 2388; Tenby, 2128; and Dogmels,
                    2109.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
