<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-4090-0231-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERICLES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 231</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:975732">Intellect</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4377609d">Intellect</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193494090" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERICLES</label>, one of the most celebrated of the Greek
                    statesmen, was a native of Athens, and descended, both by the father and
                    mother’s side, from the most distinguished families of that city. His father
                    Zanthippus had been concerned in the prosecution of the great Miltiades, and
                    commanded the fleet which defeated the Persians at Mycale, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b. c.</hi> 479. He married Agariste, the niece of Cleisthenes, the chief of the
                    noble family of the Alemaeonidae, and the leader of the party which had expelled
                    the Pisistratidae. It is not known in what year Pericles was born; but as he
                    began to take part in public affairs about <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 469,
                    it could scarcely be later than <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 490. He died in
                    the autumn of B. c. 431, in the third year of the Peloponnesian war. He studied
                    under the ablest masters that Athens could then furnish. Anaxagoras of
                    Clazomenae, whose force of understanding and extent of knowledge had acquired
                    him the appellation of Intellect <hi rend="italic">(νους),</hi> was the
                    philosopher to whom he was chiefly indebted for the cultivation of his mental
                    powers; but he also derived instruction from Zeno, the founder of the Eleatic
                    school of philosophy, and from Damon, who, professing only music, was considered
                    as the ablest speculative politician that Athens then produced. It is said that
                    the young Pericles resembled much, both in person and voice, the tyrant
                    Pisistratus, and this prevented him for some time from taking any part in public
                    business. But when Aristides was dead, Themistocles banished, and Cimon employed
                    in distant military expeditions, Pericles ventured to make his appearance before
                    the people about <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 469; and his eloquence soon
                    enabled him to acquire great influence over them. Although his inclination and
                    feelings might have led him to unite himself to the aristocratical party, his
                    interest and his peculiar talents made him solicit the favour of the people, and
                    he became in course of time the leader of the popular faction. He concurred in
                    the policy of his party in procuring, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 461, the
                    banishment of Cimon; and he also exerted himself to reduce the dignity of the
                    Areiopagus, one of those measures which proved in <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193494103" xml:id="kp-eb0717-4103-0232"/>the end fatal to the Athenian
                    constitution, as it tended to leave the power of the democracy without
                    control.</p>
                <p>The increased expenses of the government rendered it necessary that some means
                    should be adopted to improve the income of the state. Pericles proposed that the
                    common treasury of the confederacy, at the head of which Athens stood, should be
                    removed from Delos to Athens. This fund was intended to provide the means of
                    defence against any attack on Greece by a foreign enemy, more particularly by
                    the Persians; and a small yearly assessment was made on each of the confederate
                    states for this purpose. By the will of the Athenians this assessment was
                    increased; and it was determined that the tribunals of Athens should decide all
                    disputes which might arise respecting it. These measures were by no means fair,
                    but the supremacy of Athens by sea made any opposition to its demands at present
                    hopeless. Pericles took part in all the proceedings of his party, although he
                    had not yet acquired the chief control in the state. He was present at the
                    battle of Tanagra, B. c. 457, and distinguished himself the more as he had
                    insisted that Cimon,,who had offered his services, should not be allowed to be
                    present on the occasion. The Athenians, however, were defeated, and obliged to
                    retire. In their distress they began to turn their eyes towards Cimon, and it
                    seems to have been thought advisable by the popular party that he should be
                    recalled. Pericles himself moved the decree, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi>
                    456, and Cimon returned to Athens, after the expiration of only five years of
                    the term of his banishment. On the death of Cimon in Cyprus, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 449, Pericles was left nearly without a rival; and
                    the nobility thought it necessary that they should bring forward some one to
                    oppose his monopoly of power. Thucydides, son of Melesias, brother-in-law of
                    Cimon, was the person to whom they looked; and, by his abilities, his rank, and
                    his conduct through life, he was certainly entitled to high consideration. The
                    two parties now gradually separated; and they never afterwards coalesced, as
                    they had done under Cimon. A war of words was carried on; but we have little
                    account of it, except the anecdote in which Thucydides candidly acknowledges the
                    superiority of his rival: “When I wrestle with Pericles,” he said, “if I throw
                    him ever so decidedly, he can persuade the spectators that he threw me.”</p>
                <p>It was about this time that some Boeotians, who had been driven from their
                    country in consequence of the Athenian conquest, contrived to get possession of
                    Orchomenos, Chaeroneia, and some other towns in that neighbourhood. The Athenian
                    army under Tolmides easily dispossessed them, but on its return it was attacked
                    by another party of exiles at Coronea, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 447, and
                    entirely defeated, with the death of the general. The revolt of Euboea was the
                    immediate consequence of this defeat; and an army under Pericles had scarcely
                    landed upon the island, when intelligence reached him that the adverse party in
                    Megara had risen, and, with the assistance of Corinth, had overpowered the
                    Athenian garrison, and driven it out of the city. Rumours of an intended
                    invasion of Attica by the Spartans were likewise brought to him. Pericles led
                    back his army from Euboea, defeated the Megareans, and compelled them to confine
                    themselves within the walls of their city. The attack of the Spartans did not
                    take place till the following spring, and Pericles was believed to have
                    succeeded in bribing the Spartan general CJeandrides to withdraw his troops, as
                    he retreated without striking a blow. Pericles then returned to Euboea, and the
                    whole island was quickly reduced. The insecure tenure of the Athenian power
                    induced the leading men to seek an accommodation with Sparta, even on conditions
                    that were highly disadvantageous. They had already lost Boeotia, and they now
                    agreed to give up all pretensions to Megara and its territory, to withdraw their
                    garrisons from Troe zen in Argolis, and to afford no assistance whatever to the
                    democratical party in Achaia. On these conditions, a truce for thirty years was
                    concluded, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 445, between the two states. The two
                    parties in Athens were now left at liberty to contend with each other; and as
                    neither was willing to concede any thing to its rival, matters soon came to a
                    crisis, and Pericles succeeded in procuring the banishment, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b. c.</hi> 444, of Thucydides, by ostracism. From that moment Pericles became
                    the master of Athens and all her dependencies.</p>
                <p>The administration of Pericles lasted for fifteen years; and though the seeds of
                    future evils were then plentifully sown, it was a period during which arts,
                    science, and taste reached a perfection which no country has ever surpassed. The
                    policy, not less than the inclination, of Pericles, led him to encourage them,
                    as he found it easier to direct the will and caprices of the sovereign people
                    whilst he excited their admiration by the magnificence of his undertakings.
                    Nothing seems more wonderful than the expedition with which works of stupendous
                    magnitude, and of inimitable beauty, were completed. Many edifices, each of
                    which might have required the labour of many successive ages, were finished
                    during the administration of one prosperous man. The celebrated Phidias was the
                    superintendent to whose taste and skill the whole management was intrusted; and
                    the perfection of design, and even of workmanship, can still be appreciated from
                    the reliques, after a lapse of more than two thousand years. The Parthenon was
                    erected under his eye; and it is by no means unlikely that we may still possess
                    many of his designs in the bas-reliefs which have been transferred from that
                    temple, and now form the most valuable part of the British Museum. Whilst
                    Phidias was employed in executing works of sculpture, Zeuxis and Parrhasius were
                    not less eminent in painting; and Aeschylus, Sophocles, and Euripides were
                    calling forth the plaudits of the Athenians by those tragedies which still
                    equally excite our admiration. To this love of the fine arts Pericles added
                    eloquence, such as was fitted to control the passions of a multitude, and an
                    assiduity in public business which never flagged. His integrity, too, was never
                    once called in question; and though he had unlimited control over the public
                    revenues for so long a period, at his death it was found that his private
                    property was even less than when he had received it from his father. Although he
                    was the constant object of satire to the comic poets, and both his person and
                    administration were daily attacked with the severest invectives, he stood firm
                    in the affections of the people, who appear to have never for a moment wavered.
                    It was the chief object of his policy to keep the people either amused or
                    employed; and for this purpose he sent out during peace a squadron of sixty
                    galleys, to exercise for eight months every year. He got rid of the more
                    restless citizens by sending them to various colonies; and it was under his
                    direction that the colony of Thurium, in the south of Italy, was settled, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 443, whither went Herodotus and the orator
                    Lysias.</p>
                <p>The first interruption of the peace arose from a dispute between two Asiatic
                    states of the Athenian confederacy, Samos and Miletus, who each claimed the
                    sovereignty over Priene, and it was found impossible to settle the dispute
                    without having recourse to arms. Miletus finding itself worsted, applied to the
                    Athenians for assistance, which Pericles thought proper to grant. His enemies
                    asserted that he was induced to come to this decision by a wish to gratify his
                    mistress Aspasia, a native of Miletus, and one of the most celebrated women of
                    ancient times. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Aspasia.)</hi> There are sufficient
                    reasons assigned, however, why the Athenians should have interfered, without
                    supposing that Pericles was swayed by any thing but a regard for the interests
                    of his country. He led a considerable fleet, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi>
                    440, against the Samians; and, after a nine <pb break="no" facs="nls:193494116"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0717-4116-0233"/>months’ siege, they were compelled to capitulate.
                    Pericles returned with increased popularity, and gained much applause from the
                    eloquence with which he pronounced the funeral oration over those who had fallen
                    in battle. The historian Thucydides does not mention what part Pericles took in
                    those measures which eventually led to the Peloponnesian war; but Plutarch
                    asserts that he was the sole author of that contest. It is said that the people
                    were beginning to show some symptoms of dissatisfaction with his sway, and were
                    listening readily to all accusations against his friends. Phidias had been
                    thrown into prison, and had there died, not without suspicion of poison. Aspasia
                    had been accused and acquitted only through the great exertions of Pericles; and
                    he hgd found it necessary to recommend to his friend Anaxagoras to retire from
                    Athens for a time, as he was not certain that he could protect him from the
                    malice of his enemies. He knew that upon any critical emergency they must have
                    recourse to him; and, to withdraw the attention of the people from himself and
                    friends, it is said he used every means to fan the flame of war, and to prevent
                    all possibility of an arrangement between the Spartans and Athenians. When war
                    at last was determined on, <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> 431, Pericles took
                    the whole direction of it on himself, and, thinking it hazardous to venture a
                    battle against the united forces of the Peloponnesians, kept the Athenians
                    within the fortifications of the'city. The crowded state of the city, from the
                    peasants who had fled before the enemy, and an insufficiency of food, were the
                    main causes probably of that pestilential disease which broke out with such
                    violence in Athens during the second year of the war, and which is so
                    graphically described by the historian Thucydides (ii.). The Athenians now lost
                    all patience, and wreaked their vengeance upon Pericles, by imposing a fine of
                    fifteen talents on him. At the same time that his influence with the people was
                    thus diminished, he was suffering much from the calamities which had befallen
                    many of his relations, and from a misunderstanding which had for some time
                    prevailed in his own family. He had originally married one of his own relations,
                    but as their dispositions were by no means suited to each other, they had
                    separated, after having two sons, Xanthippus and Paralus. Pericles then lived
                    with Aspasia, towards whom he bore the tenderest regard. Xanthippus was
                    naturally extravagant, and had married a young and expensive wife, who was
                    unwilling to brook the frugality of her father-in-law. They lived therefore in a
                    constant state of irritation with Pericles, and took every opportunity of
                    annoying him. Xanthippus was carried off by the plague, as well as many other of
                    his relations. Pericles bore up against all his misfortunes until the death of
                    Paralus, his last surviving legitimate son, which completely subdued his
                    unbending spirit, and he gave up all attention to public business. It was soon
                    found, however, that no one was capable of filling his place, and the people
                    again solicited Pericles to re-assume the reins of government. To this he
                    acceded; and one of the first favours that he asked was, that they would allow
                    him to enrol a natural son in his tribe, and thereby make him legitimate. In
                    compassion for his misfortunes this was granted, and his son, Pericles, was
                    afterwards one of the ten commanders in the naval engagement of Arginusae.
                    Pericles was soon after this seized with the plague, and died in the year 428 B.
                    c. to the great regret of the Athenians. He is said to have left nothing in
                    writing, except some public decrees. (Thucydides, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Peloponnesian War</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Plutarch, <hi rend="italic">Life
                    of Pericles.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
