<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-4051-0228-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERGAMUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 228</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193494051" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERGAMUS</label>, an ancient kingdom of Asia, formed out of
                    the ruins of the empire of Alexander the Great. It commenced about the year 283
                    before our era. The first sovereign was one Philetaerus, an eunuch, by birth a
                    Paphlagonian, a man of mean descent, and in his youth a menial servant to
                    Antigonus, one of Alexander’s captains. He afterwards served Lysimachus, king of
                    Macedonia and Thrace, who appointed him keeper of his treasures lodged in
                    Pergamus. Whilst he held this employment, having fallen under the displeasure of
                    Arsinoe, wife of Lysimachus, she found means to excite a quarrel between him and
                    his master; upon which Philetaerus seized on the castle of Pergamus, together
                    with the treasures intrusted to his care, amounting to ninety thousand talents.
                    At first he offered his service, together with his treasure, to Seleucus, the
                    king of Syria; but both Seleucus and Lysimachus dying soon afterwards, he kept
                    possession of the town and treasure until his death, which happened twenty years
                    after his revolt from Lysimachus.</p>
                <p>Philetaerus left the city of Pergamus to his brother, or, according to some, to
                    his brother’s son, Eumenes the First, who, laying hold of the opportunity
                    offered by the dissensions amongst the Seleucidae, possessed himself j)f many
                    strongholds in the province of Asia; and, having hired a body of Galatians,
                    defeated Antiochus as he was returning from a victory gained over his brother
                    Seleucus Callinicus. By this victory he obtained possession of the greater part
                    of Asia. But he did not long enjoy his acquisitions; for he died next year of
                    immoderate drinking, a vice to which he was greatly addicted.</p>
                <p>Eumenes was succeeded by Attalus the First, nephew of Philetaerus, who, on his
                    accession, assumed the title of king of Pergamus. He defeated the Gauls, who
                    seemed desirous of settling in his territory; and, according to Livy, he was the
                    first of the Asiatic princes who refused to pay a contribution to these
                    barbarians. When Selèucus Cera-nus<pb break="no" facs="nls:193494064"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0717-4064-0229"/> was engaged in other wars, he invaded his
                    territories, and conquered all the provinces on the Anatolian side of the
                    Taurus; but was soon driven out of his new acquisitions by Seleucus and his
                    grandfather Achaeus, who, entering into an alliance against him, deprived him of
                    all his newly-acquired territories, and even besieged him in his capital. Upon
                    this Attalus invited to his assistance the Gauls who had settled in Thrace; and
                    with their help he not only obliged the enemy to raise the siege of Pergamus,
                    but quickly recovered all the provinces he had lost. After this he invaded Ionia
                    and the neighbouring provinces, where several cities voluntarily submitted to
                    his sway. The Teians, Colophonians, and the inhabitants of Aegea and Lemnos,
                    sent deputies declaring themselves ready to acknowledge him as their sovereign;
                    and the Carsenes, on the other side of the river Lycus, opened their gates to
                    him, having first expelled the governor placedover them by Achaeus. Thence he
                    advanced to Apia, and encamping on the banks of the river Megithus, received
                    homage from the neighbouring nations. But here the Gauls, being frightened by an
                    eclipse of the moon, refused to proceed farther; a circumstance which obliged
                    Attalus to return to the Hellespont, where he allowed his allies to settle,
                    giving them a large and fruitful territory, and promising that he would always
                    assist and protect them to the utmost of his power.</p>
                <p>Attalus having thus settled his affairs with equal honour and advantage to
                    himself, entered into an alliance with the Romans, and afterwards joined them in
                    their war against Philip, king of Macedonia. Here he had the command of the
                    Rhodian fleet, with which he not only drove the Macedonians quite out of the
                    Greek seas, but having landed his men, he, in conjunction with the Athenians,
                    invaded Macedonia, and obliged Philip to raise the siege of Athens, which he had
                    greatly distressed. For these services the Athenians not only heaped on him all
                    the favours they could bestow, but called one of their tribes by his name; an
                    honour which they had never before bestowed upon any foreigner.</p>
                <p>Attalus now attempted to organise a general confederacy of the Greeks against
                    Philip. But whilst he was haranguing the Boeotians with a view to this object,
                    and exhorting them with great vehemence to enter into an alliance with the
                    Romans against their common enemy, he fell down speechless. However, having
                    somewhat recovered, he desired to be carried by sea from Thebes to Pergamus,
                    where he died soon after his arrival, in the seventy-second year of his age and
                    forty-third of his reign.</p>
                <p>Attalus was succeeded by his eldest son Eumenes the Second. The latter was
                    exceedingly attached to the Romans, insomuch that he refused the daughter of
                    Antiochus the Great in marriage, lest he should thus be led into a quarrel with
                    that people. He also gave intimation to the Roman senate of the transactions of
                    Ariarathes, king of Cappadocia, who was making great preparations both by sea
                    and land. Nor did Eumenes stop here; for when he saw the war about to break out
                    between Antiochus and the Romans, he sent his brother Attalus to Rome in order
                    to give information of the proceedings of Antiochus. The senate heaped honours
                    both on Eumenes and his brother; and in the war which followed, they gave the
                    command of their fleet to the king of Pergamus, in conjunction with C. Livius
                    Salinator. The victory gained on this occasion was in a great measure owing to
                    Eumenes, who boarded some of the enemy’s ships in person, and during the whole
                    action behaved with uncommon bravery. Some time afterwards, Eumenes, having
                    entered the territories of Antiochus with a body of five thousand men, ravaged
                    all the country about Thyatira, and returned with an immense booty. But in the
                    mean time Antiochus invaded Pergamus in his turn, ravaged the whole country, and
                    even laid siege to the capital. Attalus, the king’s brother, held out with a
                    handful of men, until the Achaeans, who were in alliance with Eumenes, sent a
                    thousand foot and a hundred horse to his assistance. As this small body of
                    auxiliaries were all chosen men, and commanded by an experienced officer, they
                    behaved with such bravery that the Syrians were obliged to raise the siege. At
                    the battle of Magnesia, too, Eumenes behaved with the greatest bravery, not only
                    sustaining the first attack of the enemy’s elephants, but driving them back
                    again upon their own troops; which threw the ranks in disorder, and gave the
                    Romans an opportunity of giving them a total defeat, by attacking them
                    opportunely with their horse. In consequence of this defeat, Antiochus was
                    obliged to conclude a peace with the Romans on such terms as they pleased to
                    prescribe; one of which was, that he should pay Eumenes four hundred talents,
                    and a quantity of corn, in recompense for the damage he had done to that
                    prince.</p>
                <p>Soon after this Eumenes was engaged in a contest with Prusias, king of Bithynia,
                    who made war upon him by the advice of Hannibal, the celebrated Carthaginian
                    general. But Eumenes, being assisted by the Romans, defeated Prusias in an
                    engagement by sea, and another by land; disasters which so disheartened him,
                    that he was ready to accept of peace on any terms. However, before the treaty
                    was concluded, Hannibal found means to draw into the confederacy Philip of
                    Macedonia, who sent Philocles, an old and experienced officer, with a
                    considerable body of troops, to join Prusias. Eumenes then sent his brother
                    Attalus to Rome with a golden crown, worth fifteen thousand talents, to complain
                    of Prusias for making war on the allies of the Roman people without any
                    provocation. The senate accepted the present, and promised to adjust every thing
                    to the satisfaction of their friend Eumenes, whom they looked upon as the most
                    steady ally they could boast of in Asia. But in the mean time, Prusias, having
                    ventured another sea-fight, gained a complete victory by a contrivance of
                    Hannibal. The greatest part of the ships of Eumenes were burned, several were
                    taken, and the others were so much shattered that they became quite
                    unserviceable. The same year Prusias gained over Eumenes two remarkable
                    victories by land, both of which were entirely owing to stratagems of Hannibal.
                    But, whilst matters were thus going on to the disadvantage of Eumenes, the
                    Romans interfered, and by their deputies not only put an end to the differences
                    between the two kings, but prevailed on Prusias to betray Hannibal; upon which
                    the illustrious fugitive poisoned himself.</p>
                <p>Eumenes being thus freed from such a dangerous enemy, engaged in a new war with
                    the kings of Cappadocia and Pontus, in which also he proved victorious. His
                    friendship for the Romans he carried to such a degree of enthusiasm, that he
                    went in person to Rome to inform them of the machinations of Perses king of
                    Macedonia. He had before quarrelled with the Rhodians, who sent ambassadors to
                    Rome to complain of him. But as the ambassadors happened to arrive whilst the
                    king himself was present in the city, the Rhodian ambassadors could not obtain
                    any hearing, and Eumenes was dismissed with new marks of favour. This journey,
                    however, had almost proved fatal to him; for, on his return, as he was going
                    toperform a sacrifice at Delphi, two assassins, sent by Perses, rolled down two
                    great stones upon him as he entered the straits of the mountains. By one of
                    these he was dangerously wounded on the head, and by the other he received a
                    contusion on the shoulder. In consequence of the blows, he fell from a steep
                    place, and thus received so many other bruises, that when he was carried on
                    board his ship it could not well be known whether he was dead or alive. His
                    people, however, finding that he was still alive, conveyed him to Corinth, and
                    from Corinth to Aegina, having caused their vessels to be carried over the
                    isthmus.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193494077" xml:id="kp-eb0717-4077-0230"/>
                <p>Eumenes remained at Aegina till his wounds were cured, which was done with so
                    great secrecy, that a report of his death was spread all over Asia, and even
                    believed at Rome; nay, his brother Attalus was so convinced of the truth of this
                    report, that he not only assumed the government, but even married Stratonice the
                    wife of Eumenes. But in a short time Eumenes convinced both parties of his being
                    alive, by returning to his kingdom. On receiving this intelligence, Attalus
                    resigned the sovereignty in great haste, and went to meet his brother, carrying
                    a halberd, as one of his guards. Eumenes received both him and the queen with
                    great tenderness; only it is said he whispered in his brother’s ear when he
                    first saw him, “Be in no haste to marry my wife again till you are sure I am
                    dead.”</p>
                <p>The king joined the Romans in their war against Perses; but during the course of
                    it he suddenly cooled in his affection towards those allies whom he had hitherto
                    served with so much zeal, and that to such a degree that he admitted ambassadors
                    from Perses, and offered to remain neutral if the latter would pay him a
                    thousand talents, and, for fifteen hundred, to influence the Romans to grant him
                    a safe and honourable peace. But these negociations were broken off, by reason
                    of the distrust which these two kings had of each other. Eumenes would not trust
                    Perses unless he paid him the money beforehand; whilst, on the other hand,
                    Perses did not care to part with the money until Eumenes had first performed
                    what he promised; neither could he be induced to pay the sum in question, though
                    the king of Pergamus offered to give hostages for the due performance of his
                    promise. These negociations were as long as possible concealed from the Romans;
                    but they at length came to be known, after which the republic began to entertain
                    no little jealousy of their old friend, and therefore heaped favours upon his
                    brother Attalus. Eumenes had sent him to Rome to congratulate the senate on the
                    happy issue of the war with Perses, not thinking that his own practices had been
                    discovered. However, the senate, without taking any notice of their disaffection
                    towards Eumenes, entertained Attalus with the greatest magnificence; then
                    several of the senators who visited him proceeded to acquaint him with their
                    suspicions of the king, and desired Attalus to treat with them in his own name,
                    assuring him that the kingdom of Pergamus would be granted him by the senate if
                    he demanded it. Eumenes, alarmed at these proceedings, resolved to proceed in
                    person to Rome, in order to justify himself. But the senate having already
                    condemned him in their own minds, resolved not to hear his vindication, and made
                    an act that no king should be permitted to enter the gates of Rome. Eumenes, who
                    knew nothing of this, set forward on his journey, and landed at Brundusium; but
                    no sooner did the Roman senate receive intelligence of his arrival, than they
                    sent ∙a quaestor to acquaint him with the decree of the senate, and at the same
                    time to apprise him, that if he had any business to transact with the senate, he
                    was appointed to hear it, and transmit it to them, but if not, that the king
                    must leave Italy without delay. To this Eumenes replied, that he had no business
                    of any consequence to transact, and that he did not stand in need of any of
                    their assistance; and, without saying a word more, went on board his ship, and
                    returned to Pergamus. On his return, the Gauls, encouraged by the cold reception
                    which he had met with at Rome, invaded his territories, but were repulsed with
                    great loss. This produced new complaints at Rome, and Eumenes was accused of
                    keeping up a secret correspondence with the king of Macedonia; and the senators
                    having conceived the most implacable hatred against him, seemed absolutely bent
                    on his destruction, when he died, in the thirty-ninth year of his reign, leaving
                    his kingdom and his wife to his brother Attalus.</p>
                <p>Attalus, in the commencement of his reign, found himself greatly distressed by
                    Prusias king of Bithynia, who not only overthrew him in a pitched battle, but
                    advanced to the very walls of Pergamus, ravaging the country as he marched
                    along, and at last reduced the royal city itself. The king, however, saved
                    himself by a timely flight, and despatched ambassadors to Rome, complaining of
                    the conduct of Prusias. The latter endeavoured to defend himself, and to throw
                    the blame on Attalus. But, after a proper inquiry was made into the matter,
                    Prusias was found to be entirely in the wrong, and was at last obliged to
                    conclude a peace with his adversary upon the following terms, viz. that he
                    should immediately deliver up to Attalus twenty ships with decks; that he should
                    pay five hundred talents to Attalus within the space of twenty years; that he
                    should pay a hundred talents to some of the other Asiatic nations, by way of
                    reparation for the damages they had sustained from him; and that both parties
                    should be content with what they had possessed before the beginning of the war.
                    The last enterprise in which we find Attalus engaged was against Andriseus, the
                    pretended son of Perses, .king of Macedonia, in which he assisted the Romans.
                    After this he gave himself up to ease and luxury, committing state affairs
                    entirely to his ministers; and thus continued till his death, which happened in
                    the eighty-second year of his age, and about 138 years before our era.</p>
                <p>Attalus the Second was succeeded by Attalus the Third, the son of Eumenes; for
                    the late king, considering that he only held the crown as a trust for his
                    nephew, passed by his own children in order to give it to him, though he appears
                    to have been by no means worthy of it. He is said to have been deprived of his
                    senses through the violence of his grief for his mother’s death; and, indeed,
                    throughout bis whole reign, he behaved more like a madman than a person of sane
                    mind. On the death of this tyrant, a will was found, by which he left the Roman
                    people heirs of all his goods; upon which they seized on the kingdom, and
                    reduced it to a province of their empire by the name of Asia Proper. But
                    Aristonicus, a son of Eumenes by an Ephesian courtesan, reckoning himself the
                    lawful heir to the crown, and being by no means satisfied with this usurpation
                    of the Romans, assembled a considerable army in order to maintain his
                    pretensions. The people in general, having been accustomed to a monarchy,
                    dreaded a republican form of government; and having, in consequence, assisted
                    Aristonicus, they soon put him in a condition to reduce the whole kingdom to
                    obedience. The news, however, were speedily carried to Rome; and Licinius
                    Crassus, the pontifex maximus, was sent into the East, with orders to enforce
                    submission to the king’s will. Historians take no notice of any forces which
                    were sent along with this commander; from which it is supposed, that he depended
                    on assistance from the Asiatics, who were in alliance with Rome, or from the
                    Egyptians. But when he went thither, he found both the Syrians and Egyptians so
                    reduced that he could not expect any assistance from them. However, he was soon
                    supplied with troops by the kings of Pontus, Bithynia, Cappadocia, and
                    Paphlagonia; but he managed matters so ill that he was entirely defeated and
                    taken prisoner. Those who took him designed to carry him to Aristonicus; but
                    Crassus, not being able to endure the disgrace, would have laid violent hands on
                    himself if he had not been disarmed.</p>
                <p>∕∖,ristonicus did not long enjoy the fruits of his victory. Indeed he behaved
                    very improperly after it; for, instead of preparing to oppose the next army,
                    which he might have been assured the Romans would send against him, he spent his
                    time in feasting and revelling. But he was soon roused out of his lethargy by
                    Perpenna, the new consul, who having assembled with incredible expedition the
                    troops of the allies, came unexpectedly upon him, obliged him to venture an
                    engagement at a disadvantage, and entirely defeated him. Aristonicus fled to a
                    city called <pb break="no" facs="nls:193494090" xml:id="kp-eb0717-4090-0231"
                    />Stratonice, but was so closely pursued by the conqueror, that the garrison,
                    having no means of supplying themselves with provisions, delivered up their
                    leader, as well as a philosopher named Blosius, who had been the companion and
                    counsellor of Aristonicus. The philosopher behaved with great resolution after
                    being taken, and openly defended his siding with Aristonicus, because he thought
                    his cause just. He exhorted the latter to prevent the disgrace and misery of
                    captivity by a voluntary death; but Aristonicus, looking upon death as a greater
                    misery than any captivity, suffered himself to be treated as his conquerors
                    pleased.</p>
                <p>In the mean time, a new consul, named Manius Aquilius, having arrived from Rome,
                    sent a haughty message to Perpenna, requiring him immediately to deliver up
                    Aristonicus as a captive belonging to his triumph when the war should be ended.
                    with this demand Perpenna refused to comply, and his refusal had almost produced
                    a civil war; but this was prevented by the death of Perpenna, which happened
                    soon after the dispute commenced. The Pergamenians, notwithstanding the defeat
                    and captivity of their leader, still held out with such obstinacy, that Aquilius
                    was obliged to besiege, and take by force, almost every city in the kingdom. At
                    last, however, the whole country being reduced, Aquilius triumphed, and the
                    unhappy Aristonicus, being led in chains before his chariot, probably ended his
                    miserable life in a dungeon.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
