<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-1971-0068-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PARDON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 68</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1053286">Pardon</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1112660">Sentimentalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47m0428c">Pardon</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193491971" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PARDON</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Criminal Law,</hi> is
                    the remitting or forgiving an offence committed against the king.</p>
                <p>Law, says Beccaria, cannot be framed on principles of compassion to guilt; yet
                    justice, by the CQnstitution of England, is bound to be administered in mercy.
                    This is promised by the king in his coronation oath; and it is that act of his
                    government which is the most personal and most entirely his own. The king
                    condemns no man; that unpleasant task he leaves to his courts of justice; the
                    great operation of his sceptre is mercy. His power of pardoning was said by the
                    Saxons to be derived <hi rend="italic">a lege suae dignitatis ς</hi> and it is
                    declared in parliament, by stat. 27 Henry VIII. c. 24, that no other person has
                    power to pardon or remit any treason or felonies whatsoever, but that the king
                    has the whole and sole power thereof, united and knit to the imperial crown of
                    this realm.</p>
                <p>Mr Godwin, in his Inquiry concerning Political Justice, attacks this prerogative
                    in the following terms: “What is the rule that ought in all cases to prescribe
                    to my conduct? Surely justice; understanding by justice the greatest utility of
                    the whole mass of things that may be influenced by my conduct. What then is
                    clemency? It can be nothing but the pitiable egotism of him who imagines he can
                    do something better than justice. Is it right that I should suffer constraint
                    for a certain offence? The rectitude of my suffering must be founded on its
                    tendency to promote the general welfare. He therefore that pardons me,
                    iniquitously prefers the imaginary interest of an individual, and utterly
                    neglects what he owes to the whole. He bestows that which I ought not to
                    receive, and which he has no right to give. Is it right, on the contrary, that I
                    should not undergo the suffering in question? Will he, by rescuing me from
                    suffering, do a benefit to me, and no injury to others? He will then be a
                    notorious delinquent, if he allow me to suffer. There is indeed a considerable
                    defect in this last supposition. If, while he benefits me, he do no injury
                    toothers, he is infallibly performing a public<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193491984" xml:id="kp-eb0717-1984-0069"/> service. If I suffered in
                    the arbitrary manner which the supposition includes, the whole would sustain an
                    unquestionable injury in the injustice that was perpetrated. And yet the man who
                    prevents this odious injustice has been accustomed to arrogate to himself the
                    attribute of clement, and the apparently sublime, but in reality tyrannical,
                    name of forgiveness. For, if he do more than has been here described, instead of
                    glory he ought to take shame to himself, as an enemy to the interest of human
                    kind. If every action, and especially every action in which the happiness of a
                    rational being is concerned, be susceptible of a certain rule, then caprice must
                    be in all cases excluded; there can be no action which, if I neglect, I shall
                    have discharged my duty; and if I perform, I shall be entitled to applause.”</p>
                <p>That human nature is such as in the aggregate to need control, no one who is
                    acquainted with it will deny; and there appears to be no other method of
                    controlling mankind but by general laws, which, through the natural imperfection
                    of human affairs, may be cruel in one case if they are just in another. Cases
                    may likewise occur where the sentence of the law, without its execution, will
                    answer every purpose which could be expected from it, and where the execution of
                    it would be extreme cruelty, although it might in strict unfeeling language be
                    called justice, because in strict conformity with the letter of the law. Yet
                    though such cases may and do often occur, it would be absurd to abolish any of
                    those laws which the security of civil society has required; and therefore the
                    only natural remedy against legal injustice is the system of pardons.</p>
                <p>Mr Godwin next goes on to trace the origin of pardons; and instead of a definite
                    system of law, we are told that it is necessary to have a court of reason, to
                    which the decisions of a court of law shall be brought for révisai. But this is
                    a remedy apparently too vague and indeterminate to produce any lasting or good
                    effect; for the proposal of such a tribunal results from supposing mankind more
                    virtuous and intelligent than they really are. He next proceeds to consider the
                    abuses of pardons, whence he would draw an argument for their abolition. He
                    tells us that the authority in this case is placed, first in the judge, and next
                    in the king and council. . “Now,” says he, “laying aside the propriety or
                    impropriety of this particular selection, there is one grievous abuse which
                    ought to strike the most superficial observer. Those persons with whom the
                    principal trust is reposed consider their functions in this respect as a matter
                    purely incidental, exercise them with supineness, and in many instances with the
                    most scanty materials to guide their judgment. This grows in a considerable
                    degree out of the very name of pardon, which implies a work of supererogatory
                    benevolence.”</p>
                <p>But it is obvious that pardons are in general granted in consequence of an
                    application from people who have more than scanty materials to guide their
                    judgments, and on whose fidelity in relating the circumstances of the case
                    confidence is or is not placed, according to their several characters. Mr Godwin
                    next proceeds to the arbitrary character of pardons. “Such a system,” he says,
                    “to speak it truly, is a lottery of death, in which each man draws his ticket
                    for reprieve or execution, as undefinable accidents shall decide.” The allusion
                    here to a lottery ticket is peculiarly unfortunate, nor does the whole sentence
                    show any great degree of candour. It is possible to define a particular crime,
                    and to annex a particular punishment to the commission of it; but the nature of
                    morality consists not in the external action, but in the motives which prompted
                    to it. Definite law, however, cannot always make this distinction; and after the
                    sentence of the law is pronounced, it comes to be considered whether there are
                    any alleviating circumstances in the case; and whether there are or not, must
                    depend on the particulars or accidents of the case. But it is impossible to
                    suppose that these accidents could be previously defined; their nature does not
                    admit of it. To particularize and define every mode of an action which
                    imagination can conceive, or which experience has shown us may happen, would
                    indeed be an Herculean labour; and we might literally say with the apostle,
                    “that the world could not contain the books that might be written.” We are,
                    however, told that “reason is a thousand times more explicit and intelligible
                    than law; and when we are accustomed to consult her, the certainty of her
                    decisions would be such as men practised in our present courts are totally
                    unable to conceive.” Were reason, however, to be appealed to in all cases, and
                    to be the final criterion, it would leave far greater room for villany than any
                    mode at present in practice. Reason is a very uncertain and indefinite term, and
                    may be made any thing, according to the circumstances or passions of men, at any
                    given time.</p>
                <p>We are next told that pardons are destructive to morality. “Another very
                    important consequence,” says Mr Godwin, “grows out of the system of pardons. A
                    system of pardon is a system of unmitigated slavery. I am taught to expect a
                    certain desirable event. From what? From the clemency, the uncontrolled,
                    unmerited kindness of a fellow-mortal. Can any lesson be more degrading? The
                    pusillanimous servility of the man who devotes himself with everlasting
                    obsequiousness to another, because that other, having begun to be unjust,
                    relents in his career,—the ardour with which he confesses the rectitude of his
                    sentence and the enormity of his deserts,—will constitute a tale that future
                    ages will find it difficult to understand. What are the sentiments in this
                    respect that are alone worthy of a rational being? Give me that, and that only,
                    which without injustice you cannot refuse. More than justice it would be
                    disgraceful for me to ask, and for yon to bestow. I stand upon the foundation of
                    right. This is a title which brute force may refuse to acknowledge, but which
                    all the force in the world cannot annihilate. By resisting this plea you may
                    prove yourself unjust, but in yielding to it you grant me but my due. If, all
                    things considered, I be the fit subject of a benefit, the benefit is merited;
                    merit in any other sense is contradictory and absurd. If you bestow upon me
                    unmerited advantage, you are a recreant from the general good. I may be base
                    enough to thank you; but if I were virtuous I should condemn you. These
                    sentiments alone are consistent with true independence of mind. He that is
                    accustomed to regard virtue as an affair of favour and grace, cannot be
                    eminently virtuous. If he occasionally perform an action of apparent kindness,
                    he will applaud the generosity of his sentiments; and if he abstain, he will
                    acquit himself with the question, May I not do what I will with my own? In the
                    same manner, when he is treated benevolently by another, he will in the first
                    place be unwilling to examine strictly into the reasonableness of this
                    treatment, because benevolence, as he imagines, is not subject to any
                    inflexibility of rule; and, in the second place, he will not regard his
                    benefactor with that erect and unembarrassed mien, that complete sense of
                    equality, which is the only immoveable basis of virtue and happiness.”</p>
                <p>Such being Mr Godwin’s conclusion on this subject, we leave it with our readers
                    to determine whether his system or that which we at present enjoy would be the
                    more rigorous or unjust; or whether mankind have indeed arrived at so eminent a
                    pitch of virtue as to disdain every favour which they do not absolutely merit.
                    The Christian religion speaks a very different language.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
