<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-0720-0741-14" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PILATE, or Pontius Pilate</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 741</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1012480">Mattes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1010918">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193500720" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PILATE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Pontius Pilate</hi></label>,
                    was governor of Judaea when our Lord was crucified. Of his family or country we
                    know little, though it is believed that he was a native of Rome, or at least of
                    Italy. He was sent to govern Judaea in the room of Gratus, in the year 26 or 27
                    of the common era, and he governed this province for ten years, that is, from
                    the twelfth or thirteenth to the twenty-second or twenty-third year of Tiberius.
                    He is represented, both by Philo and by Josephus, as a man of an impetuous and
                    obstinate temper, and, as a judge, accustomed to sèll justice, and to pronounce
                    any sentence that was desired, provided he' was paid for it. The same authors
                    mention his rapines, his injuries, his murders, the torments he inflicted upon
                    the innocent, and the persons he put to death without any form of process.
                    Philo, in particular, describes him as a <pb break="no" facs="nls:193500733"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0717-0733-0742"/>man who exercised excessive cruelty during the
                    whole time of his government, disturbed the repose of Judaea, and gave occasion
                    to the troubles and revolt which followed. St Luke (xiii. I, 2, et seq.)
                    acquaints us that Pilate had mingled the blood of the Galileans with their
                    sacrifices, and that the matter having been related to our Lord, he said,
                    “Suppose ye that these Galileans were sinners above all the Galileans, because
                    they suffered such things? I tell you, nay; but except ye repent, ye shall all
                    likewise perish.” It is not known upon what particular occasion Pilate caused
                    these Galileans to be slain in the temple whilst they were sacrificing; for this
                    is the meaning of die expression about mingling their blood with their
                    sacrifices. Some think they were disciples of Judas the Gaulonite, who taught
                    that the Jews ought not to pay tribute to foreign princes, and that Pilate had
                    put some of them to death even in the temple; but there is no proof of this
                    fact. Others are of opinion that these Galileans were Samaritans, whom Pilate
                    cut to pieces in the village of Tira-taba,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Josephus, Antip Jud. lib. xviii. c. 5.</p></note> as they
                    were preparing to go up to Mount Gerizim, where a certain impostor had promised
                    to discover to them treasures; but this event did not happen before the year 35
                    of the common era, and consequently two years after the death of Jesus Christ.
                    At the time of our Saviour’s passion, Pilate made some faint endeavours to
                    rescue him out of the hands of the vindictive Jews. He knew that they had
                    delivered him up, and pursued his life with so much violence, solely out of
                    malice and envy (Matt, xxvii. 18). His wife, also, who had been disturbed the
                    night before with frightful dreams, sent to tell him that she desired him not to
                    meddle in the affair of that just person <hi rend="italic">(ibid.</hi> 19). He
                    attempted to appease the wrath of the Jews, and to give them some satisfaction,
                    by scourging our Lord (John, xix. 1; Matt, xxvii. 26). He also tried to take him
                    out of their hands by proposing to deliver him or Barabbas, on the day of the
                    festival of the passover. Lastly, he had a mind to discharge himself from
                    pronouncing judgment against him by sending him to Herod king <hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi> Galilee (Luke, xxiii. 7, 8). But when he saw that all this would not
                    satisfy the Jews, and that they even in a manner threatened him, saying he could
                    be no friend to the emperor if he let him go (John, xix. 12, 15), he caused
                    water to be brought, and having washed his hands before all the people, publicly
                    declared himself innocent of the blood of Jesus, in whom he found no fault
                    (Matt, xxvii. 23, 24); though at the same time this miserable juggler with
                    conscience delivered him up to his soldiers that they might crucify him. His
                    conduct, however, was sufficient to justify Jesus Christ, as Calmet observes,
                    and to show that the governor held him to be innocent; but it was not enough to
                    vindicate the conscience and integrity of a judge, whose duty it was to assert
                    the cause of oppressed innocence, as well as to punish the guilty and criminal.
                    He ordered to be inscribed on our Saviour’s cross an abstract as it were of his
                    sentence, and the motive of his condemnation, “Jesus of Nazareth, king of the
                    Jews,” which was written in Latin, Greek, and Hebrew. Some of the Jews found
                    fault with it, and remonstrated with Pilate, alleging that he ought to have
                    written “Jesus of Nazareth, who pretended to be king of the Jews.” But Pilate
                    could not be prevailed on to alter it, and gave them this peremptory answer,
                    that what he had written he had written.</p>
                <p>Towards evening, he was applied to for leave to take down the bodies from the
                    cross, that they might not continue there the following day, which was the
                    passover and the sabbath-day (John, xix. 31). This he allowed, and granted the
                    body of Jesus to Joseph of Arimathea, that he might pay to it his last duties
                    <hi rend="italic">(ibid.</hi> 33). Lastly, when the priests, who had solicited
                    the death of our Saviour, came to desire him to set a watch upon the sepulchre,
                    lest his disciples should steal him away by night, he answered them, that they
                    had a guard, and might place it there themselves (Matt, xxvii. 65). This is the
                    substance of what the gospel tells us concerning Pontius Pilate.</p>
                <p>Justin Martyr, Tertullian, Eusebius, and several other succeeding writers, both
                    ancient and modern, assure us that it was formerly the custom for Roman
                    magistrates to prepare copies of all verbal processes and judicial acts which
                    took place in their several provinces, and to send these to the emperor. Pilate,
                    therefore, in compliance with this custom, having sent intelligence to Tiberius
                    of what had passed relating to Jesus Christ, the emperor wrote an account of it
                    to the senate, in a manner which gave reason to infer that he thought favourably
                    of the religion of Jesus Christ, and showed that he had no §erious objection to
                    their decreeing him divine honours. But the senate was not of the same opinion,
                    and so the matter dropped. It appears, from what Justin says of these acts, that
                    the miracles of Jesus Christ were mentioned there, including even the
                    circumstance of the soldiers having divided his garments amongst them. Eusebius
                    insinuates that they spoke of his resurrection and ascension. Ter-tuilian and
                    Justin refer to these acts with so much confidence, that we cannot suppose them
                    to have written without authority. However, neither Eusebius nor St Jerome, who
                    were both inquisitive and intelligent persons, nor any other author who wrote
                    afterwards, seems to have seen these acts, at least not the true and original
                    acts; for as to those which we have now in great number, they are not authentic,
                    being neither ancient nor uniform. There are also some pretended letters of
                    Pilate to Tiberius, giving a history of our Saviour; but they are universally
                    allowed to be spurious.</p>
                <p>Pilate being a man who, by his excessive cruelties and rapine, had disturbed the
                    peace of Judaea during the whole time of his government, was at length deposed
                    by Vitellius, -the proconsul of Syria, in the 36th year of Jesus Christ, and
                    sent to Rome to give an account-of his conduct to the emperor. But though
                    Tiberius died before Pilate arrived at Rome, yet his successor Caligula banished
                    him to Vienne in Gaul, where he was reduced to such extremity that he put
                    himself to death with his own hands. The Evangelists call him governor, although
                    in reality he was only procurator of Judaea.</p>
                <p>With regard to Pilate’s wife, the general tradition is, that she was named
                    Claudia Procula or Proscula; and in relation to her dream, some are of opinion,
                    that as she had intelligence of our Lord’s apprehension, and knew by his
                    character that he was a righteous person, her imagination, being struck with
                    these ideas, had naturally produced the dream we read of; but others think that
                    this dream was sent to her providentially, for the clearer manifestation of our
                    Lord’s innocence.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
