<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-0772-0745-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PINDAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 745</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1066729">Plataea</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1043867">Odes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:937529">Games</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193500772" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PINDAR</label>, the most celebrated lyric poet that Greece
                    produced, was a native of Thebes in Boeotia, and born <hi rend="smallcaps">b.
                    c.</hi> 518, forty years before the expedition of Xerxes. He was the
                    contemporary of Aeschylus, but younger than Simonides, and somewhat older than
                    Bacchylides. It was scarcely to be expected that the early years of such a
                    distinguished poet should pass without some extraordinary event taking place,
                    and it is accordingly stated that he was exposed on a desert mountain, and that
                    he was fed by bees. Whether his father’s name was Diophantus or Scopelinus is
                    uncertain, but he was of the humble profession of a player on the flute, which
                    he at first intended that his son should pursue. Finding, however, that his
                    talents entitled him to occupy a higher position in the drama of life, he placed
                    him under Lasus of Hermione, a poet who then enjoyed a high reputation. Although
                    he lived in one of the most eventful periods of Grecian history, it does not
                    appear that he took any active part in the political struggles of his country.
                    It has been even doubted whether his feelings in favour of the liberty of Greece
                    were so ardent as to induce him to oppose the progress of the Persians. Before
                    the battle of Plataea a seditious movement had taken place in Thebes, and a
                    strong party had joined the Persians. In a passage of the poet written at this
                    period, Polybius imagines he can satisfactorily discover that Pindar was the
                    advocate of this step, and of course visits him with not unmerited reproach.
                    Stobaeus, however, gives this same passage more fully, and it there appears that
                    the poet recommends peace, not in reference to the Persians, but to his
                    fellow-citizens, who were tearing one another to pieces in civil broils. But a
                    still stronger proof that Polybius had taken a prejudiced view of his character,
                    is found in the circumstance that the poet wrote a dithyrambic poem after the
                    battle of Plataea, in which he spoke so warmly in admiration of Athens, that the
                    prevailing party amongst his countrymen took umbrage at it, and visited him with
                    punishment. The Athenians, on the other hand, erected a statue to his honour.
                    Again we find him comparing the victories of Hiero at Cumae and Himera to the
                    most illustrious engagements of the Greeks against the Persians. It is
                    impossible, therefore, to doubt that he joined heartily in support of Greek
                    independence, though he does not seem to have thought that a monarchical
                    government, justly and mildly administered, was unworthy of respect. Of his
                    private history nothing farther is known, except that he died at an advanced
                    age, probably about the year B. c. 439. According to one tradition, he died
                    whilst he was resting on the bosom of his young disciple Theoxenus, after he had
                    taken part in the active exercises of the gymnasium. He was the writer of many
                    poems, but they have all perished except some fragments, and those hymns which
                    he composed in honour of the conquerors at the solemn games of Greece. They are
                    divided into four books, of which the first contains those who had conquered at
                    the Olympic games, and consists of fourteen odes; the second, addressed to the
                    conquerors of the Pythian games, contains twelve odes; the third, addressed to
                    the Nemean conquerors, contains eleven odes; and the fourth, celebrating the
                    Isthmian conquerors, contains eight odes. It is difficult to believe that the
                    reputation of Pindar was founded upon the poetry which has come down to us, and
                    indeed his dithyrambic hymns are spoken of as his finest productions. He is no
                    doubt distinguished by a warm and enthusiastic genius, and by bold and
                    figurative expressions; but the abruptness of his transitions, and the numerous
                    allusions to persons and things now altogether unknown, and which, if known,
                    would not interest the reader, very much diminish the pleasure with which his
                    poetry is read. Still the opinion of Horace must for ever place him in the
                    foremost rank of lyric poets.</p>
                <p>Fiery, immense, profound he flowes As from a mountaille tumbling goes A torrent
                    fed with showers, flyes o’er The well-knowne limits of the shore. √∖ polio’s
                    bayes are due to him, Whether new words swolne to the brim, He (bold) through
                    dithyrambies throw, Where every new word doth loosely flow; Whether gods, kings,
                    or gods’ allies He chant, who by a just surprise, The Centaurs vanquish’d, and
                    supprest Chimaera’s dreadful flamingerest.</p>
                <p>Hawkins’ Translation, 1G35.</p>
                <p>The oldest edition of this poet is that of Aldus, Venice, 1513, in 8vo. The best
                    editions are those by Erasmus Schmid, Wittenburg, 1616, in 4to; by Heyne,
                    Göttingen, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193500785" xml:id="kp-eb0717-0785-0746"
                    />1773; by Aug. Böckh, Leipzig, 1811-1822, particularly valuable for criticism
                    and metre; by Thiersch, with a German translation, Leipzig, 1820, in 8vo;
                    Pindari Carmina commentario perpetuo illustravit L. Dissen, Goth., 1830, in 8vo;
                    Schneider de Vita et Scriptis Pindari, Strasburg, 1774, in 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
