<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-2478-0107-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PASCAL, Blaise</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 107</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:981348">Jansenists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193492478" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PASCAL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Blaise</hi></label>, one of the
                    greatest geniuses and best writers that France has produced, was born at
                    Clermont, in Auvergne, in the year 1623. His father, Stephen Pascal, born in
                    1588, and descended of an ancient family, was president of the court of aids in
                    his province; and being a very learned man, and an able mathematician, he was a
                    friend of Descartes. Having an extraordinary tenderness for this child, who was
                    his only son, he quitted his office, and settled at Paris in 1631, that he might
                    be at leisure to attend to his instruction; and young Pascal never had any
                    master but his father. From his infancy he gave proofs of extraordinary
                    capacity; for he desired to know the reason of every thing, and when good
                    reasons were not given him, he would seek for better, refusing to yield his
                    assent except upon such as appeared to him to be well grounded. It was feared
                    that, with such a turn of mind, he might fall into free-thinking, or at least
                    into heterodoxy; but this apprehension proved groundless.</p>
                <p>What is told of his'manner of learning the mathematics, as well as of the rapid
                    progress which he made in that science, seems almost miraculous. His father,
                    perceiving in him an extraordinary inclination to reasoning, was afraid lest the
                    knowledge of the mathematics might prevent his acquiring the languages. He
                    therefore kept him as much as he could from all notions of geometry, locked up
                    all his books on that subject, and even refrained from speaking of it in his
                    presence. He could not, however, prevent his son from musing upon geometrical
                    propositions, and one day surprised him at work with some charcoal upon his
                    ’chamber floor, and in the midst of figures. Having asked the boy what he was
                    doing, he received for answer, I am searching for such a property, which was in
                    fact that demonstrated in the thirty-second proposition of the first book of
                    Euclid. His father then asked him how he came to think of this’? It was, says
                    Pascal, because I had found out such another thing; and so going backwards and
                    using the names of <hi rend="italic">bar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">round,</hi>
                    he came at length to the definitions and axioms which he had formed to himself.
                    Does it not seem almost miraculous that a boy should work his way into the heart
                    of a mathematical work, without ever having seen that or any other book upon the
                    subject, or knowing any thing of the terms? Yet we are assured of the truth of
                    this by Madame Perrier, and by several other writers, the credit of whose
                    testimony cannot reasonably be questioned. Thenceforward he had full liberty to
                    indulge his genius in mathematical pursuits. He understood Euclid’s Elements as
                    soon as he cast his eyes upon them; and this need not seem strange, for, as we
                    have seen, he understood them before. '</p>
                <p>At sixteen years of age he wrote a treatise on Conic Sections, which was
                    accounted by the learned a mighty effort of genius; and therefore it is not
                    wonderful that Descartes, who had been a long time in Holland, should, upon
                    reading it, have been inclined to believe that Μ. Pascal the father was the real
                    author of the work. At nineteen he contrived an admirable mathematical machine,
                    which was esteemed a wonderful thing, and would have done credit as an invention
                    almost to any man conversant with science, far less to a mere youth. About this
                    time his health became impaired, and he was in consequence obliged to suspend
                    his labours; nor was he in a condition to resume them till nearly four years
                    afterwards. About that period, having seen Torricelli’s experiment respecting a
                    vacuum and the weight of the air, he turned his thoughts towards that subject;
                    and in a conference with Μ. Petit, intendant of fortifications, proposed to make
                    farther researches. In pursuance of this idea, he undertook several new
                    experiments. In particular, having provided a glass tube, forty-six feet in
                    length, open at one end, and sealed hermetically at the other, he filled it with
                    red wine, that he might distinguish the liquor from the tube. He then elevated
                    the latter in this condition; and having placed it perpendicularly to the
                    horizon, stopped up the bottom, and plunged it into a vessel full of water to
                    the depth of a foot; after which he opened the extremity of the tube, and the
                    wine descended till about thirty-two feet above the surface of the vessel,
                    leaving a considerable vacuum at the upper extremity. He next inclined the tube,
                    and remarked that the wine rose higher; and having inclined it till the top was
                    within thirty-two feet of the ground, making the wine thus run out, he found
                    that the water rose in it, so that it was partly filled with that fluid, and
                    partly with wine. He made also a great many experiments with syphons, syringes,
                    bellows, and all kinds of tubes, employing different liquors, such as
                    quicksilver, water, wine, and oil; and having^published an account of his
                    experiments in 1647, he dispersed his work throughout all France, and also
                    transmitted it to foreign countries. All these experiments, however, ascertained
                    effects, without demonstrating the causes. Pascal knew that Torricelli
                    conjectured that those phenomena which he had observed were occasioned by the
                    weight of the air; and, in order to discover the truth of this theory, he made
                    an experiment at the summit and foot of a mountain in Auvergne√called Le
                    Puy-de-Dôme, the result of which led him to conclude that air had weight. Of
                    this experiment he also published an account, and sent copies of it to most of
                    the learned men in Europe. He likewise renewed the experiment at the top of
                    several high towers, such as those of Nôtre Dame at Paris, St Jacques de la
                    Boucherie, and some others; and he always remarked the same difference in the
                    weight of the air at different elevations. This fully convinced him of the
                    weight of the atmosphere; and from this discovery he drew many useful and
                    important inferences. He also composed a large treatise, in which he thoroughly
                    explained this subject, and replied to all the objections which had been started
                    against it. As he thought this work rather too prolix, and as he was fond of
                    brevity and precision, he divided it into two small treatises, one of which he
                    entitled a Dissertation on the Equilibrium of Liquors; and the other, an Essay
                    on the Weight of the Atmosphere. These labours procured Pascal so much
                    reputation, that the greatest mathematicians and philosophers of the age
                    proposed various questions to him, and consulted him respecting such
                    difficulties as they could not resolve.</p>
                <p>Some years after, whilst tormented with a violent fit of the toothach, he
                    discovered the solution of a problem proposed by Father Mersenne, which had
                    baffled the penetration of all those who had attempted it. This problem was to
                    determine the curve described in the air by the nail of a coach-wheel whilst the
                    machine is in motion. Pascal offered a reward of forty pistoles to any one who
                    should give a satisfactory answer to the question. As no one succeeded, however,
                    he published his own at Paris; but as he now began to be disgusted with the
                    sciences, he did not put his real name to it, and sent it abroad under that of
                    A. d’Et-tenvillc<pb break="no" facs="nls:193492491" xml:id="kp-eb0717-2491-0108"
                    />. This was the last work which he published in the mathematics; and his
                    infirmities now increased so much that he was under the necessity of renouncing
                    severe study, and of living so recluse that he scarcely admitted any person to
                    see him.</p>
                <p>After he had laboured thus successfully in mathematical and philosophical
                    disquisitions, he forsook these studies and all human learning at once. He was
                    not twenty-four years of age, when the perusal of some pious books had inspired
                    him with this resolution; and he became as great a devotee as any age has
                    produced. He now devoted himself entirely to a state of prayer and
                    mortification. He had always in his thoughts the great maxim of renouncing all
                    pleasures and all superfluity; and this he practised with rigour even in his
                    illnesses, to which he was frequently subject, being of a very feeble habit of
                    body. He had no violent affection for those he loved; and he even thought it
                    sinful, since a man possesses a heart which belongs only to God. He found fault
                    with some discourses of his sister, which she thought very innocent; and
                    subjected himself to severe mortification and abstinence.</p>
                <p>But though Pascal had thus abstracted himself from the world, yet he could not
                    forbear paying some attention towhat was passing in it; and he even interested
                    himself deeply in the contest between the Jesuits and the Jansenists. The
                    Jesuits, although they had popes and kings on their side, were yet decried by
                    the people, who raked up afresh against them the assassination of Henry IV., and
                    all the old stories which were likely to render them odious. Pascal went
                    farther, and by his <hi rend="italic">Lettres Provinciales,</hi> published in
                    1656, under the name of Louis de Montalte, made them the subject of the keenest
                    irony and ridicule. These letters may justly be considered as a model of
                    eloquence and humour. The best comedies of Molière have not more wit than the
                    first part of them; and the sublimity of the latter part is equal to any thing
                    in Bossuet. It is true, indeed, that the whole book was built upon a false
                    foundation; for the extravagant notions of a few Spanish and Flemish Jesuits
                    were artfully ascribed to the whole society. Many absurdities might likewise
                    have been discovered amongst the Dominican and Franciscan casuists; but this
                    would not have answered the purpose; for the whole raillery was to be levelled
                    only at the Jesuits. The Provincial Letters were intended to prove that the
                    Jesuits had formed a design to corrupt mankind; a design which no sect or
                    society ever had or can have. Voltaire considers Pascal as the first of the
                    French satirists; for Despreaux, says he, must be regarded as only the second.
                    In another place, speaking of this work, he says, that examples of all the
                    various species of eloquence are to be found in it. “Though it has been now
                    written almost a hundred years, yet not a single word occurs in it savouring of
                    that vicissitude to which living languages are so subject. Here then we are to
                    fix the epoch when our language may be said to have assumed a settled form. The
                    Bishop of Lucon, son of the celebrated Bussy, told me, that asking one day the
                    Bishop of Meaux what work he would covet most to be the author of, supposing his
                    own performances set aside, Bossuet replied, the Provincial Letters.” These
                    letters have been translated into all languages, and printed in every possible
                    form. Some have said that there were decrees of formal condemnation against
                    them; and, further, that Pascal himself, in his last illness, detested them, and
                    repented of having been a Jansenist; but neither of these statements seems to
                    rest upon any good authority. Father Daniel wrote an answer to the Provincial
                    Letters, entitled the Dialogues of Cleander and Eudoxus. These celebrated
                    Letters appear to have been the joint productions of Arnauld, Nicoe, and Pascal.
                    Nicoe and Arnauld supplied the materials, which Pascal worked up into those
                    finished productions that fixed the language in which they were written, and
                    have been admired by every succeed ing age, as well as by that in which they
                    were first given to the world.</p>
                <p>Pascal was only about the age of thirty when the Provincial Letters were
                    published; yet he was extremely infirm, and soon afterwards his disorders
                    increased so much that, conceiving his end to be fast approaching, he gave up
                    all farther thoughts of literary composition. He resolved to spend the remainder
                    of his days in retirement and religious meditation; and with this view he broke
                    off all his former connections, changed his habitation, and spoke to no one, not
                    even to his own domestics. He made his own bed, fetched his dinner from the
                    kitchen, carried it to his apartment, and brought back the plates and dishes in
                    the evening; so that he employed his servants only to cook for him, to go to
                    town, and to do such other offices as he could not conveniently perform himself.
                    In his chamber nothing was to be seen but two or three chairs, a table, a bed,
                    and a few books. It had no kind of ornament whatever; he had neither a carpet on
                    the floor nor curtains to his bed: But this did not prevent him from sometimes
                    receiving visits; and when his friends appeared surprised to find him thus
                    without furniture, he replied, that he had what was necessary, and that anything
                    else would be a superfluity, unworthy of a wise man. He employed his time in
                    prayer, and in reading the Holy Scriptures; and he wrote down such thoughts as
                    this exercise inspired. Though his continual infirmities obliged him to use very
                    delicate food, and his servants employed the utmost care in providing only what
                    was excellent, he never relished what he ate, and seemed quite indifferent
                    whether what they brought him was good or bad.</p>
                <p>But although he had now abandoned intense study, and lived in the most temperate
                    manner, his health continued to decline rapidly; and his disorders had so
                    enfeebled his organs, that his reason became in some measure affected. He always
                    imagined that he saw a deep abyss on his left side; and he never would sit down
                    till a chair was so placed as to secure him from the fancied danger which he
                    apprehended. His friends did everything in their power to banish this melancholy
                    idea from his thoughts, and to cure him of his error, but without effect. Though
                    he would become calm and composed for a little, yet the phantom would in a few
                    moments return again and torment him with this painful delusion. The cause of
                    his seeing this singular vision for the first time is said to have been the
                    following. His physicians, alarmed on account of the exhausted state to which he
                    was reduced, had advised him to substitute easy and agreeable exercise for the
                    exhausting labours of the closet. One day, in the month of October 1654, having
                    gone, according to custom, to take an airing on the Pont de Neuilly, in a coach
                    and four, the two leading horses suddenly took fright opposite to a place where
                    there was no parapet, and threw themselves violently into the Seine; but the
                    traces having luckily given way, the carriage remained on the brink of the
                    precipice. The shock which Pascal, in his languishing situation, must have
                    received from this dreadful accident, may easily be imagined. It threw him into
                    a fit, which continued for some time, and it was with great difficulty that he
                    could be restored to his senses. After this period his brain became so
                    disordered that he was continually haunted by the remembrance of his danger,
                    especially when his infirmities prevented him from enjoying sleep. During the
                    last years of his life, in which he exhibited a melancholy example of the
                    humiliating changes which take place in this transitory world, and which, if
                    properly considered, might teach mankind not to be too proud of those abilities,
                    however splendid, which a moment may take from them, he attended all the stated
                    prayers, visited every church in which relics were exposed, and had always a
                    spiritual almanack, containing an account of all those places where particular
                    acts of devotion were performed. On this occasion it has <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193492504" xml:id="kp-eb0717-2504-0109"/>been said that religion
                    renders great minds capable of little things, and little minds capable of great
                    things.</p>
                <p>In company Pascal was distinguished by his amiable behaviour, his easy,
                    agreeable, and instructive conversation, and his great modesty. He possessed a
                    natural kind of eloquence, which was in a manner irresistible; and no one ever
                    had the happiness of meeting him, without being at once instructed and
                    delighted. His divine humility showed itself in all things, attempered with a
                    grace and simplicity which imparted to it an indescribable charm. Towards the
                    close of his life he employed himself wholly in pious and moral reflections,
                    writing down those which he judged worthy of being preserved. The first piece of
                    paper that he could find was employed for this purpose; and he commonly put down
                    only a few words of each sentence, as he wrote them merely for his own use. The
                    bits of paper upon which he had written these thoughts were found after his
                    death filed upon different pieces of string, without any order or connection;
                    but being copied exactly as they were written, they were afterwards arranged and
                    published. He died at Paris on the 19th of August 1662, aged thirty-nine
                    years.</p>
                <p>The works of Pascal were collected in five volumes octavo, and published at the
                    Hague by De Tune, and at Paris by Nyon, in 1779. This edition of Pascal’s works
                    may be considered as the first published; at least the greater part of them were
                    not before collected into one body, and some of them had still remained in
                    manuscript. For this collection the public were indebted to the Abbé Bossu, and
                    Pascal deserved to have such an editor. See remarks on his philosophical
                    character in the <hi rend="italic">First Dissertation,</hi> prefixed to this
                    work.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
