<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-6612-0425-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHILOSOPHER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 17, page 425</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:944368">Gold</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91b3s">Gold</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193496612" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHILOSOPHER</label>, a person versed in philosophy, or one
                    who makes profession of, and applies himself to, the study of wisdom or real
                    knowledge.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Philosopher’s</hi><hi rend="italic">Stone,</hi> the great
                    object of alchemy, a long-sought-for preparation, which, when found, was to
                    transmute all the true mercurial part of metal into pure gold, better than any
                    that is obtained from mines, or perfected by the refiner’s art.</p>
                <p>Some Greek writers belonging to the fourth and fifth centuries speak of this art
                    as being then known; and towards the end of the thirteenth century, when the
                    learning of the East had been imported by the Arabians, the same pretensions
                    began to spread throughout Europe. It is supposed that this art, called <hi
                    rend="italic">alchemy,</hi> was of Egyptian origin; and that when the ancient
                    Greek philosophers travelled into Egypt, they brought back some of the
                    allegorical language of this Egyptian art, which, being ill understood,
                    afterwards passed into their mythology. Alchemy was the earliest branch of
                    chemistry, considered as a philosophical science. In the other parts of chemical
                    knowledge, facts preceded reasoning or speculation; but in alchemy all was
                    originally speculative.</p>
                <p>The alchemists supposed that the general principles of metals consisted chiefly
                    of two substances, which they called mercury and sulphur. They apprehended, that
                    the pure mercurial, sulphureous, or other principles of which they imagined gold
                    to be composed, were contained separately in other bodies; wherefore they
                    endeavoured to collect these principles, and to concoct and incorporate them by
                    long digestions; and by thus conjoining the principles of gold, they expected
                    that gold would be produced. But the alchemists pretended to a product of a
                    higher order, <hi rend="italic">called the elixir, the medicine far metals, the
                    tincture, the philosopher’s stone,</hi> which, by being projected on a large
                    quantity of any of the inferior metals in fusion, should change them into fine
                    gold; or which, being laid on a plate of silver, copper, or iron, and moderately
                    heated, should sink into the metal, and change into gold all the parts to which
                    it was applied; or which, on being properly heated with pure gold, should change
                    the gold into a substance of the same nature and virtue with itself, so as to be
                    susceptible of perpetual multiplication, and, by continued coction, to have its
                    power more and more exalted, so as to be able to transmute greater and greater
                    quantities of the inferior metals, according to its different degrees of
                    perfection.</p>
                <p>The alchemists attempted to arrive at the making of gold by three different
                    methods. The first was by separation; for every metal yet known was supposed to
                    contain some quantity of gold, though, in most, the quantity was believed to be
                    so little as not to defray the expense of disengaging it. The second was by
                    maturation. The alchemists considered mercury as the basis and matter of all
                    metals; they thought that quicksilver purged from all heterogeneous bodies would
                    be much heavier, denser, and simpler, than the native quicksilver, and that by
                    subtilizing, purifying, and digesting it with much labour, and by long
                    operations, it was possible to convert it into pure gold. This method was only
                    for mercury. With respect to the other metals, it was ineffectual, because their
                    matter was not pure mercury, but had other heterogeneous bodies adhering to it;
                    and because the digestion, by which mercury is turned into gold, would not
                    succeed in other metals, from their not having been long enough in the mines. W
                    eight is the inimitable character of gold. But mercury, according to them, has
                    always some impurities in it, which are lighter than mercury; and could these be
                    purged away, which they thought not impossible, mercury would be as heavy as
                    gold, and what was as heavy as gold was gold, or at least might very easily be
                    made gold. The third method was by transmutation, or by turning all metals
                    readily into pure gold, by melting them in the fire, and casting a little
                    quantity of a certain preparation into the fused matter; upon which the faeces
                    would be volatilized and burned, or carried off, and the rest of the mass would
                    be turned into pure gold. That which was to work this change in the metals
                    received the denomination of the <hi rend="italic">philosopher’s stone.</hi></p>
                <p>The following historical notices on this curious subject occur in Holt’s
                    Characters of the Kings and Queens of England. “The opinion,” says he, “that one
                    metallic or other foreign substance might be changed into another, was, it
                    seems, at this time (in the reign of Henry VI. of England) propagated by certain
                    chemists, whose observations on the surprising effects and alterations produced
                    in certain substances by the force of heat carried their imaginations beyond
                    what sound judgment might warrant; the first instance of which on record is in
                    Rymer’s <hi rend="italic">Foedara</hi> (vol. xi. p. 68), wherein Henry VI.
                    grants a license to John Cobbe, freely to work in metals, he having, by
                    philosophical art, found out a method of transmuting imperfect metals into
                    perfect gold and silver. This pretended secret, known afterwards by the name of
                    the <hi rend="italic">philosopher s stone</hi> or <hi rend="italic">powder,</hi>
                    was encouraged by four licenses, granted to different projectors, during this
                    reign, and at sundry times after during this century particularly, and in
                    succeeding times all over Europe.” <pb break="no" facs="nls:193496625"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0717-6625-0426"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
