<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-3253-0615-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLAXMAN, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1105622">Satanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115918">Shields</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817559">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109473">Sculptors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qs54">Satanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03xx31">Shields</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hg87">Sculptors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193753253?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FLAXMAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, an
                    eminent English sculptor, was born at York on the 6th of July 1755. He was the
                    second son of John Flaxman, a moulder in plaster, who, besides keeping a shop in
                    London for the sale of his figures, sought employment in the country. He was of
                    a weakly consti- . tution, and slightly deformed, which prevented him from
                    mingling with associates of his own age in the robust pastimes of youth. But he
                    was not idle. Behind his father’s counter he usually seated himself during the
                    day, and, with drawing materials before him, busily employed himself in
                    transferring to paper representations of the numerous figures with which he was
                    surrounded. Indeed, almost from childhood he evinced that partiality for and
                    love of works of art, ' in the creation of which he so much excelled in maturer
                    years. But he did not confine himself to copying alone. Young as he was, he had
                    dipped into the Iliad, and actually attempted to design historical illustrations
                    of that immortal epic. His education seems to have devolved principally upon his
                    parents; and as his thirst for knowledge was great, the superintendence of his
                    studies must have been an easy task. At his books and models he laboured
                    incessantly, and before he entered his tenth year he had made a great number of
                    small models in plaster of Paris, wax, and clay, some of which are still
                    preserved; and, besides being interesting as the first efforts of genius, they
                    possess considerable merit as works of art. At ten years of age, a salutary
                    change took place in his health. Fie became strong, lively, and active; and the
                    crutches, by means of which he had hitherto walked, were thrown aside, not to be
                    again resumed. With renovated health he came to the determination to follow
                    sculpture as a profession. In his father s shop, where he assiduously pursued
                    his studies, he learned form and proportion from the casts of antique statues
                    which it contained; whilst in the woods and fields, to which he could now
                    repair, he was supplied with new images and ideas of beauty. At the house of a
                    Mrs Mathcw, whose husband had been attracted to the youthful sculptor, Flaxman
                    often spent his evenings hearing her read Homer and Virgil, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193753266?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-3266-0616"/>discourse
                    upon sculpture and poetry; for the lady was very accomplished, and the companion
                    of Mrs Montague, Mrs Chapone, and Mrs Barbauld. Here he was encouraged to
                    acquire the dead languages, so necessary to one of his profession; and although
                    he never attained to great scholarship, he, by this desultory mode of study,
                    obtained such a knowledge of Greek as enabled him to embody the ideas of the
                    ancient poets in a manner which no modern artist has surpassed. He embodied
                    those passages which caught his fancy whilst lie sat listening to Mrs Mathew;
                    and the taste which he displayed in these juvenile efforts induced a gentleman
                    to order six large drawings in chalk, the subjects being chosen from antiquity.
                    The praise which was bestow ed upon them gave new impulse to the genius of the
                    youth, and refreshed that consciousness of superior power which he early
                    experienced. But he never overrated himself, nor allowed his industry to relax
                    on account of the flatteries of friends. He continued to labour assiduously in
                    his vocation, well knowing that it was only in this manner that he could attain
                    great eminence, and succeed in embodying those idealised conceptions of beauty
                    which, although they scarcely admit of being defined or described, are
                    nevertheless not less real, nor less universally acknowledged.</p>
                <p part="N">In his fifteenth year Flaxman became a student of the Royal Academy, and
                    soon made himself known by assiduous and enthusiastic application. In the same
                    year he carried off the silver medal; and in due time became a candidate for the
                    gold one, the reward of the highest degree of merit, but proved unsuccessful.
                    This defeat, however, only increased his assiduity. But finding himself now
                    compelled to labour for bread, he was employed by the Wedgewoods, the
                    enterprising potters, in making designs for adorning their wares. His sketches
                    consisted chiefly of small groups in very low relief, the subjects being taken
                    from ancient poetry and history. Previously to this period the porcelain of
                    England had little external beauty to recommend it; and the genius of Flaxman
                    may be said to have created this branch of art in his native country. The rude
                    and unseemly shapes which formerly prevailed were no longer tolerated, and
                    figures of classic elegance and beauty were invented to supply their place. In
                    1782, Flaxman having quitted his paternal roof, took a small house, and entered
                    into a matrimonial alliance with a person of considerable accomplishments, in
                    whose society he enjoyed much domestic happiness. During the ten years which
                    preceded this event, he had exhibited some thirteen works at the Royal Academy,
                    but, from the pecuniary difficulties under which he laboured, none of these were
                    executed in marble. Shortly after his marriage, he formed the resolution of
                    studying at Rome, and at the end of five years of incessant labour, during which
                    he executed several monuments and other works of considerable merit, he was
                    enabled to carry his design into execution. It is unnecessary to observe, that
                    Flaxman, like every other artist, was struck with the noble specimens of art
                    which Italy possesses, and that by a close study of these he greatly improved
                    himself. But he was no servile imitator, for he was as capable of creating as of
                    copying. In Rome Flaxman executed a number of works, ror three individuals of
                    his own country he illustrated Homer, AEschylus, and Dante. These designs are
                    splendid, being varied with great skill, and drawn with a fine sense of the
                    beautiful and harmonious in composition. Of w orks in marble he executed a small
                    size groμp of Cephalus and Aurora; a statue of Lord Mansfield; a group
                    representing the fury of Athamas, from Ovid’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Metamorphoses,</hi> consisting offour figures of the heroic size; and the
                    restoration of that splendid torso which is generally believed to be a fragment
                    of+ Hercifles This last undertaking was as difficult as it turned out to be
                    thankless. He not only completed the figure of Hercules, but added another of
                    Omphale· But this statue did not give satisfaction to the connoisseurs of Italy,
                    and Flaxman caused it to be destroyed some time previously to his death, without
                    any injury to his fame. The remains of ancient sculpture in Rome, and in other
                    cities of Italy, engaged not a little of his attention. He executed numerous
                    drawings, and made a great many memoranda, the most valuable of which were
                    subsequently embodied in his lectures on sculpture. He had been elected a member
                    of the academies of Florence and Carrara; and after seven years’ residence in a
                    foreign country, he at length returned to his own.</p>
                <p part="N">Flaxman’s statue of Lord Mansfield had raised the expectations of his
                    countrymen to a high pitch. In 1797 he was elected associate of the Royal
                    Academy, during which year he sent to the exhibition three sketches in
                    bas-relief from the New Testament, anu a monument to Sir William Jones. The
                    sketches are distinguished for their elegance of grouping. The monument is a
                    bas-relief, but not one of the artist’s most fortunate efforts in that line. In
                    the forty-fifth year of his age Flaxman was elected a member of the Royal
                    Academy, and, as is usual on such occasions, presented to the institution a work
                    of art. His offering on this occasion was a marble group of Apollo and Marpessa;
                    the conception of which is fine, though the workmanship is not so good. In the
                    mechanical use of the chisel he never excelled. It was now his ambition to be
                    employed upon some great national work, and he proposed to make a statue of
                    Britannia two hundred feet in height, but the project was not carried into
                    execution. His fame, however, was now firmly established, and employment flowed
                    rapidly in. A quick succession of noble works followed from his hand, one of
                    which, a monument in memory of the family of Sir Francis Baring, is considered
                    among the greatest efforts of the national genius of England. One of his
                    biographers remarks with respect to it, “This is one of the finest pieces of
                    motionless poetry in the land.” Of historical monuments Flaxman executed
                    several, but they are not equal to his other works. They have been admired for
                    the fine sentiment which pervades them, but their execution is considered by
                    many as too coarse and heavy. The statue of Sir Joshua Reynolds is one of his
                    best productions. But the works he loved most were those which embodied poetical
                    passages in the Bible, and of these he executed a great number. In 1810 the
                    Royal Academy created a professorship of sculpture, and bestowed it upon
                    Flaxmau. His lectures are ten in number. The style is rather heavy; yet although
                    his compositions are destitute of those flashes of poetry which irradiate the
                    pages of Fuseli, they display a very comprehensive knowledge of the subject,
                    much sound sense, and are more calculated to convey definite information to the
                    student than those of the other artist above named. But if the offspring of his
                    pen was cold and uninformed with ideal beauty, the productions of his pencil and
                    chisel display an exuberance of imagination. His sketches and drawings are very
                    numerous. Amongst the works which he illustrated were the Pilgrim’s Progress,
                    Sotheby’s translation of Oberon, an Hesiod. These designs are in all respects
                    fully equal to his other works, and unsurpassed by any thing which ever was
                    executed in that line. During the last ten years o his life Flaxman produced
                    some of his noblest works· Amongst these were the group of the Archangel Michae
                    vanquishing Satan, the Shield of Achilles, Psyche, the Pastoral Apollo, and the
                    statues of Michel Angelo and 1 a faelle∙ The first is a work of the highest
                    merit, and wort y of the great poem which it illustrates. “In the lsycιe and the
                    Pastoral Apollo,” says Mr Allan Cunningham, “the genius of him who illustrated
                    Homer is şuflicient y . apparent; a certain austere composure is breathed over
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193753279?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0709-3279-0617"/>them. The Michael Angelo and the Raphael are
                    poetic yet real; heroic, yet familiar; and their costume, though not antique, is
                    at once historic and picturesque.” Flaxman’s statues of Burns and Kemble,
                    executed about the same time <hi rend="subscript">:</hi> are scarcely so happy.
                    Amongst his other works were monuments to Collins at Chichester, and to Earl
                    Howe in Si Pauľs; and statues of Washington, Nclson, Pitt, and Siι John Moore.
                    They are of various excellence, yet all more or less bear the impress of genius
                    and taste. But the careeι of this great sculptor was drawing to a close. In the
                    beginning of December 1826 hc was seized with an inflammation of the lungs,
                    which terminated fatally on the 7th of the same month.</p>
                <p part="N">In stature Flaxman was small, and his figure was slim. In manners hc was
                    mild, gentlc, and placable; and his mind, whilst it was rich in the gifts of
                    genius, was embued with unaffected piety. Of his works there are four kinds; the
                    religious, the poetic, the classic, and the historical. In each of these he has
                    left specimens which entitle him to rank very high as an artist, but in all he
                    has not attained the same degree of excellence. In the historical and the
                    classic he was less successful; but in the religious and poetic he has been
                    surpassed in purity, simplicity, and taste, by no modern sculptor. His religious
                    compositions consist of groups and figures embodying moral and spiritual
                    passages from Scripture. They are generally of small dimensions, but very
                    numerous. His mind was essentially poetical; and his productions are embued with
                    the finest inspiration. It was probably of some of these works that Sir Thomas
                    Lawrence spoke when hc said of Flaxman, “His solitude was made enjoyment to him
                    by a fancy teeming with images of tenderness, purity, or grandeur. His genius,
                    in the strictest sense of the words, was original and inventive.” His lectures
                    were published in 1829, in one vol. 8vo, illustrated with fifty-two plates.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
