<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-4995-0749-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FORM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936106">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193754995?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FORM</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Physics,</hi>
                    denotes the manner of being peculiar to each body; or that which constitutes it
                    such a particular body, and distinguishes it from every other. But Mr Harris
                    uses the term <hi rend="italic">form</hi> in another sense, as an efficient
                    animating principle; to which he supposes Ovid to refer in the first lines of
                    his Metamorphoses.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">In noυafert animus</hi><hi rend="italic">mutatas
                        dicere</hi> formas, <hi rend="italic">Corpora.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">These animating forms are not of themselves objects either of the ear or
                    of the eye; but their nature or character is understood in this, that were they
                    never to exert their proper energies on their proper subjects, the marble on
                    which the sculptor exercises his art would remain for ever shapeless, and the
                    harp from which the harper calls forth sounds would remain for ever silent.</p>
                <p part="N">Substantial forms seem to have been first broached by the followers of
                    Aristotle, who thought matter, under different modes or modifications, not
                    sufficient to constitute different bodies, but that something substantial was
                    necessary to set them at a greater distance, and thus introduced substantial
                    forms, on the footing of souls, which specify and distinguish animals. What led
                    to this erroneous notion were the circumstances of life and death. For observing
                    that, as soon as the soul had departed out of a man, all motion, respiration,
                    nutrition, and other animal functions, immediately ceased, they concluded that
                    these functions depended on the soul, and consequently that the soul was the
                    form of the animal body, or that which constituted it such; indeed nobody
                    doubted that the soul was a substance independent of matter; and hence it was
                    concluded that the forms of other bodies were to be equally substantial. But to
                    this it is answered, that though the soul be that by which man is man, and
                    consequently the form of the human body as human, yet it does not follow that it
                    is properly the form of this body of ours, as it is a body, or of the several
                    parts thereof, ∞nsidered as distinct from one another. For those several parts
                    have their proper forms so closely connected with their matter, that it remains
                    inseparable therefrom long after the soul has quitted the body; thus flesh has
                    the form of flesh, bone of bone, and so forth, long after the soul is removed,
                    as well as before. The truth is, the body does not become incapable of
                    performing its accustomed functions because the soul has deserted it; but the
                    soul takes its leave because the body is no longer in a condition to perform its
                    functions.</p>
                <p part="N">The ancient and modern corpuscular philosophers, therefore, with the
                    Cartesians, exclude the notion of substantial forms, and show, by many
                    arguments, that the form is only the <hi rend="italic">modus</hi> or manner of
                    the body in which it ;s inherent.</p>
                <p part="N">And as there are only three primary modes of matter, figure, rest, or
                    motion, with two others arising therefrom, magnitude and situation, the form of
                    all bodies they hold to consist in these modes, and suppose the variations which
                    they are capable of sufficient to present all the variety observable in
                    bodies.</p>
                <p part="N">Forms are usually distinguished into <hi rend="italic">essential</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">accidental.</hi> Though the five modes above mentioned,
                    generally taken, be adventitious, yet to this or that body, as to fire or water,
                    they are <hi rend="italic">essential.</hi> Thus it is <hi rend="italic"
                        >accidental</hi> to iron to have this or that magnitude, figure, or
                    situation, since it might exist in different ones; yet to a knife or hammer, the
                    figure, magnitude, and position of parts, which constitute it a hammer or knife,
                    are essential, and they cannot exist or be conceived without these. Hence it is
                    inferred, that though there be no substantial, yet there are essential forms, by
                    which the several species of bodies become what they are, and are distinguished
                    from all others. <hi rend="italic">Accidental</hi> forms are those really
                    inherent in bodies, but in such manner as that the body may exist in all its
                    perfection without them; such as whiteness in a wall, heat in water, a figure of
                    a man in wax, and so on.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Form,</hi> in carpentry, is used to denote the long
                    seats or benches in the choirs of churches or in schools, for the priests,
                    prebends, religious persons, or scholars, to sit on. Du Cange supposes the name
                    to be derived from this, that the backs of the seats were anciently enriched
                    with figures of painting and sculpture, called in Latin <hi rend="italic"
                        >forma</hi><hi rend="italic">et typi.</hi> In the life of St William of
                    Roschild, we meet with <hi rend="italic">forma</hi> as signifying a seat for an
                    ecclesiastic, or religious person, in a choir; and in that of St Lupicin, we
                    find <hi rend="italic">formula</hi> used in the same sense. In the rule of the
                    monastery of St Caesarea, the man who presides over the choir is called the
                    occupant of the first form or seat.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
