<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-3305-0619-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLETCHER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131380">Stairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1157239">Triumph</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k675">Freedom</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wf2d">Militia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193753305?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FLETCHER</label>. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Beaumont
                        and Fletcher.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Andrew,</hi> of Saltoun, a celebrated Scottish patriot and political
                    writer, was descended from an ancient family, who traced their origin to some
                    one of the followers of William the Conqueror. He was the son of Sir Robert
                    Fletcher of Saltoun and Innerpeffcr, and was born in the year 1650. The tuition
                    of young Fletcher was committed by his father, on his deathbed, to Mr,
                    afterwards Bishop, Burnet, then his parish minister, to whose care and attention
                    he was indebted for a pious, learned, and polite education. Being endowed with
                    uncommon genius, and possessed of virtues and abilities peculiarly suited to the
                    times in which he lived, Mr Fletcher quickly shone forth the ornament of his
                    country and the champion of its freedom. Having in the course of his classical
                    studies and historical reading been impressed with an enthusiastic admiration
                    both of ancient and modern republics, he had early contracted an ardent love of
                    liberty, and an aversion to arbitrary rule. Hence his spirit the more readily
                    took alarm at certain measures in the reign of Charles II. Being knight of the
                    shire for Lothian to the parliament where the Duke of York appeared as
                    commissioner, he openly opposed the designs of that prince and the bill of
                    accession; and he had a share with Lord Viscount Stair in framing the test act,
                    by which the Duke of York complained that he had lost Scotland. On these
                    accounts he became peculiarly obnoxious to his royal highness, and was at last
                    obliged to fly to Holland, to avoid the fatal consequences of prosecutions which
                    on various pretences were commenced against him. Being cited before the privy
                    council and justiciary courts, and not appearing, hc was declared a traitor, and
                    his estate confiscated.</p>
                <p part="N">In Holland, Fletcher and Baillie of Jerviswood were the only persons
                    whom the Earl of Argyll consulted concerning the designs which were then in
                    agitation. In 1681 they came over to England in order to concert matters with
                    their party in that country; and they were the only persons who were entrusted
                    so far as to be admitted to the secrets of Lord Russell’s council of six. Mr
                    Fletcher managed his part of the negotiation with so much address, that the
                    administration could find no pretext for seizmg him; nor could they fix upon him
                    those articles on account of which Baillie was condemned; and to the honour of
                    the latter be it remembered, that although offered a pardon on condition of
                    accusing his friend, he persisted in rejecting the proposal with
                    indignation.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Fletcher having joined the Duke of Monmouth upon his landing,
                    received a principal command under him; but the duke was deprived of his
                    services owing to a circumstance which is related by Sir John Dalrymple. Being
                    sent upon an expedition, and not esteeming “times of danger to be times of
                    ceremony, he had seized for his own ιiding the horse of a country gentleman (the
                    mayor of Lynne), which stood ready equipped for its master. Γhe master, hearing
                    this, ran in a passion to Fletcher, gave him opprobrious <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193753318?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-3318-0620"/>language,
                    shook his cane, and attempted to strike. Fletcher, though rigid .in the duties
                    of morality, having been accustomed to foreign service both by sea and land, in
                    which he had acquired high ideas of the honour of a soldier and a gentleman, and
                    of the affront of a cane, pulled out his pistol and shot him dead on the spot.
                    The action was unpopular in countries where such refinements were not
                    understood. A clamour was raised against it among the people of the country; in
                    a body they waited upon the duke with their complaints; and he was forced to
                    desire the only soldier, and almost the only man of parts, in his army, to
                    abandon him. With Fletcher all Monmouth s chance of success in war left him.” In
                    a manuscript memoir belonging to the family there is the following notice
                    concerning Mr Fletcher’s connection with Monmouth, in which his separation from
                    that prince is very differently accounted for: “To Lord Marischal Mr Fletcher
                    explained the motives which first induced him to join, and afterwards abandon,
                    the Duke of Monmouth. The former he ascribed to the duke’s manifesto in Scotland
                    relating to religion, and in England to liberty. For the latter he accounted by
                    the disgust produced in his own mind, and that of his associates, when the duke
                    declared himself king, and broke faith with all who had embarked with him on his
                    principles. He complained heavily of the account commonly given of the death of
                    the mayor of Lynne; and mentioned to Lord Marischal, in proof of the contrary,
                    that he did not leave the duke till he came to Taunton, where he was proclaimed
                    king, several weeks after the death of the mayor of Lynne.”</p>
                <p part="N">Seeing all the efforts of his friends and of himself in favour of
                    liberty frustrated at Taunton, he endeavoured to secure his own personal freedom
                    by taking his passage in the first ship bound to a foreign country. It was his
                    misfortune, however, to land in Spain, where he was immediately arrested, cast
                    into prison, and guarded by three different bands of soldiers, till a vessel
                    could be prepared to carry him a victim in chains to the court of London. But on
                    the morning upon which the ship was to sail, whilst he looked pensively through
                    the bars of his window, he was hailed by a venerable personage, who made signs
                    to speak with him. The prison doors he found open; and whilst his friendly
                    conductor motioned to him to follow,' he passed through three different guards
                    of soldiers all fast asleep. Without being permitted to offer his thanks to his
                    deliverer, he found himself obliged to prosecute with all speed his journey, in
                    which he was directed by a person concerning whom he could never collect any
                    information, and thus he proceeded in safety through Spain.</p>
                <p part="N">During his exile he maintained a frequent and extensive correspondence
                    with the friends of liberty at home, and.he partly employed himself in making a
                    curious collection of books. But his genius also prompted him to engage in more
                    active employments. He repaired to Hungary, and served several campaigns with
                    much reputation as a volunteer unţler the Duke of Lorrain. At length,
                    understanding that the great design then projected in Holland, and upon the
                    issue of which he considered the liberties of Britain to depend, had obtained a
                    considerable degree of maturity, he hastened thither, and his counsels and
                    address were of eminent service to the cause. He came over with King William;
                    and in zeal, activity, penetration, and political skill, proved inferior to none
                    of the leaders m the Revolution.</p>
                <p part="N">Such, however, was his magnanimity, that whilst others laboured to
                    render this grand eventa source of emolument to themsel ves and aggrandisement
                    to their families, Mr Fletcher asked for nothing. His estate had been forfeited,
                    and his house abandoned to military execution; his fortune was greatly
                    shattered, and his family reduced to circumstances of distress; yet nothing was
                    given him in recompense of all his sufferings. On the contrary, he had the
                    honour, along with the Duke of Hamilton, to be distinguished by marks ' of both
                    royal and ministerial dislike. Still, whatever private resentment he might
                    entertain, his ruling principle was the good of his country, and to this grand
                    object of his heart he was willing to sacrifice all personal considerations.
                    Accordingly, in 1692, when the abdicated king meditated an invasion, Mr Fletcher
                    addressed a letter, preserved in Sir John Dalrymple’s collection, to the Duke of
                    Hamilton, in which every argument is employed with skill and energy to engage
                    his grace to forget his injuries, and in the actual crisis to employ the
                    extensive influence which he then possessed in the cause of freedom and of his
                    country. This letter produced its full effect, and the duke returned to his
                    duty, from which he had in some degree begun to estrange himself.</p>
                <p part="N">To follow our author throughout all the mazes of his political life
                    subsequently to the Revolution, is beyond our purpose, and would exceed our
                    limits. It will be sufficient to mention one or two additional circumstances
                    illustrative of his character. Being elected a member for the parliament 1693,
                    he showed an uniform zeal for the interest of his country. The thought of
                    England domineering over Scotland was what his generous soul could not endure.
                    The indignities and oppression which Scotland lay under galled him to the heart;
                    and in his learned and elaborate discourses he exposed them with undaunted
                    courage and affecting eloquence. In that great event, the Union, he performed
                    essential service. He got the act of security passed, which declared that the
                    two crowns should not be placed on the same head until Scotland had been secured
                    in her civil and religiouş liberties. After the queen’s demise, therefore, Lord
                    Godolphin was forced into the Union, in order to avoid a civil war. Although Mr
                    Fletcher disapproved of some of the articles, and indeed of the whole frame of
                    the Union; yet, as the act of security was his own work, he had all the merit of
                    that important transaction.</p>
                <p part="N">We must not omit mentioning, that in the ardour of his political career
                    Mr Fletcher forgot not the interests of the place which gave him birth. He
                    esteemed the education of youth as one of the noblest objects of government. On
                    this subject he wrote a treatise, still extant, which is most characteristic of
                    himself; and he established at Saltoun a foundation for the same purpose, of
                    great utility while it lasted. This remarkable person died at London in 1716, at
                    the age of sixty-six, and his remains were conveyed to Scotland, where they were
                    deposited in the family vault at Saltoun.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Fletcher was master of the English, Latin, Greel French, and Italian
                    languages, and well versed in history, the civil law, and other kinds of
                    learning. In his travels he had not only acquired considerable knowledge in the
                    ar of war, but had also become conversant with the respective interests of the
                    several princes and states of Europe, hţ private life he was affable to his
                    friends, and free from al manner of vice. He had a penetrating, clear, and
                    lively apprehension; but is said to have been too much wedde to opinions, and
                    impatient of contradiction. He was by tar the finest speaker in the parliament
                    of Scotland, and tie Earl of Stair alone rivalled him. The latter was famed or a
                    splendid, the former for a close and nervous eloquence·</p>
                <p part="N">In 1698 he published a <hi rend="italic">Discourse on Goveru</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> meη</hi><hi rend="italic">^</hi><hi rend="italic
                        superscript"> wt</hi><hi rend="italic">Relation to Militias,</hi> and two
                        <hi rend="italic">Discourses concerning the affairs of Scotland</hi>. These
                    and some other pieces, together with a few of his speeches, were after his death
                    collecte and published in an octavo volume, entitled <hi rend="italic">Political
                        Works of Andrew Fletcher, Esq.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Phineas,</hi> an English poet who enjoyed con siderable
                    popularity in his own day, but regarding whom few particulars have descended to
                    posterity. He was <pb break="no" facs="nls:193753331?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0709-3331-0621"/> son of Dr Giles Fletcher, who, on account of
                    his abilities, was entrusted by Queen Elizabeth with several important missions,
                    especially one to Russia, in which he negotiated a treaty highly advantageous to
                    England. He published an account of <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Russe</hi><hi rend="italic">Commonwealth,</hi> which was at first
                    suppressed, but afterwards reprinted in 1643. Phineas, his eldest son, was
                    educated at Eton, and in 1600 was elected to King’s College, Cambridge, where he
                    took the degrees of bachelor and master of arts. Having entered into holy
                    orders, hc received the living of Hilgay in Norfolk in the year 1621. It appears
                    from Blomefield’s <hi rend="italic">Norfolk,</hi> that he continued to officiate
                    in his clerical capacity for twenty-nine years, and it is probable that he died
                    here. These are all the facts known regarding Phincas Fletcher, a poet who was
                    styled “the Spenser of his age,” but whose fame is scarcely equal to his merit.
                    He -wrote <hi rend="italic">Sicelides,</hi> a piscatory drama, which was printed
                    anonymously in 1631. In the year following he printed at Cambridge a work
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">De literatis aηtiqucε</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Britannice,</hi><hi rend="italic">prcesertim</hi><hi rend="italic">qui
                        doctrina claruerunt, quique collegia Cantabrigice fundarunt,</hi> 12mo. In
                    the year following hc printed, in one vol. 4to, his <hi rend="italic">Purple
                        Island, Piscatory Eclogues,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Miscellanies.</hi>
                    These poems have all been reprinted, but not frequently. They are, however, to
                    be found in Anderson’s <hi rend="italic">British Poets.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The character of Phineas Fletcher appears to have been mild and amiable,
                    and his contemporaries passed liberal encomiums upon him for his learning and
                    piety. As a poet he possesses more merit than posterity seems disposed to
                    attribute to him. The <hi rend="italic">Purple Island</hi> is his longest and
                    his best production. It is an allegorical poem, of which man is the subject. The
                    first five cantos may be entitled the anatomy of the human body in rhyme. In the
                    remainder of the poem the poet quits the dissecting-room for the academic grove
                    of intellectual philosophy, and the learning of the schools. Although the design
                    is bad, and the reader sickens over anatomical details and abstract subtilties,
                    it is impossible not to admire the ingenuity with which the writer has invested
                    them with the flowers of fancy and of poetry. There is a profusion of images;
                    and although, as might have been expected, many of his allegorical personations
                    are too elaborately drawn and too highly coloured, some of them are
                    distinguished by a boldness of outline, a majesty of manner, a brilliancy of
                    tint, a propriety of attribute, and an air of life, which are rarely met with in
                    modern productions, and rival the best things of the kind even in Spencer, the
                    author from whom he caught his inspiration. Too often, indeed, his conceptions
                    are incongruous, and his conceits fantastical; but many beautiful thoughts are
                    interspersed throughout, and the whole is enriched with a vein of genuine
                    poetry.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Fletcher,</hi><hi rend="italic">Giles,</hi> brother
                    of the preceding, and of whom also few memorials remain, was born in the year
                    1558. He was bred at Cambridge, and died at his living at Al-denston in Suffolk,
                    in the year 1623. He is principally known as the author of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Christ?s Victory and Triumph over οηd after Death,</hi> a poem
                    characterized by a tone of enthusiasm peculiarly solemn. Like his brother, he
                    was an imitator of Spencer, and, with the diction of the latter slightly
                    modernized, hc retains much of his melody and luxuriant expression. Giles
                    Fletcher, there can be no doubt, is inferior both to Spencer and Milton, but he
                    frequently reminds us of both; and it secms evident that the latter was indebted
                    to him for hints, particularly with reference to <hi rend="italic">Paradise
                        Regained</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and some of the finest parts of <hi
                        rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> appear likewise to have been suggested by
                    passages in <hi rend="italic">Christs Victory and Triumph.</hi> Although in
                    several parts rather fantastical and quaint, that poem is a fine effusion θf
                    genius, and one of the best productions of the kind in the language.</p>
                <p part="N">rLETEWOOD, <hi rend="smallcaps">William,</hi> an eminent English lawyer
                    and recorder of London in the reign of Queen Elizabeth. He was very zealous in
                    suppressing mass-houses, and in imprisoning Roman Catholic priests; but having
                    oncc rushed in upon mass at the Portuguese ambassador’s house, he was committed
                    to the Fleet for breach of privilege. Mr Wood says he was a learned man and a
                    good antiquary, but of a marvellous merry and pleasant conceit. He was a good
                    popular speaker, and wrote well upon subjects of government. His principal works
                    are, <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic">Annalium
                        tam</hi><hi rend="italic">regum Edwardi V. Richardi III. etHenrici VII.
                        quarn Henrici VIII.</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">A
                        Table of the Reports of Edmund Plowden</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> 3. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Office of a Justice of Peace.</hi> He died about the year
                    1593.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
