<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-3279-0617-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FLECHIER, Esprit</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v395">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:875210">Congregationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193753279?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FLECHIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Esprit</hi></label>,
                    bishop of Nismes, one of the most cbrated preachers of his age, and author of a
                    number of works, was born at Pernes, a small town in the diocese of Carpentras,
                    on the 10th of June 1632, and educated under the eye of his uncle, Father
                    Audifret, general of the congregation of Christian doctrine, a learned and
                    estimable man. According to the constitution of the congregation, Fléchier,
                    having completed his own education, was immediately employed in teaching. In
                    1659, when only twenty-seven, he professed rhetoric at Narbonne, and there
                    pronounced the neral oration of Μ. de Rebé, archbishop of that city, which,
                    however, is not to be found in his collected works, probably because it was
                    deemed unworthy of the reputation which he subsequently acquired. A few months
                    afterwards, on the death of Audifret, followed as it was by some changes in the
                    government of the congregation, which he d not relish, Fléchier laid aside the
                    habit of the <hi rend="italic">doctri</hi><hi rend="italic">naires,</hi> and
                    proceeded to Paris, where he was at first emp oyec m the humble occupation of a
                    parochial catechist; but he soon made himsclf known by his Latin and French
                    Γηθηϊ’π· P <hi rend="superscript"> articularl</hi> y.by <hi rend="superscript">
                        a</hi> description in Latin verse of <hi rend="italic">•</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> ne</hi><hi rend="italic
                        subscript"> 1 ι</hi><hi rend="italic">.,</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        r</hi><hi rend="italic">''</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> lill</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">'</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        carousal</hi><hi rend="italic">&gt; Circus Regius,</hi> given by Louis XIV.
                    in 16U2. This was the commencement of Fléchier’s reputation. He was now
                    entrusted with the education of Louis Urbain Lefevre de Caumartin, afterwards
                    intendant of finances and counsellor of state; and as the house of Louis de
                    Caumartin, the father of his pupil, was then frequented by the most considerable
                    personages both of the court and the city, Fléchier was thus introduced into the
                    first society, amongst which his talents, amiability, gentleness of demeanour,
                    and regularity of manners, soon procured him many friends. The Duke of
                    Montausier, who was not prodigal of his notice, conceived a great regard for
                    Fléchier, declared himself his patron, and having presented him to the dauphin,
                    procured him the place of reader to that young prince. The sermons of Fléchier
                    increased his reputation, which was afterwards raised to the highest pitch by
                    his funeral orations. Having been chosen to pronounce that of Madame de
                    Montausicr, he displayed so great talent on the occasion that his discourse
                    opened to him the doors of the French Academy, into which he was received in
                    1673, in the room of Μ. Godeau, bishop of Venice. He was admitted the same day
                    with Racine, and having precedence in addressing the Academy, his discourse was
                    warmly applauded; the great poct however was less fortunate than the orator, for
                    his address being scarcely audible, was coldly received and unfavourably judged
                    of; so much is chancc concerned even in the success of eminent merit. The
                    favours of the court now flowed upon Fléchier. The king gave him successively
                    the abbey of St Leverin, in the diocese of Poitiers, the office of almoner to
                    the dauphiness, and, in. 1685, the bishopric of Lavaur, aecompanying his
                    kindness with the most flattering expressions of favour and regard. “I have made
                    you wait a little for a place which you have long merited,” said the monarch;
                    “but I did not wish to deprive myself sooner of the pleasure of hearing you.”
                    From the see of Lavaur Fléchier was, in 1687, translated to that of Nismes,
                    which was more valuable, and also accounted more honourable. His own wish was to
                    remain at Lavaur; but the king overcame his repugnance to the proposed
                    translation by making him sensible that he would be more useful to the church at
                    Nismes than at Lavaur, and that in the former place there was more labour to be
                    performed and more good to be done. In fact the Calvinists were very numerous at
                    Nismes; and although several had made abjuration, their conversion was at best
                    but equivocal. But Fléchier, by his prudent conduct, in which zeal was tempered
                    by charity, brought back the greater number of these sectaries to the bosom of
                    the church, and made himself esteemed and beloved even by those who declined to
                    abjure their faith. During the troubles in the Cevenncs he softened, as much as
                    in him lay, the rigour of the edicts, and showed himself so sensible of the
                    evils of persecution, and so indulgent even to what he regarded as error, that
                    his memory is, even at this day, held in veneration amongst the Protestants of
                    that district. In the famine which succeeded the winter of 1709, he distributed
                    immense sums, making no distinction between Catholics and Protestants; all were
                    his children, and all shared his beneficence in proportion to their respective
                    wants. He also published an eloquent pastoral letter on the subject of a cross
                    of St Gervais, which, it was pretended, worked miracles, and warned his flock
                    against those lying wonders, by which the credulity of the people has frequently
                    been abused. This appears to have been amongst his last efforts in the cause of
                    truth and religion. I he good bishop, indeed, foresaw that his end was now
                    approaching; and, having prepared for himsclf a humble tomb, he died at <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193753292?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-3292-0618"
                    />Montpellier on the 16th February 1710, at the advanced age of seventy-eight.
                    “He died,” says D’Alembert, “lamented bv the Catholics, regretted by the
                    Protestants, and having always exhibited to his brethren an admirable model of
                    zeal and charity, simplicity and eloquence.” Flechιer s works are, <hi
                        rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Antonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Mariae</hi><hi rend="italic">Gratiani</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">do Vita Jοanms Lrancιscι Commendoni</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Cardinalis</hi> libri iv. Paris, 1669, in 12mo; 2. <hi rend="italic">La Vie
                        du Cardinal Cammendon,</hi> Paris, 16 1, in 4to; 3. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pe</hi><hi rend="italic">Casibus Virorum Illustrium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >autοre Antonio Mana</hi><hi rend="italic">Gratiano,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >opera</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">studio Sp.
                        Elech£rii,</hi> Paris, 1680, in 4to; 4. <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Theodose-le-Grand,</hi> Paris, 1679, in 4to, composed for
                    the education of the dauphin; 5. <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">du Cardinal Xιmenes,</hi> Paris, 1693, in 4to; 6. <hi
                        rend="italic">Oraisons</hi><hi rend="italic">Funebres,</hi> 1681, in 4to and
                    in 12mo; 7. <hi rend="italic">Panégyriques</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                        Saints,</hi> Paris, 1690, in 4to; <hi rend="italic">S.. Sermons de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Marale</hi><hi rend="italic">prêches devant le Roi,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">aece</hi><hi rend="italic">des Discours synodaux et les
                        Sermons prêches par Flechier aux Etats de Languedoc et dans sa
                        Cathédrale,</hi> in 3 vols. 12mo; 9. <hi rend="italic">OEuvres Posthumes,
                        contenant ses Harangues, Compliments, Discours,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Poesies</hi><hi rend="italic">Latines, Poésies Françaises,</hi> Paris,
                    1712, in 12mo; 10. <hi rend="italic">Mandements et Lettres pastorales, avec son
                        Oraison funèbre par</hi><hi rend="italic">l’Abbe</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                        Jarry,</hi> Paris, 1712, in 12mo; 11. <hi rend="italic">Lettres Choisies sur
                        divers sujets,</hi> Paris, 1715, in 2 vols. 12mo; 12. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Relation d’un Voyage en Auvergne.</hi> The only collection yet published of
                    the works of Fléchier is that of the Abbé Ducreux, canon of Auxerre, which
                    appeared under the tide of <hi rend="italic">OEuvres</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Completes de Messire Esprit Flechier,</hi> Nismes, 1782, in 10 vols. 8vo.
                    If we except the History of Theodosius, pulpit eloquence is the only branch of
                    the belles-lettres cultivated by Fléchier in which he excelled. His Funeral
                    Orations have been compared with those of Bossuet, without attending to this
                    distinction, that comparisons become useless between two kinds of genius which
                    are totally different. That of Bossuet was sublime throughout. Fléchier, on the
                    other hand, was only remarkable for the nobleness of his thoughts and the
                    harmony of his diction. It is true that he possessed in an eminent degree these
                    two qualities of an orator, and that nobody has carried the latter further than
                    hc; but even in that department where he has been most successful, Fléchier is
                    not without faults, and may bc reproached with an ambition of giving point to
                    his thoughts, an affectation of symmetry in the style, and a love of antitheses,
                    all at variance with the principles of good taste. But if his funeral orations
                    and sermons lose much of their merit by a too measured elegance, his pastoral
                    instructions and synodal discourses are wholly free from such affectation,
                    indeed as remarkable for simplicity of style as for generosity of sentiment, and
                    that indulgent spirit which laments whilst it combats error, and which,
                    repudiating all attempts at persecution, seeks to win men over to the right way,
                    not by the instrumentality of fear, but through the medium of their
                    understanding and affections. “C’est dans ceş ouvrages,” says a distinguished
                    French critic, “que la philosophie elle-même apprendra l’usage qu’on doit faire
                    des lumières et du sentiment, et se convaincra que l’humanité n’a pas de
                    consolation plus solide que la religion, comme la politique n’a pas de meilleur
                    appui.” <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
