<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-1706-0496-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FEAST, or Festival</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999743">Liquors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205364">Mauritania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t2w">Feasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6487x">Liquors</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193751706?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FEAST, or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Festival</hi></label>, in a religious sense, is the ceremony of feasting and
                    thanksgiving. The word is formed from the Latin <hi rend="italic">festum,</hi>
                    which some derive <hi rend="italic">a feriari,</hi> to keep holiday; others,
                    however, derive it from the Greek <hi rend="italic">⅛τια,(n, I feast</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">entertain,</hi> from i&lt;rnα, <hi rend="italic">hearth,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">fire.</hi> Feasts and the ceremonies connected with them
                    have formed great part of the religion of almost all nations and sects; of the
                    Greeks, Romans, Hebrews, Christians, and Mahommedans.</p>
                <p part="N">The first feasts amongst the Greeks were celebrated in solemn assemblies
                    of the whole nation, on occasion of their games, as the Olympian, the Pythian,
                    the Isthmian, and Nemaean; but in process of time they had many others the
                    principal of which are enumerated in the course of this work.</p>
                <p part="N">The Romans also had abundance of stated feasts in honour of their
                    deities and heroes; as the Saturnalia, Cerealia, Lupercalia, Liberalia,
                    Neptunalia, Consualia, Portumnalia, Vulcanalia, Palilia, Divalia, and others.
                    They had also feasts instituted occasionally, as Carmentalia, Quirinalia,
                    Terminalia, Floralia, Compitalia, Lemuria, Vernalia; besides other moveable and
                    occasional ones, to give thanks to the gods for benefits received; to implore
                    their assistance, or to appease their wrath, as the Paganalia, Feralia,
                    Bacchanalia, Ambarvalia, Amburbalia, Suovetaurilia, and various others,
                    denominated <hi rend="italic">feriae</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> as Sementinae,
                    Latinae, &amp;c. The feasts were divided into days of sacrifice, and days of
                    banqueting and feasting; days of games, and days of rest or <hi rend="italic"
                        >feriae.</hi> As there was but little history written, or at least
                    published, in those days, one end of these feasts was to preserve the
                    remembrance of past occurrences.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal festivals of the Jews were the feast of trumpets, that of
                    the expiation, that of tabernacles, that of the dedication, that of the
                    passover, that of pentecost, and that of purification. The modern Jews have
                    other feasts marked in their kalendar, but these are of modern institution. The
                    Mahommedans, besides their weekly feast or Sabbath, which is observed on Friday,
                    have two solemn feasts, the first of which is called the Feast of Victims, and
                    celebrated on the tenth day of the last month of their year; and the second is
                    called Bairam. The Chinese have two solemn annual feasts, in the memory of
                    Confucius, besides others of less note on various days of the year.</p>
                <p part="N">Festivals amongst us are either <hi rend="italic">immoveable</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">rnονeαble. Immoveable feasts</hi> are those constantly
                    celebrated on the same day of the year. The principal of these are Christmas day
                    or the Nativity, the Circumcision, Epiphany, Candlemas or the Purification, Lady
                    Day or the Annunciation, called also the Incarnation and Conception, All Saints,
                    and All Souls; besides the days of the several apostles, which with us are
                    feasts, though not <hi rend="italic">feriae. Moveable feasts</hi> are those
                    which are not confined to the same day of the year. Of these, the principal is
                    Easter, which gives the law to the rest, all of them following and keeping their
                    proper distances from it; as Palm Sunday, Good Friday, Ash-Wednesday,
                    Sexagesima, Ascension-Day, Pentecost, and Trinity-Sunday. The four feasts which
                    the English laws take special notice of are, the Annunciation of the blessed
                    Virgin Mary, or Lady Day, the 25th of March; the nativity of St John the
                    Baptist, on the 24th of June; the Feast of St Michael the Archangel, on the 29th
                    of September; and that of St Thomas the Apostle, on the 21st of December.</p>
                <p part="N">Besides these feasts, which are <hi rend="italic">general,</hi> and
                    enjoined bv the church, there are others <hi rend="italic">local</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">occasional)</hi> enjoined by the magistrate, or voluntarily
                    observed by the people, as days of thanksgiving for delivery from wars, plague»,
                    and other evils; and also the vigils or wakes in commemoration of the dedication
                    of particular churches.</p>
                <p part="N">The prodigious increase of festival days in the Christian church
                    commenced towards the close of the fourth century, and was occasioned by the
                    discovery which was tnθ <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> made of the remains of
                    martyrs and other holy men, or the commemoration of whom they were established.
                    B¶ instead of being set apart for pious exercises, these festiva s were abused
                    in indolence, voluptuousness, and criminal prac <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193751719?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-1719-0497"/>tices. Many
                    of them were instituted on’ a Pagan model, and perverted to the most scandalous
                    purposes.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Feast</hi> is also used to signify a banquet or
                    sumptuous entertainment, without any immediate view to religion.</p>
                <p part="N">The use of the word, in this sense, arises from the circumstance that
                    part of the ceremony in many of the ancient festivals, both those of the
                    heathens and of the Christians, was good eating; though Huet chooses to derive
                    the word from <hi rend="italic">festinare,</hi> which, in an ancient Latin
                    version of Origen’s Commentary on Matthew, signifies to feast: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ui</hi><hi rend="italic">veniens illuc</hi><hi rend="italic">Jesus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">festinet, cum discipulis</hi><hi rend="italic">suis.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Social or civil feasts were also expressed by the words <hi
                        rend="italic">convivium</hi> and <hi rend="italic">compotatio</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">concarnatio.</hi> Cicero says that, in the Roman language, the
                    word <hi rend="italic">convivium,</hi> which means people assembled at table, is
                    more significant of refinement than the Greek word <hi rend="italic"
                        >compotatio</hi> or <hi rend="italic">concoenatio.</hi> The Roman term, says
                    he, expresses the conjunction of body and mind which ought to take place at an
                    entertainment; the Greek merely denotes what relates to the body alone.</p>
                <p part="N">As food is necessary to our existence, eating together forms a bond of
                    association among mankind. People at a feast, says one of the ancients, seem to
                    form but one body and one soul. All nations, whether savage or civilized, have
                    regarded the pleasures of the table as the occasion of the most agreeable
                    society. This species of enjoyment, abstracting from its susceptibility of
                    abuse, makes but one family of all whom it brings together. It levels the
                    distinctions introduced by policy or prejudice, and disposes men to regard one
                    another as brethren. It is here that people feel the equality established by
                    nature, forget the evils of life, extinguish their hatred, and cause their
                    enmities to cease. For this reason Aristotle considers as a breach of die social
                    principle the custom of eating apart which obtained amongst the ancient
                    Egyptians, and praises the convivial repasts established by Minos and
                    Lycurgus.</p>
                <p part="N">The Persians generally deliberated on business at table, but never
                    determined or put their determinations in execution, except in the morning
                    before having eaten.</p>
                <p part="N">When the Germans, says Tacitus, wanted to reconcile enemies, to form
                    alliances, to appoint chiefs, or to treat of war and peace, it was during the
                    repast that they took counsel; a time in which the mind is most open to the
                    impressions of simple truth, or most easily animated to great attempts. These
                    artless people during the conviviality of the feast spoke without disguise, and
                    next day weighed the counsels of the former evening; they deliberated at a time
                    when they were not disposed to deceive, and took their resolution when they were
                    least liable to be deceived.</p>
                <p part="N">By a fundamental law of the state, people of rank amongst the Rhodians
                    were obliged to dine daily with those who ∣ad the management of affairs, in
                    order to deliberate with them concerning such things as were necessary or useful
                    for the country; and on this account the principal ministers of the kingdom were
                    obliged to keep open table for all who could be of service to the state.</p>
                <p part="N">Amongst the Romans, the place where they supped was generally the
                    vestibule, lest a more retired part of the house should encourage licentiousness
                    and disorder. There were several laws which restricted their meals to the
                    vestibules. But when luxury reigned at Rome, the wealthy had superb halls for
                    their entertainments. Lucullus had many, each of which bore the name of some
                    deity; and this was a mark which indicated to the servants the expense of the
                    entertainment. The expense of a supper in Lucullus’s hall of Apollo amounted to
                    fifty thousand drachmas. The all i∏ which Nero feasted imitated the revolutions
                    of the <hi rend="superscript"> e</hi> avens, by the circular motion of its walls
                    and its ceiling; . represented the different seasons of the year, changing at
                    every course, and showering down flowers and perfumes on the guests.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> uP <hi rend="superscript"> ie r</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> "≡ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> s</hi> did not, like us, confine themselves to one table
                    at their feasts; they had generally two; one for the service of animal food,
                    which was afterwards removed; and another for the dessert, at which last they
                    sung, and poured out their libations. The Greeks and eastern nations observed
                    the same custom, and even the Jews in their solemn feasts and at sacrifices.</p>
                <p part="N">The Romans, in the time of Nero, had tables made of citron wood brought
                    from Mauritania, which were covered with purple and gold, and raised on feet of
                    carved ivory. It is said that these tables were more precious than gold itself.
                    Dion Cassius affirms that Seneca had five hundred of these, which he made use of
                    one after another; and Tertullian informs us that Cicero had only one. The
                    Romans usually chose the king of the feast, or chairman as we would call him, by
                    a cast of the dice.</p>
                <p part="N">We learn from Herodotus that the ancients had neither cups nor bowls,
                    but drank out of little horns tipped with silver or gold. <hi rend="superscript"
                        > l</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The Greeks and Romans kept a domestic for the purpose of reading during
                    their meals and feasts. The head of the family sometimes performed the office of
                    reader himself; and we learn that the Emperor Severus often read whilst his
                    family sat or rather reclined at table. The time of reading was generally at
                    supper; and guests were invited to a reading, as they arc now a-days to play
                    cards. In their flourishing times the Greeks did not, according to their own
                    expression, profane the sanctity of the table, but rather adorned it with
                    ingenious and elegant conversation, proposing moral topics, of which Plutarch
                    has preserved a collection. Ancient philosophers have remarked, that heroes
                    rarely assembled convivially without bringing affairs of consequence into
                    discussion, or deliberating upon those which regarded either present affairs or
                    future contingencies.</p>
                <p part="N">When Rome became corrupted with luxury, singers, dancers, musicians,
                    stage-players, and people who told pleasant tales, were brought into the hall to
                    amuse the guests. Plutarch informs us that Caesar, after his triumphs, treated
                    the Roman people at twenty-two thousand tables; and by calculation it would seem
                    that there must have been at these tables upwards of two hundred thousand
                    persons.</p>
                <p part="N">It was a custom among the Romans, at the end of a feast, to drink out of
                    a large cup as often as there were letters in the names of their mistresses.</p>
                <p part="N">Feasting seems to have been the chief delight of the Germans, Gauls,
                    Britons, and all the other Celtic nations; and in this they indulged themselves
                    to the utmost, as often as they had an opportunity. “Amongst these nations,”
                    says an author who had carefully studied their manners, “there is no public
                    assembly, either for civil or religious purposes, duly held; no birth-day,
                    marriage, or funeral, properly celebrated; no treaty of peace or alliance
                    rightly cemented, without a great feast.” It was by frequent entertainments of
                    this kind that the great men or chieftains gained the affections and rewarded
                    the services of their followers; and those who made the greatest feasts were
                    sure to be most popular, and to have the largest retinue. These feasts, in which
                    plenty was more regarded than elegance, commonly lasted several days, and the
                    guests seldom retired until they had consumed the provisions and exhausted the
                    liquors provided for the occasion. Athenaeus describes an entertainment given by
                    Arcamnes, a wealthy prince of Gaul, which continued a whole year without
                    interruption, and at which all the people of Gaul, and even all strangers who
                    passed through that country, were made welcome. At these feasts they sometimes
                    consulted about the most important affairs of state, and formed resolutions
                    relating to peace and war; imagining that men spoke their real sentiments with
                    the greatest freedom, and were apt to form the boldest designs, <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193751732?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-1732-0498"/>when their
                    spirits were exhilarated with the pleasures of the table. The conversation at
                    these entertainments frequently turned on the great exploits which the guests
                    themselves or their ancestors had performed in war; a circumstance which
                    sometimes occasioned quarrels, and even bloodshed.</p>
                <p part="N">As to the drink used at these feasts, particularly in Britain, it seems
                    probable that before the introduction of agriculture into the island, mead, or
                    honey diluted with water, was the only strong liquor known to its inhabitants,
                    as it was to many other ancient nations. And this continued to be a favourite
                    beverage amongst the ancient Britons and their posterity long after they had
                    become acquainted with other liquors. The mead-maker was the eleventh person in
                    dignity in the courts of the ancient princes of Wales, and took place next to
                    the physician. An ancient law of that principality shows how much this liquor
                    was esteemed by the British princes. “There are three things in the court which
                    must be communicated to the king before they are made known to any other person:
                    first, every sentence of the judge; second, every new song; and, third, every
                    cask of mead.” This was perhaps the liquor which is called by Ossian the joy and
                    strength of shells, with which his heroes were so much delighted. After the
                    introduction of agriculture, ale or beer became the most general drink of all
                    the British nations who practised that art, as -it had long been of all the
                    Celtic nations on the Continent. If the Phoenicians or Greeks imported any wine
                    into Britain, it was only in small quantities; and that generous liquor was but
                    little known in this island until after it had been conquered by the Romans.</p>
                <p part="N">In the reign of Charles V. of France, the custom of placing the lights
                    upon the table had not yet been introduced. A number of domestics held the
                    lights in their hands during the whole time of the repast.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
