<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-1654-0492-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FAST</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mh6r">Fasting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wv7t">Paganism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921717">Fasting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819237">Assyrians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193751654?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FAST</label>, in general, denotes abstinence from
                    food; but is more particularly used for such abstinence on a religious
                    account.</p>
                <p part="N">Religious fasting has been practised by most nations from the remotest
                    antiquity. Some divines even pretend that it had its origin in the earthly
                    paradise, where our first parents were forbidden to eat of the tree of
                    knowledge. But though this seems carrying the matter too far, it ⅛ certain that
                    the Jewish church has observed fasts ever since its first institution. Nor were
                    the neighbouring nations, the Egyptians, Phoenicians, and Assyrians, without
                    their fasts. The Egyptians, according to Herodotus, sacrificed a cow to Isis,
                    after having prepared themselves by fasting and prayer; a custom which he
                    likewise ascribes to the women of Cyrene. Porphyry affirms, that the Egyptians,
                    before their stated sacrifices, always rested a number of days, sometimes even
                    of weeks; and that during this time the priests and devotees not only abstained
                    from flesh, fish, wine, and oil, but even from bread, and some kinds of pulse.
                    These austerities were communicated by them to the Greeks, who observed their
                    fasts much in the same manner. The Athenians had the Eleusinian and
                    Thesmophorian fasts, the observance of which was very rigorous, especially
                    amongst the women, who spent one whole day sitting on the ground in a mournful
                    dress, without taking any nourishment. In the island of Crete, the priests of
                    Jupiter were obliged to abstain during their whole lives from fish, flesh, and
                    baked meats. Apuleius informs us, that whoever had a mind to be initiated in the
                    mysteries of Cybele was obliged to prepare himself by fasting ten days; and,
                    indeed, all the pagan deities, whether male or female, required this duty of
                    those who desired to be initiated into their mysteries, of the priests and
                    priestesses who gave out the oracles, and of those who came to consult them.</p>
                <p part="N">Amongst the heathens fasting was also practised before some of their
                    military enterprises. Aristotle informs us, that the Lacedaemonians having
                    resolved to succour a city of the allies, ordained a fast throughout the whole
                    extent of their dominions, without excepting even the domestic animals; and this
                    they did for two ends, first, to spare provisions in favour of the besieged,
                    and, secondly, to draw down the blessing of heaven upon their enterprise. The
                    inhabitants of Tarentum, when besieged by the Romans, demanded succours from
                    their neighbours of Rhegium, who immediately commanded a fast throughout their
                    whole territories. Their enterprise having proved successful by throwing a
                    supply of provisions into the town, the Romans were obliged to raise the siege;
                    and the Tarentines, in memory of this deliverance, instituted a fast to be
                    annually observed ever afterwards.</p>
                <p part="N">Fasting has always been reckoned a particular duty amongst philosophers
                    and religious people, some of whom have carried their abstinence to an
                    incredible length. At Rome it was practised both by kings and emperors. Numa
                    Pompilius, Julius Caesar, Augustus, Vespasian, and others, we are told, observed
                    stated fasts; and Julian surnamed the Apostate was so exact in this observance
                    as to outdo the priests themselves, and even the most rigid philosophers. The
                    Pythagoreans kept a continual lent; but with this difference, that they believed
                    the use of fish to be equally unlawful with that of flesh. Besides their
                    constant temperance, they also frequently fasted rigidly for a considerable
                    time. In this respect, however, they were all outdone by their master
                    Pythagoras, who continue his fasts for no less than fifty days together. Even
                    Apollonius Tyaneus, one of his most celebrated disciples, cou never equal him in
                    the length of his fasts, though these greatly exceeded those of the ordinary
                    Pythagoreans. The Gymnosophists, or Brahmins of the East, are a s° very
                    remarkable for their severe fastings; and thθ 0 J nese, according to Father
                    Lecomte, have likewise t <hi rend="superscript"> eιr</hi> stated fasts, with
                    forms of prayer, for preserving them <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ° <hi
                        rend="superscript"> m</hi> barrenness, inundations, earthquakes, and other
                    calamitae®· The Mahommedans too, who possess so large a part or ≡ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ' &gt; <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193751667?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-1667-0493"/>are very
                    remarkable for the strict observance of fasts; and the exactness of their
                    dervises in this respect is extraordinary.</p>
                <p part="N">Fasting was often used by the heathens for superstitious purposes;
                    sometimes to procure the interpretation of dreams; at others, to serve as an
                    antidote against the pernicious consequences of nocturnal visions. The Jews,
                    though expressly forbidden to fast upon Sabbath days, think themselves at
                    liberty to dispense with this duty when they happen the night preceding to have
                    had frightful and unlucky dreams, which they consider as presaging great
                    misfortunes. On these occasions they observe a formal fast during the whole day;
                    and at night the patient, having invited three of his friends, addresses himself
                    to them seven times in a very solemn manner, saying, “May the dream I have had
                    prove a lucky one and his friends answer as many times, “Amen, may it bc lucky,
                    and God make it so after which, in order to encourage him, they conclude the
                    ceremony with the words of Ecclesiastes, “Go eat thy bread with joy,” and then
                    set themselves down to table. They have also added several fasts not commanded
                    in the law of Moses, particularly three, in memory of sore distresses which
                    their nation has at different times suffered. The abstinence of the ancient Jews
                    commonly lasted twenty-seven or twenty-eight hours at a time, beginning before
                    sunset, and not ending till some hours after sunset the next day. On these days
                    they were obliged to wear white robes in token of grief and repentance, to cover
                    themselves with sackloth, or their worst clothes, to lie on ashes, to sprinkle
                    these on their heads, and to perform other like ceremonies. Some spent the whole
                    night and day following in the temple or synagogue, in prayers and other
                    devotions, barefooted, with a scourge in their hands, of which they sometimes
                    made a good use, in order to excite their zeal. Lastly, to complete their
                    abstinence, they were accustomed at night to eat nothing but a little bread
                    dipped in water, with some salt for seasoning; except indeed they chose to add
                    to their repast some bitter herbs and pulse.</p>
                <p part="N">The ancients, both Jews and Pagans, had also their fasts or purifying
                    the body, particularly the priests and such as were any way employed at the
                    altars; for when nocturnal disorders happened to them, it was unlawful to
                    approach the altars all the next day, which they were bound to employ in
                    purifying themselves. On this account, at great festivals, where their ministry
                    could not be dispensed with, it was usual for them, on the eve of these solemn
                    occasions, not only to fast, but also, for the greater certainty, to abstain
                    from sleep. For this purpose the high priest had. under officers to awake him,
                    if overtaken with sleep, against which other preventives were also employed.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
