<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-2785-0579-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">FILIGRANE, Filigree, or Fillagree, Work</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91b3s">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4251fv6s">Wire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:944368">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176150">Wire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193752785?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">FILIGRANE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Filigree</hi>, or
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Fillagree, Work</hi></label>, a kind of enrichment
                    on gold or silver, wrought delicately in the manner of little threads or grains,
                    or both intermixed. The word is compounded of <hi rend="italic">fil
                        οrjilum,</hi> a thread, and <hi rend="italic">granum,</hi> a grain, and in
                    Latin is called <hi rend="italic">filatim</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >elaboratum</hi><hi rend="italic">opus, argentum,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >aurum.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">There is no manufacture in any part of the world which has been more
                    admired and celebrated than the fine gold and silver fillagree of Sumatra; and
                    what renders it a matter of still greater curiosity, is the coarseness of the
                    tools employed in the workmanship, and which, in the hands of an European, would
                    not be thought sufficiently perfect for the most ordinary purposes. They are
                    rudely and inartificially formed by the goldsmith, from any piece of old iron
                    which he can pick up. When one of them is engaged to execute a piece of work,
                    his first request is usually for a piece of iron hoop to make his wire-drawing
                    instrument; an old hammer head, stuck in a block, serves him for an anvil; and
                    his pair of compasses is often composed of two old nails tied together at one
                    end. The gold is melted in a piece of <hi rend="italic">ρreeoo</hi> or earthen
                    rice-pot, or sometimes in a crucible of ordinary clay. In general no bellows are
                    used, but the fire is blown with the mouth, through a joint of bamboo; and if
                    the quantity of metal to be melted is considerable, three or four persons sit
                    round the furnace, which is an old broken quallee or iron pot, and blow
                    together. At Padang alone, where the manufacture is most considerable, they have
                    adopted the Chinese bellows. The method of drawing the wire differs but little
                    from that which is used by European workmen. When drawn to a sufficient
                    fineness, it is flattened by beating it on the anvil; and when flattened, a
                    twist is given to it like tlιat in the whalebone handle of a punch ladle, by
                    rubbing it on a block of wood with a flat stick. After twisting they again beat
                    it upon the anvil, and thus it becomes flattened wire with indented edges. The
                    end of the wire is folded down with a pair of pincers, and thus is formed a
                    leaf, or element of a flower in their work, which is cut off. The end is again
                    folded and cut off, till they have <hi rend="italic">got</hi> a sufficient
                    number of leaves, yhich are laid on singly. Patterns of the flowers or foliage,
                        <hi rend="superscript"> ιn</hi> which there is seldom much variety, are
                    prepared on paper of the size of the gold plate on which the fillagree is to be
                    laid. According to these, they begin to dispose on the plate the larger
                    compartments of the foliage, for which they use plain flattened wire of a larger
                    size, and fill it up with the leaves before mentioned. In order to fix the work,
                    they employ a gelatinous substance, made of the red-hot berry called <hi
                        rend="italic">boca sago,</hi> ground to a pulp on a rough stone, which pulp
                    they place on a young cocoa nut about the size oτ a walnut, the top and bottom
                    being cut off. After the leaves have been all placed in order, and stuck on bit
                    by bit, a solder is prepared of gold filings and borax moistened with water,
                    which is strewed over the plate, when it is put in the fire for a short time,
                    and the whole becomes united. This kind of work on a gold plate is called <hi
                        rend="italic">carrang</hi><hi rend="italic">papan;</hi> but when the work is
                    open, it is called <hi rend="italic">carrang trousc.</hi> In executing the
                    latter, the foliage is laid out upon a card, or soft kind of wood, and stuck on,
                    as before described, with the sago berry; and the work, when finished, being
                    strewed over with the solder, is put into the fire, when the card or soft wood
                    burning away, the gold remains connected. If the piece be large it is soldered
                    at several times. In the manufacture of badjoo buttons, they first make the
                    lower part flat, and having a mould formed of a piece of buffalo’s horn,
                    indented to several sizes, each like one half of a bullet mould, they lay their
                    work over one of these holes, and with a horn punch press it into the form of a
                    button; after which they complete the upper part. When the fillagree is finished
                    they cleanse it by boiling it in water with common salt and alum, or sometimes
                    lime juice; and in order to give it that fine purple colour which they call <hi
                        rend="italic">sapo,</hi> they boil it in water mixed with brimstone. The
                    manner of making the little balls with which their works are sometimes
                    ornamented, is simple. They take a piece of charcoal, and having cut it flat and
                    smooth, make in it a small hole, which they fill with gold dust, and this being
                    melted in the fire, becomes a little ball. They are very inexpert at finishing
                    and polishing the plain parts, hinges, screws, and the like, being in this as
                    much excelled by the European artists as the latter fall short of them in the
                    fineness and minuteness of the foliage. The Chinese also make fillagree mostly
                    of silver, which looks elegant, but wants the extraordinary delicacy of the
                    Malay work. The price of the workmanship depends upon the difficulty or
                    uncommonness of the pattern. In some articles of usual demand it does not exceed
                    one third of the value of the gold, but in matters of fancy it is generally
                    equal to that of the metal.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
