<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0651-0620-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MASSYS, or Matsys, Quintin</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 620</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:949055">Guilds</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sk1m">Guilds</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n651/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MASSYS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Matsys, Quintin</hi></label>
                    (1466-1530), was born at Louvain, where he first learned a mechanical art.
                    During the greater part of the 15th century the centres in which the painters of
                    the Low Countries most congregated were Bruges, Ghent, and Brussels. Towards the
                    close of the same period Louvain took a prominent part in giving employment to
                    workmen of every craft. It was not till the opening of the 16th century that
                    Antwerp usurped the lead which it afterwards maintained against Bruges and
                    Ghent, Brussels, Mechlin, anti Louvain. Quintin Massys was one of the first men
                    of any note who gave repute to the guild of Antwerp. A legend still current
                    relates how the smith of Louvain was induced by affection for the daughter of an
                    artist to change his trade and acquire proficiency in painting. A less poetic
                    but perhaps more real version of the story tells that Quintin had a brother with
                    whom he was brought up by his father Josse Massys, a smith, who held the
                    lucrative offices of clockmaker and architect to the municipality of Louvain. It
                    came to be a question which of the sons should follow the paternal business, and
                    which carve out a new profession for himself. Josse the son elected to succeed
                    his father, and Quin tin then gave himself to the study of painting. But it is
                    not improbable that as he lived in an age when single individuals were cunning
                    in various branches of design, Quintin was equally familiar with the chisel and
                    file or the brush and pencil. We are not told expressly from whom Quintin
                    learned the profession in which he acquired repute, but his style seems
                    necessarily derived from the lessons of Dierick Bouts, who took to Louvain the
                    mixed art of Memling and Van der Weyden. When he settled at Antwerp, at the age
                    of twenty-five, he probably had a style with an impress of its own, which
                    certainly contributed most importantly to the revival of Flemish art on the
                    lines of Van Eyck and Van der Weyden. What particularly characterizes Quintin
                    Massys is the strong religious feeling which he inherited from earlier schools.
                    But that again was permeated by realism which frequently degenerated into the
                    grotesque. Nor would it be too much to say that the facial peculiarities of the
                    boors of Van Steen or Ostade have their counterparts in the pictures of Massys,
                    who was not, however, trained to use them in the same homely way. From Van der
                    Weyden’s example we may trace the dryness of outline and shadeless modelling and
                    the pitiless finish even of trivial detail, from the Van Eycks and Memling
                    through Dierick Bouts the superior glow and richness of transparent pigments,
                    which mark the pictures of Massys. The date of his retirement from Louvain is
                    1491, when he became a master in the guild of painters at Antwerp. His most
                    celebrated picture is that which he executed in 15.08 for the joiners’ company
                    in the cathedral of his adopted city. Next in importance to that is the Maries
                    of Scripture round the Virgin and Child, which was ordered for a chapel in the
                    cathedral of Louvain. Both altar-pieces are now in public museums, one at
                    Antwerp, the other at Brussels. Both challenge attention for the qualities which
                    have already been described. They display great earnestness in expression, great
                    minuteness of finish, and a general absence of effect by light or shade. As in
                    early Flemish pictures, so in those of Massys, superfluous care is lavished on
                    jewellery, edgings, and ornament. To the great defect of want of atmosphere such
                    faults may be added as affectation, the result of excessive straining after
                    tenderness in women, or common gesture and grimace suggested by a wish to render
                    pictorially the brutality of jailers and executioners. Yet in every instance an
                    effort is manifest to develop and express individual character. This tendency in
                    Massys is chiefly illustrated in his pictures of male and female market bankers
                    (Louvre and Windsor), in which an attempt is made to display concentrated
                    cupidity and avarice. The other tendency to excessive emphasis of tenderness may
                    be seen in two replicas of the Virgin and Child at Berlin and Amsterdam, where
                    the ecstatic kiss of the mother is quite unreal. But in these examples there is
                    a remarkable glow of colour which takes us past many defects. Expression of
                    despair is strongly exaggerated in a Lucretia at the museum of Vienna. On the
                    whole the best pictures of Massys are the quietest; his Virgin and Christ or
                    Ecce Homo and Mater Dolorosa (London and Antwerp) display as much serenity and
                    dignity as seems consistent with the master’s art. A telling example of his
                    partiality for grotesque character in face is an Epiphany in the collection of
                    Mr H. R. Hughes in England. His skill as a portrait painter has not been
                    sufficiently admired, probably because most of his likenesses have ceased to be
                    identified with his name. Egidius at Longford, which drew from Sir Thomas More a
                    eulogy in Latin verse, is but one of a numerous class, to which we may add the
                    portrait of Maximilian of Austria in the gallery of Amsterdam, a masterpiece
                    which at some future period may afford a clue to other works of similar
                    treatment in English and Continental galleries. Massys in this branch of
                    practice was much under the influence of his contemporaries Lucas of Leyden and
                    Mabuse. His tendency to polish and smoothness excluded to some extent the
                    subtlety of modulation remarkable in Holbein and Durer. There is reason to think
                    that he was well acquainted with both these German masters. He probably met
                    Holbein more than once on his way to England. He saw Dürer at Antwerp in 1520.
                    Quintin died at Antwerp in 1530. The puritan feeling which slumbered in him was
                    fatal to some of his relatives. His sister Catherine and her husband suffered at
                    Louvain in 1543 for the then capital offence of reading the Bible, he being
                    decapitated, she buried alive in the square fronting the cathedral.</p>
                <p>Quintin’s son, Jan Massys, inherited the art but not the skill of his parent. The
                    earliest of his works, a St Jerome, dated 1537, in the gallery of Vienna, the
                    latest, a Healing of Tobias, of 1564, in the museum of Antwerp, are sufficient
                    evidence of his tendency to substitute imitation for original thought.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
