<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0569-0542-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARIETTE, Auguste</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 542</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xh4p">Hieroglyphics</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1054286">Pashas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071040">Poor</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n569/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARIETTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Auguste</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Ferdinand</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">François,</hi> elder son of
                    François P. Mariette, advocate and town-clerk of Boulogne-sur-Mer, was born in
                    that town on the 11th of February 1821. Educated at the Boulogne municipal
                    college, he distinguished himself in geometry, physics, chemistry, history,
                    Latin, Greek, and English. He also evinced a remarkable talent for art. In 1839,
                    when but eighteen years of age, he went to England in the capacity of professor
                    of French aud drawing at a boys’ school at Stratford-on-Avon, which occupation
                    he exchanged in 1840 for that of pattern-designer to a ribbon manufacturer at
                    Coventry. Weary of ill-paid exile, he returned that same year to Boulogne,
                    resumed his interrupted studies, and in March 1841 took his bachelor’s degree
                    (with honourable mention) at Douai. He now became a professor at the college
                    where he had formerly been a student, and for some years supplemented his modest
                    salary by giving private lessons, and writing on historical and archaeological
                    subjects for various local periodicals. In the meanwhile his cousin, Nestor
                    I.’Hôte, the friend and fellow-traveller of Champoilion, died; and upon Auguste
                    Mariette devolved the pious task of sorting the multitudinous papers of the
                    deceased savant. The young man thenceforth became passionately interested in
                    Egyptology, devoted himself to the study of hieroglyphs and Coptic, and in 1847
                    published a <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi><hi rend="italic">Analytique</hi> of
                    the Egyptian Gallery of the Boulogne Museum. He had now found his vocation, and
                    in 1849, being appointed to a subordinate position in the Louvre, left Boulogne
                    for Paris. Entrusted shortly after with a Government mission for the purpose of
                    seeking and purchasing Coptic, Syriac, Arabic, and Ethiopie MSS. for the
                    national collection, he started for Egypt in 1850. Soon after his arrival he
                    made his celebrated discovery of the ruins of the Serapeum and the subterraneous
                    catacombs of the Apis-bulls, buried for probably some two thousand years under
                    the sands of the Libyan desert (see vol. vii. p. 773). His original mission
                    being abandoned, funds were now advanced for the prosecution of his researches,
                    and he remained in Egypt for four years, excavating, discovering, and
                    despatching archaeological treasures to the Louvre, of which museum he was, on
                    his return, appointed an assistant conservator. In 1858, by permission of his
                    own Government, he accepted the position of conservator of Egyptian monuments to
                    the ex-khedive, Ismail-Pasha, and so removed with his family to Cairo. His
                    history thenceforth becomes a chronicle of unwearied exploration and brilliant
                    success. The pyramid-fields of Memphis and Sakkara, and the necropolises of
                    Meydum, Abydos, and Thebes were ransacked for sepulchral treasures; the great
                    temples of Denderah and Edfoo were disinterred, and, with their tens of
                    thousands of inscriptions and bas-reliefs, restored to the light of day;
                    important excavations were carried out at Karnak, Medinet-Habu, and
                    Deir-el-Babari; Tanis (the Zoan of the Bible) was partially explored in the
                    Delta; and even Gebel Barkal in the far Soudan was made to yield monuments of
                    the Ethiopie kings. The Sphinx was also bared to the rock-level, and the famous
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0570-0543"/> granite and alabaster monument miscalled the
                    “Temple of the Sphinx” was discovered. In the meanwhile Mariette, raised
                    successively to the rank of bey and then of pasha, had founded the “École
                    Française d’Égyptologie” and the “Institut Égyptien,” and created <hi
                    rend="italic">ab ovo</hi> the museum at Bulak, the richest and by far the most
                    interesting Egyptian collection in the world. Honours and orders were showered
                    upon him. Poor in purse but rich in fame, he received in 1852 the grand cross of
                    the Legion of Honour and of the Medjidie, in 1855 the Red Eagle (first <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> class) of Prussia, in 1857 the Italian order of SS.
                    Maurice and Lazarus, and in 1858 the Austrian order of Francis-Joseph. In 1873
                    the Academy of Inscriptions decreed to him the great biennial prize of 20,000
                    francs, and in 1878 he was elected a member of the Institute. He was also an
                    honorary member of most of the learned societies of Europe. Though of herculean
                    strength and indomitable energy, he was not proof against over-work of all
                    kinds, physical, mental, and official. Prostrated in 1877 by a first attack of
                    the insidious malady from which only death released him, he lingered for a few
                    years, working to the last, and died at Cairo January 19, 1881. His remains,
                    enclosed in an ancient Egyptian sarcophagus chosen by himself for that purpose,
                    are interred within the precincts of the museumgarden at Bulak, facing the
                    entrance to that unrivalled collection which is his own noblest monument.</p>
                <p>Of Mariette’s numerous and important contributions to the literature of
                    Egyptology, we may here especially note the following works, which are not only
                    distinguished for their erudition and accuracy, but for the exquisite grace of
                    style with which they arc written :— <hi rend="italic">Le Sérapéum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Memphis,</hi> folio, 1857 and following years; <hi
                    rend="italic">Dendérah,</hi> five folios· and one 4to, 1873-75; <hi
                    rend="italic">Abydos,</hi> two folios and one 4to, 1870-80; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Karnak,,</hi> folio and 4to, 1875; <hi rend="italic">Deir-el-Bahari,</hi> folio
                    and 4to, 1877; <hi rend="italic">Listes géographiques des pylônes de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Karnak,</hi> folio, 1875; <hi rend="italic">Catalogue du Musée de
                    Boulaq,</hi> six éditions, 1864-76; <hi rend="italic">Aperçu de l'histoire
                    d'Égypte,</hi> four editions, 1864-74, &amp;c. His last, and one of his most
                    important works, <hi rend="italic">Les Mastabas</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">Ancien</hi><hi rend="italic">Empire,</hi> text and
                    illustrations facsimiled from the original MSS., folio, is now in course of
                    publication, edited by Professor G. Maspero.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
