<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0860-0829-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MEGATHERIUM (9th edition, volume 15, page 829)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c824h78">Sloths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mp4vr0s">Edentata</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26q36p">Armadillos</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1015576">Megatherium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120978">Sloths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205550">Paraguay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n860/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MEGATHERIUM</label> is the name given by Cuvier to a large
                    extinct animal belonging to the order <hi rend="italic">Edentata</hi> (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mammalia,</hi> p. 384). A nearly complete skeleton, found
                    on the banks of the river Luxan, near Buenos Ayres, and sent in 1789 to the
                    Royal Museum at Madrid, long remained the principal if not the only source of
                    information with regard to the species to which it belonged, and furnished the
                    materials for many descriptions, notably that of Cuvier, who determined its
                    affinities with the Sloths.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>An excellent figure of this skeleton, which unfortunately was
                            incorrectly articulated, and w <hi rend="superscript"> ι</hi> anted the
                            greater part of the tail, was published by Pander and D’Alton in 1821,
                            and has been frequently reproduced in subsequent works.</p></note> In
                    1832 an important collection of bones of the Megatherium were discovered near
                    the Rio Salado, and were secured for the museum of the College of Surgeons of
                    England, and these, with another collection found at Luxan in 1837, and now in
                    the British Museum, supplied the materials for the complete description of the
                    skeleton published by Professor Owen in 1861. Other skeletons have subsequently
                    been received by several of the Continental museums, as Milan and Paris, and,
                    consequently, our knowledge of the organization of the Megatherium, so far as it
                    can be deduced from the bones and teeth, is as complete as that of any other
                    animal, recent or extinct.</p>
                <p>The remains hitherto spoken of are all referred to one species, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Megatherium americanum</hi> of Blumenbach, <hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">cuvier</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                    Desmarest, and are all from the newest or ρost-Tertiary geological formations of
                    the Argentine Republic and Paraguay, or the lands forming the basin of the Rio
                    de la Plata. Dr Leidy has described, from similar formations in Georgia and
                    South Carolina, bones of a closely allied species, about one-fourth smaller,
                    which he has named <hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi rend="italic">mirabile.</hi> A
                    third species, <hi rend="italic">Μ. laurillardi</hi> of Lund, is founded upon
                    remains found in Brazil.</p>
                <p>The following description will apply especially to the best known South American
                    form, <hi rend="italic">Megatherium americanum.</hi> In size it exceeded any
                    existing land animal except the elephant, to which it was inferior only in
                    consequence of the comparative shortness of its limbs, for in length and bulk of
                    body it was its equal, if not superior. The full length of a mounted skeleton
                    from the fore part of the head to the end of the tail is 18 feet, of which the
                    tail occupies 5 feet. The head, which is small for the size of the animal,
                    presents a general resemblance to that of the Sloth; the anterior part of the
                    mouth is, however, more elongated, and the malar bone, though branched
                    posteriorly in the same way as that of the Sloth, meets the zygomatic process of
                    the squamosal, completing the arch. The lower jaw has the middle part of its
                    horizontal ramus curiously deepened, so as to admit of implantation of the very
                    long-rooted teeth. In number the teeth exactly resemble those of the Sloths,
                    being five above and four below on each side, and they are limited to the
                    lateral parts of the mouth, front teeth being entirely wanting. They resemble
                    those of the Sloths also in their persistent growth, and in their composition of
                    three tissues — vaso-dentine, true dentine, and cement; but they are of
                    prismatic or quadrate form, and the constituent materials of different densities
                    are so arranged that, as they wear, two transverse ridges of hard dentine remain
                    at a greater elevation than the rest of the tooth, producing a very efficient
                    triturating apparatus (see figs. 35 and 36, article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Mammalia,</hi> p. 385). The vertebral column consists of seven cervical,
                    sixteen dorsal, three lumbar, five sacral, and eighteen caudal vertebrae. The
                    spinous processes are much better developed than in the Sloths, and are all
                    directed backwards, there being no reversing of the inclination near the
                    posterior end of the dorsal series, as in most active-bodied mammals. In the
                    lumbar region, the accessory zygapophyses, rudimentary in Sloths, are fully
                    developed, as in the Anteaters.</p>
                <p>The tail is large, and its basal vertebrae have strong lateral and spinous
                    processes and chevron bones, indicating great muscular development. The scapula
                    resembles that of the Sloths in the union of the acromion with the coracoid, and
                    in the bridging over of the supra-scapular notch. The clavicle is complete and
                    very large much resembling that of man on a large scale. I he fore limbs are
                    longer than the hind limbs. The radius and ulna are both well-developed, and
                    have a considerable amount of freedom of movement. The hand is singularly
                    modified. The first digit is represented only by a rudimentary metacarpal, but
                    the next three are large, and terminate in phalanges <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n861/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0861-0830"/> adapted for the support of immense claws, the
                    middle one being especially large. The outer or fifth digit has no claw, and it
                    may be considered as certain that the weight of the foot was, in standing and
                    walking, chiefly thrown upon this, and that it was protected by a callous pad
                    below as in the existing great Anteater, while the other toes were curved
                    inwards towards the palm, only coming in contact with the ground by their outer
                    surfaces. The mechanical arrangements by which the weight of the body was thrown
                    entirely upon the outer side, of the foot are very curious, and are fully
                    described in Professor Owen’s memoir. The pelvis is remarkably wide, even more
                    so than that of the Elephant, but it is formed on the same principle as in the
                    Sloths. The femur is extremely broad and flattened; the tibia and fibula are
                    short and strong, and united together at each end. The hind foot, contrary to
                    the usual rule in the <hi rend="italic">Edentata,</hi> is even more singularly
                    modified than the hand. The ankle-joint is formed upon a peculiar plan, quite
                    unlike that of the Sloths, or of any other mammal, except the Megatherium’s
                    nearest allies. The calcaneum projects nearly as far backwards as the fore part
                    of the foot does forwards. There is no trace of great toe or hallux, or of its
                    corresponding cuneiform bone. The second toe is rudimentary. The third has an
                    enormous ungual phalanx, which, like those of the hand, is remarkable for the
                    immense development of the bony sheath which is reflected from its proximal end
                    around the base of the claw. The two outer toes have large and very
                    peculiarly-shaped metatarsals, but only small phalanges, and no claws. The
                    creature probably walked upon the outer edge of the sole, so that the great
                    falcate claw of the third toe did not come into contact with the ground, and so
                    was kept in a state of sharpness ready for use. The foot was therefore formed
                    upon quite a different principle from that of the Anteaters or Sloths, though
                    somewhat like the latter in having two of the toes aborted.</p>
                <p>Taking all the various points of its structure together, they clearly indicate
                    affinities both with the existing Sloths and with the Anteaters, the skull and
                    teeth more resembling those of the former, and the vertebral column and limbs
                    the latter It is also not difficult to infer the food ând habits of this
                    enormous creature. That it was a leaf-eater there can be little doubt, but the
                    greater size and more complex structure of its teeth might have enabled it to
                    crush the smaller branches as well as the leaves and succulent shoots which form
                    the food of the existing Sloths. It is, however, very improbable that it climbed
                    into the branches of the trees like its diminutive congeners, but it is far more
                    likely that it obtained its subsistence by tearing them down with the great
                    hook-like claws of its powerful prehensile fore limbs, being easily enabled to
                    reach them by raising itself up upon the massive tripod formed by the two hind
                    feet, firmly fixed to the ground by the one huge falcate claw, and the stout,
                    muscular tail. The whole conformation of the hinder part of the animal is
                    strongly suggestive of such an action. There can also be little doubt but that
                    all its movements were as slow and deliberate as those of its modern
                    representatives.</p>
                <p>An idea at one time prevailed that the Megatherium was covered externally with a
                    coat of bony armour like that of the Armadillos, but this originated in dermal
                    plates belonging to the Glyptodon, a totally distinct animal, having been
                    accidentally associated with bones of the Megatherium. Similar plates, on a
                    smaller scale, have indeed been found in connexion with the skeleton of both
                    Mylodon and Scelidotherium, animals of the same family, but never yet with the
                    Megatherium, which we may therefore imagine with a covering of coarse hair like
                    that of its nearest living allies, the Sloths and Anteaters.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> J. Garriga and J. B. Bry, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Description del esque∙ leto</hi><hi rend="italic">de un</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">cuadrupedo muy</hi><hi rend="italic">corpulento</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">y</hi><hi rend="italic">raro,</hi><hi rend="italic">que se
                        conserva en el Real Gabinete de</hi><hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Natural</hi><hi rend="italic">de Madrid, con</hi> 5 <hi
                        rend="italic">laminas,</hi> fol., 1796; G. Cuvier, in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annales du Muséum,</hi> vol. v. p. 376, 1804; Pander and D’Alton, <hi
                        rend="italic">Das Riesenfaulthier abgebildet und beschrieben,</hi> 1821; R
                    Owen, “On the Megatherium,” in <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi>
                    for 1851, 1855, 1856, and 1858, republished as a separate work in 1861; J.
                    Leidy, “Memoir on the Extinct Sloth Tribe of North America,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Smithsonian Contributions to Knowledge,</hi> vol. vii. 1855; H. Burmeister,
                        <hi rend="italic">Description physique</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                        République</hi><hi rend="italic">Argentine,</hi> t. iii. pt. 1, “Mammifères
                    vivants et éteints,” 1879, p. 285. (W. H. F.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
