<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0615-0588-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARVELL, Andrew</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 588</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s33k">Creeds</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cs62">Hoods</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rq88">Growth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1169492">Wages</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:948571">Growth</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1129153">Speech</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n615/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARVELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew</hi></label>
                    (1621-1678), was born on March 31, 1621, at the parsonage of Winestead in
                    Holderness. He was educated at Hull grammar school by his father, who had
                    obtained high position in that town, until his admission to Trinity College,
                    Cambridge, on December 14, 1633. There he became ensnared by the Jesuits, who at
                    that time were keen to secure youths of promise at the universities, and by
                    them, probably in the beginning of 1G38, was taken to London; but he was
                    recaptured by his father, and again received into Trinity on April 13 of the
                    same year. He appears to have contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Musa
                    Cantabrigiensis</hi> in 1637; and beyond this nothing is known or even
                    conjectured as to his college career. In 1640 his father was drowned under
                    remarkable circumstances, an event which appears to have entirely unsettled him,
                    for by an entry in the College Conclusion book, dated September 24, 1641, we
                    find that he was adjudged by the seniority to have forfeited the benefits of the
                    college. He used his liberty during the next four years to travel through the
                    Continent, remaining abroad until 1646. It has been assumed that during this
                    journey Marvell became acquainted with Milton, but a comparison of dates shows
                    that this is an error. His first employment was in 1650, as tutor to Lord
                    Fairfax’s daughter. During his stay at Nunappleton were written the <hi
                    rend="italic">Poems of the Country</hi> and some of the <hi rend="italic">Poems
                    of Imagination and Love.</hi> In 1652 he was in communication with Milton, to
                    whom he had probably been introduced by Fairfax, and was by him sent on February
                    21 to President Bradshaw with a letter urging his appointment as assistant Latin
                    secretary to himself. The post was, however, otherwise filled up, and he was
                    provided instead with another tutorship, that of Cromwell’s nephew, Mr Dutton.
                    This has been wrongly stated by several writers as not occurring until six years
                    later. In 1657 the secretaryship again fell vacant, and was then conferred upon
                    him, but he held office for a year only, and no record of his work appears in
                    the calendar of state papers. Marvell accepted the Commonwealth as a practical
                    fact, and the rule of Cromwell as the only guarantee for government at once
                    tolerant and strong. But he never lost his belief in the monarchical theory. His
                    line “ ’Tis godlike good to save a falling king” is well known; and throughout
                    his most vehement invective against corruption there is a great tenderness and
                    desire to spare the king.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n616/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0616-0589"/>
                <p>The assistant secretaryship opened the way to public life, and in 1658 Marvell
                    was elected member for Kingston-upon-Hull in Richard Cromwell’s parliament. From
                    1663 to 1665 he acted as secretary to Lord Carlisle’s embassy to Muscovy,
                    Sweden, and Denmark; and this is the only official post he ever filled during
                    the reign of Charles. With the exception of this and of shorter unexplained
                    intervals of travel, Marvell was constant in his parliamentary attendance to the
                    day of his death. He seldom spoke in the House, some five or six times in all,
                    but his parliamentary influence is amply established by other evidence; and his
                    correspondence with his constituents, from 1660 to 1678, forms a source of
                    information all the more valuable because by a resolution passed at the
                    Restoration the publication of the proceedings of the House without leave was
                    forbidden. He made it a point of duty to write at each post—that is, every two
                    or three days— both on local interests and on all matters of public interest.
                    The discreet reserve of these letters, natural at a time when the post-office
                    was a favourite source of information to the Government, contrasts curiously
                    with the freedom of the few private letters which state opinions as well as
                    facts. Marvell’s constituents, in their turn, were not unmindful of their
                    member. He makes frequent references to their presents, usually of Hull ale and
                    of salmon, and he regularly drew from them the wages of a member, six and
                    eightpence a day during session.</p>
                <p>During these years Marvell wrote a good deal of verse, chiefly satire, often very
                    coarse, but always vigorous and full of an honest hatred at corruption. He chose
                    verse merely as being the usual vehicle of satire, and cared little about form.
                    “He plucked a cudgell from the nearest hedgerow, careless if it became fuel
                    after it had served his turn.” It was very different with his prose satires. His
                    peculiar talent was first displayed in the mock <hi rend="italic">King's
                    Speech,</hi> issued in 1675. This is written in a vein of genial banter, perhaps
                    the greatest tribute to the influence which the bonhomie of Charles exercised
                    even over such men as Marvell. But his tone soon changed, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Growth of Popery and Arbitrary Poιver,</hi> published in the year of his
                    death, is a grave indictment of the conduct of ministers of the crown, and, by
                    implication, of Charles himself, since the Restoration. So shrewdly did this
                    strike the conscience of the king that a proclamation, of which Marvell takes
                    laughing notice, offered a large reward for the discovery of the author.</p>
                <p>As a political pamphleteer Marvell holds a high place; as a satirist he stands
                    still higher. Tolerance in religion was his creed, and this creed had been
                    lately attacked by a clergyman seeking promotion, Dr Parker, afterwards bishop
                    of Oxford, who asserted in their most extravagant form the claims of the civil
                    magistrate over the consciences of subjects in matters of external religion.
                    Marvell’s reply, <hi rend="italic">The Rehearsal Transprosed,</hi> is a
                    masterpiece of prolonged banter. It contains passages of lofty indignation,
                    hearty laughter, coarse vituperation; but the prevailing tone is that of grave
                    and ironical banter. The effect, as witnessed to by Anthony Wood, Burnet, and
                    other contemporary writers, was to set the whole public “from the king to the
                    tradesman” in a laugh against Parker. This stung him to an ill-tempered
                    rejoinder, affording Marvell a second opportunity, of which he availed himself
                    so well that no more was heard from his opponent; and Swift was shortly
                    afterwards able to say that people remembered Parker’s book only by Marvell’s
                    answer. Marvell’s second controversial work, <hi rend="italic">Mr Smirke, or the
                    Divine in Mode,</hi> was written in the same strain and under similar
                    circumstances, and obtained a success fully equal to that of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Rehearsal Transprosed.</hi> It was a defence of Croft, bishop of
                    Hereford, against a violent attack by Dr Turner, the High Church master of St
                    John’s, Cambridge. Prefixed to it was a “short historical essay concerning
                    general councils,” intended to show the folly of religious impositions. Several
                    other writings, often ascribed to him, more especially the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Parliamenti</hi><hi rend="italic">Angliae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Declaratio,</hi><hi rend="italic">A Sensible Question and an Usefull
                    Answer,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Flagellum Parlia-mentarium,</hi> were
                    certainly not his.</p>
                <p>As a humorist, then, and as a great “parliament man,” no name is of more interest
                    to a student of the reign of Charles II. than that of Marvell. But other
                    qualities entitle him to still higher respect. To a personal charm so great, to
                    wit so brilliant, to learning so extensive, and to sympathies so wide that he
                    was at the same time dear to John Milton and courted by Charles II., he joined
                    the· rarest quality of that evil time, a robust and intrepid rectitude. In the
                    very heyday of political infamy, at a time when he says passionately “we are all
                    venal cowards except some few,” and when opposition to the court was likely to
                    be resented by personal violence of the brutalest kind, he, a needy man, obliged
                    to accept wages from his constituents, tempted in winning phrases from royal
                    lips by his old schoolfellow Danby, and with nothing to gain from the court by
                    purity, kept his political virtue unspotted and unsuspected. · The meaning of
                    this fact can barely be felt by any one who has not read with minute care the
                    annals of that time. When the grossest forms of selfindulgence were the ordinary
                    habits of town life, Marvell was a temperate man, in spite of Aubrey’s witness
                    that he “kept bottles of wine at his lodgings and would drink liberally by
                    himself to refresh his spirits and exalt his muse.” Lastly, in the worst times
                    of parliamentary violence, he stood forward throughout his career as the
                    champion of moderate and tolerant measures. His person corresponded singularly
                    with his mind, so far as can be judged from the portrait by Hannemann and from
                    the few words of John Aubrey—“He was of a middling stature, pretty strong set,
                    roundish faced, cherry cheeked, hazel eyed, brown haired. In his conversation he
                    was modest and of very few words.”</p>
                <p>He died suddenly in 1678 on his return from Hull to take his seat in August. That
                    he was poisoned, and at the instigation of the court, has been roundly asserted,
                    naturally enough, though without the slightest foundation. The matter has been
                    finally set at rest by a very interesting letter by Dr Samuel Gee in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Athenaeum</hi> for March 7, 1874.</p>
                <p>The following works may be consulted on Marvell :— <hi rend="italic">Life and
                    Works—</hi> (1) by Thomas Cooke, 2 vols., 1726 (there is a reprint by Thomas
                    Davies in 1772); (2) by Captain Thomson, 3 vols. 4to, 1776; (3) by John Dove,
                    1832; (4) by Edwin Paxton Hood, 1853; and essays by Hartley Coleridge in <hi
                    rend="italic">Lives of the Northern Worthies,</hi> Henry Rogers in his collected
                    <hi rend="italic">Essays,⅛nA</hi> an anonymous author in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cornhill Magazine</hi> for July 1869, and in the <hi rend="italic">Saturday
                    Review</hi> for April 26, 1873. All these authorities are mentioned, collated,
                    and corrected in the very important and laborious work of Mr Grosart, whose
                    book, in spite of its excessive mannerism and one or two curious inaccuracies,
                    is indispensable to the student of Marvell’s correspondence and career. (0.
                    A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
