<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0211-0194-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAeCENAS, C</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 194</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1043867">Odes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916316">Etruscans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n211/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAeCENAS, C</label>. <hi rend="smallcaps">Cilnius,</hi> is,
                    from two <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> different points of view, a prominent
                    representative man of the ancient world. He was the first, and one of the most
                    capable and successful, of those who filled the office of a great minister under
                    the Roman empire. He was also, if not the first, certainly the most fortunate
                    and influential among the patrons of Roman literature. It is in the latter
                    capacity that he is best known. Among all the names, royal, noble, or otherwise
                    eminent, associated with the patronage of letters, none either in ancient or
                    modern times is so familiarly known as that of Maecenas. Yet, if we had any
                    contemporary history of the establishment of the empire, possessing the same
                    permanent interest which the poetry of Virgil and Horace possesses, it is
                    probable that his influence in shaping the political destinies of the world
                    would have been as amply recognized as his influence on its literature.</p>
                <p>The date and place of his birth are unknown. He first appears in history in the
                    year 40 B.C., when he is employed by Octavianus in arranging his marriage with
                    Scribonia, and afterwards in negotiating, along with Pollio and Cocceius Nerva
                    (“aversos soliti componere amicos,” Hor., <hi rend="italic">Sat.,</hi> i. 5,
                    28), the peace of Brundisium, and the reconciliation with Antony, which was
                    confirmed by the marriage of the latter with Octavia. From the fact that he was
                    then the most trusted friend and agent of the future emperor it is likely that
                    he had been associated with his fortunes from the time when he came forward to
                    claim his inheritance after the death of Julius Caesar; and expressions in
                    Propertius (ii. 1, 25-30) seem to imply that he had borne some share in the
                    campaigns of Mutina, Philippi, and Perusia. He may have been a few years older
                    than Octavianus, who began to play the foremost part in Roman politics before he
                    was twenty years of age. The men of the Augustan age great in action and
                    literature were all born within a few years of one another. Agrippa, the right
                    hand of Augustus in war as Maecenas was in peace, was born in the same year as
                    his master; and there is no indication in the relations of Maecenas to Augustus
                    or to his friend Horace that he stood towards either of them in the relation of
                    an older to a yoiιnger man. Although the place of his birth is unknown, we learn
                    from Horace and Propertius that he prided himself on his ancient Etruscan
                    lineage, and claimed descent from the princely house of the Cilnii, who, as is
                    recorded by Livy (x. 3), excited the jealousy of their townsmen by their
                    preponderating wealth and influence at Arretium in the 4th century before our
                    era. He probably prized the glories of his paternal and maternal ancestry (Hor.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Sat.,</hi> i. 6, 3) as compensating him for his original
                    social inferiority to the members of the great Roman houses; and the fact dwelt
                    on so prominently by his panegyrists, that, through all his life, he preferred
                    .the position of a great commoner to the new honours of the senate and of the
                    Roman magistracies, may have been the result as much of pride in his provincial
                    ancestry as of a politic desire to disarm the jealousy of his master or of the
                    Roman aristocracy. Cicero, in his defence of Cluentius, speaks of a C. Maecenas
                    as one of the most substantial members of the equestrian order during the
                    tribunate of Drusus (91 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> and as one of those Who
                    preferred the position their fathers had enjoyed before them to the higher rank
                    obtainable through office (Cic,, <hi rend="italic">Cluent.,</hi> 56,153). From
                    the identity of the <hi rend="italic">praenomen</hi> and the rarity of the <hi
                    rend="italic">cognomen</hi> it is not unlikely that he may have been the
                    grandfather, or perhaps the father, of the future minister. It was in accordance
                    with the policy of Julius Caesar to choose his confidential friends from men of
                    this order, as he chose his tools from a less reputable class; and the two most
                    trusted friends and ministers of his successor would both have been regarded as
                    “novi homines” by the representatives of the great senatorian families. The
                    testimony of Horace <hi rend="italic">(Odes,</hi> iii. 8, 5) and his own
                    literary tastes imply that he had profited by the highest education of his time.
                    His great wealth may have been in part hereditary, as there was no district of
                    Italy in which the inequalities of wealth and station were greater than in
                    Etruria j<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The lines of
                    Propertius (iv. 8, 27-8)—</p><p>Et tibi ad effectum vires det Caesar et <hi
                    rend="italic">omni Tempore tam faciles insinuentur opes—</hi> show that his
                    position under the empire also brought very substantial additions to his
                    original fortune.</p></note> but he owed his position and influence in the state
                    to his early adherence to and close connexion with Augustus. Among the charges
                    brought against him by Seneca, one of the most prominent is that he had been
                    spoiled by his excessive good fortune.</p>
                <p>From the year 40 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> his influence as the confidential
                    adviser of Octavianus seems to have been thoroughly established. It was in the
                    following year that Horace was introduced to him, and he had before this
                    received Varius and Virgil into his intimacy. In the “Journey to Brundisium,”
                    which took place in the year 37 B.C., Maecenas and Cocceius Nerva are described
                    as “missi magnis de rebus uterque Legati,” and were again successful in patching
                    up, by the treaty of Tarentum, a reconciliation between the two claimants for
                    supreme power. During the Sicilian war against Sextus Pompeius in 36 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> he was sent back to Rome, and was entrusted with
                    supreme administrative control in the city and in Italy. He is again found
                    acting as vicegerent of Octavianus during the campaign of Actium, when with
                    great promptness and secrecy he crushed the conspiracy of the younger Lepidus;
                    and during the subsequent absences of his chief in the provinces he held the
                    same position. During the latter years of his life he fell somewhat out of
                    favour with his master, or his services were less needed. Perhaps the freedom
                    with which, in the earlier stages of his career, he had offered advice and told
                    unpleasant truths had become distasteful. One cause for a comparative coolness
                    between the old friends was said to be the emperor’s relations with Terentia,
                    the wife of Maecenas, to whom he was uxoriqusly attached. Perhaps the ennui
                    resulting from the cessation of a life of constant vigilance and activity may
                    account for the state of sleepless restlessness and fever in which he passed the
                    last three years of his life. He died in the year 8 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> leaving the emperor heir to his wealth, and affectionately
                    commending his friend Horace, who only survived him a few days, to his
                    protection.</p>
                <p>Opinions were much divided in ancient times as to the personal character of
                    Maecenas; but the testimony as to his administrative and diplomatic ability was
                    unanimous. He enjoyed the credit—or discredit, as the adherents of the republic
                    must have regarded it—of sharing largely in the establishment of the new order
                    of things,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This is
                    implied by the long speech which Dion Cassius puts into his mouth, recommending
                    the establishment and prompting the policy of the new empire (Dion Cass., lii.
                    14-40).</p></note> of reconciling parties, and of carrying the new empire safely
                    through many dangers. To his influence especially was attributed <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n212/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0212-0195"/> the humaner policy of Octavianus after his first
                    alliance with Antony and Lepidus. Even Seneca, who shows a very bitter animus
                    against him, admits that he deserved the credit bf clemency,—although he
                    attributes it to effeminacy rather than to true humanity. The highest tribute
                    paid to him in his capacity of minister is to be found in the least eminent of
                    the poets whose genius he fostered. “The true trophies of Maecenas,” says
                    Propertius, “will be his loyalty.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Propert., <hi rend="italic">El.</hi> iv. 9, 34; ii. 1,
                    36.</p></note> And in another elegy he addresses him as “fidele caput.” One
                    great testimony both to his loyalty and to his tact is the saying of Augustus,
                    when he had made public the scandal concerning his daughter Julia, “that all
                    this would never have happened if Agrippa or Maecenas had lived” (Sen., <hi
                    rend="italic">De Ben.,</hi> vi. 32). The only instance in which he is said to
                    have acted with indiscretion as ⅛ minister was in his betrayal to his wife
                    Terentia of his knowledge of the conspiracy in which her brother Licinius
                    Muraena was involved.</p>
                <p>The best summary of his character as a man and a statesman is that of Velleius
                    (ii. 88), who describes him as “in critical emergencies of sleepless vigilance
                    far-seeing and knowing how to act, but in his relaxation from business more
                    luxurious and effeminate than a woman.” The latter is the aspect of his
                    character on which Seneca chiefly dwells. He draws attention to the enervating
                    effect which his good fortune had even on his literary style. We néed not ask
                    how far “the stately mansion on the Esquiline” outdid in luxury the “gardens of
                    Seneca the millionaire” (“Senecae praedivitis hortos”).<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Juv. x. 16.</p></note> Maecenas was certainly
                    a man who combined an epicurean love of pleasure with a thorough devotion to
                    business; and verses of his own are quoted against him indicative of an unmanly
                    clinging to life after the loss of all that makes life valuable. These may have
                    been written in the feverish unrest of his last years, when he was no longer
                    himself; but expressions in the <hi rend="italic">Odes</hi> of Horace (ii. 17,
                    1), written at a much earlier period, seem to imply that he was deficient in the
                    robustness of fibre characteristic of the average Roman. His style of dress and
                    his indolent lounging walk exposed him to animadversion; and the Maltinus of
                    Horace’s <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi> (i. 2, 25) was supposed by some ancient
                    commentators to be a sketch of the great man, drawn before the poet was admitted
                    to his intimacy. Probably there may have been some affectation or politic
                    dissimulation in this assumption of a character so alien to the standard of the
                    aspirants to public honours at Rome. It was an exaggerated form of that
                    indifference to appearances and conventionalities which made him satisfied with
                    the position of an eques, and induced him to choose his intimate associates from
                    poets of obscure and provincial origin. His ambition was to be the second man in
                    the empire, and to enjoy the reality without the show of power. A similar
                    character is attributed by Tacitus to Sallustius Crispus, whσ, after the death
                    of Maecenas, most enjoyed the favour of Augustus.</p>
                <p>His character as a munificent patron of literature is not only acknowledged
                    gratefully by the recipients of it in his own time, but is attested by the
                    regrets of the men of letters of a later age, expressed through the mouths of
                    Martial and Juvenal. His patronage was exercised, not from vanity or a mere
                    dilettante love of letters, but with a view to the higher interest of the state.
                    He recognized in the genius of the poets of that time, not only the truest
                    ornament of the court, but a power of reconciling men’s minds to the new order
                    of things, and of investing the actual state of affairs with an ideal glory and
                    majesty. The change in seriousness of purpose between the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eclogues</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Georgies</hi> of Virgil was, in a great
                    measure, the result of the direction given by the statesman to the poet’s
                    genius. A</p>
                <p>similar change between the earlier odes of Horace, in which he declares his
                    epicurean indifference to affairs of state, and the great national odes of the
                    third book is to be ascribed to the same guidance. He endeavoured also to divert
                    the less masculine genius of Propertius from harping continually on his love to
                    themes of public interest.</p>
                <p>But, if the motive of his patronage had been merely politic, it never could have
                    inspired the affection which it did in its recipients. The great charm of
                    Maecenas in his relation to the men of genius who formed his circle was his
                    simplicity, cordiality, and sincerity. Although not particular in the choice of
                    some of the associates of his pleasures, he admitted none but men of worth to
                    his intimacy, and when once admitted they were treated like equals. That loyalty
                    which was his own distinction in his public life was, if we may trust the
                    evidence of Horace, the characteristic of his own relations to his intimates,
                    and of their relations to one another. But, while loyal to all, to Horace he was
                    bound by a closer tie. Among the great friendships of history, none is more
                    certainly attested, or more honourable to both parties, than that between the
                    poet and the statesman. Much of the wisdom of Maecenas probably lives in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Satires</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi> of Horace. - It
                    has fallen to the lot of no other patron of literature to have his name
                    associated with works of such lasting interest as the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Georgics^oî</hi> Virgil, the first three books of Horace’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Odes,</hi> and the first book of his <hi rend="italic">Epistles.</hi> Such a
                    fortune can scarcely have been altogether undeserved. Accepting as literally
                    true the disparaging statements of Seneca, admitting the weakness, and perhaps
                    the vanity, which were the blots in his character, and considering at the same,
                    time the difficulties of an unprecedented position, we must allow that few
                    ministers of an irresponsible monarch have accomplished so much with such
                    immunity from the baser and more violent passions, for the gratification of
                    which that position holds out unlimited opportunities. As a minister and friend
                    of the emperor he compared favourably, both as regards capacity and character,
                    not with men of the stamp of Sejanus and Tigellinus, but with Seneca. Few men
                    have used the influence of a grand seigneur with such enlightened beneficence,
                    with such lasting results on human culture and civilization, with such genuine
                    simplicity and cordial loyalty. (w. γ. s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
