<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0596-0569-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARRYAT, Frederick</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 569</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1116352">Shipping</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1167345">Violets</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1039784">Novelle</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23k3t">Novelists</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dr26">Sketching</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qj78735">Violet</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n596/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARRYAT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederick</hi></label>
                    (1792-1848), has never been surpassed as a writer of tales of nautical
                    adventure. His own life supplied him with abundant raw materials for his art.
                    The son of a wealthy London gentleman (who sat in parliament for several years
                    for the boroughs of Horsham and Sandwich, and was a writer of verses and
                    political pamphlets), he distinguished himself as a boy by frequently running
                    away towards sea; and at last, at the age of fourteen, he was allowed to enter
                    the navy. His first service was under Lord Cochrane in the famous “Impérieuse,”
                    and no midshipman ever had a livelier apprenticeship to the sea. “The cruises of
                    the ‘Impérieuse ’ were,” he says, “periods of continual excitement, from the
                    hour in which she hove up her anchor till she dropped it again in port; the day
                    that passed without a shot being fired in anger was with us a blank day.” During
                    his two and a half years of service under the daring and active Cochrane, the
                    young midshipman witnessed more than fifty engagements, many of them extremely
                    brilliant, and had experience of every description of service, fighting duels
                    with fairly matched ships of war, engaging gunboats, engaging batteries,
                    storming forts, capturing and cutting out merchantmen. Before the general peace
                    of 1815 he had added considerably to this experience of active service, and
                    gained a wide knowledge of conditions of life on board ship under various
                    commanders. He frequently received honourable mention for his behaviour in
                    action, and in 1818 he received the medal of the Humane Society for “at least a
                    dozen” gallant rescues. He commanded with distinction in the Burmese war of
                    1824-25. And Marryat’s honours were not confined to gallant exploits; he was the
                    inventor of a code of signals, obtained some celebrity as a caricaturist, and
                    was elected an F.R.S.</p>
                <p>Marryat brought ripe experience and unimpaired vivacity to his work when he
                    commenced novelist. His first production was <hi rend="italic">Frank Mildmay, or
                    the Naval Officer,</hi> published in 1829, and his second, published nine months
                    later, <hi rend="italic">The King's Own.</hi> “I think,” Washington Irving wrote
                    to him soon after, “the chivalry of the ocean quite a new region of fiction and
                    romance, and to my taste one of the most captivating that could be explored.”
                    This was the general feeling. The freshness of the new field opened up to the
                    imagination, so full of vivid lights and shadows, lighthearted fun, grinding
                    hardship, stirring adventure, heroic action, warm friendships’ bitter hatreds,
                    was felt all the more keenly from its contrast with the world of the historical
                    romancer and the fashionable novelist, to which the mind of the general reader
                    was at that date given over. The novels of the sea captain at once won public
                    favour. His first attempt was somewhat severely criticized from an artistic
                    point of view. It was without form, though the reverse of void; he had packed
                    into it matter enough for half a dozen novels. Marryat was accused also of
                    gratifying private grudges by introducing real personages too thinly disguised.
                    He admitted the justice of these criticisms, and rapidly learnt the mechanical
                    part of his new business without losing any of the vivacious charm of his style.
                    <hi rend="italic">The King’s Own</hi> was a vast improvement, in point of
                    construction, upon <hi rend="italic">Frank Mildmay</hi>; and he wen’t on,
                    through a quick succession of tales, <hi rend="italic">Newton Forster, Peter
                    Simple, Jacob Faithful, The Pacha of Many Tales, Japhet in Search of a Father,
                    Mr Midshipman Easy, The Pirate and the Three Cutters,</hi> till he reached his
                    highwater mark of constructive skill in <hi rend="italic">Snarley-yow, or the
                    Dog Fiend</hi> (1837). If he never surpassed this in storytelling art, humorous
                    portraiture, and richness of incident, the records of circulating libraries and
                    the pencilled comments of their subscribers show that his subsequent works —he
                    produced twenty-four in all during his twenty years of authorship—were no less
                    capable of riveting the attention, especially of youthful readers. The following
                    is the list, with the dates of publication :— <hi rend="italic">The Phantom
                    Ship</hi> (1839), Al <hi rend="italic">Diary in America</hi> (1839), <hi
                    rend="italic">Olla Podrida</hi> (1840), <hi rend="italic">Poor Jack</hi> (1840),
                    <hi rend="italic">Masterman Ready</hi> (1841), <hi rend="italic">Joseph
                    Rushbrook</hi> (1841), <hi rend="italic">Percival Keene</hi> (1842), <hi
                    rend="italic">Monsieur</hi><hi rend="italic">Violet</hi> (1842), <hi
                    rend="italic">The Settlers in Canada</hi> (1843), <hi rend="italic">The
                    Privateer's Man</hi> (1844), <hi rend="italic">The Mission, or Scenes in
                    Africa</hi> (1845), <hi rend="italic">The Children of the Neιv Forest</hi>
                    (1847), <hi rend="italic">The Little Savage</hi> (1847), and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Valerie,</hi> not completed by Marryat (1849). Captain Marryat retired from the
                    naval service in 1830, and thereafter worked as hard at literature as any
                    professional man of letters, making special historical and geographical studies
                    for several of the works in the above list. He edited the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Metropolitan Magazine</hi> for four years (1832-36). Marryat’s novels were in
                    the first flush of their success when Dickens was a youth, and they have an
                    interest in the history of literature as forming an important link between
                    Smollett and Fielding and the author of <hi rend="italic">Sketches by Boz.</hi>
                    He died in 1848. There is a biography by his daughter, Florence Marryat.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
