<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0857-0826-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MEGALOPOLIS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 826</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795626">Achaeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:893284">Diet</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n857/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MEGALOPOLIS</label>, a city of southern Arcadia, situated in
                    a plain about 20 miles south-west of Tegea, on both banks of the Helisson, about
                    2∣ miles above its junction with the Alpheus. Like Messene, it owed its origin
                    to Epaminondas, and was founded in 370 B,c., the year after the battle of
                    Leuctra, as a bulwark for the southern Arcadians against Sparta, and as the seat
                    of the Arcadian federal diet, which consisted of ten thousand men. The builders
                    of the city were protected by a Theban force, and directed by ten native
                    oecists, who likewise attended to the peopling of the new city, which apparently
                    drew inhabitants from all parts of Arcadia, out more especially from the
                    neighbouring districts of Maenalia and Parrhasia. Forty townships are mentioned
                    by Pausanias (viii. 27, 3-5) as having been incorporated in it. It was fifty
                    stadia in circumference, and was surrounded with strong walls. Its territory was
                    the largest in Arcadia, extending northward 24 miles. The city was built on a
                    magnificent scale, and adorned with many handsome buildings, both public and
                    private. Its temples contained many ancient statues brought from the towns
                    incorporated in it. On the north side of the Helisson, which divided it into two
                    nearly equal parts, was the agora with four porticos, the gymnasium, a sacred
                    grove, temples to the Lycaean Zeus, Pan Oinoeis, Bhea, Tyche, the great
                    goddesses (Demeter and Core), Zeus Philios (with a statue by Polycletus),
                    Aρhro-dite<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n858/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0858-0827"/>, Core, Athena Polias, and Hera Teleia. Among the
                    numerous statues which stood in the open air the finest was that of Apollo
                    Epicurius, 12 feet high, brought from the beautiful temple of Bassae, which was
                    built by Ictinus, and is still in great part standing. On the south side of the
                    river were the theatre, the largest in Greece, the Thersilion •or hall for the
                    assembly of the Arcadian diet, a house built for Alexander the Great, with a
                    statue of Zeus Ammon, the stadium, temples to the Muses, Apollo, and Hermes, to
                    Aphrodite, to Ares, to Dionysus, to Hercules and Hermes, to Artemis Agrotera, to
                    Asclepius and Hygiea, to the son of Asclepius, and to Apollo. Of all these
                    buildings, with the exception of the theatre, hardly a trace remains above
                    ground. The ruins of Megalopolis are near Sinanou.</p>
                <p>The foundations of Megalopolis were hardly laid when Agesilaus undertook an
                    expedition in the hope of breaking up the union of which it was the visible sign
                    and capital. He accomplished nothing, and had hardly reached home when the
                    Thebans and their allies under Epaminondas and Pelopidas entered the
                    Peloponnesus and marched through Laconia almost unopposed. After the departure
                    of Epaminondas, Lycomedes of Mantinea succeeded in drawing the Arcadian
                    federation away from its alliance with Thebes, in consequence of which it had to
                    make common cause with Athens An attempt on the part of the federation to use
                    the treasures of the temple of Zeus at Olympia led to internal dissensions, so
                    that in the battle of Mantinea (362) one half of the Arcadians fought on the
                    side of the Spartans, the other on that of the Thebans. After this battle many
                    of the inhabitants of Megalopolis sought to return to their former homes, and it
                    was only by the assistance of three thousand Thebans under Pammenes that the
                    authorities were able to prevent them from doing so. In the year 352, when
                    Thebes had her hands full with the so-called Sacred War, the Spartans made an
                    attempt to reduce Megalopolis; but the Thebans promptly sent assistance, and the
                    city was rescued. Not sure of this assistance, the Megalopolitans had appealed
                    to Athens, an aj&gt;peal which gave occasion to Demosthenes’s oration ∏∈pl <hi
                    rend="italic">tΛeyaKoιtoKιτωv.</hi> The Spartans were now obliged to conclude
                    peace with Megalopolis and acknowledge her autonomy. Nevertheless their feeling
                    of hostility did not cease, and Megalopolis consequently entered into friendly
                    relations with Philip of Macedon. Twenty years later, when the Spartans and
                    their allies rebelled against the power of Macedon, Megalopolis remained firm in
                    its allegiance, and was subjected to a siege of considerable duration. After the
                    death of Alexander, Megalopolis was governed by native tyrants. In the war
                    between Cassander and Polysperchon it took part with the former, and was, in
                    consequence, besieged by the latter. On this Occasion it was able to send into
                    the field an army of fifteen thousand. In 234 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    Lydiades, the last tyrant of Megalopolis, voluntarily resigned his power, and
                    the city joined the Achaean league. In consequence of this it was once more
                    exposed to the bitteι hatred of Sparta. In 222 Cleomenes took and plundered it,
                    and killed or dispersed its inhabitants, but in the year following it was
                    restored and its inhabitants reinstated by Philopoemen, a native of the city At
                    this time the circuit of its walls always too great, seems to have been
                    contracted. At all events it never again attained political importance, and
                    gradually sank into insignificance. The only great men whom it produced were
                    Philopoemen and Polybius the historian. Lycortas, the father of the latter, may
                    be accounted a third In the time of Pausanias the city was mostly in ruins.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
