<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0209-0192-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MADRIGAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 192</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v474">Taverns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rn30b7z">Freemasons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:878236">Cooperativeness</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:992930">Lasso</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MADRIGAL</label>. The notice of this branch of musical art
                    which will be included in the general article Music may here be anticipated by
                    an approximately chronological list, according to nationalities, of the masters
                    who have been chiefly distinguished for their compositions of the class :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Flanders</hi>: Egide Binchois, Brusnois, Jean Okeghem or
                    Ockenheim, Jean Tinctor, Adrian Willaert, Cyprian di Rore, Jacques Hobrecht,
                    Firmin Caron, Josquin des Près, Alexander Agricola, Antoine Brumel, Pierre de la
                    Rue, Jacques Arcadelt, Claude Goudimel, Philippe Verdelot, Jacques de Wert,
                    Hubert Waelrent, and Orlando di Lasso; <hi rend="italic">Pome</hi>: Costanzo
                    Festa, Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina, Felice and Francesco Anerio, Giovanni
                    Maria, Bernardino Nanini, and Luca Marenzio (styled in his own time “Il più
                    dolce Cigno d’Italia”); <hi rend="italic">Venice·.</hi> Giovanni Croce, Andrea
                    and Giovanni Gabrielli, Costanzo Porta, Orazio Vecchi, and Giovanni Giacomo
                    Gastoldi; <hi rend="italic">England·.</hi> William Cornyshe (father and son),
                    Richard Taverner, Robert Fayrefax, Thomas Phelyppes, Richard Edwards, William
                    Byrd, Thomas Morley, Giles Farnaby, Edward Johnson, Thomas Weelkes, George
                    Kirbye, John Dowland, Michael Este, Thomas Tomkins, John Benet, John Hilton,
                    John Wilbye, Thomas Ford, Thomas Bateson, Richard Allison, John Ward, and
                    Orlando Gibbons, also John Cooper and Peter Philips, who dwelt long in Rome, and
                    published their works under the names respectively of Giovanni Coperario and
                    Pietro Filippi. Many of all these wrote strictly madrigals, that is, continuous
                    compositiohs abounding in ingenious artifices of imitation of one part by
                    another; others wrote rhythmical songs of four or more parts, or ballets, or
                    fal-las, all of which, being for unaccompanied voices, or for viols instead of
                    voices, are often erroneously ranked as madrigals, though differing entirely in
                    structure from them. The English composers, to Byrd inclusive, produced pieces
                    distinctly of the madrigal class, but described them by other definitions; it
                    was in the year 1588, when Byrd published <hi rend="italic">Psalms, Sonets, and
                    Songs of Sadness and Pietie,</hi> that the word madrigal was first introduced
                    into England by Nicholas Yonge, a merchant, a lover of music who, having
                    received copies of some foreign compositions in his chests of merchandise,
                    adapted English words to these, and printed a collection under the title <hi
                    rend="italic">Mmsica</hi><hi rend="italic">Transalpina,</hi> the success of
                    which stimulated the powers of English writers that had already been proved, and
                    excited others to emulate their example. The art of madrigal composition was
                    never practised in Germany, and it died out in other countries early in the 17
                    th century. The knowledge of the works that endear the madrigal writers to
                    lovers of a high and most pure form of music was revived, and has since been
                    kept alive, by the Madrigal Society. This was founded in 1741 by John Immyns, an
                    attorney, and its original members were mechanics or small tradesmen; it held
                    its first meeting at the Twelve Bells Tavern in Bride Lane, made many migrations
                    to other houses of entertainment, and has its present home at the Freemasons’
                    Tavern, where its members are of a far higher social caste than the men who
                    associated themselves for the practice of contrapuntal vocal music when the rank
                    and fashion of the land went to worship Farinelli at the Italian opera, and to
                    take part with the followers of the king or the prince of Wales in supporting
                    one or other of the opposition establishments for its performance. In 1811 the
                    society offered a prize for the composition of a madrigal, which was won by
                    William Beale. The same incentive has occasionally been repeated. This
                    encouragement, and still more the love for the class of music engendered by the
                    public performance of madrigals by large choral societies during the last fifty
                    years, have incited later composers to more or less successful imitations of the
                    style, especially distinguished among whom was Robert Lucas Pearsall
                    (1795-1856).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
