<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0499-0476-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANDRILL (9th edition, volume 15, page 476)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz6179h">Apes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4794135j">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:824977">Baboons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:811248">Apes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834915">Blue</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006685">Males</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n499/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANDRILL</label>, the name of one of the most remarkable, at
                    all events in outward appearance, of the Baboons, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cynocephalus</hi><hi rend="italic">maimon</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >mormon.</hi> The general characters of the genus to which it belongs are
                    given in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Ape,</hi> vol. ii. p. 152. The word
                    appears to have been first introduced into our literature in a w ork published
                    in 1744 called <hi rend="italic">A New Voyage to Guinea,</hi> by William Smith,
                    who in an account of the animals of Sierra Leone describes one “called by the
                    white men in this country Mandrill,” but adds, “why it is so called I know
                        not.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“ ‘ Mandrill’
                            seems to signify a ‘man-like ape,’ the word ‘ Drill ’ or ‘ Dril ’ having
                            been anciently employed in England to denote an Ape or Baboon. Thus in
                            the fifth edition of Blount’s ‘ <hi rend="italic">Glossographia,</hi> or
                            a dictionary interpreting the hard words of whatsoever language now used
                            in our refined English tongue . . . very useful for all such as desire
                            to understand what they read,’ published in 1681, I find ‘ Dril, a
                            stonecutter’s tool wherewith he bores little holes in marble, <pb
                                corresp="kp-eb0915-0500-0477" xml:id="pbn9477"/> &amp;c. Also a
                            large overgrown Ape and Baboon, so called. ’ ‘ Drill ’ is used in the
                            same sense in Charlton’s <hi rend="italic">Onomasticon Zoicon,</hi>
                            1668. The singular etymology of the word given by Buffon seems hardly a
                            probable one.”—Huxley’s <hi rend="italic">Man's Place in Nature,</hi> p.
                            10, 1863.</p></note> Smith gives sufficiently accurate details to show
                    that his animal is not <pb corresp="pbn9477"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n500/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0500-0477"/> that now called Mandrill, but the Chimpanzee.
                    Buffon, however, while quoting Smith’s description, transferred the name to the
                    very different species now under consideration, and to that it has been attached
                    ever since.</p>
                <p>The Baboons generally are distinguished from other Monkeys by the comparative
                    equality of the length of their limbs, which with the structure of the vertebral
                    column adapts them rather for quadrupedal progression on the ground than for
                    climbing among the branches of trees. They are also remarkable for the great
                    size of their face and jaws as compared with the part of the skull which
                    encloses the brain. The Mandrill, in addition to these characters, is
                    distinguished by the heaviness of its body, stoutness and strength of its limbs,
                    and exceeding shortness of its tail, which is a mere stump, not 2 inches long,
                    and usually carried erect. It is, moreover, remarkable for the prominence of its
                    brow ridges, beneath which the small and closely approximated eyes are deeply
                    sunk; the immense size of the canine teeth; the great development of a pair of
                    oval bony prominences on the maxillary bones in front of the orbits, rising on
                    each side of the median line of the face, and covered by a longitudinally-ribbed
                    naked skin; and more especially for the extraordinarily vivid colouring of some
                    parts of the skin.</p>
                <p>The body generally is covered with a full soft coating of hair of a light
                    olive-brown above and silvery-grey beneath, and the chin is furnished underneath
                    with a small pointed yellow beard. The hair of the forehead and temples is
                    directed upwards so as to meet in a point on the crown, which gives the head a
                    triangular appearance. The ears are naked and of a bluish-black colour. The
                    hands and feet are naked and black. A large space around the greatly developed
                    ischial callosities, as well as the upper part of the insides of the thighs, is
                    naked and of a crimson colour, shading off on the sides to lilac or blue, which,
                    depending not upon pigment but upon injection of the superficial blood-vessels,
                    varies in intensity according to the condition of the animal—increasing under
                    excitement, fading during sickness, and disappearing after death. But it is in
                    the face that the most remarkable disposition of vivid hues occur, more
                    resembling those of a brilliantly coloured flower than what might be expected in
                    the cutaneous covering of a mammal. The cheek prominences are of an intense
                    blue, the effect of which is heightened by deeply sunk longitudinal furrows of a
                    darker tint, while the central line and termination of the nose are a bright
                    scarlet. Notwithstanding the beauty of these colours in themselves, the whole
                    combination, with the form and expression of features, quite justifies Cuvier’s
                    assertion that “il serait difficile de se figurer un être plus hideux que le
                    Mandrill.”</p>
                <p>It is only to fully adult males that this description applies. The female is of
                    much smaller size, and of more slender make; and, though the general tone of the
                    hairy parts of the body is the same, the prominences, furrows, and colouring of
                    the face are very much less marked. The young males have black faces. At the age
                    of three the blue of the cheeks begins to appear, and it is not until they are
                    about five, when they cut their great canine teeth, that they acquire the
                    characteristic red of the end of the nose.</p>
                <p>The Mandrills, especially the old males, are remarkable for the ferocity of their
                    disposition, as well as for other disagreeable qualities, which are fully
                    described in Cuvier’s account of the animal in <hi rend="italic">La
                        Ménagerie</hi><hi rend="italic">du Museum d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >IIistoire Naturelle</hi> (1801), but when young they can easily be tamed.
                    Like the rest of the Baboons, they appear to be rather indiscriminate eaters,
                    feeding upon fruit, roots, reptiles, insects, scorpions, &amp;c., and inhabit
                    open rocky ground rather than forests. Not much is known of the Mandrill’s
                    habits in the wild state, nor of the exact limits of its geographical
                    distribution. The specimens brought to Europe all come from the west coast of
                    tropical Africa, from Guinea to the Gaboon.</p>
                <p>An allied species, the Drill <hi rend="italic">(Cynocephalus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">leucophseus')</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> which
                    resembles the Mandrill in size, general proportions, and shortness of tail, but
                    wants the bright colouring of the face which makes that animal so remarkable,
                    inhabits the same district. (w. <hi rend="smallcaps">h. f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
