<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0553-0526-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARAT, Jean Paul</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 526</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851789">Chains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44x4f">Doctors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n553/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARAT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Paul</hi></label>
                    (1743-1793), a famous revolutionary leader, was the eldest child of Jean Paul
                    Mara of Cagliari and Louise Cabrol of Geneva, 'and was born at Boudry, in the
                    principality of Neuchâtel, on May 24, 1743. His father was a doctor of some
                    learning, who had abandoned his country and his religion, and had married a
                    Swiss Protestant. It was he that laid the basis of the young Jean Paul’s
                    scientific learning, and the son at the same time imbibed the doctrines of
                    Rousseau. On his mother’s death in 1759 he set out on his travels, and spent two
                    years at Bordeaux in the study of medicine, whence he moved to Paris, where he
                    made use of his knowledge of his two favourite sciences, optics and electricity,
                    to subdue an obstinate disease of the eyes. After some years in Paris he went to
                    Holland, the retreat of philosophers, where all the works of the Encyclopédiste
                    were printed for the French market, and then on to London, where he settled in
                    Church Street, Soho, a fashionable district, and practised his profession. In
                    1773, at the age of thirty, he made his first appearance as an author with a <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophical Essay on Man, being an Attempt to Investigate the
                    Principles and Laws of the Reciprocal Influence of the Soul on the Body,</hi> of
                    which only two volumes are extant, though at the end of the second volume he
                    speaks of a third. The book shows a wonderful knowledge of English, French,
                    German, Italian, and Spanish philosophers, and directly attacks Helvetius, who
                    had in his <hi rend="italic">I.’Esprit</hi> declared a knowledge of science
                    unnecessary for a philosopher. Marat, as he now began to call himself, declares
                    that physiology alone can solve the problems of the connexion between soul and
                    body, and proposes the existence of a nervous fluid as the true solution. In
                    1774 he published a political work, <hi rend="italic">The Chains of
                    Slavery,</hi> which appeared without his name, and was intended to influence
                    constituencies to return popular members, and reject the king’s friends, with
                    innumerable examples from classical and modern history of the ways in which
                    kings enslaved their peoples. The book was too late to have any influence on the
                    general election, and was got up in a style too costly for a wide circulation,
                    but its author declared later that it procured him an honorary membership of the
                    patriotic societies of Carlisle, Berwick, and Newcastle. He remained devoted to
                    his profession, and in 1775 published in London a little <hi rend="italic">Essay
                    on Gleets,</hi> price Is. 6d., of which no copy is to be found, and in Amsterdam
                    a French translation of the first two volumes of his <hi rend="italic">Essay on
                    Man.</hi> In this year, 1775, he visited Edinburgh, and on the recommendation of
                    certain Edinburgh physicians, was, on June 30, made an M.D. of St Andrews
                    University. On his return to London he published an <hi rend="italic">Enquiry
                    into the Nature, Cause, and Cure of a Singular Disease of the Eyes,</hi> with a
                    dedication to the Royal Society. In the same year there appeared the third
                    volume of the French edition of the <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man,</hi> which
                    reached Ferney, and exasperated Voltaire, by its onslaught on Helvetius, into a
                    sharp attack, that only made the young author more conspicuous. His fame as a
                    clever doctor was now great, and on June 24, 1777, the Comte d’Artois,
                    afterwards Charles X. of France, “owing to the report he had heard of the good
                    and moral life, and of the knowledge and experience in the art of medicine, of
                    J. P. Marat,” made him by brevet physician to his guards, with 2000 livres a
                    year and allowances.</p>
                <p>Marat was soon in great request as a court doctor among the aristocracy; and even
                    Brissot, in his <hi rend="italic">Mémoires,</hi> admits his influence in the
                    scientific world of Γaris. The next years were much occupied with scientific·
                    work, especially the study of heat, light, and electricity, on which he
                    presented memoirs to the Académie des Sciences, but the Academicians were
                    horrified at his temerity in differing from Newton, and, though acknowledging
                    his industry, would not receive him among them. His experiments greatly
                    interested Benjamin Franklin, who used to visit him; and Goethe always regarded
                    his rejection by the Academy as a glaring instance of scientific despotism. In
                    1780 he had published at Neuchâtel without his name a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Plan</hi><hi rend="italic">de Législation Criminelle,</hi> founded on the
                    humane principles established by Beccaria. In April 1786 he resigned his court
                    appointment. The results of his leisure were in 1787 a new translation of
                    Newton’s <hi rend="italic">Optics,</hi> and in 1788 his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires Académiques, ou Nouvelles Découvertes sur la Lumière.</hi></p>
                <p>His scientific life was now over, his political life was to begin; in the
                    notoriety of that political life his great scientific and philosophical
                    knowledge was to be forgotten, the high position he had given up denied, and he
                    himself to be scoffed at as an ignorant charlatan, who had sold quack medicines
                    about the streets of Paris, and been glad to earn a few sous in the stables of
                    the Comte d’Artois. In 1788 the notables had met, and advised the assembling of
                    the states-general. The elections were the cause of a flood of pamphlets, of
                    which one, <hi rend="italic">Offrande à</hi><hi rend="italic">la Patrie,</hi>
                    was by Marat, and, though now forgotten, dwelt on much the same points as the
                    famous brochure of the Abbé Siéyès. When the states-general met, Marat’s
                    interest was as great <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n554/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0554-0527"/> as ever, and in June 1789 he published a
                    supplement to his <hi rend="italic">Offrande,</hi> followed in July by Zu <hi
                    rend="italic">Constitution,</hi> in which he embodies his idea of a constitution
                    for France, and in September by hrs <hi rend="italic">Tableau des Vices de la
                    Constitution</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Angleterre,</hi> which he presented to the
                    assembly. The latter alone deserves remark. The assembly was at this time full
                    of Anglomaniacs, who desired to establish in France a constitution exactly
                    similar to that of England. Marat, who had lived in England, had seen that
                    England was at this time being ruled by an oligarchy using the forms of liberty,
                    which, while pretending to represent the country, was really being gradually
                    mastered by the royal power. His heart was now all in politics; and, feeling
                    that his energies needed a larger scope than occasional tracts afforded, he
                    decided to start a paper. At first appeared a single number of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Moniteur patriote,</hi> followed on September 12 by the first
                    number of the <hi rend="italic">Publiciste</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >p&gt;arisien,</hi> which on September 16 took the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >I.'Ami</hi><hi rend="italic">du Peuple,</hi> and was to absorb his future
                    life.</p>
                <p>The life of Marat now becomes part of the history of the French Revolution. From
                    the beginning to the end he stood alone. He was never attached to any party; the
                    tone of his mind was to suspect whoever was in power; and therefore no historian
                    has tried to defend him, and all state the facts about him with a strong
                    colouring. About his paper, the incarnation of himself, the first thing to be
                    said is that the man always meant what he said; no poverty, no misery or
                    persecution, could keep him quiet; he was perpetually crying—“nous sommes
                    trahis.”</p>
                <p>Further, the suspicious tone of his mind extended to his paper, and he made it
                    play the part of the lion’s mouth at Venice: whoever suspected any one had only
                    to denounce him to the <hi rend="italic">Ami</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                    Peuple,</hi> and the denounced was never let alone till he was proved innocent
                    or guilty. He began by attacking the most powerful bodies in Paris,—the corps
                    municipal, with Bailly at their head, and the court of the Châtelet,—and after a
                    struggle found them too strong for him, and fled to London (January 1790). There
                    he wrote his <hi rend="italic">Dénonciation contre</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Necker,Ατ∖A,</hi> in May dared to return to Paris and continue the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ami</hi><hi rend="italic">du Peuple.</hi> He was embittered by
                    persecution, and continued his vehement attacks against all in power—against
                    Bailly, against La Fayette, and at last, after the day of the Champs du Mars,
                    against the king himself. All this time he was hiding in cellars and sewers,
                    where he was attacked by a horrible skin disease, tended only by the woman
                    Simonne Evrard, who remained true to him. The end of the constituent assembly he
                    heard of with joy, and with bright hopes (soon dashed by the behaviour of the
                    legislative) for the future, when almost despairing in December 1791 he fled
                    once more to London, where he wrote his <hi rend="italic">École</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">du</hi><hi rend="italic">Citoyen.</hi> In April 1792, summoned
                    again by the Cordeliers, he returned to Paris, and published No. 627 of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Ami.</hi> The war was now the question, and Marat saw clearly
                    enough that it was not sought for the sake of France, that it was to serve the
                    purposes of the royalists and the Girondins, who thought of themselves alone.
                    The early days of the war being unsuccessful, the proclamation of the duke of
                    Brunswick excited all hearts; who could go to save France on the frontiers and
                    leave Paris in the hands of his enemies? Marat, like Danton, foresaw the
                    massacres of September. After the events of August 10th he took his seat at the
                    commune, and demanded a tribunal to try the royalists in prison. No tribunal was
                    formed, and the massacres in the prisons were the inevitable result. In the
                    elections to the convention, Marat was elected seventh out of the twenty-four
                    deputies for Paris, and for the first time took his seat in an assembly of the
                    nation. At the declaration of the republic, he closed his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ami</hi><hi rend="italic">du Peuple,</hi> and commenced a new paper, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic">de la République Française,</hi>
                    which was to contain Ins sentiments as its predecessor had done, and to be
                    always on the watch. In the assembly Marat had no party; he would always suspect
                    and oppose the powerful, refuse power for himself. After the battle of Λ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> almy, Dumouriez was the greatest man in France; he
                    could almost have restored the monarchy, yet Marat did not fear to go uninvited
                    to the tragedian Talma’s, and there accuse Dumouriez in the presence of his
                    friends of want of patriotism. His unpopularity in the assembly was extreme, yet
                    he insisted on speaking on the question of the king’s trial, declared it unfair
                    to accuse Louis for anything anterior to his acceptance of the constitution,
                    and, though implacable towards the king, as i7ιeone man who must die for the
                    people’s good, he would not allow Malesherbes, the king’s counsel, to be
                    attacked in his paper, and speaks of him as a “sage et respectable vieillard.”
                    The king dead, the months from January to May were spent in an unrelenting
                    struggle between Marat and the Girondins. Marat despised the ruling party
                    because they had suffered nothing for the republic, because they talked too much
                    of their feelings and their antique virtue, because they had'for their own
                    purposes plunged the country into war; while the Girondins hated Marat as
                    representative of that rough red republicanism which would not yield itself to a
                    Roman republic, with themselves for tribunes, orators, and generals. The
                    Girondins conquered at first in the convention, and ordered that Marat should be
                    tried before the Tribunal Révolutionnaire. But their victory ruined them, for
                    Marat was acquitted on April 24, and returned to the convention with the people
                    at his back. Their fall was a veritable victory for Marat. But it was his last.
                    The skin disease he had contracted in the subterranean haunts was rapidly
                    closing his life; he could only ease his pain by sitting in a warm bath, where
                    he wrote his journal, and accused the Girondins, who were trying to raise France
                    against Paris. Sitting thus on the 13th July he heard in the evening a young
                    woman begging to be admitted to see him, saying that she brought news from Caen,
                    where the escaped Girondins were trying to rouse Normandy. He ordered her to be
                    admitted, asked her the names of the deputies then at Caen, and, after writing
                    their names, said, “They shall be soon guillotined,” when the young girl, whose
                    name was Charlotte Corday, stabbed him to the heart. Grand was the funeral given
                    to the man who had suffered so much for the republic. Whatever his political
                    ideas, two things shine clearly out of the mass of prejudice which has shrouded
                    the name of Marat—that he was a man of great attainments and acknowledged
                    position, who sacrificed fortune, health, life itself, to his convictions, and
                    that he was no <hi rend="italic">bête</hi><hi rend="italic">feroce,</hi> no
                    factious demagogue, but a man, and a humane man too, who could not keep his head
                    cool in stirring times, who was rendered suspicious by constant persecution, and
                    who has been regarded as a personification of murder, because he published every
                    thought in his mind, while others only vented their anger and displayed their
                    suspicions in spoken words.</p>
                <p>The only works of Marat not mentioned in the text are <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les</hi><hi rend="italic">aventures</hi><hi rend="italic">du Comte
                    Potoιvski,</hi> a poor novel, which must have been written in his early days,
                    and which was discovered in MS. and published by Bibliophile Jacob; two
                    brochures on a balloon accident, 1785; <hi rend="italic">Les Charlatans</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Modernes, ou Lettres sur le Charlatanisme académique,</hi> 1791;
                    <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Junius</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Français, journal politique,</hi> June 2 to June 24, 1790; translation of <hi
                    rend="italic">Chains of Slavery,</hi> with fifty pages on French history
                    prefixed, year 1.</p>
                <p>On Marat’s life should be read <hi rend="italic">I.'ami du peuple,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Skizzen aus</hi><hi rend="italic">Marat's jour</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi rend="italic">nalistichen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Leben,</hi> Hamburg, 1846; A. Bougeait, <hi rend="italic">Marat,
                    Vami</hi><hi rend="italic">du, peuple,</hi> 2 vols., 1864; G. Piazzoli, <hi
                    rend="italic">Marat, Γ</hi><hi rend="italic">amico</hi><hi rend="italic">del
                    Popolo e la Rivoluzione,</hi> Milan, 1874; A. Vermorel, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Oeuvres</hi><hi rend="italic">de J. P. Marat,</hi><hi rend="italic">l'ami du
                    peuple, recueillies et annotées,</hi> 1869; F. Chevremont, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Marat, Index du Bibliophile,</hi> &amp;c., 1876; Id., <hi rend="italic"
                    >Placards de Marat,</hi> 1877; and particularly his <hi rend="italic">Jean Paul
                    Marat, esprit politique, accompagné de sa vie scientifique, politique, et
                    privée,</hi> 2 vols , 1881. (H. Μ. S.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n555/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0555-0528"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
