<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0557-0530-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARCANTONIO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 530</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n557/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARCANTONIO</label>, or, to give him his full name, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Marcantonio Raimondi,</hi> is celebrated as the chief Italian
                    master of the art of engraving in the age of the Renaissance. The date of his
                    birth is uncertain, nor is there any good authority for assigning it, as is
                    commonly done, approximately to the year 1488. He was probably born some years
                    at least earlier than this, inasmuch as he is mentioned by a contemporary
                    writer, Acbillini, as being an artist of repute in 1504. His earliest dated
                    plate, illustrating the story of Pyramus and Thisbe, belongs to the following
                    year, 1505. Marcantonio received his training in the workshop of the famous
                    goldsmith and painter of Bologna, Francesco Raibolini, usually called Francia.
                    “Having more aptitude in design,” says Vasari, “than his master, and managing
                    the graver with facility and grace, he made waist-buckles and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n558/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0558-0531"/> many other things in niello, such being then
                    greatly in fashion, and made them most beautifully, as being in truth most
                    excellent in that craft.” The real fame, however, of Marcantonio was destined to
                    be founded on his attainments, not in the goldsmith’s art generally, but in that
                    particular development of it which consists of engraving designs on metal plates
                    for the purpose of reproduction by the printing press. This art was not new in
                    Italy in the days of Marcantonio’s apprenticeship. It had been practised, in a
                    more or less elementary form, for not less than forty or fifty years in the
                    workshops of both Tuscany and Lombardy. A school of engravers had formed itself
                    at Florence under the inspiration, as it appears, chiefly of Sandro Botticelli;
                    in Lombardy the prevailing influence upon the nascent art had been that of
                    Andrea Mantegna. But hitherto neither the engravers of Florence nor those of the
                    Lombard cities had produced anything comparable for richness of effect and
                    technical accomplishment to the work done during the same period on the other
                    side of the Alps. The aim of the Italian engravers had not hitherto been
                    directed, like that of Schongauer or Dürer, towards securing such freedom and
                    precision in the use of the burin as should impart to the impressions taken from
                    their engraved plates both a striking decorative effect and a power of
                    suggesting to the eye a complex variety of natural objects and surfaces in light
                    and shade. The Italian masters had been satisfied with a much more primitive
                    order of effects. They had been content to omit all accessories and details
                    except the simplest. They had merely drawn with the needle, or dry-point, upon
                    the copper, in just the same way as they were accustomed to draw on paper with
                    the pen or silver point,—taking great pains to get the outlines true and pure,
                    and indicating shadows only by means of straight lines rapidly drawn in, or very
                    simple hatchings.</p>
                <p>By the beginning of the 16th century, however, when Marcantonio began to work at
                    engraving along with the other pupils of Francia, a desire for a more
                    complicated kind of effects was already arising among the followers of the art
                    in Italy. Both backgrounds and passages of foreground detail were often
                    imitated, inartificially enough, from the works of the northern masters.
                    Marcantonio himself was among the foremost in carrying out this movement. There
                    exist about eighty engravings which can be referred to the first five or six
                    years of his career (1505-11). Their subjects are very various, including many
                    of pagan mythology, and some of obscure allegory, along with those of Christian
                    devotion. The types of figures and drapery, and the general character of the
                    compositions, bespeak for the most part the inspiration, and sometimes the
                    direct authorship, of that artist as graceful as he was grave, Francia. But the
                    influence of German example is very perceptible also in the work of the young
                    Marcantonio, particularly in the landscape backgrounds, and in the endeavour
                    shown by him to express form by means of light and shadow with greater freedom
                    than had been hitherto the practice of the southern schools. In a few subjects
                    also the figures themselves correspond to a coarse Teutonic, instead of to the
                    refined Italian, ideal. But so far we find Marcantonio only indirectly leaning
                    on the north for the sake of self-improvement. It must have been for the sake of
                    commercial profit that he by and by produced a series of direct counterfeits of
                    northern work. We allude to the celebrated facsimiles engraved by Marcantonio on
                    copper from Albert Dürer’s woodcuts. These facsimiles are sixty-nine in number,
                    including seventeen of Dürer’s <hi rend="italic">Life of the Virgin,</hi>
                    thirty-seven of his <hi rend="italic">Little Passion</hi> on wood, and a number
                    of single pieces. According to Vasari, Dürer’s indignation over those
                    counterfeits was the cause of his journey to Venice, where he is said to have
                    lodged a complaint against Marcantonio, and induced the signoria to prohibit the
                    counterfeiting of his monogram, at any rate, upon any future imitations of the
                    kind. Vasari’s account must certainly be mistaken, inasmuch as Dürer’s journey
                    to Venice took place in 1506, and neither of the two series of woodcuts imitated
                    by Marcantonio was published until 1511. The greater part of the designs for the
                    <hi rend="italic">Life of the Virgin</hi> had, it is true, been made and
                    engraved seven years earlier than the date of their publication; and it is to be
                    remarked that, whereas Marcantonio’s copies of the <hi rend="italic">Little
                    Passion</hi> leave out the monogram of Dürer, it is inserted in his copies of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Life of the Virgin</hi>; whence it would after all seem
                    possible that he had seen and counterfeited a set of impressions of this series
                    at the time when they were originally executed, and before their publication.
                    But the real nature of the transaction, if transaction there was, which took
                    place between Dürer and Marcantonio, we cannot now hope to recover. Enough that
                    the Bolognese engraver evidently profited, both in money and in education of the
                    hand, by his work in imitating in a finer material the energetic characters of
                    these northern woodcuts. He was soon to come under a totally different
                    influence, and to turn the experience he had-gained to account in interpreting
                    the work of a master of a quite other stamp. Up till the year 1510 Marcantonio
                    had lived entirely at Bologna, with the exception, it would appear, of a visit
                    or visits to Venice. Very soon afterwards he was attracted for good and all into
                    the circle which surrounded Raphael at Rome. Where or when he had first made
                    Raphael’s acquaintance is uncertain. His passage to Rome by way of Florence has
                    been supposed to be marked by an engraving, dated 1510, and known as the
                    Climbers, <hi rend="italic">Les Grimpeurs</hi> (Bartsch 487), in which he has
                    reproduced a portion of the design of Michelangelo’s cartoon of the Battle of
                    Anghiari, and has added behind the figures a landscape imitated from the then
                    young Dutch engraver Lucas of Leyden. The piece in which he is recorded to have
                    first tried his hand after Raphael himself is the Lucretia (Bartsch 192). From
                    that time until he disappears in the catastrophe of 1527, Marcantonio was almost
                    exclusively engaged in reproducing, by means of engraving, the designs of
                    Raphael or of his immediate pupils. Raphael, the story goes, was so delighted
                    with the print of the Lucretia that he personally trained and helped Marcantonio
                    afterwards, adding, as some think, a touch of his own here and there to the
                    engraver’s work. A printing establishment was set up under the charge of
                    Raphael’s colour grinder, Il Baviera, and the profits, in the early stage of the
                    business, were shared between the engraver and the printer. The sale soon became
                    very great; pupils gathered round about Marcantonio, of whom the two most
                    distinguished were Marco Dente, known as Marco da Ravenna, and Agostino de’
                    Musi, known as Agostino Veneziano; and he and they, during the last ten years of
                    Raphael’s life, and for several years following his death, gave forth a great
                    profusion of engravings after the master’s work,—not copying, in most instances,
                    his finished paintings, but working up, with the addition of simple backgrounds
                    and accessories, his first sketches and trials, which often give the composition
                    in a different form from the finished work, and are all the more interesting on
                    that account.</p>
                <p>The best of these engravings produced in the workshop of Marcantonio—those,
                    namely, done by his own hand, and especially those done during the first few
                    years after he had attached himself to Raphael—justly count among the most
                    prized and coveted examples of the art. In them he enters into the genius of his
                    master, the genius of choice, of balance, of rhythmical purity and charm; he
                    loses little of the chastened science and subtle grace of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n559/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0559-0532"/> Raphael’s contours, or of the inspired and
                    winning sentiment of his faces; while in the parts where he is left to
                    himself—the rounding and shading, the background and landscape—he manages his
                    burin with all the skill and freedom which he had gained by the imitation of
                    northern models, but puts away the northern emphasis and redundance of detail.
                    His work, however, does not long remain at the height marked by pieces like the
                    Lucretia, the Dido, the Judgment of Paris, the Poetry, the Philosophy, or the
                    first Massacre of the Innocents. Marcantonio’s engravings after the works of
                    Raphael’s later years are cold, ostentatious, and soulless by comparison. Still
                    more so, as is natural, were those which he and his pupils produced after the
                    designs of the degenerate scholars of Raphael and Michelangelo, of a Giulio
                    Romano, a Polidoro, or a Bandinelli. Marcantonio’s association with Giulio
                    Romano was the cause of his first great disaster in life. He engraved a series
                    of obscene designs by that painter in illustration of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sonnetti lussuriosi</hi> of Pietro Aretino, and thereby incurred the anger of
                    Pope Clement VIΓ., at whose order he was thrown into prison. Marcantonio’s ruin
                    was completed by the calamities attendant on the sack of Rome in 1527. He had to
                    pay a heavy ransom in order to escape from the hands of the Spaniards, and fled
                    from Rome, in the w.ords of Vasari, “all but a beggar.” It is said that he took
                    refuge in his native city, Bologna; but he never again emerges from obscurity,
                    and all we know with certainty is that in 1534 he was dead. (s. c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
