<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0682-0651-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAZANDARÁN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 651</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137272">Sugar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1105558">Saris</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:989403">Kurds</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669j0w">Turkomans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4280544r">Kurds</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43x83n13">Sugars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n682/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAZANDARÁN</label>, a province of northern Persia, lying
                    between the Caspian Sea and the Elbùrz range, and bounded E. and W. by the
                    provinces of Astrâbâd and Gilân respectively, is 220 miles in length and 60
                    miles in (mean) breadth, with an area of about 10,000 square miles and a
                    population estimated at from 150,000 to 200,000. Mazandarân comprises two
                    distinct natural regions presenting the sharpest contrasts in their relief,
                    climate, and products. In the north the Caspian is encircled by the level and
                    swampy lowlands, varying in breadth from 10 to 30 miles, partly under
                    impenetrable jungle, partly under rice, cotton, sugar, and other crops. This
                    section is fringed northwards by the sandy beach of the Caspian, here almost
                    destitute of natural härbours, and rises somewhat abruptly inland to the second
                    section, comprising the northern slopes and spurs of the Elbùrz, which approach
                    at some points within 1 or 2 miles of the sea, and which are almost everywhere
                    covered with dense forest. The lowlands, rising but a few feet above the
                    Caspian, and subject to frequent floodings, are extremely malarious, while the
                    highlands, culminating with the magnificent Damâvand (18,600 feet), enjoy a
                    tolerably salubrious climate. But the climate, generally hot and moist in
                    summer, is everywhere capricious and liable to sudden changes of temperature,
                    whence the prevalence of rheumatism, dropsy, and especially ophthalmia, noticed
                    by all travellers. Snow falls heavily on the uplands, where it often lies for
                    weeks on the ground. The direction of the long sandbanks at the river mouths,
                    which project with remarkable uniformity from west to east, shows that the
                    prevailing winds blow from the west and north-west. The rivers themselves, of
                    which there are as many as fifty, are little more than mountain torrents, all
                    rising on the northern slopes of Elbιιrz, flowing mostly in independent channels
                    to the Caspian, and subject to sudden freshets and inundations along their lower
                    course. The chief are the Safed-rud on the Gilân frontier, the Lâr, Hari-rùd,
                    Alain-nid, Rùstam-nid, and Hârez, and all are well stocked with trout, mullet
                    (safed mâhi), carp, sturgeon, and other fish, which with rice form the staple
                    food of the inhabitants, and supply large quantities of caviare for the Russian
                    market. Near their mouths the rivers, running counter to the prevailing winds
                    and waves of the Caspian, form long sand-hills 20 to 30’feet high and about 200
                    yards broad, behind which are developed the so-called <hi rend="italic"
                    >murd-db,</hi> or “dead waters,” stagnant "pools and swamps characteristic of
                    this coast, and a chief cause of its unhealthiness.</p>
                <p>The province abounds in iron ores and in mineral pitch in every state of
                    transition from pure petroleum to the finest naphtha. The chief cultivated
                    plants are rice, cotton, sugar, a little silk, and fruits in great variety,
                    including several kinds of the orange, lemon, and citron. Some of the slope⅜ are
                    covered with extensive thickets of the pomegranate, and the wild vine climbs to
                    a great height round the trunks of the forest trees. These woodlands are haunted
                    by the tiger, panther, bear, wolf, and wild boar in considerable numbers. Of the
                    domestic animals, all remarkable for their small size, the chief are the black,
                    humped cattle somewhat resembling the Indian variety, the yabu (a sturdy breed
                    of horses), and sheep and goats.</p>
                <p>Kinneir, Frazer, and other observers speak unfavourably of the Mazandarâni
                    people, whom they describe as very ignorant and bigoted, arrogant, rudely
                    inquisitive, and almost insolent towards strangers. Tlιe peasantry, however,
                    although called the “Boeotians of Persia,” are far from dull, and betray much
                    shrewdness where their interests are concerned. In the healthy districts they
                    are stout and well made, and are the most warlike race in Persia, furnishing
                    5000 cavalry and 12,000 foot to the Government. Of the latter 2000 are always in
                    attendance on the shah at Tehran. They speak a marked and somewhat rude Persian
                    dialect; but a Tùrki idiom closely akin to the Turkoman is still current amongst
                    the foreign tribes, although they have mostly already passed from the nomad to
                    the settled state. Of these intruders the most numerous are the Modaunlιi,
                    Khojehvand, and Abdul Maleki, originally of Lek or Kurd stock, besides branches
                    of the royal Afshar and Kâjâr tribes of Tιirki descent. All these are exempt
                    from taxes in consideration of their military service.</p>
                <p>The export trade is chiefly with Russia through Baku, where broadcloths, flour,
                    saffron, and bar iron are taken in exchange for the white and coloured calicoes,
                    caviare, rice, and raw cotton of Mazandaran. Owing to the almost impenetrable
                    character of the country, there are scarcely any roads accessible to wheeled
                    carriages, and the great causeway of Shah Abbas has in many places even
                    disappeared under the jungle. Two routes, however, lead to Tehran, one by Firoz
                    Koh, 180 miles long, the other by Larijân, 144 miles long, both in tolerably
                    good repair. Except where crossed by these routes the Elbιirz forms an almost
                    impassable barrier to the south.</p>
                <p>The administration is in the hands of the prince governor, who appoints most of
                    the beglerbegs and governors of .the nine districts of Am&lt;jl, Bârfarôsh,
                    Mashhad-i-Sar, Sari, Ashraf, Farah-âbâd, Tennacorben, Kellauristak, and Kiijùr
                    into which the province is divided. There is fair security for life and
                    property; and, although otherwise indifferently administered, the country is
                    quite free from marauders or local disturbances. The revenue is about 105,000
                    tomans, of which nothing goes to the state treasury, all being required, for the
                    governors, troops, pensions, and police. The capital is Sari, the other chief
                    towns being Bârfarôsh, Mashhad-i-Sar, Ashraf, and Farah-âbâd.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
