<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0354-0333-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MALESHERBES, Chrétien Guillaume de Lamoignon (9th
                    edition, volume 15, page 333)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881212">Counseling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994346">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075837">Press</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cm39">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7751w">Press</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xn18">Checks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n354/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MALESHERBES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Chrétien Guillaume de
                            Lamoignon</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> (1721-1794), minister
                    and afterwards counsel for the defence of Louis XVI., came of a famous legal
                    family, and was born at Paris on December 6, 1721. He too was destined for the
                    legal profession, much to the surprise of Marcel, the famous dancing master, who
                    declared that his pupil would never be able to dance well enough to be a soldier
                    or a lawyer, and must therefore be a priest. The young lawyer soon proved his
                    intellectual capacity, when he was appointed president of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >cour</hi><hi rend="italic">des aides</hi> in the parlement of Paris in 1750
                    on the promotion of his father to be chancellor. One of the chancellor’s duties
                    was to control the press, and this duty was entrusted to Malesherbes by his
                    father during his eighteen years of office, and brought him into connexion with
                    the public far more than his judicial functions. To carry it out efficiently he
                    kept in communication with the literary leaders of Paris, and especially with
                    Diderot, and Grimm even goes so far as to say that “without the assistance of
                    Malesherbes the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie</hi> would probably never have
                    been published.” Though he met with abuse from all sides, there can be no doubt
                    that it was the eminently judicious manner in which he carried out his
                    objectionable duties which laid the foundation of his subsequent popularity. In
                    1771 he was called upon to mix in politics; the parlements of France had been
                    dissolved, and a new method of administering justice devised by Maupeou, which
                    was in itself commendable as tending to the better and quicker administration of
                    justice, but pernicious as exhibiting a tendency to overcentralization, and as
                    abolishing the hereditary “nobility of the robe,” which, with all its faults,
                    had from its nature preserved some independence, and been a check on the royal
                    power. Malesherbes presented a strong remonstrance against the new system, and
                    was at once banished to his country seat at St Lucie, to be recalled, however,
                    with the old parlement on the accession of Louis XVI., and to be made minister
                    of the <hi rend="italic">maison du roi</hi> in 1775. He only held office nine
                    months, during which, however, he directed his attention to the police of the
                    kingdom, which came under his department, and did much to check the odious
                    practice of issuing <hi rend="italic">lettres</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        cachet.</hi> On retiring from the ministry with Turgot in 1776, he betook
                    himself entirely to a happy country and domestic life. He had always been an
                    enthusiastic botanist; his avenue at St Lucie was world famous; he had written
                    against Buffon on behalf of the botanists whom Buffon had attacked, and had been
                    elected a member of the Académie des Sciences as far back as 1750. He was now
                    elected a member of the Académie Française, and everything seemed to promise a
                    quiet and peaceful old age spent in the bosom of his family and occupied with
                    scientific and literary pursuits, when the king in his difficulties wished for
                    the support of his name, and summoned him back to the ministry in 1787. Again he
                    held office but a short time, but returned to his country life this time with a
                    feeling of insecurity and disquiet, and, as the troubles increased, retired to
                    Switzerland. Nevertheless, in December 1792, in spite of the fair excuse his old
                    age and long retirement would have given him, he voluntarily left his asylum and
                    undertook with Tronchet and Desèze the defence of the king before the
                    convention, and it was his painful task to break the news of his condemnation to
                    the king. After this effort he returned once more to the country, but in
                    December 1793 he was arrested with his daughter, his son-in-law Μ. de Rosambô,
                    and his grandchildren, and on April 23, 1794, he was guillotined, after having
                    seen all whom he loved in the world executed before his eyes for their
                    relationship to him. Malesherbes is one of the sweetest characters of the 18th
                    century; though no man of action, hardly a man of the world, by his charity and
                    unfeigned goodness he became one of the most popular men in France, and it was
                    an act of truest self-devotion in him to sacrifice himself for a king who had
                    done little or nothing for him. With reason does his statue stand in the hall of
                    justice at Paris, for he is the greatest representative of that noble
                    independence which should prevent any thought of self when a counsel is pleading
                    his client’s cause, however perilous such advocacy might be.</p>
                <p>There are in print several scientific works of Malesherbes of varying value, of
                    which the most interesting is his <hi rend="italic">Observations</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sur</hi><hi rend="italic">Buffon</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        Daubenton,</hi> written when he was very young, and published with a notice
                    by Abeille in 1798. There exist also his <hi rend="italic">Mémoire</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">pour Louis X7I.,</hi> his <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur la
                        liberté de la presse,</hi> published 1809, and extracts from his
                    remonstrances, published as <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres choisies</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Malesherbes</hi> in 1809. For his life should be read the
                        <hi rend="italic">Notice</hi><hi rend="italic">historique</hi> of Dubois,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Éloge historique</hi> of Gaillard, and the interesting <hi
                        rend="italic">Essai,</hi> in 2 vols., 1818, of Boissy d’Anglas. There are
                    also many <hi rend="italic">éloges</hi> on him in print, of which the best-known
                    is that of Μ. Dupin, which is interestingly reviewed with much light on
                    Malesherbes’s control of the press by Sainte-Beuve in the second volume of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Causeries</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Lundi.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
