<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0331-0312-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MALACCA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 312</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1150910">Tiles</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n331/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MALACCA</label>. The town of Malacca lies on the southwest
                    coast of the Malay Peninsula, in 2° 14' N. lat. and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n332/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0332-0313"/> 102° 12' E. long. It is situated on a small river
                    bearing its name, which separates it into two parts. That on the right bank is
                    occupied by the old Dutch town, and that on the left by the business quarter,
                    which is connected with the former by a small bridge, and is chiefly inhabited
                    by Chinese and native traders. The view of Malacca from the harbour is
                    picturesque and pleasing to the eye. From Flagstaff Hill on the left—whose
                    slopes are always of a bright emerald green—to St John’s Hill on the right, on
                    which stand the ruins of the old “Dutch redoubt,”—hidden in a mass of wild
                    vegetation,—stretches for a distance of about half a mile a row of spacious
                    dwelling houses belonging to European and wealthy Chinese and Arab residents.
                    These houses are roofed with neat red tiles, and have windows opening to a stone
                    verandah facing the sea. Each house is surrounded by a large “compound,” laid
                    out with a flower garden in front and a “plantation” or orchard at the back.
                    Adjoining this European quarter lies a large suburb of native and other
                    dwellings almost concealed in a dense forest of beautiful fruit trees. Behind
                    this we see a prominent green hill, formerly used as a fort, and now as a
                    Chinese burial-ground, and beyond this the horizon is hemmed in by a long chain
                    of the Bruong and Rumbow Hills, while far in the extreme east rises the jagged
                    cone of Mount Ophir, blue as sapphire in the distance.</p>
                <p>Since the destruction (in 1807) of the old Portuguese fort erected by
                    Albuquerque, the “antiquities” of Malacca are reduced to a mere name. At the
                    foot of Flagstaff Hill, however, are the remains of the massive wall which
                    surrounded the hill, with an arched and carved gateway. On the summit of the
                    hill, where a fine view is had of the harbour and the Water Islands, are the
                    ruins of the first Christian church planted in Malayan territory, and also a
                    portion of the old convent. At the back of this hill to the right may be noted
                    the barracks, hospital, and convict lines, and massing under some fine “ansana”
                    trees—the shady elms of the East—we reach the garden of the old Dutch
                    stadthouse, and then a green square, facing which are the court-house and other
                    Government buildings, and the old Dutch church. All these buildings have sloping
                    roofs covered with small square, tiles after the Dutch style of architecture of
                    the 16th century. This is quite a unique example of Dutch domestic architecture
                    in the East, and several of the adjoining streets still bear their Dutch
                    designation, as “Heren Straat,” “Jonker •Strait,” &amp;c. The stadthouse is
                    approached by a fine flight of stone steps, forming a covered way to the upper
                    rooms. These are occupied by the governor of the Straits Settlements and the
                    judge during their annual or biennial visits, and those in the lower story are
                    used as Government offices. From the interesting ruins of the Dutch redoubt on
                    St John’s Hill an extensive view may be had of the country running around and to
                    the north and south of Malacca. Its general aspect in the immediate vicinity is
                    that of a flat country covered with luxuriant “dusoons” or plantations of fruit
                    trees, and extensive forests of tall timber; beyond this is an open country,
                    interspersed with •extensive plantations of tapioca, which at a distance
                    resemble fields of clover; then follow rice-fields, and marshes or fens, and at
                    the foot of the hills patches of virgin forest, the whole being walled in by a
                    range of blue hills. The climate of Malacca is very healthy, and the thermometer
                    in the shade ranges from 72° to 84° or even 90° Fahr. The population, which is
                    not very large, consists of Malays of the surrounding countries, of Malacca
                    Portuguese (the mixed descendants of early Portuguese settlers), of Chinese
                    proper and a large number born of Malay mothers. There is also a sprinkling of
                    natives of India and of Arabs. The Malacca Portuguese employ themselves as
                    fishermen, servants, and clerks: the rest are chiefly engaged in agricultural
                    and commercial pursuits.</p>
                <p>In consequence of its shallow harbour, Malacca has been completely outstripped as
                    a seaport by Singapore and Penang, though it still carries on a brisk trade with
                    the surrounding countries in Malacca canes, stuffed birds of beautiful plumage,
                    poultry, and large quantities of the most luscious fruits. The import and export
                    returns, show a large apparent increase in the trade,—the imports in 1880
                    amounting to $3,817,848 (£812,308), and the exports to $3,634,640, as against an
                    average of $2,505,175 and $2,577,020 respectively for 1869-72; and, though
                    Malacca has been a drag on the revenue of the colony generally, a marked
                    increase is shown in the principal items of revenue, viz., in land rents, tenths
                    in paddy, tapioca, and fruits, royalty on timber, and survey fees. In 1880 the
                    revenue was $182,323, and the expenditure $174,333, while the income and
                    expenditure of the municipality in the same year were $22,428 and $18,899
                    respectively. The Government is improving the drainage of the country by
                    clearing its natural water course. The municipality has no debts, and the
                    general progress of the settlement during the year ending 1880 must be regarded
                    as satisfactory, with an increase under almost every heading of revenue that
                    bids fair to continue.</p>
                <p>See C. A. Cameron, <hi rend="italic">Our Tropical Possessions in Malayan
                    India,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Papers Relating to H. Μ. Colonial
                    Possessions,</hi> 1879-1881.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
