<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0567-0540-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARIE ANTOINETTE, Josephe (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    540)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f1p">Jacobins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828986">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:981035">Jacobins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n567/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARIE ANTOINETTE, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Josephe</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">Jeanne</hi> (1755- 1793), queen of
                    France, was the fourth daughter of Maria Theresa and the emperor Francis T., and
                    was born on the 2d November 1755, on the day of the great earthquake at Lisbon,
                    and in the year in which the hereditary policy of enmity between the houses of
                    France and Austria was changed to an alliance between them. From her earliest
                    years she was destined by her mother to sustain this alliance, and was educated,
                    with a view to a marriage with a French prince, by the Abbé de Vermond, who was
                    to have a great influence on her future life. In 1770 Choiseul negotiated her
                    marriage to the young dauphin, which took place on May 16 with the greatest
                    pomp, but which was soon overshadowed by a terrible accident in Paris at the
                    fête given in honour of the marriage. The dauphine soon found her position very
                    difficult; she was but fourteen, and was intended by her mother to support the
                    Austrian alliance and Choiseul at the court of France. This use of her daughters
                    for political purposes has been recently denied by Von Arneth, the able editor
                    of Maria Theresa’s letters; b it a consideration of the letters themselves
                    confirms the i lea, which was at the bottom of Marie Antoinette’s unpopularity
                    in France, that she was only an Austrian spy in a high position. She had hardly
                    arrived at Paris, when her friend and the friend of the Austrian alliance,
                    Choiseul, was dismissed from the ministry, and she was left alone to steer a
                    difficult course by the advice of the Austrian minister, the Count de
                    Mercy-Argenteau, whose reports of her d ιily doings to Maria Theresa have been
                    published. In May 1774 Louis XV. died, and Marie Antoinette became queen of
                    France. Through the first years of her reign she played a very important
                    political part, but, except, as in the cases of Poland and the Bavarian
                    succession, when her mother pressed her to maintain the alliance, she chiefly
                    exerted her influence with regard to individuals, not to measures or policies.
                    Thus she effected the dismissal of Turgot, and, by the Abbé de Vermond’s advice,
                    the summons of Loménie de Brienne to the ministry, not from political but from
                    personal motives, and obtained enormous presents for her intimate friends
                    without thinking that they were interested in her for selfish motives of their
                    own. This political rôle of hers, which was more than suspected, made her
                    intensely unpopular to the French people, and this feeling was increased by her
                    social mistakes. Her extravagance in dress and her passion for the card-table
                    had greatly incensed and disgusted her mother; and, when her mother’s death
                    removed her only frank and bold adviser, she became more extravagant and more
                    frivolous than ever. Her passion for play, her love of amusement, her intimacy
                    with the Polignacs and their wild and dissipated society, her night visits to
                    masked balls in Paris, and her favours to many officers of her guards and young
                    foreigners at her court were the subject of ribald conversation in every coterie
                    of Paris. The scandal of the diamond necklace, in which the queen was not to
                    blame, spread her name with infamy all over France as if she had been guilty;
                    and among the people her extravagance was regarded as a potent cause of their
                    poverty and want. Such was her unpopularity when the states-general met in May
                    1789; she was believed to be debauched and dissipated, when her real faults were
                    that she was frivolous and careless of public opinion, Austrian at heart, though
                    queen of France, and opposed to Necker as she had been to Turgot, and to all the
                    reforms and economies her husband, Bonhomme Louis, was willing to institute.
                    From July 14 onward Marie Antoinette headed the party of reaction and armed
                    opposition to the Revolution, and became unwittingly the means of her husband’s
                    unpopularity and downfall; for she always had influence enough to prevent his
                    carrying out the frank, honest policy of reform which he desired, but not enough
                    to make him adopt hers in its stead, and is to blame for his vacillations in
                    decisive moments. Left to himself, Louis would, from the beginning of his reign,
                    have been a reforming king like Charles III. of Spain, and the great outbreak
                    might have passed over. To trace her policy minutely from 1789 to 1793 is made
                    very difficult by the numerous pretended letters of hers which have been
                    published, and till recently believed in. She inspired the collection of foreign
                    troops round Paris, contrary to the king’s opinion, and thus brought on the
                    taking of the Bastille. She was present at the banquet at Versailles which
                    caused the march of the women to Versailles and the transference of the royal
                    family to Paris. When there, she still looked forward to undoing all that had
                    been done, and would never frankly recognize her position. When brought into
                    negotiation with Mirabeau, she refused to trust him or deal frankly with him.
                    Had she done so, she would probably have established a strong constitutional
                    government, but she would not have been the self-willed Marie Antoinette. He
                    advised her to go with the king and royal family to some provincial capital,
                    declare the royal adherence to all the early acts of the assembly, but declare
                    also that its later acts were passed under constraint, and were null and void;
                    but she must not do two things—she must not fly towards the frontier, else she
                    would be suspected of seeking foreign aid, and she must not depend on the army
                    but the people. She would not act while Mirabeau was alive,—she was too
                    independent to act by any one’s advice; but when he was dead she did what he had
                    advised her not to do, fled towards the frontier, and to Bouillé’s army. The
                    royal family were stopped at Varennes, and brought back to Paris, but from that
                    time were regarded as traitors to France. She had yet two more chances. She
                    might have thrown herself into the hands of Barnave, Duport, and the
                    constitutional party of the constituent assembly, who were ready to rally round
                    their constitutional king, but she would not trust them or take their advice.
                    When she was at the end of her power, when the Tuileries had been stormed, and
                    she was in prison, and the republic proclaimed, Dumouriez was ready, after his
                    victory of Valmy, to turn his army on Paris, dissolve the Jacobins, and
                    re-establish the old constitution, but she would not trust him. It was her last
                    chance. When once the republic was proclaimed, it was evident that Louis must
                    die both to cement its foundations and to remove a dangerous centre of reaction;
                    and in January 1793 Marie Antoinette became a widow, never to the last
                    recognizing that she had sacrificed her husband to her obstinacy and self-will.
                    Harrowing descriptions have been given of her treatment in prison during the few
                    remaining months of her life, but, though she was separated from her children,
                    she had every material comfort, no less a sum than 1110 livres being spent on
                    her food alone between August and October, at the rate of 15 livres a day. At
                    last her trial came on,—a mock trial indeed, as all those of the time, for her
                    execution was determined before she came before the tribunal. Much has been said
                    of the shameful charges made against her; but, shameful as they were, they were
                    based on a confession made by her son, which, though probably forced from him
                    and utterly false, was yet put in evidence. The trial was soon over, and on the
                    same day, October 16, 1793, she was guillotined.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n568/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0568-0541"/>
                <p>It is hard to speak of Marie Antoinette with justice; her faults were caused by
                    her education and position rather than her nature, and she expiated them far
                    more bitterly than was deserved. She was thoroughly imbued with the imperial and
                    absolutist ideas of Maria Theresa, and had neither the heart, nor the
                    understanding to sympathize with the aspirations of the lower classes. Her love
                    of pleasure and of display ruined both her character and her reputation in her
                    prosperous years, and yet, after a careful examination of many of the libels
                    against her, it may be asserted with confidence that she was personally a
                    virtuous woman, though always appearing to be the very reverse. Innocence is not
                    always its own protection, and circumspection is as necessary for a queen as for
                    any other woman. Her conduct throughout the Revolution is heart-rending; we, who
                    live after the troubled times, can see her errors and the results of her pride
                    and her caprice, but at the time she was the only individual of the royal family
                    who could inspire the devotion which is always paid to a strong character. In
                    the Marie Antoinette who suffered on the guillotine we pity, not the
                    pleasure-loving queen, not the widow, who had kept her husband against his will
                    in the wrong course, not the woman, who throughout her married life did not
                    scruple to show her contempt for her slow and heavy but good-natured and loving
                    king, but the little princess, sacrificed to state policy, and cast uneducated
                    and without a helper into the frivolous court of France, not to be loved, but to
                    be suspected by all around her, and eventually to be hated by the whole people
                    of France.</p>
                <p>For lives and memoirs of Marie Antoinette before 1863, as well as engravings of
                    her, the student is referred to a complete and careful bio-bibliography,
                    contained in Μ. de Lescure's La Vraie Marie Antoinette, Paris, 1863. This work,
                    however, contains many forged letters, purporting to be hers, and leads to the
                    quest ion of Marie Antoinette’s published letters. There can be no doubt that
                    very many fabrications by autograph makers for autograph collectors are
                    published as authentic in D'Hunolstein, Correspondance inédite de Marie
                    Antoinette. Pans, 1864; and in Feuillet des Conches, Louis XV/., Marie
                    Antoinette, et Madame Elisabeth, lettres et documents inédites, Paris, 1865. The
                    falsity of these letters was shown by Professor Von Sy bel and by Μ. Geffroy in
                    the Revue des Deux Mondes, and still more clearly in the latter’s appendix to
                    his Gustave III. et la cour de France, Paris, 1867. To study Marie Antoinette as
                    she really lived, the student must consult Von Arneth’s numerous publications on
                    her and her mother and brothers, and particularly Ameth and Geffroy, Marie
                    Antoinette: Correspondance secrète entre Marie-Thérèse et le Comte de
                    Mercy-Argenteau, Paris, 3 vols., 1874, in which Marie Antoinette’s daily life
                    for ten years, from 1770-80, is described for her mother’s own eyes. For the
                    affair of the necklace read Carlyle’s Essay. For her imprisonment, trial, and
                    execution, see Campardon’s Tribunal Révolutionnaire, vol. i., and the same
                    author’s Marie Antoinette à la Conciergerie, Paris, 1863. (H. Μ. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
