<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0864-0833-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MELANCHTHON, Philip</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 833</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2s98r">Augustinians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892p9k">Spiritism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n864/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MELANCHTHON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Philip</hi></label>
                    (1497-1560), was born at Bretten, a town of the lower Palatinate, on February
                    16, 1497. His father, George Schwartzerd, was a kinsman of the famous Reuchlin,
                    and by profession an armourer or commissary of artillery under the Palatinate
                    princes. His mother, Barbara Reuter, was a thrifty housewife and affectionate
                    parent, whose pious character is evidenced by a well-known German rhyme, of
                    which she is the reputed author, beginning <hi rend="italic">Almosen
                    geben</hi><hi rend="italic">armet</hi><hi rend="italic">nicht.</hi> His mother’s
                    father, John Reuter, who was for many years mayor of Bretten, charged himself
                    with the education of Philip. Taught first by John Hungarus, then by George
                    Simler at the academy of Pfortzheim, where he lived in the house of Reuchlin’s
                    sister, young Schwartzerd exhibited remarkable precocity, and speedily won the
                    regard of Reuchlin, who dubbed him Melanchthon (the Greek form of Schwartzerd),
                    according to the fashion of that age. He lived two years at Heidelberg, and the
                    next three at Reuchlin’s university of Tübingen, where he studied law, medicine,
                    and theology, taking his doctor’s degree in 1514. He began soon after to give
                    public lectures on rhetoric, and to comment on Virgil and Terence, and ere long
                    it became known among European scholars that anew brilliant star of learning had
                    risen on the horizon, Erasmus prophesying that he would himself be speedily
                    eclipsed. In 1518, on Reuchlin’s recommendation, Melanchthon was appointed by
                    the elector of Saxony professor of Greek in the university of Wittenberg. This
                    appointment marked an epoch in German university education; Wittenberg became
                    the sch00l <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> 0f the nation; the scholastic methods of
                    instruction were summarily set aside, and in a <hi rend="italic">Discourse on
                    Reforming the Studies of Youth</hi> Melanchthon gave proof, not only that he had
                    thoroughly caught the Renaissance spirit, but that he was fitted to become one
                    of its foremost leaders. He began to lecture on Homer and the Epistle to Titus,
                    and in connexion with the former he announced that, like Solomon, he sought
                    Tyrian brass and gems for the adornment of God’s temple. Luther himself received
                    a fresh impulse towards the study of Greek, and his translation of the
                    Scriptures, begun as early as 1517, now made rapid progress, Melanchthon helping
                    to collate the Greek versions and revising Luther’s translation. Melanchthon on
                    his part felt the spell of Luther’s large personality and spiritual depth, and
                    he seems to have been prepared on his first arrival at Wittenberg to accept the
                    new theology, which indeed as yet existed mainly in subjective form, and as a
                    living spiritual force, in the person of Luther. To reduce it to an objective
                    system, to exhibit it dialectically, the calmer mind of Melanchthon, with its
                    architectural faculty and delicate moral tact, was requisite. Theologically it
                    is impossible to separate Melanchthon from Luther; “the miner’s son drew forth
                    the metal, the armourer’s son fashioned it.” Luther, in whom courage and energy
                    were too much akin to violence and zealous decision to narrow intolerance, and
                    Melanchthon, whose calm deliberation was apt to degenerate into vacillation and
                    whose conciliatory temperament was too much allied to timidity, were each the
                    fit complement of the other.</p>
                <p>Melanchthon was first drawn into the arena of the Reformation controversy through
                    the Leipsic discussion, of which he was an eager spectator. He had been sharply
                    reproved by Dr Eck for giving aid to Carlstadt (“Tace tu, Philippe, ac tua
                    studia cura nec me perturba”), and he was shortly afterwards himself attacked by
                    the blustering Ingolstadt doctor. Melanchthon replied in a brief treatise —a
                    model of Christian moderation—setting forth Luther’s first principle of the
                    supreme authority of Scripture in opposition to the patristic writings on which
                    Eck so boastfully relied. His marriage in 1520 to Catherine Krapp of Wittenberg
                    increased his own happiness, and gave a domestic centre to the Reformation. In
                    1521, during Luther’s confinement in the Wartburg, Melanchthon occupied the
                    important position of leader of the Reformation cause at the university. He
                    defended the action of the Augustinian monks when they substituted for the
                    celebration of the mass the sacrament of the supper partaken of by <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n865/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0865-0834"/> the people under both kinds; but, on the advent
                    of the Anabaptist enthusiasts of Zwickau, he had a still more difficult part to
                    play. Melanchthon was irresolute. In their attacks upon infant baptism they
                    seemed to him to have hit upon a “weak point”; and in regard to their claim to
                    personal inspiration his position was summed up in his own words, “Luther alone
                    can decide; on the one hand let us beware of quenching the Spirit of God, and on
                    the other of being led astray by the spirit of Satan.” In the same year he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Loci Communes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Berum</hi><hi rend="italic">Theologicarum.</hi> ’ After the first diet of
                    Spires (1526), where a precarious peace was patched up for the Reformed faith,
                    Melanchthon was deputed as one of twenty-eight commissioners to visit the
                    Reformed states and regulate the constitution of churches, he having just
                    published a famous treatise called the <hi rend="italic">Libellus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Visitatorius,</hi> a directory for the use of the commissioners.
                    At the Marburg conference (1529) between the German and Swiss Reformers, Luther
                    was pitted against Oecolampadius and Melanchthon against Zwingli in the
                    discussion regarding the real presence in the sacrament. How far the candid
                    conciliatory spirit of Melanchthon was biassed by Luther’s intolerance is
                    evident from the exaggerated and inaccurate accounts of the conference written
                    by the former to the elector of Saxony. At the diet of Augsburg (1530)
                    Melanchthon was the leading representative of the Reformation. With anxiety and
                    tears he drew up for that diet the seventeen articles of the evangelical faith,
                    which are known as the “Augsburg Confession.” He held conferences with Romish
                    divines appointed to adjust differences, and afterwards wrote an <hi
                    rend="italic">Apology for the Augsburg Confession.</hi> After the Augsburg
                    conference further attempts were made to settle the Reformation controversy by a
                    compromise, and Melanchthon, from bis conciliatory spirit and facility of
                    access, appeared to the Romanists the fittest of the Reformers to deal with. His
                    historical instinct led him ever to revert to the original unity of the church,
                    and to regard subsequent Romish errors as excrescences rather than proofs of an
                    essentially anti-Christian system. He was weary of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >rabies</hi><hi rend="italic">theologorum,</hi> and fondly dreamed that the
                    evangelical leaven, if simply tolerated, would at length purify the church’s
                    life and doctrine. In 1537, when the Protestant divines signed the Lutheran
                    Articles of Smalkald, Melanchthon appended to his signature the reservation that
                    he would admit of a pope provided he allowed the gospel and did not claim to
                    rule by divine right.</p>
                <p>The year after Luther’s death, when the battle of Mühlberg (1547) had given a
                    seemingly crushing blow to the Protestant cause, an attempt was made to weld
                    together the iron and clay of the evangelical and the papal doctrines, which
                    resulted in the compilation by Pflug, Sidonius, and Agricola of the Augsburg
                    “Interim.” This was proposed to the two parties in Germany as a provisional
                    ground of agreement till the decision of the council of Trent. Melanchthon, on
                    being referred to, declared equivocally that, though the Interim was
                    inadmissible, yet so far as matters of indifference <hi rend="italic"
                    >(adiaphora)</hi> were concerned it might be received. Hence arose that
                    “adiaphoristic” controversy in connexion with which he has been misrepresented
                    as holding among matters of indifference such cardinal doctrines as
                    justification by faith, the number of the sacraments, as well as the dominion of
                    the pope, feast-days, and so on. The fact is that, in these tentative
                    negotiations, Melanchthon sought, not really to minimize differences, but to
                    veil them under an intentional obscurity of expression. Thus he allowed the
                    necessity of good works to salvation, but not in the Romish sense, proposed to
                    allow the seven sacraments, but only as rites which had no inherent efficacy to
                    salvation, and so on. He afterwards retracted his compliance with the adiaphora,
                    and never really swerved from the views set forth in the <hi rend="italic">Loci
                    Communes;</hi> but he regarded the surrender of more perfect for less perfect
                    forms of truth or of expression as a painful sacrifice rendered to the weakness
                    of erring brethren. Luther, though he had uttered certain expressions of
                    dissatisfaction with Melanchthon, and had more keenly defended in his last years
                    what was distinctively his own, yet maintained hearty and unbroken friendship
                    with him; but after Luther’s death certain smaller men arose in name of Luther
                    who formed a party emphasizing the extremest points of the doctrine of the
                    latter. Hence the later years of Melanchthon were much occupied with acrid
                    controversies within the evangelical church; an account of these, however, would
                    be out of place here. His last years were spent in fruitless conferences with
                    his Romanist adversaries, and amid various controversies among the Reformed, but
                    the flame of his piety burnt brightly till the close. He died in his sixty-third
                    year, on the 19th April 1560, and his body was laid beside that of Martin
                    Luther.</p>
                <p>Melanchthon’s ever ready pen, clear thought, and elegant stylo made him the
                    scribe of the Reformation, most public documents on that side being drawn up by
                    him. He never attained entire independence of Luther, though he gradually
                    modified some of his positions from those of the pure Lutherism with which he
                    set out. His development is chiefly noteworthy in regard to these two leading
                    points—the relation of the <hi rend="italic">cυangelium</hi> or doctrine of free
                    grace (1) to free will and moral ability, and (2) to the law and <hi
                    rend="italic">poenitcntia</hi> or the good works connected with repentance. At
                    first Luther’s cardinal doctrine of grace appeared to Melanchthon inconsistent
                    with any view of free will; and, following Luther, he renounced Aristotle and
                    philosophy in general, since “philosophers attribute everything to human power,
                    while the sacred writings represent all moral power as lost by the fall.” In the
                    first edition of the <hi rend="italic">Loci</hi> (1521) he held, to the length
                    of fatalism, the Augustinian doctrine of irresistible grace, working according
                    to God’s immutable decrees, and denied freedom of will in matters civil and
                    religious alike. In the Augsburg Confession (1530), which was largely due to
                    him, freedom is claimed for the will in non-religious matters, and in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Loci</hi> of 1533 he calls the denial of freedom Stoicism, and
                    holds that in justification there is a certain causality, though not worthiness,
                    in the recipient subordinate to the Divine causality. In 1535, combating
                    Laurentius Valla, he did not deny the spiritual incapacity of the will <hi
                    rend="italic">per sc,</hi> but held that this is strengthened by the word of
                    God, to which it can cleave. The will co-operates with the word and the Holy
                    Spirit. Finally, in 1543, he says that the cause of the difference of final
                    destiny among men lies in the different method of treating grace which is
                    possible to believers as to others. Man may pray for help and reject grace. This
                    he calls free will, as the power of laying hold of grace. Melanchthon’s doctrine
                    of the three concurrent causes in conversion, viz., the Holy Spirit, the word,
                    and the human will, suggested the semiPelagian position called Synergism, which
                    was held by some of his immediate followers.</p>
                <p>In regard to the relation of grace to repentance and good works, Luther was
                    disposed to make faith itself the principle of sanctification. Melanchthon,
                    however, for whom ethics possessed a special interest, laid more stress on the
                    law. He began to do this in 1527 in the <hi rend="italic">Libellus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Visitatorius,</hi> which urged pastors to instruct their people in
                    the necessity of repentance, and to bring the threatenings of the law to bear
                    upon men in order to faith. This brought down upon him the opposition of the
                    Antinomian John Agricola. In the <hi rend="italic">Loci</hi> of 1535 Melanchthon
                    sought to put the fact of the co-existence of justification and good works in
                    the believer on a secure basis by declaring the latter necessary to eternal
                    life, though the believer’s destiny thereto is already fully guaranteed in his
                    justification. In the <hi rend="italic">Loci</hi> of 1543 he did not retain the
                    doctrine of the necessity of good works in order to salvation, and to this he
                    added, in the Leipsic Interim, “that this in no way countenances the error that
                    eternal life is merited by the worthiness of our own works.” Melanchthon was led
                    gradually to lay more and more stress upon the law and moral ideas; but the
                    basis of the relation of faith and good works was never clearly brought out by
                    him, and he at length fell back on his original position that we have
                    justification and inheritance of bliss in and by Christ alone, and that good
                    works are necessary by reason of immutable Divine command.</p>
                <p>Melanchthon’s life has been written by Camerarius. See also Matthes, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ph. Melanchthon,</hi><hi rend="italic">sein Leben und Wirken,</hi>
                    1841; Galle, <hi rend="italic">Charakteristik Melanchthons als Theologen,</hi>
                    Halle, 1845; Rothe’s <hi rend="italic">Gedächtnissredeauf Melanchthon,</hi>
                    1860; Nitzsch, <hi rend="italic">Melanchthon,</hi> 1860; Schmidt, <hi
                    rend="italic">Melanchthons Leben,</hi> 1864. There is a biography In English by
                    F. A. Cox, 2d ed., London, 1817. The works of Melanchthon, including his
                    correspondence, are contained in the voluminous <hi rend="italic">Corpus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Reformatorum,</hi> edited by Bretschncider and Bindseil. (J. WI.)
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n866/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0866-0835"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
