<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0301-0284-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAGPIE, or simply Pie (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    284)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10v2q">Crows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn85">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx6497c">Wings</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1063903">Pies</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950030">Habit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204724">Missouri</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204928">California</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n301/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAGPIE, or simply <hi rend="smallcaps">Pie</hi></label>
                    (French, <hi rend="italic">Pie),</hi> the prefix being the abbreviated form of a
                    human name (Margaret<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>“Magot” and “Madge,” with the same origin, are names frequently
                            given in England to the Pie; while in France it is commonly known as <hi
                                rend="italic">Mαrgοt,</hi> if not termed, as it is in some
                            districts, <hi rend="italic">Jaquette.</hi></p></note>) applied as in so
                    many other instances to familiar animals, as this bird once was throughout Great
                    Britain, though of late years almost exterminated in many parts, and now nearly
                    everywhere scarce. Its pilfering habits have led to this result, yet the
                    injuries it causes are unquestionably exaggerated by common report; and in many
                    countries of Europe it is still the tolerated or even the cherished neighbour of
                    every farmer, as it formerly was in England if not in Scotland also. There is
                    ample evidence<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A
                            compendious summary of this will be found in Yarrell’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >British Birds,</hi> ed. 4, ii. pp. 318-320.</p></note> to prove
                    that it did not exist in Ireland in 1617, when Fynes Morison<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>His predecessor Derricke,
                            in 1578, said :—</p><p>“No Pies to plucke the Thatch from house, are
                            breed in Irishe grounde:</p><p>But worse then Pies, the same to bume, a
                            thousande maie be founde.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">—The Image of
                                Irelande</hi><hi rend="italic                     subscript"> t</hi>
                            London, 1581.</p></note> wrote his <hi rend="italic">Itinerary,</hi> and
                    that it had appeared there within a hundred years later, when Swift mentions its
                    occurrences in his <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> to Stella, under date of 9th
                    July 1711. It is now common enough in that country, and there is a widespread
                    but of course unfounded belief that it was introduced by the English out of
                    spite. It is a species that when not molested is extending its range, as Wolley
                    ascertained in Lapland, where within the last century it has been gradually
                    pushing its way along the coast and into the interior from one fishing-station
                    or settler’s house to the next, as the country has been peopled.</p>
                <p>Since the persecution to which the Pie has been subjected in Great Britain, its
                    habits have undoubtedly altered greatly in character. It is no longer the merry,
                    saucy hanger-on of the homestead, as it was to writers of former days, who were
                    constantly alluding to its disposition, but is become the suspicious thief,
                    shunning the gaze of man, and knowing that danger may lurk in every bush. Hence
                    opportunities of observing it fall to the lot of few, and most persons know it
                    only as a curtailed captive in a wicker cage, where its vivacity and natural
                    beauty are lessened or wholly lost. At large few European birds possess greater
                    beauty, the pure white of its scapulars and inner web of the flightfeathers
                    contrasting vividly with the deep glossy black on the rest of its body and
                    wings, while its long tail is lustrous with green, bronze, and purple
                    reflexions. The Pie’s nest is a wonderfully ingenious structure, placed either
                    in high trees or low bushes, and so massively built that it will stand for
                    years. Its foundation consists of stout sticks, turf, and clay, wrought into a
                    deep, hollow cup, plastered with earth, and lined with fibres; but around this
                    is erected a firmly-interwoven, basket-like outwork of thorny sticks, forming a
                    dome over the nest, and leaving but a single hole in the side for entrance and
                    exit, so that the whole structure is rendered almost impregnable. Herein are
                    laid from six to nine eggs, of a pale bluish-green freckled with brown and
                    blotched with ash-colour. Superstition as to the appearance of the Pie still
                    survives even among many educated persons, and there are several versions of a
                    rhyming adage as to the various turns of luck which its presenting itself,
                    either alone or in company with others, is supposed to betoken, for some of
                    these versions contradict one another in details, though all agree in this that
                    the sight of a single Pie unquestionably presages sorrow.</p>
                <p>The Pie belongs to the same Family of birds as the <hi rend="smallcaps">Crow</hi>
                    (vol. vi. p. 617), and is the <hi rend="italic">Corvus pica</hi> of Linnaeus,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Pica</hi><hi rend="italic">caudata,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >P. melaηoleuca,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">P. rustica</hi> of modern <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n302/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0302-0285"/> ornithologists, who have recognized it as
                    forming a distinct genus, but the number of species thereto belonging has been a
                    fruitful source of discussion. Examples from the south of Spain differ slightly
                    from those inhabiting the rest of Europe, and in some points more resemble the
                        <hi rend="italic">P. mauritanica</hi> of north-western Africa; but that
                    species has a patch of bare skin of a fine blue colour behind the eye, and much
                    shorter wings. No fewer than five species have been discriminated from various
                    parts of Asia, extending to Japan; but only one of them, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >P. leucoptera</hi> of Turkestan and Tibet, has of late been admitted as
                    valid. In the west of North America, and in some of its islands, a Pie is found
                    which extends to the upper valleys of the Missouri and the Yellowstone, and has
                    long been thought entitled to specific distinction as <hi rend="italic">P.
                        hudsonia</hi>; but its claim thereto is now disallowed by some of the best
                    ornithologists of the United States, and it can hardly be deemed even a
                    geographical variety of the Old-World form. In California, however, there is a
                    permanent race if not a good species, <hi rend="italic">P. nuttalli,</hi> easily
                    distinguishable by its yellow bill and the bare yellow skin round its eyes; and
                    it is a curious fact that on two occasions in the year 1867 a bird apparently
                    similar was observed in Great Britain <hi rend="italic">(Zoologist,</hi> ser. 2,
                    pp.</p>
                <p>706, 1016). <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
