<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0228-0211-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAGIC LANTERN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 211</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:992536">Lanterns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1077002">Prisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="fasttopic:998476">Light</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:1109343">Screens</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:996178">Lenses</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:943029">Glass</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term n="20" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn3j">Screens</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dk97">Lenses</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s8p">Prisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n228/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAGIC LANTERN</label> is the name given to an optical
                    instrument for projecting on a white wall or screen largely magnified
                    representations of transparent pictures painted or photographed on glass.</p>
                <p>The invention of the magic lantern is usually attributed to Athanasius Kircher,
                    who died in 1680, although, according to some, it was known four centuries
                    earlier to Roger Bacon (see p. 207). For long after its discovery the magic
                    lantern was used chiefly to exhibit comic pictures, or in the hands of so-called
                    wizards to summon up ghosts and perform other tricks astonishing to those who
                    were ignorant of the simple optical principles employed. Within the last twenty
                    or thirty years, however, and mainly on account of the invention of photography,
                    the magic lantern has been greatly improved in construction, and its use widely
                    extended. By its means finely executed photographs on glass can be shown greatly
                    magnified to large audiences. The scientific lecturer is thus saved the trouble
                    and expense of preparing large diagrams, besides having his subject better
                    illustrated. When suitably constructed, the magic lantern can be used in the
                    form of a microscope to exhibit on a screen the forms and movements of minute
                    living organisms, or to show to an audience delicate physical and chemical
                    experiments which could otherwise be seen only by a few at a time.</p>
                <p>The magic lantern in its simplest form is represented in fig. 1. A is a dark box
                    surmounted by a suitable chimney for carrying off the products of combustion
                    from the source <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n229/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0229-0212"/> of light I., which is placed in the focus of a
                    spherical reflector. On the side opposite the reflector the box is pierced by a
                    round hole, into which is fitted the metal tube D, which may either be
                    cylindrical or slightly tapered. To the inner end of the tube D is fitted a lens
                    or combination of lenses C called the “condenser.” Immediately in front of the
                    condenser, and at right angles to the axis of the tube, is a vertical slit S for
                    receiving the transparent pictures usually called “slides.” To the outer end of
                    D is fitted a lens or combination of lenses 0 called the “objective” or
                    “projecting lens.” At a suitable distance from O is placed the screen for
                    receiving the magnified picture —the screen and slit being in the conjugate foci
                    of the lens O. Since the objective reverses, the picture must be inserted in the
                    slit upside down. The objective can be moved backwards and forwards in the tube
                    D by means of a rack and pinion. Since the screen and slide are in the conjugate
                    foci of O the diameter of the picture on the screen has the same ratio to the
                    screen’s distance from O that the diameter of the picture on the slide has to
                    the slide’s distance from O. The ratio adopted is generally 1 to 3 or 4.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Source of Light.—</hi> Almost any good source of light can be
                    used in the magic lantern. In the earlier forms a simple oil light was used; and
                    in the toy forms either an oil light or simple gasflame is still employed.
                    Better effects are obtained from the Argand fountain lamp (fig. 2) or from the
                    common Argand gas burner with a glass chimney. In the sciopticon (fig. 3)—a
                    handy and excellent form recently introduced—a specially constructed paraffin
                    lamp is employed with three parallel flat wicks set edgeways to the condenser.
                    With this lamp a clear, well-defined picture varying from 6 to 10 feet in
                    diameter can be readily thrown on the screen. For the best effects, however,
                    recourse must be had to the oxy-calcium light (fig. 4), in which a small
                    cylinder of lime is heated to intense luminosity in the flame of a spirit lamp
                    through which a jet of oxygen plays; the <hi rend="smallcaps">Oxy-hydrogen
                    Light</hi></p>
                <p>(ç.v.); the magnesium light, in which two narrow ribands of magnesium are put
                    through slits bya clock-work arrangement and burn as they advance; or, best of
                    all,—unless when sunlight can be used with the aid of a heliostat (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Heliography),</hi> —the electric light.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Condenser and Objective.—</hi> The object of the condenser
                    (fig. 5, C) is to collect as much light as possible from the source, and pass it
                    through the transparent picture in the slit. For this purpose the condenser
                    should subtend as large an angle as possible at the source of light. To secure
                    this, the condenser should be tolerably large, and its distance from the light,
                    that is, its focal length, small. Since effective single lenses of large
                    diameter are necessarily of long focus, a really good condenser of considerable
                    diameter and yet of short focus must be a combination of two or more lenses.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> and ∕ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> be the focal lengths of two lenses, and <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> the focal length of their combination. Then, neglecting the
                    thickness of the lenses, we have when the two are close toegther</p>
                <p>7"⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> ⅛</p>
                <p>From which we get/-a fraction which ie always less than either <hi rend="italic"
                    >f</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi> or∕ <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    provided these are not zero. Suppose, for example, two lenses of 6 and 10 inches
                    focal length respectively; the focal length of their combination will be <hi
                    rend="strikethrough">θ^θ</hi> =3f inches.</p>
                <p>In the earlier lanterns, as still in the cheaper forms, only a single
                    plano-convex lens or bull’s-eye was employed as a condenser. Better effects are
                    produced by two such lenses. Perhaps the best condenser for ordinary work is
                    that proposed by Herschel and represented in fig. 5, C, consisting of a biconvex
                    lens and a meniscus mounted together with the concave side of the meniscus next
                    the light. The diameter of such a condenser is about 6 inches, and its focal
                    length a little over 3 inches. The focus must not be so short as to bring the
                    lens too near the light, and render it liable to crack from the intense heat. In
                    some lanterns this is guarded against by placing a plate of thin glass between
                    the condenser and the light. In the sciopticon (fig. 3) the condenser consists
                    of two plane-convex lenses, each about 4 inches in diameter. Condensers of large
                    diameter are not so essential now as formerly, seeing that small pictures can
                    easily be produced by photography.</p>
                <p>The function of the objective (fig. 5, 0) is to produce a magnified inverted
                    image of the picture on the screen. In toy lanterns it is a simple double-convex
                    lens of short focus. This, however, can only produce a small picture, and that
                    not very distinct at the edges. The best objective is the portrait combination
                    lens used in ordinary photographic cameras. These are carefully corrected both
                    for spherical and chromatic aberration, which is absolutely essential in the
                    objective, although not so necessary in the condenser. It is essential, however,
                    that the condenser be free from cracks or flaws, as these would appear and mar
                    the picture.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Slides.—</hi> These are pictures, painted with transparent
                    water or oil colours, or photographed on pieces of glass. The pieces of glass
                    are usually fixed in small wooden frames for insertion in the slit. If parts of
                    the picture are to be movable, two disks of glass are employed, the one movable
                    in front of the other, the fixed part of the picture being painted on the fixed
                    disk and the movable part on the other. By means of a lever the latter disk is
                    moved in its <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n230/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0230-0213"/> own plane and in this way a cow for instance can
                    be represented drinking, or a donkey cutting amusing capers. A lever slide is
                    represented in fig. 6. In the chromatrope elide (fig. 7) two circular disks of
                    glass are placed face to face, each containing a design radiating from the
                    centre, and painted with brilliant transparent colours. By a small pinion
                    gearing in toothed wheels or endless bands the disks are made to move in
                    opposite directions in their own plane.</p>
                <p>The effect produced is a singularly beautiful change of design and colour. In
                    astronomical slides the motions of the heavenly bodies, eclipses, the phases of
                    the moon, or the like are similarly represented by mechanical means. »Slides can
                    also be made from narrow glass tanks with parallel sides. When these are filled
                    with water containing delicate living organisms the forms and movements of the
                    latter are beautifully seen. Such tanks can also be employed to show such
                    phenomena as the gradual growth of crystals, the electrolysis of water between
                    platinum electrodes, &amp;c. A great variety of physical and chemical
                    experiments can be shown in this way.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dissolving Views.—</hi> For this purpose two magic lanterns are
                    necessary, arranged either side by side or the one on the top of the other. The
                    fronts of the lanterns are slightly inclined to each other so as to make the
                    illuminated disks on the screen due to each lantern coincide. By means of a pair
                    of thin metallic shutters terminating in comb-like teeth, and movable by a rack
                    or lever, the light from either lantern can be gradually cut off at the same
                    time that the light from the other is allowed gradually to fall on the screen.
                    In this way one view appears to melt or dissolve into another. This arrangement
                    was first adopted by Childe in 1811.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Phantasmagoria.—</hi> In this arrangement the pictures on the
                    screen appear gradually to increase or diminish in size and brightness. To
                    effect this a semi-transparent screen of cotton or other material is used, the
                    lantern being behind and the audience in front. The lantern is mounted on wheels
                    so that it can be rapidly moved up to or withdrawn from the screen; and an
                    automatic arrangement is provided whereby simultaneously with this the objective
                    is made to approach or recede from the slide so as to focus the picture on the
                    screen in any position of the lantern. In this way a very small picture appears
                    gradually to grow to enormous dimensions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lantern Polariscope.—</hi> This, perhaps the most beautiful
                    modification of the magic lantern for scientific purposes, consists of an
                    elbowshaped tube, containing mirrors, lenses, &amp;c., and attached to the front
                    of the lantern in place of the tube containing the objective. It is represented
                    in section in fig. 8. C' is the usual condenser belonging to the lantern. G is a
                    set of thin glass plates inclined at the polarizing angle 56° 45' to the axis of
                    the tube. The beam of polarized light from I. reflected from G passes through
                    the lenses</p>
                <p>F and the analysing Nicol’s prism P, and falls on the screen. The objects to be
                    examined by the polarized light are placed in the transverse slit 0. When thin
                    plates of selenite or other doubly refracting crystals are placed in 0, a most
                    beautiful display of complementary colours is produced on the screen by rotating
                    the N icol’s prism. Almost all the experiments on polarized light can be well
                    shown by this arrangement.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">sdopticon</hi> (fig. 3) is an excellent and convenient
                    lantern, very suitable for all the requirements of the lecturer, as well as for
                    school use in teaching geography, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>See Brewster's optics; Ganot's Physics; and Chadwick’s Manual of the Magic
                    Lantern. (J. BL.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
