<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0305-0288-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAHOGANY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 288</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1019244">Mexicans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942527">Gibbons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:824720">Aztecs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1006009">Mahogany</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1001952">Logging</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1125500">Solids</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1150988">Timber</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205805">Cuba</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm14059">Logging</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4377639r">Solids</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m62">Aztecs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cr5ng9z">Mahogany</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n305/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAHOGANY</label>, a familiar dark-coloured wood largely used
                    for household furniture, and supplied by a large tree indigenous to Central
                    America and the Antilles. It was originally received from Jamaica; 521,300 feet
                    were exported from that island in 1753. <hi rend="italic">Swietenia
                    Mahogani,</hi> I.., is the sole species of the genus of the order <hi
                    rend="italic">Meliaceae</hi> (Benth. and Hook., <hi rend="italic">Gen. Pl.,</hi>
                    i. 338). It bears imparipinnate leaves, like those of the ash, and panicles of
                    small pentamerous flowers with 10 monadelphous stamens. The fruit is a
                    pear-shaped woody capsule, with many winged seeds. The dark-coloured bark has
                    been considered a febrifuge, and the seeds were used by the ancient Aztecs with
                    Oil for a cosmetic, but the most valuable product is the timber, first noticed
                    by the carpenter on board Sir Walter Raleigh’s ship in 1595, for its great
                    beauty, hardness, and durability. Dr Gibbons brought it into notice as well
                    adapted for furniture in the early part of the 18 th century, and its use as a
                    cabinet wood was first practically established by a cabinetmaker named
                    Wollaston, who was employed by Gibbons to work up some mahogany brought to
                    England by his brother. Since its introduction no wood has been more generally
                    used for cabinet-making purposes, and none possesses like advantages of combined
                    soundness, large size, uniform grain, durability, beauty of colour, and richness
                    of figure.</p>
                <p>In the trade the wood is generally classified under the two heads of Spanish
                    Mahogany and Honduras Mahogany or Baywood. The former comprises the rich, solid,
                    and heavy varieties, susceptible of a high degree of polish, and frequently
                    showing rich wavy figuring, in which case the wood is enormously enhanced in
                    value, and used only in the form of veneers. Under the name of Honduras mahogany
                    or baywood is embraced the light open-grained and plain classes of mahogany,
                    uniform in colour, and valuable for the ease with which they can be worked for
                    an endless variety of uses where sound straight timber, free from all tendency
                    to warp, is required. By importers, however, several classes of mahogany are
                    recognized. The original Spanish mahogany is the produce of the island of San
                    Domingo, whence only small supplies now come, and these mostly in logs of not
                    more than 8 to 10 feet in length by 12 or 13 inches in thickness. Cuba mahogany
                    is in richness of figure and other properties little inferior for ornamental
                    purposes to San Domingo wood, while it possesses the advantage of being obtained
                    in logs up to 35 feet long and 2 feet square in cross section. Squared Honduras
                    logs are sometimes obtained 40 feet long and 2 feet thick, and, although the
                    wood is generally plain in character, richly figured logs are occasionally got.
                    It appears that the Honduras wood obtained in the north, near the Mexican
                    boundary, is much more rich, dense, and solid than the soft swamp-grown timber,
                    which commonly goes by the name of Honduras or baywood. In Mexico the mahogany
                    tree attains its greatest dimensions, and thence logs squared to 40 and even 48
                    inches are sometimes obtained, whilst the common size of logs varies between 15
                    inches and 3 feet. The Mexican wood is cut into lengths of from 18 to 30 feet,
                    for convenience of shipment, and, while in general the wood is plain and
                    somewhat soft in the core, the produce of some provinces, Tabasco especially, is
                    firm, solid, and not unfrequently richly figured. Occasionally the wood which
                    has been .floated in tropical seas is found to be badly “wormed” or attacked by
                    marine borers. The cutting, squaring, and shipment of the wood in the tropical
                    regions which are its home are conducted under circumstances of great
                    difficulty. The tree has recently been introduced into the north-west provinces
                    of India under very favourable conditions, and its successful cultivation there
                    is likely to prove a matter of considerable economic importance. Mahogany is
                    included among the second-class woods in Lloyd’s list for ship-building
                    purposes; it is a good deal employed in internal joiner work both in ships and
                    houses; it is a favourite turnery wood, and is equally preferred by
                    wood-carvers. The imports of mahogany into the United Kingdom during 1881 were
                    42,412 tons, of an estimated value of £390,418, fully one-half of which came
                    from Mexico.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
