<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0212-0195-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAESTRICHT, or Maastricht (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    195)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:918881">Expression</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830115">Belgians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n212/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAESTRICHT, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Maastricht</hi></label>,
                    the chief town of the province of Limburg, in the Netherlands, lies, as the name
                    expresses, at the <hi rend="italic">trecht</hi> or crossing of the Maas (Meuse),
                    where the Romans erected a military post on the road between Bagacum (Bavay)and
                    Colonia Agrippina (Cologne). Aix-la-Chapelle is 18 miles east-south-east, and
                    Liége 18 miles south by west. The baths discovered in 1840 io the Groote
                    Stokstraat show that the settlement at Trajectum ad Mosam became a place of some
                    considerable importance. The town is divided by the river into two parts—the
                    larger portion, or Maestricht proper, on the left bank, and the smaller portion,
                    distinguished as Wijk, on the right. A stone bridge of eight arches connecting
                    the two took the place of a wooden structure as early as 1280, and was greatly
                    improved in 1828 and 1836. Formerly a fortress, Maestricht is still a
                    considerable garrison town, but its ramparts were dismantled 1871—78; formerly
                    the seat of a bishop, it still bears a strongly Roman Catholic impress; and, in
                    modern times more especially, it has developed into a great centre of commerce
                    and industry. The churches and religious foundations are almost the only
                    buildings of note, the chief exceptions being the town-house, completed in 1683,
                    and the solitary Protestant church, Janskerk (13th century). The church of St
                    Servatius was, according to one account, rebuilt and enlarged as early as the
                    time of Charles the Great. It is now 260 feet in length, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n213/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0213-0196"/> in the varied character of its Gothic
                    architecture bears evidence of the frequency with which it has been restored and
                    altered. The high altar has a Descent from the Cross by Anthony Vandyck. The
                    saint whose name it preserves obtained great reputation in Maestricht by
                    transferring his bishopric thither from Tongres, and his miracle-working relics
                    became the occasion of a great septennial fair which was formerly of great
                    service to the city. The Church of Our Lady (Lieve-Vrouwe-kerk), possibly
                    founded in the 6th century, has two very ancient crypts and an 11th century
                    choir of exceptional beauty, but in the nave has suffered severely from a
                    restoration in 1764. St Matthyskerk was founded by the cloth-weavers’ guild in
                    the 13th century; and, though the present Gothic building of St Martin’s (in
                    Wijk) was erected so late as 1859, the original church was one of the oldest in
                    the city, and is said by tradition to have occupied the site of one of the old
                    heathen temples. The twelve hospitals, the poorhouse, the orphanage, and most of
                    the other charitable foundations are Roman Catholic institutions, and neither
                    the administrative bodies nor the educational establishments are free from
                    ecclesiastical influence. Though Maestricht is no doubt mainly indebted for its
                    commercial prosperity to its position on the river, it did not begin to reap the
                    full advantages of the situation till the removal of the fortifications and the
                    opening of the railways (Aix-la-Chapelle, 1853; Hasselt, 1856; Liège, 1861;
                    Vanlo, 1865, &amp;c.). At first a trade was carried on in wine, colonial wares,
                    alcoholic liquors, and salt; but now, besides Regout’s well-known earthenware,
                    glass, and crystal factory, there are establishments for the making of arms,
                    tools, lead, copper, and zinc work, &amp;c., as well as tobacco and cigar
                    factories. The Maestricht beer also is highly esteemed. The population, which
                    was 18,000 in the beginning of the century, was 28,917 on January 1, 1882.</p>
                <p>Maestrichtwas taken and plundered by the Normans(881 and 884), by Bishop Henry of
                    Guelders (1267), by Adolph de la Marek (1334), and by the people of Liège (1407
                    and 1408). In the war with Spain it was successively besieged by the Spaniards,
                    the prince of Orange, Prince Maurice, and Frederick Henry (1579, 1580, 1594,
                    1632); and in the struggle between Louis XIV. of France and William III., and
                    again during the French Revolution and the Napoleonic period, it paid the
                    penalty of its frontier position—witness the sieges of 1673, 1676, 1701, and
                    1793. During the revolution of 1830 it was invested by the Belgians. Among the
                    more peaceful memories of the place is the marriage of Otto IV. with Mary of
                    Brabant. The people of Maestricht have a special dialect of their own; <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> but French and Dutch are in use among the upper
                    classes. In the neighbourhood of the town are the great sandstone quarries of
                    Petersberg, one of the most extraordinary labyrinths of subterranean excavation
                    in the world.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
