<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0863-0832-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">MELA, Pomponius</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 15, page 832</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q80j">Ocean</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kh5s">Columns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915906">Ethiopians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:868845">Columns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1043442">Ocean</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n863/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MELA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pomponius</hi></label>, a Roman
                    writer on geography. His little work, though a mere compendium, is the only
                    systematic treatise on the subject preserved to us in the Latin language, with
                    the exception of that which forms part of the encyclopaedic work of the elder
                    Pliny, and from this circumstance it derives a value to which it would be little
                    entitled from its intrinsic merits. Nothing is known of the author except his
                    name, and that he was born, as he himself informs us, at a small town called
                    Tingentera in the south of Spain. But the date of his work may be fixed with
                    little doubt from an allusion in the preface to a proposed expedition of the
                    reigning emperor to Britain, which can hardly be referred to any other event
                    than the visit to that island of the emperor Claudius in 43 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.</hi> This conclusion is accepted by all the recent editors; the view of
                    some earlier scholars, who understood this passage as referring to the
                    expedition of Julius Caesar, is clearly disproved by the mention of several
                    facts w hich were not anterior to the reign of Augustus. The little treatise is
                    not only a mere abridgment, occupying less than one hundred pages of ordinary
                    print, but is so deficient in method and systematic character that we should
                    have supposed it to be little more than a mere schoolbook, were it not that we
                    find the name of the author figuring in a prominent manner among the authorities
                    cited by Pliny for the geographical books of his vast compilation.</p>
                <p>His general views of the geography of the earth do not differ materially from
                    those which were current among Greek writers from the time of Eratosthenes to
                    that of Strabo, and are well known to us from the great work of the latter
                    author, which was, however, in all probability unknown to Mela, as it certainly
                    was to Pliny. But in one of his views he stands alone among ancient writers on
                    geography, that after describing the division of the earth into five zones, of
                    which two only were inhabitable, he states as an undoubted fact the existence of
                    <hi rend="italic">antichthones,</hi> who inhabited the southern temperate zone,
                    but were inaccessible and consequently unknown to the inhabitants of the
                    corresponding zone in the north, on account of the excessive heat of the
                    intervening torrid zone. His views <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n864/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0864-0833"/> of the division and boundaries of the three
                    continents of Europe, Asia, and Africa coincide with those of Eratosthenes; and,
                    in common with all ancient geographers from the time of Alexander to that of
                    Ptolemy, he regarded the Caspian Sea as an inlet from the Northern Ocean,
                    corresponding to the Persian Gulf on the south. His ideas concerning India are
                    extremely confused and imperfect,— altogether inferior to those possessed by
                    Greek writers long before; he follows Eratosthenes in supposing that country to
                    occupy the south-eastern angle of Asia, whence the coast trended northwards to
                    Scythia, and then swept round to the westward to the opening of the Caspian Sea.
                    As usual he places the Rhipaean Mountains and the Hyperboreans near the Scythian
                    Ocean, which he of course connects with that supposed to exist to the north of
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>With regard to the west of Europe, on the other hand, his knowledge was somewhat
                    in advance of the Greek geographers, as might be expected from the extension of
                    the Roman dominion and civilization in that quarter, and from a writer who was
                    himself a native of Spain. Accordingly we find him possessing a more accurate
                    idea than either Eratosthenes or Strabo of the western coast-line of Spain and
                    Gaul, and its deep indentation by a gulf (the Bay of Biscay) between the
                    projecting headlands of the two countries. Of Britain, on the contrary, he has
                    little to tell us, beyond what we find in Caesar or Strabo, though he appears to
                    have had a clearer idea of the position of the British Islands than the Greek
                    geographer. He is also the first ancient writer who mentions the name of the
                    Orcades or Orkneys, which he correctly describes as a large group of islands to
                    the north of Britain. Of the north of Europe his knowledge was still utterly
                    imperfect; but he had a vague notion of the existence to the north of Germany of
                    a large bay, which he calls Codanus Sinus, containing many islands, large and
                    small, among which was one much larger than the rest, which he calls
                    Codanovia,—· evidently the same name that reappears in Pliny under the form
                    Scandinavia, which has been attached by modern writers to the great northern
                    peninsula of Europe.</p>
                <p>The method followed by Mela in describing the three continents is peculiar and
                    inconvenient. Instead of treating each continent separately, and describing the
                    countries included in it, he begins at the Strait of the Columns (the Straits of
                    Gibraltar), which was close to his own birthplace, and describes the countries
                    adjoining the south coast of the Mediterranean from Mauretania to Egypt, and
                    afterwards those around the east coast of the same sea with its tributary the
                    Euxine, and then back along the north of the Mediterranean from Scythia to Gaul
                    and Spain. He then begins again with the countries bordering the western and
                    northern ocean from Spain and Gaul round to India, and from thence by Persia and
                    Arabia to the Ethiopians, and thence again round Africa to the straits from
                    which he began. In common with most ancient geographers, be considered Africa as
                    surrounded by the sea, but had a very inadequate idea of its extent towards the
                    south.</p>
                <p>The first edition of Pomponius Mela-was published in 1471, and it was very often
                    reprinted in the 15th and 16th centuries. The edition of Voss in 1658, with a
                    valuable commentary, became the foundation of all the subsequent editions, of
                    which those by Gronovius (in 1685 and 1742) are among the best-known and most
                    useful. The edition by Tzschucke, in 6 vols. 8vo (1806), contains an
                    overwhelming mass of notes and commentaries, but by far the best text is that of
                    the recent edition by G. Parthey (Berlin, 1867), who has in many instances
                    restored the original readings, which had been displaced by the conjectures of
                    Voss and others. (E. H. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
