<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0667-0636-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAURETANIA, or Mauritania (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    636)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882n4f">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c24qn5t">Atlases</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q80j">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820246">Atlases</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043442">Ocean</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205592">Morocco</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205364">Mauritania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n667/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAURETANIA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Mauritania</hi></label>
                    (the former is the more correct form of the name, according to coins and
                    inscriptions), was the name given in ancient geography to the district which
                    constituted the north-western angle of the African continent. It comprised a
                    considerable part of the modern empire of Morocco, together with the western
                    portion of Algeria. But its limits varied much at different times. When it first
                    appears in history the river Mulucha constituted its eastern limit, which
                    separated it from the Numidian tribe of the Massyli, who held all the country
                    from that river to the Ampsaga; but at a later period the kingdom of Mauretania
                    was extended to the.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n668/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0668-0637"/>
                <p>latter river so as to include the whole territory from the Ampsaga to the
                    Atlantic Ocean. Towards the south it was bounded by the great range of Mount
                    Atlas, and it appears to have been regarded by geographers as extending along
                    the coast of the Atlantic as far as the point where that chain descends to the
                    sea, in about 30° N. lat., though the Roman province of the name extended but a
                    little beyond Sala (Sallee), and it is probable that there were no towns or
                    permanent settlements farther south. The magnificent plain, or rather plateau,
                    in which the city of Morocco is situated seems to have been unknown to ancient
                    geographers, and was certainly never included in the Roman empire. On the other
                    hand the Gaetulians, who inhabited the narrow strip of fertile date-producing
                    territory on the southern slopes of the Atlas, though not included under the
                    name of Mauretania, seem to have always owned a precarious subjection to the
                    kings of that country, and in after days to its Roman governors.</p>
                <p>The physical geography of the country will be described under the heading <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Morocco,</hi> though it must be observed that the term
                    Mauretania, as used by the Romans, comprised also the greater portion of the
                    French colony of Algeria, including the provinces of Oran and Algiers, and even
                    a part of that of Constantine. The range of Mount Atlas forms throughout the
                    backbone of the country, from which the streams descend to the Mediterranean and
                    the ocean. The most important of those on the north coast is the Mulucha or
                    Molochath, which in the earliest times constituted the eastern limit of the
                    country; it is still called Muluya. Farther east are the Chinala, the Usar, and
                    the Ampsaga. Of those that flow westward towards the Atlantic, the most
                    considerable were the Lixus, Subur, and Sala. But from the proximity of the
                    mountain ranges to the sea none of these streams were of any importance, or
                    navigable beyond a short distance from the sea.</p>
                <p>A large part of the country is of great natural fertility, and was in ancient
                    times extensively cultivated, and produced large quantities of corn, while the
                    slopes of Mount Atlas were clothed with vast forests, which, besides other kinds
                    of timber, supplied the celebrated ornamental wood called <hi rend="italic"
                        >Citrus,</hi> for tables of which the Romans gave such fabulous prices.</p>
                <p>Mauretania, or Maurusia, as it was called by Greek writers, unquestionably
                    signified the land of the Mauri, a term still retained in the modern name of
                    Moors, and probably meaning originally nothing but “black men.” The origin and
                    ethnical affinities of the race are unknown; but it is probable that the
                    inhabitants of all this northern tract of Africa along the coast of the
                    Mediterranean were kindred races belonging to the family which is represented at
                    the present day by the Berbers of the mountain districts and the Tuaricks of the
                    tract south of the Atlas. They first appear in history at the time of the
                    Jugurthine War (110-106 B.c.), when Mauretania west of the Mulucha was under the
                    government of a king called Bocchus, aud appears to have constituted a regular
                    and organized state. It retained its independence till the time of Augustus, who
                    in 25 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> bestowed the sovereignty of the previously
                    existing kingdom upon Juba II., king of Numidia, at the same time uniting with
                    it the western portion of Numidia, from the Mulucha to the Ampsaga, which now
                    received the name of Mauretania Caesariensis, while the province that had
                    previously constituted the kingdom, or Mauretania Proper, came to be known as
                    Mauretania Tingitana. This distinction continued to subsist after the
                    incorporation of the two provinces in the Roman empire under Claudius in 42
                    A.r&gt;., and remained unchanged till the time of Constantine.</p>
                <p>In the time of Pliny and Ptolemy, Mauretania contained a number of flourishing
                    cities and towns, several of which enjoyed the privileges of Roman colonies,
                    having been founded no doubt in great part with a view of keeping in check the
                    wild barbarians who still occupied the greater part of the country. The most
                    important of these places were—Tingis, on the site of the modern Tangier, the
                    capital of the province to which it gave its name; Lixus and Sala, on the coast
                    of the Atlantic, at the mouths of the rivers of the same name; and three towns
                    in the interior of the same province, Zilis, Babba, and Banasa, all of them
                    bearing the title of Roman colonies. On the coast of the Mediterranean stood
                    Rusaddir (now Melilla), within the limits of Tingitana; and beyond the Mulucha
                    Cartenna (now Tenes); lol, surnamed Caesarea, which was made his capital by Juba
                    II., and continued to be that of Mauretania Caesariensis under the Romans (its
                    site is now called Cherchell); Icosium (the modern Algiers); Saldae (Bujeyah);
                    Igilgili (Jijeli) near the eastern limit of the province; and Sitifis (Setif) at
                    no great distance in the interior, a town of considerable importance, which
                    after the time of Constantine gave the name of Mauretania Sitifensis to this
                    eastern portion of the province. The prosperity of this part of Africa under the
                    Roman empire, previous to the irruption of the Vandals in 429 A.D <hi
                        rend="subscript"> w</hi> is shown by the fact that no less than one hundred
                    and seventy towns which were episcopal sees are enumerated in the Notitia in the
                    two provinces of Mauretania.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
