<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0555-0528-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARBLE (9th edition, volume 15, page 528)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z7110r">Lime</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n555/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARBLE</label> is a term applied to any limestone which is
                    sufficiently close in texture to admit of being polished. Many other ornamental
                    stones—such as serpentine, alabaster, and even granite—are sometimes loosely
                    designated as marbles, but by accurate writers the term is invariably restricted
                    to those crystalline and compact varieties of carbonate of lime which, when
                    polished, are applicable to purposes of decoration. The crystalline structure is
                    typically shown in statuary marble. A fractured surface of this stone displays a
                    multitude of sparkling facets, which are the rhombohedral cleavageplanes of the
                    component grains. On placing a thin section of Carrara marble under the
                    microscope, it is seen that each grain is an imperfect crystal, or crystalloid,
                    of calcspar, having an irregular boundary, and being itself made up of a number
                    of crystalline plates twinned together (see fig. 5, article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Geology,</hi> vol. x. p. 231). It is said that a somewhat similar
                    polysynthetic structure may be artificially induced in calc-spar by means of
                    pressure. As marble appears to be, in many cases, a metamorphic rock, it is
                    probable that pressure and heat have been the principal natural agents concerned
                    in the alteration of compact into crystalline limestones. It was shown many
                    years ago by Sir James Hall that even an earthy limestone, like chalk, when
                    strongly heated in a closed vessel, might assume a saccharoidal texture; and it
                    is a fact familiar to the field-geologist that a crystalline structure is often
                    locally developed in limestone where it happens to have been invaded by an
                    eruptive rock. Prof. Geikie proposes to distinguish this kind of metamorphism by
                    the term <hi rend="italic">mar-marosis (Text-Book of Geology,</hi> 1882).</p>
                <p>Among statuary marbles the first place may be assigned to the famous Pentelic
                    marble, the material in which Phidias, Praxiteles, and other Greek sculptors
                    executed their principal works. The characteristics of this stone are well seen
                    in the Elgin marbles, which were removed from the Parthenon at Athens, and are
                    now in the British Museum. The marble was derived from the quarries of Mount
                    Pentelicus in Attica. The neighbouring mountain of Hymettus likewise yielded
                    marbles, but these were neither so pure in colour nor so fine in texture as
                    those of Pentelicus. Parian marble, another stone much used by Greek sculptors
                    and architects, was quarried in the isle of Paros, chiefly at Mount Marpessa. It
                    is called by ancient writers <hi rend="italic">l·ychnites,</hi> in allusion to
                    the fact that the quarries were worked by the light of lamps. The Venus de’
                    Medici is a notable example of work in this material. Carrara marble is better
                    known than any of the Greek marbles, inasmuch as it constitutes the stone
                    invariably employed by the best sculptors of the present day. This marble occurs
                    abundantly in the Apuan Alps, an offshoot of the Apennines, and is largely
                    worked in the neighbourhood of Carrara, Massa, and Serravezza. Stone from this
                    district was employed in Rome for architectural purposes in the time of
                    Augustus, but the finer varieties, adapted to the needs of the sculptor, were
                    not discovered until some time later. It is in Carrara marble that the finest
                    works of Michelangelo and of Canova are executed. The purest varieties of this
                    stone are of snow-white colour and of lino saccharoidal texture. Silica is
                    disseminated through some of the marble, becoming a source of annoyance to the
                    workman; while occasionally it separates as beautifully pellucid crystals of
                    quartz known as Carrara diamonds. The geological age of the marbles of the Apuan
                    Alps has been a subject of much dispute, some geologists regarding them as
                    metamorphosed Triassic or even Liassic rocks, while others are disposed to refer
                    them to the Carboniferous system. Much of the common marble is of a bluish
                    colour, and therefore unfit for statuary purposes; when streaked with blue and
                    grey veins, the stone is known as <hi rend="italic">bardiglio.</hi> Curiously
                    enough, the common white marble of Tuscany comes to England as Sicilian marble—a
                    name probably due to its having been formerly re-shipped from some port in
                    Sicily.</p>
                <p>Although crystalline marbles fit for statuary work are not found to any extent in
                    Great Britain, the limestones of the Palaeozoic formations yet yield a great
                    variety of marbles waell suited for architectural purposes. The Devonian rocks
                    of South Devon are rich in handsome marbles, presenting great diversity of tint
                    and pattern. Plymouth, Torquay, Ipplepen, Babbacombe, and Chudleigh may be named
                    as the principal localities. Many of these limestones owe their beauty to the
                    fossil corals which they contain, and are hence known as madrepore marbles.</p>
                <p>Of far greater importance than the marbles of the Devonian system are those of
                    Carboniferous age. It is from the Carboniferous or Mountain Limestone that
                    British marbles are mainly derived. Marbles of this age are worked in Derbyshire
                    and Yorkshire, in the neighbourhood of Bristol, in North Wales, in the Isle of
                    Man, and in various parts of Ireland. One of the most beautiful of these stones
                    is the encrinital marble, a material which owes its peculiarities to the
                    presence of numerous encrinites, or stone-lilies. These fossils, when cut in
                    various directions, give a characteristic pattern to the stone. The joints of
                    the stems and arms are known from their shape as “wheel-stones,” and the rock
                    itself is sometimes called entrochal marble. The most beautiful varieties are
                    those in which the calcareous fossils appear as white markings on a ground of
                    grey limestone. On the Continent a black marble with small sections of crinoid
                    stems is known as <hi rend="italic">petit</hi><hi rend="italic">granit,</hi>
                    while in Derbyshire a similar rock, crowded with fragments of minute encrinites,
                    is termed bird’s-eye marble.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most generally useful marbles yielded by the Carboniferous system are
                    the black varieties, which are largely employed for chimney pieces, vases, and
                    other ornamental objects. The colour of most black limestone is due to the
                    presence of bituminous matter, whence the mineralogical name anthraconite. Such
                    limestone commonly emits a fetid odour when struck; and the colour, being of
                    organic origin, is discharged on calcination. Black marbles, more or less dense
                    in colour, are quarried in various parts of Ireland, especially at Kilkenny and
                    near Galway; but the finest kind is obtained from near Ashford <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n556/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0556-0529"/> i.i Derbyshire. From Ashford is also derived
                    a very beautiful stone known as rosewood marble. This is a dense brown laminated
                    limestone, displaying when polished a handsome pattern somewhat resembling the
                    grain of rosewood; it occurs in very limited quantity, and is used chiefly for
                    inlaid work.</p>
                <p>With the rosewood marble may be compared the well-known landscape marble or
                    Cotham stone, an argillaceous limestone with peculiar dendritic markings, due
                    probably to the infiltration of water containing oxide of manganese. This
                    limestone occurs in irregular masses near the base of the White Lias, or
                    uppermost division of the Rhsetic series. It is found principally in the
                    neighbourhood of Bristol. The arborescent forms depicted in bluish-grey upon
                    this landscape marble form a marked contrast to the angular markings of warm
                    brown colour which are seen on slabs of ruin marble from Florence—a stone
                    occasionally known also as landscape stone, or <hi rend="italic">pietra
                        paesina.</hi></p>
                <p>British limestones of Secondary and Tertiary age are not generally compact enough
                    to be used as marbles, but some of the shelly beds are employed to a limited
                    extent for decorative purposes. Ammonite marble is a dark brown limestone from
                    the Lower Lias of Somersetshire, crowded with ammonites, principally <hi
                        rend="italic">A. planicostata.</hi> Under the name of Forest marble,
                    geologists recognize a local division of the Lower Oolitic series, so named by
                    W. Smith from Wy ch wood Forest in Oxfordshire, where shelly limestones occur;
                    and these, though of little economic value, are capable of being used as rough
                    marbles. But the most important marbles of the Secondary series are the shelly
                    limestones of the Purbeck formation. Purbeck marble was a favourite material
                    with mediaeval architects, who used it freely for slender clustered columns and
                    for sepulchral monuments. It consists of a mass of the shells of a fresh-water
                    snail, <hi rend="italic">Paludina cariniflera,</hi> embedded in a blue or grey
                    limestone, and is found in the Upper Purbeck beds of Swanage in Dorsetshire.
                    Excellent examples of its use may be seen in Westminster Abbey and in the Temple
                    Church, as well as in the cathedrals of Salisbury, Winchester, Worcester, and
                    Lincoln. Sussex marble is a very similar stone, occurring in thin beds in the
                    Weald clay, and consisting largely of the shells of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pahιdina,</hi> principally <hi rend="italic">P. sussexiensis</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">P.</hi><hi rend="italic">fluviorum.</hi> The altar stones and
                    the episcopal chair in Canterbury cathedral are of this material.</p>
                <p>Mixtures of limestone and serpentine frequently form rocks which are sufficiently
                    beautiful to be used as ornamental stones, and are generally classed as marbles.
                    Such serpentinous limestones are included by petrologists under the term
                    ophicalcite. The famous <hi rend="italic">vercle</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >antico</hi> is a rock of this character. Mona marble is an ophicalcite from
                    the metamorphic series of the Isle of Anglesey, while the “Irish green” of
                    architects is a similar rock from Connemara in western Galway. It is notable
                    that some of the “white marble” cf Connemara has been found by Messrs King and
                    Rowney to consist almost wholly of malacolite, a silicate of calcium and
                    magnesium.</p>
                <p>A beautiful marble has been worked to a limited extent in the island of Tiree,
                    one of the Hebrides, but the quarry appears to be now exhausted. This Tiree
                    marble is a limestone having a delicate carnelian colour diffused through it in
                    irregular patches, and containing rounded crystalloids of sahlite, a green
                    augitic mineral resembling malacolite in composition. When dissolved in acid the
                    marble leaves a brick-red powder, which has been studied by Dr Heddle, who has
                    also analysed the sahlite.</p>
                <p> Many marbles which are prized for the variegated patterns they display owe these
                    patterns to their formation in concentric zones,—such marbles being in fact
                    stalagmitic deposits of carbonate of lime, and probably consisting in many cases
                    of aragonite. One of the most beautiful stalagmitic rocks is the so-called onyx
                    marble of Algeria. This stone was largely used in the buildings of Carthage and
                    Rome, but the quarries which yielded it were not known to modern sculptors until
                    1849, when Μ. Delamonte rediscovered the marble near Oued-Abdallah. The stone is
                    a beautifully translucent material, delicately clouded with yellow and brown,
                    and is greatly prized by French workmen. Large deposits of a very fine onyx-like
                    marble, similar to the Algerian stone, have been worked of late years at Técali,
                    about 35 miles from the city of Mexico. Among other stalagmitic marbles, mention
                    may be made of the well-known Gibraltar stone, which is often worked into models
                    of cannon and other ornamental objects. This stalagmite is much deeper in colour
                    and less translucent than the onyx marbles of Algeria and Mexico. A richly
                    tinted stalagmitic stone worked in California is known as Californian marble. It
                    is worth noting that the “alabaster” of the ancients was stalagmitic carbonate
                    of lime, and that this stone is therefore called by mineralogists “Oriental
                    alabaster” in order to distinguish it from our modern “alabaster,” which is a
                    sulphate, and not a carbonate, of lime.</p>
                <p>The brown and yellow colours which stalagmitic marbles usually present are due to
                    the presence of oxide of iron. This colouring matter gives special characters to
                    certain stones, such as the <hi rend="italic">giallo</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >antico,</hi> or antique yellow marble of the Italian antiquaries. Siena
                    marble is a reddish mottled stone obtained from the neighbourhood of Siena in
                    Tuscany; and a somewhat similar stone is found in King’s County, Ireland. True
                    red marble is by no means common, but it does occur, of bright and uniform
                    colour, though in very small quantity, in the Carboniferous limestone of
                    Derbyshire and north-east Staffordshire. It may be noted that the red marble
                    called <hi rend="italic">rosso</hi><hi rend="italic">antico</hi> is often
                    confounded with the <hi rend="italic">porfido rosso</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >antico,</hi> which is really a red porphyritic felstone.</p>
                <p>Fire marble is the name given to a brown shelly limestone containing ammonites
                    and other fossil shells, which present a brilliant display of iridescent
                    colours, like those of precious opal. It occurs in rocks of Liassic age at the
                    lead-mines of Bleiberg in Carinthia, and is worked into snuff-boxes and other
                    small objects. By mineralogists it is often termed <hi rend="italic"
                        >lumaclιella,</hi> an Italian name which may, however, be appropriately
                    applied to any marble which contains small shells.</p>
                <p>It would unnecessarily extend this article to enumerate the local names by which
                    marble-workers in different countries distinguish the various stones which pass
                    under their hands. The quarries of France, Belgium, and Italy, not to mention
                    less important localities, yield a great diversity of marbles, and almost each
                    stone bears a distinctive name, often of trivial meaning.</p>
                <p>America possesses some valuable deposits of marble, which in the eastern States
                    have been extensively worked. The crystalline limestones of western New England
                    furnish an abundance of white and grey marble, while a beautiful material fit
                    for statuary work has been quarried near Rutland in Vermont. A grey bird’s-eye
                    marble is obtained from central New York, and the greyish clouded limestones of
                    Thomaston in Maine have been extensively quarried. Of the variegated and
                    coloured marbles, perhaps the most beautiful are those from the northern part of
                    Vermont, in the neighbourhood of Lake Champlain. A fine brecciated marble is
                    found on the Maryland side of the Potomac, below Point of Rocks. Among the
                    principal localities for black marble may be mentioned Shoreham in Vermont and
                    Glen Falls in New York. In Canada the crystalline limestones of the Laurentian
                    series yield beautiful marbles.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n557/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0557-0530"/>
                <p>Turning to India, we find important quarries at Makrana in Rajputana—a locality
                    which is said to have yielded the marble for the famous Taj Mahal at Agra. In
                    the valley of the Nerbudda, near Jabalpur, there is a large development of
                    marble. The white marble which is used for the delicately-pierced screens called
                        <hi rend="italic">jalee</hi> work is obtained from near Raialo, in Ulwar.
                    See Ball’s <hi rend="italic">Economic Geology of India,</hi> 1882.</p>
                <p>For descriptions of ancient marbles see F. Corsi’s treatise <hi rend="italic"
                        >Delle</hi><hi rend="italic">Pietre antiche</hi>; and for marbles in general
                    consult Professor Hull’s <hi rend="italic">Building and Ornamental Stones,</hi>
                    1872. (F. W. R.*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
