<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0495-0472-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANDEVILLE, Bernard de (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    472)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829774">Bees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166263">Vices</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166236">Vice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:963738">Humorists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n495/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANDEVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bernard de</hi></label>
                    (1670-1733), is generally-known as an ethical writer of debasing and degrading
                    tendency, but he was at least as much of a humorist as a philosopher, and set up
                    as an analyst of “what is,” repeatedly disavowing all pretensions as a lawgiver
                    of “what ought to be.” He was a foreigner by birth, a native of Rotterdam, where
                    his father practised as a physician for thirty years. A remarkably eloquent
                    schoolboy exercise, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Medicina Oratio
                        Scholastica,</hi> was printed for him at Rotterdam in 1685. He studied for
                    six years at Leyden, and took his degree in medicine in 1691, his inaugural
                    thesis being <hi rend="italic">De Chylosi</hi><hi rend="italic">Vitiata.</hi>
                    Immediately afterwards he came over to England “to learn the language,” which he
                    did to some purpose, writing it with such mastery as to throw doubts upon his
                    foreign extraction. He settled in London as a physician. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fable of the Bees</hi> is the general title of the miscellaneous work by
                    which he is known to fame. This work includes the fable proper, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Grumbling Hive, or Knaves Turned Honest</hi> (some two
                    hundred doggerel couplets, published as a sixpenny pamphlet and pirated as a
                    halfpenny sheet in 1705); <hi rend="italic">Remarks</hi> on the fable and <hi
                        rend="italic">An Inquiry into, the Origin of Moral Virtue,</hi> added to the
                    edition of 1714; <hi rend="italic">An Essay on Charity Schools,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">A Search into the Origin of Society,</hi> added to the edition
                    of 1723. Owing to a curious misprint in an edition published after Mandeville’s
                    death, a wrong date is commonly assigned to the <hi rend="italic">Grumbling
                        Hive,</hi> and the contemporary point of it consequently missed. It appeared
                    during the heat of the bitterly contested elections of 1705, when the question
                    before the country was whether Marlborough’s war with France should be
                    continued. The cry of the high Tory advocates of peace was that the war was
                    carried on purely in the interests of the general and the men in office; charges
                    of bribery, peculation, hypocrisy, every form of fraud and dishonesty, were
                    freely cast about among the electors. It was amidst this excitement that
                    Mandeville sought and found an audience for his grimly humorous paradox that
                    “private vices are public benefits,”— that individual self-seeking, ambition,
                    greed, vanity, luxury, are indispensable to the prosperity and greatness of a
                    nation. “Fools only strive to make a great an honest hive.” The bees of his
                    fable grumbled as many Englishmen were disposed to do,—“cursed politicians,
                    armies, fleets,” whenever there came a reverse, and cried, “Had we but honesty
                    !” Jove at last in a passion swore that he would “rid the bawling hive of
                    fraud,” and filled the hearts of the bees with honesty and all the virtues,
                    strict justice, frugal living, contentment with little, acquiescence in the
                    insults of enemies. Straightway the flourishing hive declined, till in time only
                    a small remnant was left; this took refuge in a hollow tree, “blest with content
                    and honesty,” but destitute of arts and manufactures. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Grumbling Hive</hi> was in fact a political <hi rend="italic">jeτι
                        &lt;1esprit,</hi> full of the impartial mockery that might be expected from
                    a humorous foreigner, and with as much ethical theory underlying it as might be
                    expected from a highly educated man in an age of active ethical speculation. The
                    underlying theory was made explicit in the <hi rend="italic">Remarks</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Origin of Moral Virtue,</hi> published in
                    1714. But his purpose in dwelling on the text that private vices are public
                    benefits was still rather the invention of humorous paradoxes than the
                    elaboration of serious theory. Dr Johnson, who owned that Mandeville “opened his
                    views into real life very much,” considered that the fallacy of his argument lay
                    in his defining neither vices nor benefits. But such a criticism as this
                    overlooks the hinge on which all Mandeville’s paradoxes turn. He does define
                    virtue and vice very precisely, in accordance with the current orthodoxy of the
                    time. He “gives the name of virtue to every performance by which man, contrary
                    to the impulse of nature, should endeavour the benefit of others, or the
                    conquest of his own passions, out of a rational ambition of being good”; while
                    “everything which, without regard to the public, man should commit to gratify
                    any of his appetites” is vice. His paradoxical humour has ample scope in tracing
                    how much vice and how little virtue there is in the world, when the terms are
                    thus strictly defined. He finds self-love (a vice by the definition)
                    masquerading in many virtuous disguises, lying at the root of asceticism,
                    heroism, public spirit, decorous conduct,—at the root, in short, of all the
                    actions that pass current as virtuous. These actions are not virtuous by the
                    definition, because not performed solely “out of a rational ambition of being
                    good.” “This is the way,” Dr Johnson says, “to try what is vicious, by
                    ascertaining whether more evil than good is produced by it on the whole.”
                    Mandeville would at once have admitted this, but his definition compelled him,
                    in determining virtue and vice, to consider also the motive. And having regard
                    to the motive, “the nearer we search into human nature, the more we shall be
                    convinced that the moral virtues are the political offspring which flattery
                    begot upon pride.” Man, “an extraordinary selfish and headstrong as well as a
                    cunning animal,” has been induced to subordinate his own appetites to the good
                    of others, by the dexterous management of politicians and moralists, who have
                    worked upon his pride to persuade him that self-indulgence is worthy only of the
                    brutes, and altogether “unbecoming the dignity of such a sublime creature as
                    himself.” When Mandeville, in the 1723 edition of the fable, applied his
                    analysis of self-regarding motives to the institution of charity schools, at
                    that time a highly fashionable form of munificence, a great outcry was made
                    against his doctrines; his book was presented to the justices by the grand jury
                    of Middlesex as being of an immoral and pernicious tendency, and a copy was
                    condemned to be burnt by the common hangman. Mandeville’s defence of himself was
                    that his remarks were “designed for the entertainment of people of knowledge and
                    education,” and that his inquiry could hardly be intelligible except to those
                    accustomed to matters of speculation; and he claimed that he had “diverted
                    persons of great probity and virtue and unquestionable good sense.” The truth is
                    that, to be rightly understood, the prose part of Mandeville’s fable must be
                    read in connexion with Lord Shaftesbury’s ethical writings; the intention to
                    ridicule the amiable but somewhat feebly reasoned theories of that moralist is
                    most apparent in the <hi rend="italic">Search into the Origin of Society,</hi>
                    but many lurking references may be detected elsewhere. If Mandeville were taken
                    seriously, he would certainly be open to the charge of conveying the impression
                    that those who restrain their appetites and sacrifice personal interests for the
                    public good make fools of themselves, and are the dupes of a designing society.
                    But his main purpose seems to have been to entertain himself and others at the
                    expense of more serious but less quick-witted theorizers.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n496/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0496-0473"/>
                <p>Besides his political and philosophical parerga, Mandeville wrote, in 1711, a
                    medical treatise, <hi rend="italic">Of the Hypochoridriack and Hysterick
                        Passions—</hi> their symptoms, causes, and cures. The treatise is in the
                    form of a dialogu¾ and is “interspersed with instructive discourses on the real
                    art of physic itself, and entertaining remarks on the modern practice of
                    physicians and apothecaries.” In this, with the same entertaining style and
                    clear and subtle judgment, he protests against and ridicules speculative
                    therapeutics, and pleads for patient diagnosis and careful observation and
                    record of facts. His own theories about the animal spirits and their connexion
                    with “the stomachic ferment” are fanciful enough, but he shows an intimate
                    acquaintance with the scientific methods of Locke, and a warm admiration for
                    Sydenham. <hi rend="italic">The Virgin Unmasked; Free Thoughts on Religion, the
                        Church, and National Happiness', An Inquiry into the Causes of the frequent
                        Executions at Tyburn; An Inquiry into the Origin of Honour, and Usefulness
                        of Christianity in JJ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ar</hi> —are titles of other works of Mandeville; but all that
                    is characteristic of him as a thinker and humorist may be found in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Fable of the Bees.</hi> (w. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
