<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0210-0193-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MADURA (9th edition, volume 15, page 193)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40000538">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930nw3c">Jets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dq72">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:979776">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104337">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130905">Spring</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n210/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MADURA</label>, in High Javanese <hi rend="italic"
                        >Madunten,</hi> an island of the East Indian Archipelago, separated by the
                    shallow Strait of Madura from the east end of Java. It extends from about 112’
                    32' to 114’ 7' E. long., and is divided into two nearly equal portions by the
                    parallel of 7’ S. lat.; the· area is estimated at 2100 square miles. As the few
                    travellers who have visited Madura have been for the most part content to follow
                    the highways which, though running the whole length of the island, never strike
                    very far inland either from the north or the south coast, a considerable part of
                    the country is but vaguely known to Europeans. It may be safely asserted,
                    however, that the general configuration is fairly simple,—the island being a
                    plateau-like prolongation of the limestone range of northern Java, with frequent
                    interchange of hill and dale, culminating towards the east in G unong Pedjudan
                    or Tambuko at a height of 1542 feet. Hot springs are not unfrequent; and in the
                    valley between Gunong Geger and Bandjar lies the mud volcano of Banju Ening.
                    “Round the coast runs a girdle of tropical vegetation, broken only here and
                    there by small white peaks with steep perpendicular cliffs ;” but, except in a
                    few alluvial tracts in the lower courses of the streams, the soil is thin and
                    poor, and better fitted for pastoral than agricultural purposes. Maize is by far
                    the most important of the crops; it is planted after rice in the non-irrigable
                    sawahs, and often before it in the irrigable; in the tagal fields it is
                    sometimes sown thrice in a single year, frequently along with <hi rend="italic"
                        >hαtjang</hi> (various kinds of native beans). European enterprise has not
                    yet invaded the island; there is only one sugar plantation, Tedjeh, near
                    Pamakasan, established in 1835. Much attention is paid to the rearing of
                    cattle,—the small Madura oxen being greatly prized in Java, and consequently
                    forming a regular article of export. Petroleum is found in small quantities in
                    all the departments, but the most valuable product of the island is its salt
                    (hence perhaps the name Madura; Sansk. <hi rend="italic">Mandura,</hi> salt).
                    The manufacture, a Dutch Government monopoly, was formerly carried on in several
                    places, as at Brantah and Bunder (where the salt pans now serve as fish ponds),
                    but in 1870 Sumenep was made the sole establishment for Java and Madura, and it
                    still remains by far the most important, though its annual production of 875,000
                    cwts. has since 1875 to be supplemented by Ragung and Pangaringan. The
                    population of Madura was in 1879 returned as 768,992,—472 Europeans (mostly at
                    Maringan near Sumenep), 3702 Chinese, 1445 Arabs and other Orientals, and
                    763,373 natives. These last constitute one of the three great races of Java and
                    Madura, and speak a distinct language, for which compare <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Java,</hi> vol. xiii.</p>
                <p>The following are the places of chief note in the island. Kamal at the south-west
                    corner is the point where people usually cross from Java. Bangkalang is the
                    large and flourishing chief town of Madura proper, with the old palace of the
                    sultan ana the residences of the princes of the blood; the mosque is adorned
                    with the first three suras of the Koran, thus differing from nearly all the
                    mosques in Java and Madura, though resembling those of western Islam. In the
                    vicinity once stood the Erfprins fort. Arisbaya (less correctly Arosbaya) is the
                    place where the first mosque was built in Madura, and where the Dutch sailors
                    first made acquaintance with the natives. The once excellent harbour is now
                    silted up. Ajermata, so called from its salt-springs, is the burial-place of the
                    princes of Bangkalang. Pamakasan, though a town of considerable extent, presents
                    nothing worthy of notice apart from the regent’s residence. Sampang, the seat of
                    an important market, seems hardly so flourishing as in Valentyn’s days. The town
                    or <hi rend="italic">kotα</hi> of Sumenep had 15,000 inhabitants in 1846; and
                    there are populous Malay, Arab, and Chinese villages between the town and the
                    European settlement of Maringan. On a hill in the neighbourhood, with a fine
                    outlook over the Bay of Sumenep, lies Asta, the burial-place of the Sumenep
                    princes; and Nâtâ Kusuma’s mausoleum excels everything of the kind in Java.</p>
                <p>Madura formerly consisted of three native states—Madura or Bangkalang, Pamakasan,
                    and Sumenep. Dutch authority was represented by an assistant resident, and the
                    whole island considered part of the Java residency of Surabaya. The separate
                    residency of Madura was constituted in 1857. On the death of the second sultan
                    of .Bangkalang (1847) the title had been reduced to that of panembahan; <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n211/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0211-0194"/> and in 1872 the new ruler was deprived of the
                    right of collecting taxes, and made a Government pensioner, while his territory
                    was split into the two Dutch “departments” of Madura and Sampang. The sultan of
                    Sumenep was in like manner succeeded by a panembahan in 1853; and the death of
                    the panembahan in 1879 afforded an opportunity of enlarging the Government
                    control. There are thus four “departments” in Madura,—Pamakasan, Madura,
                    Sumenep, and Sampang. The first three are also regencies, and the fourth a
                    subregency of Bangkalang; but Pamakasan alone has the full regency organization.
                    The number of village communities is 1271.</p>
                <p>The best systematic account of Madura will be found in Professor Veth’s Java,
                    vol. iii., the proof sheets of which have, by the author’s courtesy, been
                    consulted for this article. See also Bleeker, in Indisch. Archief., i., and
                    Tijds. van Ned. Ind., ix.; C. de Groot in Nat. Tijds. van Ned. Ind., iv.;
                    Hoeveil, Reis over Java, ii.; Zollinger, “Jets over de Nat. geschied. van
                    Madura,” in N. Tijds. van Ned. Ind., xvii.; Jukes, Voyage of the <hi
                        rend="superscript"> u</hi> Fly"∙, and Hageman in Tijds. van Ned. Ind.,
                    1858.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
