<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0915-0669-0638-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAURICE, John Frederic Denison (9th edition, volume 15,
                    page 638)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1074680">Prayer</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1074737">Prayers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:951448">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp12">Prayer</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s76">Prayers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wr06">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n669/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAURICE, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Frederic
                        Denison</hi></label> (1805-1872), better known without his first name, an
                    English clergyman and theologian, was born in the year 1805. He was the son of a
                    Unitarian minister, and educated in his father’s faith, entering Trinity
                    College, Cambridge, as a Nonconformist, for the sake of the university course,
                    at a time when it was impossible for any but members of the Established Church
                    to obtain a degree. Together with John Sterling, Maurice migrated to the smaller
                    college of Trinity Hall, whence he obtained a first class in civil law in 1827;
                    he then came to London, and gave himself to literary work, editing for a short
                    time the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeu/n</hi> newspaper. During this period of his
                    life he came under the influence of S. T. Coleridge,—an influence which drew
                    Maurice into conformity, and issued through him in what was known as the
                    Broad-Church school of thought.</p>
                <p>When Maurice joined the Church of England, he might no doubt have returned to
                    Cambridge for his degree, or, when he chose Oxford, his terms at Cambridge would
                    have been allowed him, but with characteristic thoroughness he elected to go
                    through the whole Oxford course. He entered Exeter College, and obtained a
                    second class in classics in 1831.</p>
                <p>The intellectual stir of Oxford life, and the vehement controversies in the clash
                    of which sparks of truth seemed struck out, were probably among the causes which
                    attracted Maurice to Oxford, and he afterwards took his full share in them,
                    always in a liberal, tolerant, yet strongly Protestant spirit. He was ordained
                    in 1834, and after a short interval spent in parish work in the country was
                    appointed chaplain of Guy’s Hospital, and became thenceforward a sensible factor
                    in the intellectual and social life of London. Carlyle has told us how “going to
                    Guy’s” Sunday after Sunday was a part of Sterling’s routine, and an appreciable
                    number of persons far above the average were attracted to the hospital chapel.
                    In 1840 Maurice was appointed professor of history and literature in King’s
                    College, to which in 1846 was added the chair of divinity. These chairs he held
                    till 1853. In that year he published <hi rend="italic">Theological Essays,</hi>
                    wherein were stated opinions which savoured, to the principal, Dr Jelf, and to
                    the council, of unsound theology in regard to eternal punishment. Maurice
                    maintained with great warmth of conviction that his views were in close
                    accordance with Scripture and the Anglican standards, but the council ruled
                    otherwise, and he was deprived of his professorships. He held at the same time
                    the chaplaincy of Lincoln’s Inn (1846-60), but no attempt was made to deprive
                    him of this. Neither was he assailed in the incumbency of St Peter’s, Vere
                    Street, which he held for nine years (1860-69), and where, though his
                    congregation was never large, partly perhaps because no parish or district was
                    apportioned to his church, he drew round him a circle of thoughtful persons,
                    attached in no common degree to himself and to his teaching.</p>
                <p>During his residence in London Maurice was specially identified with two
                    important movements for education, the Working Men’s College, and Queen’s
                    College for the education of women, while he threw himself with great energy
                    into all that affected the social life of the people. Certain abortive efforts
                    at a true co-operation among working men, and the movement known as Christian
                    Socialism, were the immediate outcome of his teaching, and directly fostered by
                    himself. In 1866 Maurice was appointed professor of moral philosophy in the
                    university of Cambridge. He died on the 1st of April 1872.</p>
                <p>Maurice was before all things a preacher. The actual message he had to proclaim
                    was apparently simple; his two great convictions, which he strove to impress on
                    all other men, were the fatherhood of God, and that all religious systems which
                    had any stability lasted because of a portion of truth which had to be
                    disentangled from the error differentiating them from the doctrines <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n670/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0915-0670-0639"/> of the Church of England as understood by
                    himself. His love to God as his Father was a passionate adoration which filled
                    his whole heart. No one who ever heard Maurice read the Lord’s Prayer can
                    possibly forget it; the intensity of his convictions in the pulpit made his
                    message seem as luminous and clear as it was brief and concentrated, though his
                    teaching apart from the living voice had by no means the same character.</p>
                <p>It was the peculiarity of his congregation that those who wanted his advice
                    sought him; having no parish, he had no definite sphere of work beyond the
                    church. Thus his preaching took the forms now of exposition and now of the
                    resolution of metaphysical difficulties, rather than of direct dealing with the
                    facts, the sins, and the temptations of human life common to all. Feeling this
                    defect, he took for a time a district for parochial visitation, but was
                    perplexed and distressed at the experience to which he was unequal. With all his
                    affectionateness and desire to give sympathy he was unable even to conceive
                    intellectual difficulties which were not his own. To those who did not demand of
                    him all they needed, but took thankfully what he had to give, he was altogether
                    a stimulating and helpful teacher. He opened new views, and encouraged men to
                    think for themselves, and see what their words meant. He was even morbidly
                    fearful of founding a party, and was deeply distressed at the name Broad-Church.
                    Those who surrounded him, and were kept together by his personal charm and
                    influence, were learning to think for themselves, and have dispersed in many
                    directions. There are probably not half a dozen persons who, even nominally,
                    reflect the precise shades of Maurician teaching.</p>
                <p>As a writer it is extremely doubtful if his work will have a great and permanent
                    place in the future. His one novel, <hi rend="italic">Eustace Conway,</hi> is
                    even now unread; his theological works, though abounding in passages of great
                    beauty, full now and then of a fiery eloquence, are as a whole somewhat obscure.
                    He published too much, and a large number of his works are sermons recast. We
                    miss the human voice, and we find a class of writing which only the highest
                    excellence can make tolerable out of the pulpit.</p>
                <p>Maurice’s greatest effect on his time is in his educational work. The Working
                    Men’s College, which owes more to him than to any one else, for which he
                    rendered great sacrifices, and which was and is more full of his spirit than are
                    most institutions of that of their founders, was a totally new departure in
                    education. It was intended to give, and it has largely succeeded in giving, not
                    what is called a popular education, but “higher education” to working men, and
                    in combining teachers and taught in a college with its social life, and a bond
                    of common interests. Queen’s College, in like manner for the higher education of
                    girls, is scarcely less identified with his life, though its influence is not so
                    great, nor can its work be so widely known.</p>
                <p>Both at King’s College and at Cambridge Maurice gathered round him a band of
                    earnest students, to whom he directly taught much that was valuable drawn from
                    wide stores of his own reading, wide rather than deep, for he never was,
                    strictly speaking, a learned man. Still more did he encourage the habit of
                    inquiry and research, more valuable than his direct teaching. In his power,
                    which has been truly called Socratic, of convincing his pupils of their
                    ignorance he did more than perhaps any other man of our time to awaken in those
                    who came under his sway the desire for knowledge and the process of independent
                    thought.</p>
                <p>If, as a social reformer, Maurice’s name be forgotten in the future, it will be
                    because in much he was before his time, and gave his eager support to schemes
                    for which the world was not ready. From a very early period of his life in
                    London the condition of the poor pressed upon him with consuming force; the
                    enormous magnitude of the social questions involved was a burthen which he could
                    hardly bear. He threw himself with characteristic energy into schemes for a true
                    co-operative system, in which some ardent young men were then engaged, and in
                    spite of his dislike for systems and party names did not shrink from being known
                    as a Christian Socialist, and taking a keen interest in the paper which bore
                    that name, and was the organ of the movement. That and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Politics for the People,</hi> much the same paper under a different name,
                    received his sanction and aid; many strifes between masters and workmen were
                    appeased, if not directly by himself, by those who were aided by his counsel,
                    and were in constant intercourse with him. For many years he was the clergyman
                    whom working men of all opinions seemed to trust even if their faith in other
                    religious men and all religious systems had faded, and his power of attracting
                    the zealot and the outcast resembled that of the Master whom he followed.</p>
                <p>Maurice was twice married, first to a sister of John Sterling, secondly to a
                    sister of his friend Archdeacon Hare. By his family ties and his closest
                    friendships he came in contact with few but intellectual people. Thus while he
                    wrote and spoke and worked for the average man he set that average somewhat
                    high. Those who were privileged to know him did not know a more beautiful
                    soul.</p>
                <p>The following are Maurice’s more important works. Some of them were rewritten and
                    in a measure recast, and the date given is not necessarily that of the first
                    appearance of the book, but of its more complete and abiding form. Eustace
                    Conway, or the Brother and Sister, a novel, 1834; The Kingdom of Christ, 1842;
                    Christmas Day and other Sermons, 1843; The Unity of the New Testament, 1844; The
                    Epistle to the Hebrews, 1846; The Religions of the World, 1847; Moral and
                    Metaphysical Philosophy (at first an article in the Encyclopaedia
                    Metropolitana), 1848; The Church a Family, 1850; The Old Testament, 1851;
                    Theological Essays, 1853; The Prophets and Kings of the Old Testament, 1853;
                    Lectures on Ecclesiastical History, 1854; The Doctrine of Sacrifice, 1854; The
                    Patriarchs and Lawgivers of the Old Testament, 1855; The Epistles of St John,
                    1857; The Commandments as Instruments of National Reformation, 1866; On the
                    Gospel of St Luke, 1868; The Conscience: Lectures on Casuistry, 1868; The Lord's
                    Prayer, a Manual, 1870. The greater part of these works were, as has been
                    already noticed, first delivered as sermons or lectures. Besides this more
                    formal work, Maurice contributed many prefaces and introductions to the works of
                    friends, as to Archdeacon Hare’s Charges, Kingsley’s Saint’s Tragedy, &amp;c.
                    His occasional sermons, speeches, periodical writings, and letters to various
                    newspapers need not be here noticed, though they were at the time evidence of
                    his interest in all the life of his time, and his eager and abounding
                    energy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
