<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-7233-0626-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HORSLEY, Samuel</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 626</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:813028">Archdeacons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193647233" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HORSLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi></label>, a very
                    learned prelate of the church of England, the son of the Rev. John Horsley, for
                    many years clerk in orders at St Martin’s in the Fields, and afterwards rector
                    of Thorley in Hertfordshire, was born at his father’s residence in St Martin’s
                    churchyard, in October 1733. He received his early education from his father,
                    and was entered at Trinity-hall, Cambridge, where he applied himself much to the
                    study of mathematics, but, at the same time, perused with care the writings of
                    the ancient and modern divines and logicians. Why he took no degree in arts
                    cannot now be ascertained; we find, however, that, in 1758, he took that of
                    bachelor of laws, and became his father’s curate at Newington, which living he
                    succeeded to the following year, and held until his elevation to the Episcopal
                    bench in 1793, as Bishop of Rochester.</p>
                <p>In April 1767, he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society, of which he
                    continued for many years an active member, and, about the same time, he
                    published a pamphlet on the Power of God, “deduced from the computable
                    instantaneous productions of it in the solar system.” This he allows to be a
                    “very singular and whimsical speculation and observes respecting it, that, in
                    all probability, it would “roll down the gutter of time, forgotten and
                    neglected.” In 1768, he went to Christ-Church, Oxford, as private tutor to
                    Hencage Earl of Aylesbury, then Lord Guernsey. In 1770, his first mathematical
                    publication, <hi rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergoei</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Inclinationum libri</hi><hi rend="italic">duo,</hi> was elegantly
                    printed at the Clarendon press. This work, though severely criticised at the
                    time, and, in reality, not distinguished by any peculiar felicity of
                    restoration, does not appear to have injured his rising reputation; for, in
                    November 1773, he was appointed secretary to the Royal Society, and in 1774 he
                    had the degree of doctor of civil law conferred on him at Oxford, and was
                    presented by the Earl of Aylesbury to the rectory of Aidbury in Surrey, along
                    with which he obtained a dispensation to hold that of Newington. The same year
                    he published Remarks on the Observations made in the Voyage towards the North
                    Pole, for determining the acceleration of the Pendulum in latitude 79° 51 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi>. These were addressed to the Hon. Constantine J.
                    Phipps, 4to, and intended to correct some errors committed by Israel Lyons, the
                    mathematician employed on the voyage.</p>
                <p>Dr Horsley having long meditated a complete edition of the works of Sir Isaac
                    Newton, issued, in 1776, proposals for printing it by subscription, in five
                    volumes 4to; but the commencement of the undertaking was delayed by severe
                    domestic affliction, nor was it completed until 1785. In the meanwhile, his
                    diligence and proficiency in science attracted the notice of Dr Lowth, who, on
                    his promotion to the see of London in 1777, appointed Dr Horsley his domestic
                    chaplain, collated him to a prebend in St Paul’s cathedral, and procured for him
                    the situation, which had been held by his father, of clerk in orders at St
                    Martin’s in the Fields. In 1778, during the controversy between Dr Priestley, Dr
                    Price, and others, on the subject of materialism and philosophical necessity, Dr
                    Horsley published a sermon on Providence and Free Agency, in which he attempted
                    to draw a distinction between the philosophical necessity of the moderns and the
                    predestination of their ancestors. This discourse was evidently directed against
                    the writings of Dr Priestley, but the latter did not take any immediate notice
                    of the attack. In 1779, Dr Horsley resigned Aidbury, and, in 1780, was presented
                    to the living of Thorley, which he held, by dispensation, along with that of
                    Newington. In 1783, he became deeply involved in a dispute with some members of
                    the Royal Society, which ended in his withdrawing himself from that learned
                    body.</p>
                <p>Dr Horsley was now about to engage in that celebrated controversy with Dr
                    Priestley; which was conducted on both sides in the fiercest spirit of polemical
                    contention, but on that of Horsley with superior learning and ability. In 1782,
                    Dr Priestley published a work in two volumes 8vo, entitled a History of the
                    Corruptions of Christianity; at the head of which he placed both the Catholic
                    doctrine of Christ’s divinity, and the Arian doctrine of his pre-existence, in a
                    nature far superior to the human, at the same time representing the Socinian
                    doctrine of his mere humanity as the unanimous faith of the first Christians. Dr
                    Horsley conceiving that the best antidote to the poison contained in this work
                    would be to destroy the credit of the writer, and the authority of his name,
                    made its imperfections, moral as well as literary, the subject of review in a
                    charge delivered to the clergy of the archdeaconry of St Alban’s, at a
                    deputation held on the 22d of May 1783. The specimens produced as evidence of
                    the imperfections of the work and the incom <pb break="no" facs="nls:193647246"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-7246-0627"/>petency of the author, may be reduced to six
                    classes. First, ' instances of reasoning in a circle; second, instances of
                    quotations misapplied through ignorance of the subject; third, instances of
                    testimonies perverted through artful and forced constructions; fourth, instances
                    of passages in the Greek fathers misinterpreted through ignorance of the Greek
                    language; fifth, instances of passages misinterpreted through ignorance of the
                    Platonic philosophy; and, sixth, instances of ignorance of the phraseology of
                    the earliest ecclesiastical writers. Dr Horsley concludes his charge by
                    observing, « I feel no satisfaction in detecting the weakness of this learned
                    writer’s argument, but what arises from the consciousness that it is the
                    discharge of some part of the duty which I owe to the Church of God.” This
                    vigorous and systematic attack staggered the admirers of Dr Priestley; but he
                    himself felt none of the apprehension with -which they were seized. He promised
                    an early and satisfactory answer; predicted that he would rise from his supposed
                    defeat more illustrious than ever; undertook to strengthen the evidence in
                    support of his favourite opinions; flattered himself that he would find a new
                    convert in his antagonist; and even hinted something concerning the shame and
                    remorse with which he felt confident that the latter must be penetrated. Dr
                    Priestley could not but be sensible that his adversary was a man of no ordinary
                    stamp; yet, with a blind self-confidence, he did not profit by this conviction
                    so as to make a careful revision of his writings, but, on the contrary,
                    immediately repeated his former assertions respecting the doctrine of the
                    Trinity, in a publication entitled, Letters to Dr Horsley, in answer to his
                    Animadversions on the <hi rend="italic">History of the Corruptions of
                    Christianity,</hi> with additional evidence that the primitive Christian Church
                    was Unitarian, 1783, in 8vo. To this production, in which there are more errors
                    of haste and infirmities of argument than could have been expected from one who
                    had so much at stake, Dr Horsley replied in the same epistolary form, by Letters
                    from the Archdeacon of St Alban’s in reply to Dr Priestley. The object of these
                    letters, which are seventeen in number, and display great learning and research,
                    is to prove that if the mistakes of Dr Priestley, formerly pointed out, are few
                    in number, they are too considerable in kind to be incident to a well-informed
                    writer; that they betrayawant of general comprehension of the subject, and an
                    incapacity to draw right conclusions from the passages cited; that they prove
                    him unskilled in the language of the writers from whom his proofs were
                    professedly derived, and unacquainted with that philosophy, the doctrines of
                    which he pretended to compare with the opinions entertained by the church. Dr
                    Priestley, in his Letters, had attempted to draw his adversary into a
                    controversy respecting the divinity of Jesus Christ; but the latter, knowing
                    that question to have been long since exhausted, defended his own argument, and
                    confined himself to the collection of proofs, from Dr Priestley’s publications,
                    of his inability to throw any light upon the subject.</p>
                <p>Dr Priestley, finding that his letters had failed to produce the expected
                    impression, and that his antagonist, untouched with either shame or remorse,
                    remained unshaken in his opinion, now lost all temper; and in a second set of
                    Letters to the Archdeacon of St Alban’s, which appeared in the autumn of 1784,
                    threw aside all profession of personal regard, or even of ordinary civility. The
                    charge of incompetency and ignorance was warmly retorted, and “the incorrigible
                    dignitary” was charged with manifest misrepresentation of his adversary’s
                    argument; with injustice to the character of Origen, whose veracity he had
                    called in question; and with the grossest perversion of ancient history. In a
                    word, he was stigmatised as a “falsifier of history, and a defamer of the
                    character of the dead.” Regardless of this reproach, Dr Horsley remained silent
                    for eighteen months. A sermon on the Incarnation, preached upon the feast of the
                    Nativity in 1785, formed the prelude to the renewal of the contest on his part,
                    and was, early in the ensuing spring, followed by Remarks on Dr Priestley’s
                    Second Letters to the Archdeacon of St Alban’s, with proofs of certain facts
                    asserted by the Archdeacon. This tract consists of two parts; one containing new
                    specimens of Dr Priestley’s temerity in assertion; and the other defending the
                    attack upon Origen, and proving the existence of a body of Christians atAElia
                    after the time of Hadrian, which was the fact upon which the Archdeacon’s
                    historical fidelity had been so loudly arraigned by Dr Priestley. With this
                    publication Dr Horsley had intended that the controversy on his part should
                    close; but having been induced to collect and republish what he had written (in
                    one vol. 8vo, 1789), this led to a second perusal of Dr Priestley’s Letters,
                    which produced not only many important notes, but some disquisitions of
                    considerable length; and as the Remarks on Dr Priestley’s second Letters had
                    elicited a third set, in which he endeavoured to support the veracity of Origen,
                    and to maintain his position respecting the orthodox Hebrews of the church at
                    Aelia, these are replied to partly in the notes, and partly also in two of the
                    disquisitions Towards the conclusion of his Remarks, Dr Horsley observes: “These
                    and many other glaring instances of unfinished criticism, weak argument, and
                    unjustifiable art, to cover the weakness and supply the want of argument, which
                    must strike every one who takes the trouble to look through those second
                    letters, put me quite at ease with respect to the judgment which the public
                    would be apt to form between my antagonist and me, and confirmed me in the
                    resolution of making no reply to him, and of troubling the public no more upon
                    the subject, except so far as might be necessary to establish some facts, which
                    he hath somewhat too peremptorily denied; and to vindicate my character from
                    aspersions which he hath too inconsiderately thrown out.”</p>
                <p>The reputation which Dr Horsley had now acquired, recommended him to the
                    patronage of Lord Chancellor Thurlow, who presented him to a prebendal stall in
                    the cathedral of Gloucester; and, by the interest of the same eminent person, he
                    was, in 1788, promoted to the see of St David’s. As a bishop, his conduct was
                    exemplary and praisew orthy; in this character he fully answered the high
                    expectations of eminent usefulness, which his elevation to the mitre had so
                    generally raised. In his diocese, he carried through a general system of reform,
                    regulated the condition of the clergy, introduced greater strictness with
                    respect to candidates for admission into holy orders, preached frequently in the
                    parish churches, and acted with Christian liberality towards the poor. Bishop
                    Horsley’s first charge to the clergy of St David’s was delivered in 1790, and
                    deservedly admired, as was also his animated speech in the House of Lords, 31st
                    May 1791, on the subject of the Catholic Bill. These effective displays are
                    understood to have occasioned his subsequent promotion to the bishopric of
                    Rochester and the deanery of Westminster, upon which he resigned the living of
                    Newington.</p>
                <p>During the agitating period between 1793 and the close of the century, Bishop
                    Horsley ranged himself on the side of the government, and with great zeal and
                    warmth opposed the enemies of the constitution, and the professors of democratic
                    principles, under which categories were then included all those who sought for
                    reform in the representation of the people as a guarantee for the removal of
                    abuses, and the progressive improvement of our institutions·, ecclesiastical as
                    well as civil. As a senator, his talents and activity necessarily gave him
                    weight; and there were few discussions of importance in Which he did not take
                    part. He was not, however, an every-day speaker, nor desirous of protracting the
                    debate, unless he had something original or important to communicate. In 1802,
                    he was translated <pb break="no" facs="nls:193647259"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-7259-0628"/>to the bishopric of St Asaph, and resigned the
                    deanery of 'Westminster. Until 1806, his vigour of body and mind remained
                    unimpaired. In the month of July of that year he went to his diocese, and after
                    a residence of two months intended to visit his patron Lord Thurlow at Brighton,
                    where he arrived on the 20th of September, after learning on the road that his
                    noble friend was no more. On the 30th, he became affected with a complaint in
                    the bowels, which, slight at first, soon terminated in mortification, and on the
                    4th of October proved fatal. Bishop Horsley died in the seventy-third year of
                    his age.</p>
                <p>Dr Horsley was throughout life an indefatigable student; he indulged no indolence
                    in youth, and amidst an accumulation of preferments, contemplated no time when
                    he might rest from his labours. His mind was constantly intent on some pursuit,
                    and, setting a high value upon the fame he had acquired, his ambition was to
                    justify the favourable opinion of the public, and the liberality of his patrons.
                    In classical acquirements, and in the critical knowledge of the languages in
                    which the sacred books were originally written, he stood in the very first rank
                    of excellence. In the mathematical and physical sciences, if he stood not in the
                    first rank, he occupied at least a very respectable station. In metaphysical
                    acuteness and research, he had probably few superiors; whilst, in his proper
                    science of theology, we will venture to affirm that he had none. The ablest
                    champion of orthodoxy that the church had for many years seen, he was so much of
                    an original thinker, and so independent of his predecessors or contemporaries,
                    that his mode of defence was entirely his own, and his style and manner, like
                    Warburton’s and Johnson’s, though dangerous to imitate, were nevertheless the
                    best, perhaps, that could have been devised in the conflict of opinions with
                    which he was surrounded. In his writings, as in his character, there was nothing
                    lukewarm, nothing compromising. His character and manner were indeed somewhat
                    harsh, and arrogant, and dogmatical; but, whilst due allowance must be made for
                    the heats and errors which controversy engenders, charity induces us to believe
                    that much of his apparent asperity arose from his zeal for the truth, and his
                    high sense of its importance, and that, in fact, he possessed more genuine
                    liberality than some of his most clamorous opponents. He was classed, indeed,
                    and he classed himself amongst High-churchmen; but he was no doubt perfectly
                    sincere in his attachment to the constitution and doctrines of the Church of
                    England; and on more than one occasion he gave proof that he understood the
                    great principles of practical toleration better than some who made louder
                    pretensions to liberality. It is certain, indeed, that he was not only willing,
                    but anxious, to enter into a Parliamentary inquiry into the claims of the Roman
                    Catholics of Ireland, and to grant them whatever that inquiry might shew could
                    be granted with security to the Protestant Establishment, and the Protestant
                    succession.</p>
                <p>In his fierce controversy with Dr Priestley, Bishop Horsley had a manifest
                    advantage both in learning and argument; and when we reflect that his adversary
                    aimed at nothing less than the overthrow of the English establishment, and
                    avowed his purpose in language not remarkable either for modesty or íòr
                    delicacy, we cannot justly wonder that he used strong language in return. Yet it
                    is dignified language; and will not now, perhaps, appear to any candid reader,
                    to be much stronger than the ease required. The concluding paragraph of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Remarks upon Dr Priestley’s Second Letters,</hi> affords a
                    striking specimen of his manner as well as of his temper; of a manner, no doubt,
                    sufficiently authoritative and decided, but of a temper which appears to us
                    entitled to the name of Christian. “For eighteen months or more,” says he, “it
                    hath been the boast of the Unitarian party, that the Archdeacon of St Alban’s
                    hath been challenged to establish facts which he had averred; that he hath been
                    insulted in his character, as a scholar and a man; charged with ignorance,
                    misrepresentation, defamation, and calumny; and that, under all this, he hath
                    continued speechless. He hath at last spoken, in a tone which, perhaps, will
                    little endear him to the Unitarian zealots. It matters not. The time seems yet
                    so distant when the train which they are laying may be expected to explode, that
                    the danger is exceedingly small that he will ever be reduced to the alternative
                    of renouncing his faith, or relinquishing his preferments; or to the harder
                    alternative which Dr Priestley seems to threaten, of a prison with a good
                    conscience, or his present emoluments without one. If those happy times of which
                    Dr Priestley prophecies, should overtake him ere his course is finished; when an
                    Arian or Soeinian Parliament shall undertake the blessed business of a second
                    reformation, and depose archbishops from their thrones, and arehdeaeons from
                    their couches of preferment; he humbly hopes that he may be supplied with
                    fortitude to act the part which may not disgrace his present professions. The
                    probability, however, seems to be, that ere those times arrive (if they arrive
                    at all, which we trust they will not), my antagonist and I shall both be gone to
                    those unseen abodes, where the din of controversy, and the din of war, are
                    equally unheard. There we shall rest together, till the last trumpet summon us
                    to stand before our God and King. That whatever of intemperate wrath, and carnal
                    anger hath mixed itself, on either side, with the zeal with which we have
                    pursued our fierce contention, may then be forgiven to us both, is a prayer
                    which I breathe from the bottom of my soul, and to which my antagonist, if he
                    hath any part in the spirit of a Christian, upon his bended knees will say <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Amen.”</hi></p>
                <p>As a preacher, or rather as a writer of sermons, Bishop Horsley must be allowed
                    to stand in the first class, yet we do not know with whom in that class we can
                    well compare him. In force, depth, and erudition, in precision and distinctness
                    of ideas, in aptitude and vigour of expression, and, above all, in the original
                    powers of thinking displayed in them, Dr Horsley’s discourses are unquestionably
                    <hi rend="italic">sui generis.</hi> But difficult as the subjects often are,
                    which he discusses in them, even ordinary readers, moderately conversant with
                    the Bible, and with the theory and practice of their religion, may derive more
                    advantage from them than from any volumes of sermons which have issued from the
                    press for more than half a century. Even difficulties, and very serious
                    difficulties, Dr Horsley frequently renders plain and practical, by clear,
                    patient, and ingenious criticism; and having fixed his principle on a scriptural
                    ground, and made that ground comparatively clear and easy, he enforces the
                    practical consequences on that direct authority of God which, within the walls
                    of a Christian church, ought to supersede every other. Dr Clarke, in his
                    sermons, which stand in the very first rank of excellence, often treats and
                    largely discusses, Christian subjects, the mysteries of redemption, and the
                    various positive ordinances of the gospel. But he does so with this remarkable
                    difference from Bishop Horsley, that he is never satisfied with any scriptural
                    principle or precept, till he has laboured to render it conformable to what he
                    calls <hi rend="italic">eternal reason</hi> and <hi rend="italic">the fitness of
                    things.</hi> Thus, even on subjects of which we should never have known any
                    thing but from Scripture, and which derive all their importance and authority
                    from revelation, we are frequently perplexed with thorny and intricate
                    discussions, intended to accommodate them to this eternal reason and immutable
                    relation of things. The evil of such discussions is, that they are apt to leave
                    an impression on the mind that the obligations of duty rest on something
                    different from, and independent of, the will of God; whereas, to a Christian,
                    the source of the obligation, whether as respects moral or religious duties, is
                    beyond all controversy, the revealed will of God <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193647272" xml:id="kp-eb0711-7272-0629"/>alone. Hence it was that
                    Bishop Horsley, when he had distinctly traced a principle, doctrine, or precept
                    to Scripture, justly conceived that he had done all which a Christian could
                    require to enforce obedience. It may be interesting, it may even be important,
                    to trace the admirable conformity which subsists between the revealed will of
                    God, and the same will as it may be deduced from the nature of things, and the
                    condition of man; but it never can be absolutely necessary to establish this
                    conformity; for whether we are able to trace it or not, the Christian obligation
                    is the same. The supposition that revelation may, in every instance, be
                    accommodated to reason, or, in other words, that a conformity can always be
                    traced between the dictates of reason and the doctrines of Scripture, is a
                    supposition not only fraught with danger, but incompatible with the very import
                    of the term revelation, which necessarily implies the disclosure to man of that
                    which reason could never have informed him of.</p>
                <p>Besides the works already mentioned, Bishop Horsley was the author of the
                    following, viz. 1. On the Properties of the Greek and Latin Languages, 1796, in
                    8vo; 2. On the Achronical Rising of the Pleiades, appended to Dr Vincent’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage of</hi><hi rend="italic">Nearchus,</hi> 1797; 3. A Circular
                    Letter to the Diocese of Rochester, on the Scarcity of Corn, 1796; 4. Another
                    Circular Letter to that Diocese on the Defence of the Kingdom, 1798; 5. Critical
                    Disquisitions on the 18th chapter of Isaiah, 1799, in 4to; 6. Hosea translated
                    from the Hebrew, with Notes explanatory and critical, 1801, in 4to; 7∙
                    Elementary Treatises on the fundamental principles of Practical Mathematics, for
                    the use of Students, 1801, in 8vo. Since his death have appeared, 1. Sermons,
                    1810 and 1812, in three vols. 8vo; 2. Tracts in controversy with Dr Priestley,
                    upon the historical question of the belief of the first ages in the Divinity of
                    Jesus Christ, revised and augmented by the author, with an appendix by his Son,
                    1812, in 8vo; 3. The Speeches in Parliament of Samuel Horsley, 1813; and, 4. The
                    Charges delivered at his several visitations of the dioceses of St David’s,
                    Rochester, and St Asaph, 1813, in 8vo.—(Chalmers’s <hi rend="italic">Biog.
                    Diet.</hi> art. <hi rend="smallcaps">Horsley</hi> i <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Review,</hi> vol. xvii. p. 465, 468.) ' <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
