<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-1344-0173-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAWKING</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 173</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gv95">Fowling</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4b853n1k">Fowls</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vc4w">Feathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:933446">Fowling</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:922098">Feathers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:887617">Danes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193641344" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAWKING</label>, the exercise of taking wild-fowl by means of
                    hawks. The method of reclaiming, manning, and bringing up a hawk to this
                    exercise, is calle <hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic">falconry.</hi></p>
                <p>There are only two countries in the world where we have any evidence that the
                    exercise of hawking was practised in ancient times. These are Thrace and
                    Britain. In the former it was pursued merely as the diversion of a particular
                    district, if we may believe Pliny, whose account is rendered obscure by the
                    indistinctness of his own ideas of the matter. The originaI Britons, with a
                    fondness for the exercise of hunting, had also a taste for that of hawking; and
                    every chief amongst them maintained a considerable number of birds for that
                    sport. To the Romans this diversion was scarcely known in the days of Vespasian,
                    yet it was introduced immediately afterwards. Most probably they adopted it from
                    the Britons; but we know certainly that they greatly improved it. In this state
                    it appears amongst the Roman Britons in the sixth century. Gildas, in a
                    remarkable passage in his first epistle, speaks of Maglocunus, on his
                    relinquishing the sphere of ambition, and taking refuge in a monastery; and
                    proverbially compares him to a dove, which hastens away at the noisy approach of
                    the dogs, and with various turns and windings takes her flight from the talons
                    of the hawk.</p>
                <p>In after times, hawking was the principal amusement of the English. A person of
                    rank scarcely stirred out without his hawk on his hand; and in old paintings
                    this is the criterion of nobility. Harold, afterwards king of England, when he
                    went on a most important embassy into Normandy, is painted embarking with a bird
                    on his hand, and a dog under his arm; and in an ancient picture of the nuptials
                    of Henry VI. a nobleman is represented in much the same manner. In those days,
                    “it was thought sufficient for noblemen to winde their horn, and to carry their
                    hawk fair, and leave study and learning to the children of mean people.” The
                    former were the accomplishments of the times. Spenser makes his gallant Sir
                    Tristram boast,</p>
                <p>Ne is there hawk which mantleth her on pearch, Whether high tow’ring, or
                    accoasting low, But I the measure of her flight doe search, And all her prey,
                    and all her diet know.</p>
                <p>In short, this diversion was, amongst the old English, the pride of the rich, and
                    the privilege of the poor. No rank of men seems to have been excluded from the
                    amusement. We learn from the book of St Alban’s, that every degree had its
                    peculiar hawk, from the emperor down to the holy-water clerk. Vast was the
                    expense which sometimes attended this sport. In the reign of James I. Sir Thomas
                    Monson is said to have given L. 1000 for a cast of hawks. We need not wonder
                    then at the rigour of the laws tending to preserve a pleasure which was carried
                    to such an extravagant pitch. In the 34th of Edward III. it was made felony to
                    steal a hawk; and to take its eggs, even in a person’s own ground, was
                    punishable with imprisonment for a year and a day, besides a fine at the king’s
                    pleasure. In Queen Elizabeth’s reign, the imprisonment was reduced to three
                    months, but the offender was to find security for his good behaviour for seven
                    years, or he in prison till he did so. Such then was the enviable state of the
                    times of old England. During the whole day the gentry were given to the fowls of
                    the air and the beasts of the field; in the evening, they celebrated their
                    exploits with the most abandoned and brutish sottishness; and the inferior ranks
                    of people, by the most unjust and arbitrary laws, were made liable to capital
                    punishments, to fines, and loss of liberty, for destroying the most destructive
                    of the feathered tribe. The love of game-laws runs in the blood of our
                    territorial aristocracy; it has descended to them from very ancient times, and
                    forms part of their inheritance.</p>
                <p>According to Olearius, the diversion of hawking is more followed by the Tartars
                    and Persians than ever it was in any part of Europe. “Il n’y avoit point de
                    hutte,” says he, “qui n’eust son aigle ou son faucon.”</p>
                <p>The falcons or hawks which were in use in these kingdoms are now found to breed
                    in Wales, and in Scotland and its isles. The peregrine falcon inhabits the rocks
                    of Caernarvonshire. The same species, with the gyrfalcon, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193641357" xml:id="kp-eb0711-1357-0174"/>the gentil, and the goshawk,
                    are found in Scotland, and the lanner in Ireland. But we may here notice, that
                    the Norwegian breed were, in old times, in high esteem in England, and were
                    thought bribes worthy a king. Jeof-frey Fitzpierre gave two good Norway hawks to
                    King John, to obtain for his friend the liberty of exporting a hundredweight of
                    cheese; and Nicholas the Dane stipulated to give the king a hawk every time he
                    came into England, that he might have liberty to traffic throughout the king’s
                    dominions. Hawks were also made the tenures by which some of the nobility held
                    their estates from the crown. Thus Sir John Stanley had a grant of the Isle of
                    Man from Henry IV. to be held of the king, his heirs, and successors, by homage
                    and the service of two falcons, payable on the day of his or their coronation.
                    And Philip de Hastang held his manor of Combertoun, in Cambridgeshire, by the
                    service of keeping the king’s falcons.</p>
                <p>Hawking, though an exercise now much disused, does yet furnish a great variety of
                    significant terms, which still obtain in our language. Thus, the parts of a hawk
                    have their proper names. The legs, from the thigh to the foot, are called <hi
                    rend="italic">arms</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the toes, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >petty singles</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and the claws, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >pounces.</hi> The wings are called the <hi rend="italic">sails</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> the long feathers of the wings, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >beams;</hi> the two longest, the <hi rend="italic">principal feathers</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and those next thereto, the <hi rend="italic">flags.</hi>
                    The tail is called the <hi rend="italic">train;</hi> the breast feathers, the
                    <hi rend="italic">mails;</hi> and those behind the thigh, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >pendant feathers.</hi> When the feathers are not yet full grown, the falcon is
                    said to be <hi rend="italic">unsummed</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when they are
                    complete, it is <hi rend="italic">summed.</hi> The craw, or crop, is called the
                    <hi rend="italic">gorge</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the pipe next the
                    fundament, where the faeces are drawn down, is called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >pannel</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the slimy substance lying in the pannel is
                    called the <hi rend="italic">glut;</hi> the upper and crooked part of the bill
                    is called the <hi rend="italic">beak</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the nether
                    part, the <hi rend="italic">clap</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the yellow part
                    between the beak and the eyes, the <hi rend="italic">sear</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">sere</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the two small holes therein, the
                    <hi rend="italic">nares.</hi></p>
                <p>As to the furniture, the leathers, with bells buttoned on the legs, are called
                    <hi rend="italic">bewits</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the leathern thong by
                    which the falconer holds the hawk, is called the <hi rend="italic">lease</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">leash</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the little straps, by which
                    the lease is fastened to the legs, <hi rend="italic">jesses</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and a line or packthread fastened to the lease, in
                    disciplining the bird, a <hi rend="italic">creance.</hi> A cover for the head,
                    to keep the falcon in the dark, is called a <hi rend="italic">hood</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and a large wide hood, open behind, to be worn at first, is
                    called a <hi rend="italic">rufter hood.</hi> To draw the strings, that the hood
                    may be in readiness to be pulled off, is called <hi rend="italic">unstrihing the
                    hood</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the blinding a hawk just taken, by running a
                    thread through her eyelids, and thus drawing them over the eyes, to prepare her
                    for being hooded, is called <hi rend="italic">seeling</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> a figure or resemblance of a fowl, made of leather and feathers, is
                    called a <hi rend="italic">lure</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the resting place,
                    when off the falconer’s fist, is called the <hi rend="italic">perch</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> the place where the meat is laid is called the <hi
                    rend="italic">hack</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and that in which the bird is
                    set, whilst the feathers fall and come again, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >mew.</hi></p>
                <p>Anything given to a hawk, to cleanse and purge the gorge, is called <hi
                    rend="italic">casting</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> small feathers given to make
                    the bird cast, are called <hi rend="italic">plumage;</hi> gravel given to help
                    to bring down the stora¢ch, is called <hi rend="italic">rangle</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> the throwing up of filth from the gorge after casting, is
                    called <hi rend="italic">gleaming</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the purging of
                    grease, or other matter, <hi rend="italic">ensearning</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> being stuffed is called <hi rend="italic">gurgiting</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> inserting a feather in the wing in lieu of a broken one, is
                    called <hi rend="italic">imping</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> giving a leg, wing,
                    or pinion of a fowl to pull at, is called <hi rend="italic">tiring</hi> The neck
                    of a bird the hawk preys on is called the <hi rend="italic">inke</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and what the hawk leaves of its prey is called the <hi
                    rend="italic">pill or pelf.</hi></p>
                <p>There are also proper terms for the several actions of the bird. When a hawk
                    flutters, as if striving to get away, either from the perch or hand, it is said
                    to <hi rend="italic">bate</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when, standing too near,
                    they fight with each other, it is called <hi rend="italic">crabbing</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> when the young ones quiver and shake their wings in
                    obedience to the elder, it is called <hi rend="italic">cowring</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> when the bird wipes its beak after feeding, it is said to
                    <hi rend="italic">feak</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when it sleeps, it is said
                    to <hi rend="italic">jouk</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> from the time of
                    exchanging the coat, till the bird turn white again, is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >intermewing</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> treading is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >cawhing</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when the hawk stretches one wing after the
                    legs, and then the other, it is called <hi rend="italic">mantling</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> the dung is called <hi rend="italic">muting</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> when the hawk mutes a good way behind, it is said to <hi
                    rend="italic">slice;</hi> when it does so directly down, instead of jerking
                    backwards, it is said to <hi rend="italic">slime,</hi> and if it be in drops, it
                    is called <hi rend="italic">dropping</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when the bird
                    as it were sneezes, it is called <hi rend="italic">sniting</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> when it raises and shakes itself, it is said to <hi rend="italic"
                    >rouze</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and when, after mantling, it crosses its
                    wings together over its back, it is said to <hi rend="italic">warble.</hi></p>
                <p>When a hawk seizes, it is said to <hi rend="italic">bind</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> when, after seizing, it pulls off the feathers, it is said to <hi
                    rend="italic">plume;</hi> when it raises a fowl aloft, and at length descends
                    with it to the ground, it is called <hi rend="italic">trussing</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> when, being aloft, it descends to strike the prey, it is
                    called <hi rend="italic">stooping</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when it flies out
                    too far from the game, it is said to <hi rend="italic">rake</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> when, forsaking the proper game, it flies at pyes, crows,
                    and the like, it is called <hi rend="italic">check</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    when, missing the fowl, the bird betakes itself to the next check, it is said to
                    <hi rend="italic">fly on head.</hi> The fowl or game it flies at is called the
                    <hi rend="italic">quarry</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the dead body of a fowl
                    killed by the hawk is called a <hi rend="italic">pelt.</hi> When the bird flies
                    away with the quarry, it is said to <hi rend="italic">carry</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> when, in stooping, it turns two. or three times on the
                    wing, to recover itself ere it seizes, it is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >canceliering</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> when it hits the prey, yet does not
                    truss it, it is called <hi rend="italic">ruff.</hi> The making a hawk tame and
                    gentle, is called <hi rend="italic">reclaiming</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the
                    bringing one to endure company, <hi rend="italic">manning</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> an old stanch hawk, used to fly and set example to a young one, is
                    called a <hi rend="italic">make-hawk.</hi></p>
                <p>The reclaiming, manning, and bringing up a hawk to the sport, cannot easily be
                    brought under any precise set of rules. It consists in a number of little
                    practices and observances, calculated to familiarize the falconer to his bird,
                    and the latter to the falconer.</p>
                <p>When the hawk comes readily to the lure, a large pair of luring bells are to be
                    put on; and the more giddy-headed and apt to rake out the hawk is, the larger
                    must the bells be. Having done this, and the bird being sharp-set, ride out in a
                    fair morning, into some large field unencumbered with trees or wood, with the
                    hawk on your hand; then having loosened the hood, whistle softly, to provoke her
                    to fly; unhood, and let the bird fly with its head into the wind; for by that
                    means it will be the better able to get upon the wing, and will naturally climb
                    upwards, flying a circle. After the hawk has flown three or four turns, then
                    lure her with your voice, casting the lure about your head, having first tied a
                    pullet to it; and if your falcon come in and approach near you, cast out the
                    lure into the wind, and if she stoop to it, reward her.</p>
                <p>You will often find, that when she flies from the hand, she will take stand on
                    the ground. This is a fault which is very common with soar-falcons. To remedy
                    it, fright her up with your wand; and when you have forced her to take a turn or
                    two, take her down to the lure, and feed her. But if this does not succeed, then
                    you must have in readiness a duck sealed, so that she may see no way but
                    backwards, and that will make her mount the higher. Hold this duck in your hand,
                    by one of the wings, near the body; then lure with the voice to make the falcon
                    turn her head; and when she is at a reasonable pitch, cast your duck up just
                    under her; when, if she strike, stoop, or truss the duck, permit her to kill it,
                    and reward her by giving her a reasonable gorge. After you have practised this
                    two or three times, your hawk will leave the stand, and, delighted to be on the
                    wing, will be very obedient.</p>
                <p>It is not convenient, for the first or second time, to show your hawk a large
                    fowl; for it frequently happens that <pb break="no" facs="nls:193641370"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-1370-0175"/><hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> they escape from the
                    hawk, and the bird not recovering them, rakes after them. This gives the
                    falconer trouble, and frequently occasions the loss of the hawk. But if she
                    happens to pursue a fowl, and, being unable to recover it, gives it over, and
                    comes in again directly, then cast out a sealed duck; and if the bird stoop and
                    truss it across the wings, permit her to take her pleasure, rewarding her also
                    with the heart, brains, tongue, and liver. But if you have not a quick duck,
                    take her down with a dry lure, and let her plume a pullet and feed upon it. By
                    this means a hawk will learn to give over a fowl that rakes out, and on hearing
                    the falconer’s lure, will make back again, and know the better how to hold in
                    the head.</p>
                <p>Some hawks have a disdainful coyness, proceeding from their being high fed. Such
                    a hawk must not be rewarded though she should kill; but you may give her leave
                    to plume alittle, and then taking a sheep’s heart cold, or the leg of a pullet,
                    when the hawk is busy in pluming, let either of them be conveyed into the body
                    of the fowl, that it may savour of it; and when the hawk has eaten the heart,
                    brains, and tongue of the fowl, take out what is enclosed, call lier to your
                    hand, and feed her with it. Afterwards give her some of the feathers of the
                    fowl’s neck, to scour her, and make her cast.</p>
                <p>If your hawk be a stately high-flying one, it ought not to take more than one
                    flight in a morning; and if the bird be made for the river, let her not fly more
                    than twice. When she is at the highest, take her down with your lure; and when
                    she has plumed and broken the fowl a little, feed her, by which means you will
                    keep her a high-flyer, and fond of the lure.</p>
                <p>So much for the technicalities of hawking, which, from change of times and
                    manners, has now in a great measure fallen into disuse. The reader, however,
                    will find some admirable descriptions of this national sport in the novels of
                    Scott, who appears to have understood it thoroughly, and who, on this, as on
                    many other subjects, has brought the past, as it were, before us, rendering us
                    familiar with its habits, customs, and amusements, and deeply engaging our
                    sympathy in favour of the feelings, notions, and even prejudices, with which
                    these were associated.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
