<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0850-0135-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">HANOVER</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 135</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:999105">Linen</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:914456">Equality</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1048908">Othoes</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rp1f">Linen</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b853n60">Guelphs</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193640850" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">HANOVER</label>, a kingdom in Germany, formed out of the
                    duchies which formerly belonged to several families of the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640863" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0863-0136"/>junior branch
                    of the house of Brunswick. In the course of the revolutionary war, under the
                    influence of France, the dukedoms of Bavaria, of Saxony, and of Wirtemburg had
                    been raised to the rank of kingdoms; and when the overthrow of Bonaparte was
                    accomplished, the dukedoms which had composed the electorate of Hanover were
                    thought by the allied powers of sufficient consequence to be elevated to the
                    same dignity, as, with the additions then made to them, they were nearly equal
                    in extent and population to the other portions of Germany whose rulers had
                    received that rank. It accordingly assumed that grade in 1814, under George
                    III., and was acknowledged as such by all the powers of Europe.</p><p>The obscurity in which antiquity has involved the early history of nations can
                    only be in a slight degree cleared up by tracing the origin of the families that
                    maintained the continued rule over them. The ruling family of Hanover has been
                    traced, by the combined efforts and researches of Muratori and Leibnitz, to an
                    Italian origin, in the dark ages, that is, to the princely house of Este; and by
                    Gibbon, from that house up to the descendants of Charlemagne. A Marquis of Este,
                    in the eleventh century, married Cuniza or Cunegonda, an heiress of a princely
                    family in Bavaria, whose son received the name of Guelph, derived from his
                    maternal ancestors, and inherited their dominions, including the dukedom of
                    Bavaria. The grandson of this Guelph, named Henry the Black, and his son named
                    Henry the Proud, acquired by marriage new and extensive dominions on the banks
                    of the Elbe and the Weser; and Henry the Lion, the most powerful prince of his
                    age, was the first of the race who assumed the title of Duke of Brunswick. Under
                    this Henry, who distinguished himself as a great warrior, an uncle wrested from
                    him the southern portion of his territory in Bavaria and Suabia, and left him,
                    at the conclusion of most bitter hostility, in the possession of the northern
                    portion of it. He made the city of Brunswick the capital of his dominions, and,
                    being in possession of the rich silver mines of the Hartz, was enabled to extend
                    his power over the tribes of Northern Germany, inhabiting Holstein, Mecklenburg,
                    and nearly the whole coast of the Baltic Sea.</p><p>FIenry the Lion was twice married. By his first wife he left no family; and by
                    his second wife, who was Maud, the daughter of Henry II. of England, though he
                    had several sons, none of them left any issue except William, under whose only
                    son Otho the partition of the house took place, Brunswick and Luneburg being
                    divided into two dukedoms. The latter branch received the Hanoverian portion as
                    a fief from William Sigefred, bishop of Hildesheim. After the death of Otho, and
                    of his two sons Otho and William, who successively followed, the male line
                    became extinct in 1369. Otho, elector of Saxony, who had married a daughter of
                    William, was, by the influence of the emperor of Germany, Charles IV. invested
                    with the government. He died without issue, having by his testament bequeathed
                    the dukedom to his uncle Wenceslaus, elector of Saxony; a bequest which was
                    contested by Torquatus Magnus, duke of Saxony, but at length was terminated in a
                    compromise, by which Bernard, the eldest son of Torquatus, obtained the
                    dominion, and reigned until 1434. After several successions, the power became
                    vested in Ernest of Zell, who first introduced the Lutheran religion into his
                    states, and died in the year 1546. The succession since has been, William, who
                    died in 1592; Ernest, in 1611; Christian, in 1633; August, in 1636; Fredrich, in
                    1648; Ernest Augustus, bishop of Osnaburg, who was made an elector of the German
                    empire in 1692, and died in 1698; George Louis, who, after the death of his
                    uncle George William, inherited the dukedom of Zell in 1705, and succeeded to
                    the crown of Great Britain by the title of George I. in 1714. He died in 1727,
                    since which period the succession has been the same as in that kingdom.</p><p>The accession of the electors of Hanover to the throne of Great Britain, though
                    it has led ultimately to a great extension of territory, has, on the other hand,
                    subjected the electorate to sufferings and to oppression during the wars between
                    Great Britain and France. At the commencement of the Seven Years’ War, a French
                    army invaded it; and the forces under the Duke of Cumberland, being unequal to
                    its defence, were compelled, by the convention of Kloster-Severn, to abandon the
                    country to the invaders. By the peace of 1763 it was again restored to its
                    ancient sovereign. At the renewal of hostilities after the treaty of Amiens,
                    Hanover was once more seized upon by the French, and by them delivered over to
                    the king of Prussia, who ruled it till after his defeat at Jena. It was then
                    incorporated as part of the kingdom of Westphalia, erected in favour of Jerome
                    Bonaparte. This rule was terminated by the battle of Leipsic, by which Hanover,
                    with the rest of Germany, was delivered from French domination, and returned to
                    its ancient sovereigns, with the addition of the provinces of Hildesheim,
                    Osnaburg, East Friesland, Goslar, and some other territories. On the other hand,
                    Hanover gave up the ancient duchy of Lauenburg, which was transferred to
                    Denmark, and some portions or bailiwicks, a part to Prussia, and a part to the
                    Duke of Oldenburg.</p><p>Hanover has thus become a compact dominion, extending over 14,720 English square
                    miles. It lies between 50° 18' and 53° 54' north latitude, and 6° 58' and ll <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 56' east longitude. It is bounded on the north by the
                    duchy of Oldenburg, the bailiwick of Ritzebüttel, belonging to Hamburg, and the
                    mouth of the Elbe. On the north-east the river Elbe divides it from Holstein and
                    Luneburg, belonging to Denmark, and from the duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin; but
                    it possesses the small territory of Neuhof on the right bank of that river. On
                    the east it is bounded by the Prussian province of Saxony, and by the duchy of
                    Brunswick; on the south it touches the dominions of Prussia, of Hesse-Cassel, of
                    both the Lippes, and of Westphalia; and on the west the kingdom of the
                    Netherlands is the boundary.</p><p>The kingdom of Hanover is divided in the following manner :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Provinces.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Extent in English Acres.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Population.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Number of Dwelling-Houses.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Hanover....</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,601,280</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>296,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>40,745</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Hildesheim.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,121,920</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>322,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>44,199</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Luneburg....</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2,871,040</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>285,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>37,037</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Stade</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,725,440</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>244,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>37,747</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Osnabruck..</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,441,280</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>244,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>39,411</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Aurich</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>743,040</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>152,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>24,261</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Clausthal...</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>122,080</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>26,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>2,738</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>9,626,080</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,569,000</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>226,138</p></cell></row></table><p>A new survey and division of provinces has been made within the last four years.
                    The population returns are grounded on a census taken in 1817, since which the
                    deaths have been deducted and the births added each year. This gives an increase
                    of inhabitants of 236,400 in fifteen years. In the year 1832 the births appear
                    to have been 48,273, and the deaths 39,806. The capital of each of the provinces
                    is the city of the same name.</p><p>The chief cities and their population are as follows: Hanover, 26,300;
                    Hildesheim, 13,800; Luneburg, 12,500; Emden, 12,100; Osnabruck, 11,800;
                    Göttingen, 11,000; Zell, 10,300; Clausthal, 8850; Goslar, 7160; Leer, 6340;
                    Hameln, 5750; Norden,-5600; Stade, 5500; Eimbeck, 5100.</p><p>The province of Hildesheim is somewhat mountainous, and that of Clausthal,
                    containing the Hartz, is <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640876" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0876-0137"/>wholly so, as well as some parts near Göttingen.
                    The other provinces form a part of that extensive plain which commences on the
                    shores of the German Ocean, and terminates on the frontiers of Russia. The whole
                    plain is a sandy soil, resting on a bed of granite, and is generally sterile,
                    except on the banks of the various rivers that water it, or near the cities,
                    where cultivation has improved it by artificial means. The most fruitful part of
                    the kingdom is on the banks of the Elbe, and near the German Ocean, where, as in
                    Holland, rich meadows are preserved from being immersed in water, by broad dykes
                    and deep ditches, constructed and kept in repair at a great expense.</p><p>The most remarkable mountains are those of the Hartz Forest, three fifths of
                    which are in this kingdom, and two fifths in the duchy of Brunswick. These
                    mountains arc not a part of any chain, but rise from a plain in a group by
                    themselves, the highest points of which are nearly in the centre. The mass is
                    about eighty miles in length from east to west, and about twenty-eight in
                    breadth from north to south. The highest points, and their height above the
                    level of the sea, are Bruchbcrg, 3020 feet; Wormberg, 2880 feet; Achtermanshöhe,
                    2710 feet; the Little Winter-berg, 2684 feet; Kahlenberg, 2180 feet; and the
                    Rammelsberg, 1915 feet. These mountains are wholly covered with forests. On
                    their lower sides the trees are of the deciduous kinds, but the summits are
                    exclusively covered with pines. These mountains abound with minerals of almost
                    every kind, and the principal employment of the inhabitants consists either in
                    mining, or in manufacturing the iron and copper into domestic utensils. Some of
                    the mining and manufacturing towns, as Clausthal, Andreasbcrg, Ccller-feld, and
                    several others, are from 1700 to 1900 feet above the level of the sea; and their
                    population would suffer most severely from the cold of the severe winters, but
                    for the abundance both of wood and fossil coal with which they arc supplied.</p><p>The whole of the kingdom of Hanover dips towards the north, and the courses of
                    all the rivers are in that direction. These are, <hi rend="italic">first,</hi>
                    the Elbe, which borders a large part of the dominion, and receives into it the
                    Ohre, which rises in the province of Luneburg; the Aland and the Jeetze, which
                    come out of Prussia, and are navigable before they terminate in the Elbe; the
                    Ilmenau, which becomes navigable at Luneburg; the Este, which is navigable to
                    Buxtehude; the Lühe, navigable to Hornburg; the Schwinge, by which vessels reach
                    Stade; the Oste, which passes Harburg, and is navigable to Kirchosters; and the
                    Medem, which runs through the land Hadeln, and admits large vessels as high as
                    Ottendorf. <hi rend="italic">Second,</hi> the Weser, which enters the dominions
                    of Hanover at Münden, being there formed by the junction of the Fulda and the
                    Werra. It is navigable for barges from the spot at which its name commences, and
                    it receives, in its course, the Hamel, the Aller, the Oertze, the Line, the
                    Böhme, the Eyther, the Wümme, the Lesum (formed by the three streams, Rodau,
                    Wiste, and Worpe), the Greste, and the Hunter; all of which are Hanoverian
                    rivers, and continue their united courses till they are lost in the German Ocean
                    near Bremen. <hi rend="italic">Third,</hi> the Ems, a river rising in the
                    Prussian province of Westphalia. After entering Hanover, it receives the waters
                    of the Aa, the Hase, the Else, and the Leda. Before reaching the sea, it falls
                    into the Dollart near Emden, which is the principal seaport in the kingdom. The
                    vessels belonging to this port are about 270, and their tonnage 19,289 lasts.
                    There are equipped at the mouth of this river upwards of fifty busses, which are
                    employed in the herring fishery, and usually take and cure from 12,000 to 14,000
                    tons of that fish annually. <hi rend="italic">Fourth,</hi> the Vecht, a river of
                    short course, rising in the Prussian province of Westphalia, and terminating in
                    the Zuydcr Zee. Its principal importance is derived from a navigable canal,
                    which commences at the city of Münster, arid is the channel õf some trade
                    through the Vecht to Amsterdam.</p><p>Though Hanover is generally a sandy soil, it has some small fresh-water lakes.
                    The Dummersee, in Diepholtz, is about twelve miles in circuit. The
                    Steinhudermecr, in the province of Kalenburg, is about four miles long and two
                    broad; and the Dollart, at the mouth of the Eins, which is rather an estuary
                    than a lake, is twelve miles across. The canals are all of short course. The
                    Bremen Canal is designed to unite the Hamme, the Oste, and the Schwinge; and the
                    Treckschuit Canal is intended to connect Witmund with Aurich. The Pappenburg
                    Canal is only navigable from the Ems to that city.</p><p>Though considerable variations, in conformity to the different natures of the
                    soils, occur in the husbandry of Hanover, yet it may be generally described as
                    at a very low standard. The land mostly belongs either to the king, or to the
                    nobles, as lords of the soil, who have under them a species of tenants called
                    bauers, having the use of small portions of land, under many and various feudal
                    conditions. These bauers pay little or no rent in money, but render the lord a
                    stipulated number of days’ work in seed time and harvest on his demesne lands,
                    or give him a certain proportion of the proceeds of their crops. In most
                    instances the lords have the right of pasture for their cattle over the whole
                    land, and arc the proprietors of most of the sheep and cows. There is an
                    exception to this mode of holding, called the <hi rend="italic">meyer law</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but it extends over so small a portion of the kingdom
                    as not to merit a detailed notice of it. The rotation of crops usually followed
                    in Hanover is first a fallow, on which the land is cultivated to potatoes, peas,
                    or flax; then follows winter corn, either rye or wheat, but chiefly the former;
                    and to these succeeds summer corn, either barley or oats. As the fields arc
                    usually divided into small portions, like many of our common fields in England,
                    and the larger divisions must all be cultivated alike, though belonging to
                    different occupiers; and as the course that has prevailed from time immemorial
                    must be continued; there is little or no room for improvement, and little
                    encouragement for superior knowledge or greater activity. Such is the bad state
                    of cultivation, that the increase of grain is not estimated to exceed four for
                    one of the quantity sown throughout the whole kingdom. The breeding and
                    fattening of cattle is a branch of rural economy, confined to particular
                    portions adapted to that purpose, and is in the same backward state as the
                    agriculture. By the latest enumeration of the live stock, which was previous to
                    some provinces of 600,000 acres in extent being added to it, there were 224,500
                    horses; 675,926 head of horned cattle; 1,540,794 sheep and lambs; 15,728 goats
                    and kids; 176,974 swine; and 1498 asses and mules. Much of the heath land,
                    especially in the province of Luneburg, is used for no other purpose but that of
                    rearing bees for the sake of their honey and wax. The hives are transported in
                    waggons, at the commencement of the spring, to those more southern countries
                    where the flowers bloom early, and are afterwards brought back when the heath
                    flowers are fit for them, and remain till the proper time for taking the
                    contents of the hives. Large numbers of geese are also kept by the bauers on the
                    moist situations: their flesh is salted for winter domestic consumption, and
                    their feathers arc preserved for sale. These two sources, affording wax, honey,
                    and feathers, yield the principal disposable produce of some of the
                    provinces.</p><p>The manufactures of Hanover arc very numerous, but none of them extensive. Except
                    linen, linen yarn, and domestic utensils, few of them afford a surplus beyond
                    the home consumption. The linen is of four kinds: first, that called <hi rend="italic">Hauseleinwand,</hi> or household linen, the making as well as use
                    of which is to be met with in every family; secondly, a coarse kind, that called
                    the <hi rend="italic">Lowentleinen</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> thirdly, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640889" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0889-0138"/> the
                    fine linen, which is only made in some of the cities to a small extent, and
                    almost wholly consumed by the richer families of the kingdom; and, fourthly,
                    sail-cloth and hempen linen, which is principally made in East Friesland and the
                    duchy of Bremen, and is mostly sold for foreign consumption. Besides the linen
                    yarn used in the home fabrics, a great quantity is spun for foreign trade.
                    Spinning is indeed the constant operation of almost all the females in the
                    villages during the long nights of winter. The spinning of coarse wool, and
                    making it into cloth, either by itself or mixed with linen, occupies a
                    considerable portion of the industry of the peasantry, and furnishes them with
                    clothing from the produce of their own lands. Besides these, they spin cotton,
                    and mixing the yarn with that of linen, manufacture dresses for the females and
                    the younger part of their families. The stockings they wear, whether of linen,
                    cotton, or worsted, arc usually made at home. In some parts of the country much
                    oil is made from linseed. Coarse pottery ware is made in many parts.
                    Paper-mills, which supply about 80,000 reams annually, are not sufficient for
                    the home consumption. In the cities, woollen cloths, silk goods, cotton of
                    various kinds, hats, hosiery, soap, and leather, are manufactured. The principal
                    branches that employ much capital are the breweries of Hanover, Eimbeck, and
                    Goslar, and the corn distilleries which are to be found in all the cities. The
                    former of these are suffering <hi rend="italic">a</hi> gradual declension,
                    whilst the latter are as rapidly increasing.</p><p>The mines are a source of wealth, which, from having been neglected during the
                    French occupation, have required considerable expenditure to make them as
                    productive as they were before that calamitous period. The gross quantities
                    delivered of all the mines in the seventeen years from the beginning of 1815 to
                    the end of 1832, have been as follows, viz.</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Gold</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Silver</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>878,699 ...</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Lead</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,683,781 quintals.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Copper</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>33,509 ...</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Zinc</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>59θ</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sulphur</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>17,396 ...</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Vitriol</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>44,058 ...</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Iron</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,329,139 ...</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Salt</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1,400,000 ...</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Fossil coal</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>17,500,000 cubic feet.</p></cell></row></table><p>It is expected that in future the proceeds will be more considerable, and the
                    expense of working much less, as some new shafts have been recently sunk, and
                    the cost of them deducted from the price of the metals.</p><p>As may be supposed from the small quantity of surplus production, the trade of
                    Hanover cannot be extensive. The principal port, Emden, has some export and
                    import trade; but from the state of the roads between that place and the more
                    populous parts of the kingdom, more of its trade passes through Hamburg and
                    Bremen than through that city. Besides the more considerable articles made from
                    flax, its honey, wax, feathers, and large quantities of timber, are sent to
                    Hamburg and Bremen. Hops, rapeseed, oil-cake, fruit, hams, and sausages, form
                    also articles of export of small amount. In very fruitful years some corn is
                    exported, but in general the consumption is equal to the produce. The imports
                    consist principally of wine, coffee, tea, sugar, indigo, tobacco, and a few
                    manufactured articles, which are consumed by the richer classes. As the roads to
                    the great fairs of Leipsic and Frankfort pass through Hanover, the transit of
                    goods by these create a pretty large commission trade, and give employment to
                    many waggons, horses, and men, as well as to the barge owners. The exports and
                    imports nearly balance each other, and the amount of neither exceeds L.500,000
                    sterling.</p><p>Hanover is a hereditary monarchy in the house of Guelph, with a Salic law, which
                    prevents the throne being filled by a female. In case the present branch becomes
                    extinct, the heir of the duchy of Brunswick will succeed. The legislative power
                    was vested in the several states formerly, which caused a great complication,
                    both in the financial and the judicial departments. This arose from the several
                    parts which have successively been added to Hanover having possessed ancient
                    constitutions, with considerable differences in the laws, religion, and
                    institutions. Ry gradual arrangements these have been assimilated into one
                    system, and a legislative body formed, which, as far as it has hitherto
                    proceeded, works rather favourably for the general good. It consists of two
                    houses. The upper house contains fifty-five members. They are in part the
                    mediatorial sovereigns within the kingdom, in part the Protestant and the
                    Catholic bishops or prelates, and in part the ministers at the head of the
                    several departments of the government; but the greater number consists of the
                    representatives of the nobility, proprietors of estates in the several
                    provinces.</p><p>The second chamber is composed of seventy-two members, who are chosen for six
                    years. Twenty-nine of them are elected by the cities, and the remainder by the
                    proprietors of the estates in their respective provinces. Amongst these are
                    several clergymen and lawyers. The president and vice-president are selected by
                    the assembly, but subject to the approbation of the king, or, in his absence, of
                    the viceroy. They assemble every year, and their attention recently has been
                    chiefly addressed to the simplification of the finances, and to the abolition of
                    those inferior local justiciaries, which had belonged to the proprietors of
                    certain estates.</p><p>The revenue of the kingdom is derived from various sources, all of which have
                    been clearly communicated to the public by one of the chiefs of the board of
                    revenue, Mr Ubbelohde, up to the beginning of 1834.</p><p>The sovereigns of Hanover were, like most others in Germany, the largest landed
                    proprietors in their dominions. Their land, called the domains, with what was
                    denominated the royalties, such as the mines, the posting, the road and harbour
                    tolls, and other branches, amounted to nearly as much as the taxes. These have
                    recently been given up by the crown, and form one branch of the general revenue
                    applicable by the legislature to the purpose of paying the interest of the
                    public debt, and defraying the expenses of the several departments of the
                    administration.</p><p>The nett amount of this royal property, after deducting the expense of management
                    and collection, and the sum appropriated to the viceregal household, appears to
                    have been, in 1833, 1,194,640 rixdollars, or L.89,598 sterling, besides that
                    derived from the mines and salt springs, which amounted to 117,000 rixdollars,
                    or L.8775 sterling. The remainder of the revenue is obtained by taxation of
                    various kinds, such as land, house, personal, and income taxes, by imposts on
                    beer and corn spirits, by stamps, and by a custom-duty on foreign goods. These
                    are the chief subjects of taxation, but there are some few of a smaller kind,
                    more troublesome than productive.</p><p>The nett revenue now is found to produce as follows:</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>From the royal treasury</p><p>From the kingdom’s
                            treasury</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Rixdollars. .2,356,543 .3,006,600</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Sterling.</p><p>L. 176,625</p><p>225,495</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>The whole expenses of the government, as enumerated
                            below</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>5,363,143</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>L.402,235</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>amounted in 1832 to</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>.5,390,800</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>L.404,3l0</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Thus leaving a deficit of</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>. 41,485</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>L.2,075</p></cell></row></table><pb break="no" facs="nls:193640902" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0902-0139"/><p>The annual expenses are as follows :—</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Cabinet ministers</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Rixdollars.</p><p>90 950</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Office in London</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>1/1 ∕1∩∩</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bailiwick and other expenses in the country</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>parts, and police</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Rift 3° iO</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Legislative body</p><p>Ministry of foreign affairs....</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">U1O</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                            j</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">JJV</hi></p><p>. 76,400</p><p>7∩
                            ∩∩∩</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ministry of war</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>• f V,VVu</p><p>1 R <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> &gt;7</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ministry of justice</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>215 600</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ministry of religion and general instruction</p><p>Ministry of the
                            interior</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>. 97⅛50</p><p>651 000</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ministry of trade</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>41 300</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Ministry of finances '.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>208 000</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Interest of debt</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>. 1 306 400</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Pensions</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>144 000</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>Expiring expenses</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>198 800</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>5,390,800</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><p>or L.404,3l0 sterling.</p></cell><cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/></row></table><p>The public debt consists in part of annuities, and in part of loans. The annual
                    interest, as is shown in the account of expenses, amounts to nearly one quarter
                    of these. It is, however, annually diminishing, by means of a sinking fund, <hi rend="italic">tillgungo fond,</hi> the amount paid towards which is included in
                    the 1,306,400 rixdollars of the expenditure. It now amounts to 311,100
                    rixdollars, or nearly one quarter of the annual interest.</p><p>In the expenditure of the ministry of the interior is comprehended the cost of
                    improving the roads, the dykes, and the navigable rivers. It has been well
                    expended, especially that on the roads, which have, within the last fifteen
                    years, from the worst become some of the best in any part of Europe.</p><p>The military force of Hanover consists of an engineer and artillery corps, the
                    latter composed of two companies of horse and one of foot, a corps of riflemen,
                    a battalion of infantry, of which two are the guards and two light troops, and
                    four regiments of cavalry. The total number amounts to about twelve thousand
                    men, but many of them are indulged with furloughs, so that the whole expense of
                    the army, including the repairs of the fortifications, is very small. Hanover
                    has a single vessel of war moored in the Elbe to collect the dues on that
                    stream, and some small craft at the mouths of the Weser and of the Ems.</p><p>The religious establishments of Hanover are the three Christian sects in
                    different parts. The Lutherans are the most numerous, comprehending 1,235,200
                    persons, having ten superintendents or bishops, and 924 clergymen. They have
                    also nine convents for men and eighteen for females, but the members of these
                    are not bound to celibacy. The tithes are commonly paid in kind, but some of
                    them have stipends from the government. The Catholics are about 200,000, having
                    one bishop, and 143 parish priests. The Reformed are about 100,000, and have 114
                    parish churches, and a minister to each. There are, besides, three Mennonite and
                    One Moravian congregation. The Jews are allowed the freest toleration as regards
                    their worship, but are excluded from some of the civil privileges. Their number
                    is about 12,000.</p><p>The business of education is well attended to, and abundant means are supplied to
                    aid it, both by the government and the voluntary contributions of corporations
                    and individuals. The first establishment is the university of Göttingen, founded
                    by George II. in 1734. Its professors are scholars of great eminence in every
                    branch of science and literature, and in 1833 it contained 845 students. There
                    are, besides, five ecclesiastical seminaries, twenty-nine schools for the common
                    sciences, and sixteen gymnasiums or public classical schools; and each village
                    and town has the appropriate number of elementary schools, amounting to the
                    number of 3560. All are taught to read and to write, and the common rules of
                    arithmetic. There are also surgical and medical schools, hospitals for
                    midwifery, and a good veterinary college. The freedom of the press is allowed to
                    the professors of the university, but all other writings must pass through a
                    very mild censorship; though of late, from the proceedings of the diet at
                    Frankfort, some restrictions have been enacted against the unlimited publication
                    of political newspapers, and other smaller works.</p><p>The poor are provided for wholly by voluntary contributions, which are made from
                    house to house at stated periods. They are in a great degree supported in
                    workhouses, where their own labour contributes in some measure to their
                    maintenance. Their food and clothing are of the coarsest kind. There are many
                    hospitals and other charitable establishments for the relief and cure of the
                    diseased; and, upon the whole, the poor are as well taken care of as in other
                    countries where their maintenance is compulsory.</p><p>The language usually spoken in Hanover is the Plat-Deutsche, a dialect of the
                    High German, more pure, and less complicated in its construction, but treated by
                    the learned with more contempt than it merits. As the service in the churches
                    and the instruction in the schools are exclusively in the High German, all the
                    peasantry understand it, though they never use it when they can avoid it. The
                    higher classes pride themselves in speaking the High German with greater purity
                    than is practised in any other part of the empire.</p><p>Hanover has two standards of money, the Leipsiger and the convention. The public
                    accounts are kept in the latter. The gold coin called Georgs d’or is five
                    rixdollars eight groschen in convention money; or, in Leipsiger money, four
                    rixdollars sixteen groschen. The other gold coin, the Gold-Gulden, is two
                    rixdollars six groschen in convention, two dollars two groschen in Leipsiger
                    money.</p><p>The long measure is the rood of eight ells; the ell is two feet; the foot twelve
                    inches. Six Hanoverian are equal to five Brabant ells. Land is measured by hufen
                    and morgens. The hufe is thirty morgens, the morgen 120 ruthen, equal to 24∙844
                    Paris feet. The morgen by which woodland is measured contains 160 ruthen. The
                    liquid measure is the cimen, ’ of 3∙136 cubic inches, or the anker of l∙960
                    cubic inches. The latter makes sixteen Stübchens or thirty-two kannen, and
                    sixty-four quartiere or 128 nosel. The weights in common use are shipspounds,
                    lies-pounds, hundreds, and customary pounds. The ships-pound is equal to twenty
                    lies-pounds; the hundred is 110 lies-pounds. The lies-pound is divided into two
                    marks, the mark into eight ounces, the ounce into two loths, the loth into four
                    quentins. The local weights and measures vary from these standards in all the
                    villages of the several provinces.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Erdebescreibung</hi><hi rend="italic">des Königreichs</hi><hi rend="italic">Hannover,</hi> von Sonne; <hi rend="italic">Weimarishe
                    Erdebescreibung,</hi> vol. iv. part i.; Jacobs’ <hi rend="italic">View of
                    Germany, &amp;c.</hi> 1820; <hi rend="italic">Weimar</hi><hi rend="italic">Almanach,</hi> 1834; Hodgskin’s <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Hannoverische Zeitungen,</hi> 1833; and
                    <hi rend="italic">Uber die Finances</hi><hi rend="italic">des Königreichs</hi><hi rend="italic">Hannover</hi><hi rend="italic">und deren Verwaltung,</hi> von
                    Hofrath, J. G. L. W. Ubbelohde, 1834.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hanover,</hi> a city, the capital of the kingdom of the same
                    name, in Germany, as well as of the province of Kalenburg. It is built on an
                    extensive plain on the river Leine, which receives the waters of the Ihme, and
                    then becomes navigable to the Weser. The former walls, which were indefensible,
                    have been destroyed, and planted, and thus converted into pleasant promenades.
                    The city is divided into the old and the new town by the river. The former is
                    old, ill built, and dirty; the latter is much <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640915" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0915-0140"/>, better,
                    contains a fine square, some good streets, and several handsome public and
                    private buildings. The most prominent of these are the palace of the Duke of
                    Cambridge, the theatre, and the house of assembly of the states. The royal
                    library, containing 25,000 volumes, and the cabinet of natural history, are
                    objects of attention. The city contains seven Lutheran, two Reformed, and one
                    Catholic church, with 2195 houses, and about 25,000 inhabitants. The chief trade
                    is brewing beer, but it has those kinds of manufactures which are naturally
                    encouraged in the capital of each kingdom, however small or poor. As the
                    residence of a court, of an armed force, of the legislature, the courts of
                    justice, and of several of the nobility, a great number of small tradesmen
                    obtain subsistence by supplying their wants. The trade by water consists chiefly
                    in transmitting wood, and some corn and flax, to Bremen, where it is shipped for
                    markets at a distance. There is, however, an exchange and a chamber of commerce,
                    and some of the bankers are considerable capitalists. It is situated in
                    longitude 9. 39. 40. E. and latitude 52. 22. 18. N. Near the city is the royal
                    palace of Hemhausen, with fine walks, gardens, graperies, and plantations.</p><p><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> ,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Hanover,</hi><hi rend="italic">New,</hi> an island in the Pacific Ocean, seen by Captain Carteret
                    in 1767, and, according to his account, about thirty miles in length. The
                    passage between this island and New Zealand is obstructed by reefs and islets.
                    The south-west part is situated in long. 148. 27. E. and lat. 2. 49. S.</p></div></body></text></TEI>