<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-1227-0164-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 164</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g235">Hats</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p88c">Beaver</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9v878">Wool</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p29x">Process</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1134466">Straw</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:951903">Hats</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:829421">Beavers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1179993">Wool</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1078061">Processions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1084913">Quakers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208401">Angola</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193641227" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAT</label> is a term of Saxon derivation, from <hi
                    rend="italic">haet,</hi> a cover for the head. It is sometimes called castor,
                    from its being made of the fur of the castor or beaver. As a piece of dress, the
                    period of its introduction is not certain, although it may with great
                    probability be referred to the early distinctions of Roman Catholic dignitaries.
                    Froissart chronicles, that it was “saide to the cardynals, Sirs, advyse you if
                    ye de-lyvere us a Pope Romayne, we be content, or els we woll maike your heddes
                    reeder than your hattes be;” from which, and many other documents, it appears
                    that at this period, as well as for some centuries thereafter, hats were
                    generally of a scarlet or red colour, and made of “a fine kinde of haire matted
                    thegither.” A “hatte of biever,” about the middle of the twelfth century, was
                    worn by some one of the “nobels of the lande, mett at Clarendom ;” and Froissart
                    describes hats and plumes which were worn at Edward’s Court in 1340, when the
                    garter order was instituted. In the Diary of Henry’s secretary, there is “ane
                    scarlet beever hatte” presented on new year’s day 1443. Even at this early
                    period hats were of various shapes, both in the crowns and the brims; the latter
                    being chiefly broad, sometimes narrowing towards the back, and a little bent up
                    and scooped in front. In Henry’s privy purse expenses, during his congress with
                    Francis I. in 1520 or 1521, there is “peid for a hatte and plume for the king,
                    in Boleyn, xvs.;” and in Wolsey’s inventory, taken on his resigning the great
                    seal to Sir Thomas Moore, there are no fewer than five mentioned. The fashion of
                    this article was then much more diversely capricious than even now, as will
                    appear from an extract from Stubbs’ <hi rend="italic">Anatomic of Abuses,</hi>
                    published about 1585: “Sometimes they use them sharpe on the crowne, pearking up
                    like the spire or shaft of a steeple, standing a quarter of a yard above the
                    crowne of theire heads; some more, some lesse, as please the fantasies of their
                    inconstant mindes. Othersome be flat, and broade on the crowne, like the
                    battlements of a house. Another sorte have rounde crownes, sometimes with one
                    kind of bande, sometimes with another; now black, now white, now russed, now
                    redde, now grene, now yellow; now this, now that; never content with one colour
                    or fashion two daies to an end. And as the fashions be rare and strange, so is
                    the stuffe whereof their hattes be made divers also; for some are silk, some of
                    velvet, some of taffetic, some of sarsnet, some of wool, and, which is more
                    curious, some of a certaine kindc of fine haire, these they call bever hattes,
                    of xx. xxx. or xl. shillings price, fetched from be-yonde the seas, from whence
                    a great sorte of other vanities doe come besides; and so common a thing it is,
                    that every servyng man, countreiman, and other, even all indifferently, doe
                    weare of these hattes.” About the beginning of 1700, the crowns of hats were
                    mostly round, much lower than before, and had very broad brims, resembling what
                    are now occasionally called Quakers’ hats, the protrusive encumbrance of which
                    soon suggested the convenience of their being turned up in front; fashion
                    dictated the upbending of another side or flap, and ultimately a third, so that
                    by this progress, in 1704, the regular three-cocked hat became the order of the
                    day, when feathers ceased to be usually worn. Near the middle of the eighteenth
                    century, a round-edged but flat-topped and fullbrimmed hat got into very general
                    use, and the flat and other cocked hats now dwindled almost into a mere
                    distinction of real or assumed rank. Twenty-five years after this, a very near
                    approach to that of the present times became fashionable, and, within ten years,
                    altogether superseded the ordinary use of the cumbrous and antique cock.</p>
                <p>Plumes, jewels, silk loops, rosettes, badges, gold and <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193641240" xml:id="kp-eb0711-1240-0165"/>silver bands and loops, have
                    at various periods ornament- <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi> ed this article of
                    dress; metal bands and loops being now esteemed proper only to naval and
                    military “men of honour,” and the humble liveried attendants on state, rank, and
                    official dignity. The <hi rend="italic">opera</hi> or soft folding hat is the
                    only relic at present in general use, of the hats worn by our grandfathers,
                    although it is not improbable that the affluent and growing extravagance of this
                    century is likely to re-introduce the elegant Spanish hat as the precursor
                    perhaps of the prevalence of various other styles, as well as the cocked hat,
                    not yet entirely discarded from the revolving wheel of luxurious fashion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hat-making</hi> now embraces two distinct kinds of
                    manufacture, felted and covered hats; the covering of the latter being sometimes
                    silk, and at other times Braganza or cotton Angola.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Felted hats</hi> comprehend two classes, differing chiefly in
                    the materials used in making, the process being nearly identical. The lower
                    class is marked by inferior ingredients, unmixed with beaver, and embraces <hi
                    rend="italic">wool, plated,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">short nap</hi> hats.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wool hats</hi> are made entirely of coarse native wool and hair
                    stiffened with glue, chiefly for negroes’ wear. Value Is. 2d. to 2s. 2d. <hi
                    rend="italic">Plates</hi> have a <hi rend="italic">nap</hi> or pile rather finer
                    than their body, and are sometimes <hi rend="italic">waterproof</hi> stiffened.
                    Value 3s∙ to 4s. 6d. <hi rend="italic">Short naps</hi> are distinguished from
                    plates by additional kinds of wool, viz. hare’s back, seal, neuter, musquash
                    (Muscovy cat), and are all waterproof stiffened. Value 5s. to 9s.</p>
                <p>The second class may be said to comprehend two orders, called stuff and beaver
                    hats. The first includes mottled and stuff bodies. The latter term is not used
                    generally, as all <hi rend="italic">stuffs</hi> are understood to be of this
                    sort when <hi rend="italic">mottled</hi> is not expressed. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mottled bodies</hi> are made chiefly of fine Spanish wool, and inferior rabbit
                    down or coney wool. Value Is. 8d. to 2s. 6d. <hi rend="italic">Stuff bodies</hi>
                    consist of the best hare, Saxony, and red wools, mixed with Cashmere hair and
                    silk. Value 3s. to 4s. <hi rend="italic">Stuff hats</hi> are <hi rend="italic"
                    >napped,</hi> that is, covered with pile of mixed seal, neuter, hare-back,
                    inferior beaver, and musquash. Value lθs. to 15s. <hi rend="italic">Seaver
                    hats</hi> are, or ought to be, napped with beaver only; the lower priced
                    qualities with <hi rend="italic">brown wοοms</hi> taken from the back; the more
                    valuable kinds with <hi rend="italic">cheek</hi> and <hi rend="italic">white
                    woorns,</hi> being the finest parts of the fur found on the belly and cheeks of
                    the beaver. Value 16s. to 22s.</p>
                <p>The apparatus and terms used in making felted hats, which it is necessary to
                    describe briefly, are the bow, bowpin, basket, hurdle, battery, and planks.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">bow</hi> is about six feet long, usually made of ash, thick
                    enough not to be elastic. The handle A, B, C, is called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >stang</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> A is named the <hi rend="italic"
                    >breech;</hi> C, the end farthest from the workman’s hold, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >cock.</hi> D, the <hi rend="italic">bowstring,</hi> is a strong catgut cord
                    tensely fastened.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">bow-pin</hi> is used (just as the finger on the guitar) for
                    vibrating the bowstring.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">hurdle</hi> is a fixed bench, with three enclosing sides,
                    to prevent the stuff being flittered off in bowing.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">basket</hi> is of light wicker-work, about twenty by
                    twenty-two inches in size.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">battery</hi> consists of A, the kettle; B, C, the planks,
                    which are inclined planes, usually eight in number, one only being appropriated
                    to each workman. The half of each plank next the kettle is lead, the upper half
                    is mahogany.</p>
                <p>The first process in hat-making is <hi rend="italic">bowing</hi> the stuff or
                    furs, which are weighed out to a proportionate scale, and laid on the hurdle,
                    immediately under the bow, which is suspended by a pulley. The bow is held
                    firmly with the left hand, rather toward the <hi rend="italic">breech-end,</hi>
                    not edgewise, but on its side, with the string in contact with the stuff, the
                    clotted and adherent portions of which are separated into single fibres, and
                    attain a loose, flocky, mixed condition by the continued vibration of the
                    bowstring, caused by a very rapid succession of touches with the bowstick. It is
                    then divided as nearly as possible, and one half laid aside, whilst the other is
                    again bowed. In this second operation, partly by the bowing, but chiefly by the
                    <hi rend="italic">gathering,</hi> or patting use of the basket, the stuff" is
                    loosely matted into a conical figure, about fifty by thirty-six inches, called a
                    <hi rend="italic">bat.</hi> In this formation care is taken to work about two
                    thirds of the wools down towards what is intended for the brim, which being
                    effected, greater density is induced by gentle pressure with the basket. It is
                    then covered with a wettish linen cloth, upon which is laid the <hi
                    rend="italic">hardening skin,</hi> a piece of dry half-tanned horse hide. On
                    this the workman presses or bakes for seven or eight minutes, until the stuff
                    shall have adhered closely to the damp cloth, in which it is then doubled up,
                    freely pressed with the hand, and laid aside. By this process, called basoning
                    (from a metal plate or <hi rend="italic">bason,</hi> used for like purposes in
                    making <hi rend="italic">wool</hi> hats), the bat has become compactly felted
                    and thinned toward the sides and point. The other half of the flocked stuff is
                    next subjected to precisely the same proceedings, after which, a cone-shaped
                    slip of stiff paper is laid on its surface, and the sides of the bat folded over
                    its edges to its form and size. It is then laid paper-side downward upon the
                    first bat, which is now replaced on the hurdle, and its edges transversely
                    doubled over the introverted side-lays of the second bat, thus giving equal
                    thickness to the whole <hi rend="italic">body.</hi> In this condition it is
                    re-introduced between folds of damp linen cloth, and again hardened, so as to
                    unite both halves, the knitting together of which is quickly effected. The paper
                    is now withdrawn, and the body being folded into three plies, is removed to the
                    plank or battery room.</p>
                <p>In the battery the <hi rend="italic">liquor</hi> is scalding heat, composed of
                    pure soft water, about half a gill of oil of vitriol as an astringent, and a
                    full handful of oatmeal to correct its pernicious tendencies. Herein the body is
                    imbrued, and withdrawn to the plank to partly cool and drain, when it is
                    unfolded, rolled gently with a pin tapering towards the ends like a liquor
                    horse, turned, and worked with in every direction, to toughen, shrink, and at
                    same time prevent adhesion of its sides. <hi rend="italic">Stopping</hi> or
                    thickening the thin spots which now appear on looking through the body, is
                    carefully performed, by additional stuff daubed on by successive supplies of the
                    hot liquor from a brush frequently dipped into the kettle, until the body be
                    shrunk sufficiently (about one half), and thoroughly equalized. When quite
                    dried, <hi rend="italic">stiffening</hi> is performed with a brush dipped into a
                    glutinous pulpy composition, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193641253"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-1253-0166"/>and rubbed into the body; the surface intended for
                    the inside having much more imposed than the outer, while the brim is made to
                    absorb many times the quantity applied to any other part. This viscous matter
                    contains <hi rend="italic">proofing,</hi> or those ingredients which render the
                    hat waterproof.</p>
                <p>On being again dried, the body is ready to be <hi rend="italic">covered,</hi> and
                    is once more taken to the battery. The first cover of beaver or napping, which
                    has been previously <hi rend="italic">bowed,</hi> is equally strewed on the
                    body, and patted upon with the brush charged with the hot liquor, until
                    incorporated; the <hi rend="italic">cut</hi> ends only, being the points which
                    naturally intrude. Here the body is put into a coarse hair-cloth dipped and
                    rolled in the hot liquor, until the beaver is quite worked in. This is called
                    <hi rend="italic">rolling off,</hi> or ruffing. A stripe for the brim, round the
                    edge of the inside, is treated in like manner, and is thus prepared for the
                    second cover, which is applied and inworked in like manner; the rolling, &amp;c.
                    being continued until the whole has become incorporated, and a clean, regular,
                    close, and well-felted <hi rend="italic">hood</hi> is the result. The dry hood,
                    after having the nap beat up and freed, is clipped to the length which may be
                    thought best, by means of common shears. A clipping machine, invented nearly
                    four years ago in Scotland, is now very generally preferred, and doubtless will
                    soon everywhere supersede the ordinary process; much greater regularity, speed,
                    and certainty being secured by it. When the nap is thus disposed of, the hood is
                    soaked in the battery kettle, and then <hi rend="italic">drawn down</hi> on a
                    block to the size and shape wanted, firmly tied at the bottom with a cord,
                    around which the brim is left in a frilled condition.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dyeing</hi> is the next step. A <hi rend="italic">suit,</hi> or
                    six dozen, are put into the dye kettle at a time, all on the croavn-blocks
                    already mentioned, and allowed to remain three quarters of an hour in the
                    liquor, which is kept as near as possible one degree below the boiling point.
                    These being taken out and set in the yard to cool, another suit is introduced
                    for a like period, and the various suits are so treated at least twelve times in
                    successive order. Each of the first four introgressions of every suit is
                    accompanied by about seven pounds of copperas, and two pounds of verdigris. The
                    body is then washed and brushed out in changes of hot water, until no colouring
                    can be recognized in it. When thus thoroughly cleansed, it is steamed on a block
                    shaped as the hat is wished to be when complete; and in the finishing shop, by
                    heavy (2l-pound) heated irons and moisture, the frilled brim is shrunk until
                    rendered quite level, the nap gently raised all over with a fine wire card, and
                    brushed and ironed smooth in the uniform directions. The tip, a thin lath sheet,
                    is then fitted and stuck to the inside of the crown, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >robbined</hi> or secured all round the edges by stripes of prepared paper. When
                    thus <hi rend="italic">got down,</hi> it is sent to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >picker,</hi> who, with tweezers, extracts the <hi rend="italic">hemps,</hi>
                    vulgarly called “grey hairs,” which are a few of those thick fibres peculiar to
                    the fur of amphibious animals, that have escaped the search of the machine used
                    in blowing the beaver, so as to separate them from its fine parts. This being
                    carefully accomplished, it is transferred to the finisher, who, with a plush
                    cushion or <hi rend="italic">velure,</hi> a brush, and hot iron, imparts to it
                    that bright sleeky lustre so characteristic of English and Scotch hats. The <hi
                    rend="italic">shaper</hi> then rounds the brim with a knife and knotched segment
                    to the breadth wanted; and shapes it in varied styles by means of a hot iron and
                    damp, with about a foot length of rope, over which the <hi rend="italic"
                    >curl</hi> is laid. The <hi rend="italic">trimming</hi> is next done, when the
                    <hi rend="italic">tipper off</hi> corrects the twists, smooths the ruffled nap
                    caused by trimming, and <hi rend="italic">papers</hi> it up with tissue and
                    cartridge, which completes it for the retailer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dye-stuffs for a gross of beaver hats</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> About 180 gallons of pure soft water, one and a half hundredweight of
                    best Campeachy logwood, eight pounds oxide of copper, and thirty pounds of
                    copperas. It is to be observed, however, that some put the chips, others only
                    the juice, of the logwood into the dye-kettle. Galls are now disused. <hi
                    rend="italic">Stiffening stuffs.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Makers differ in
                    the proportions, but the ingredients are shell-lac, rosin, mastic, saundrice,
                    and elm, all churned until dissolved. A quantity of this is then melted over
                    steam, sieved, put in hot, and well mixed. <hi rend="italic">Cleaning
                    stuffs.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> These are now seldom considered necessary.
                    One half pound of borax, diluted in five gallons of water, into which the
                    stiffened nap is dipped and well brushed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Silk hats</hi> are made upon bodies of wool, stuff, willow,
                    straw, and leghorn plait, and cambric and woollen cloth, although chiefly on
                    felted wool bodies, which are dipped in glue size, wrung out, blocked, and
                    dried. The <hi rend="italic">tip</hi> is then fitted and robbined, when a
                    flour-box charged with powdered shell-lac and rosin in like quantities is used
                    to strew equally its grainy mixture on the external surface of the <hi
                    rend="italic">shell,</hi> so called from being the frame-work. This is burned in
                    by hot irons, first on the top, which passes through to the lath-tip within;
                    then on the upper brim, the sides, and, finally, the under brim. When this is
                    hardened, it is coated with thick ordinary flour-paste, which is dried, and the
                    shell again blocked and smoothed; then once more glue-sized outside, dried, and
                    varnished, which prepares it for <hi rend="italic">covering.</hi> The shag for
                    the sides is cut across the web, in a ratio of obliquity increased by
                    inferiority. This cross part is sewn to a circular piece for the crown, whilst
                    the brims are singly patched together. These preparations being completed, the
                    <hi rend="italic">top-side</hi> or upper brim is first stuck, then the crown,
                    next the sides, and, finally, the under brim. <hi rend="italic">Sticking</hi> is
                    effected simply by the heat of the iron passing through the covering and melting
                    the varnished surface. In the finish of this manufacture, the most particular
                    part is the <hi rend="italic">side-seam,</hi> which is disposed of thus: The
                    selvidge end is cut perpendicularly from top to brim, by a sharpened
                    pallet-knife, the nap having been previously brushed clear off its edge. The
                    other selvidge end is then stuck and cut with the utmost nicety, in close
                    parallel with the other. It is then finished very much in the same manner as a
                    beaver hat.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tip stuff for silk hats.—Seven</hi> pounds of glue melted in
                    water, when three pounds of pitch and half a pound of tallow are added, and the
                    whole is boiled to the consistency of thick jelly. <hi rend="italic">Varnish
                    stuff.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> A quarter of a cwt. of turpentine, mixed
                    with two gallons of linseed oil.</p>
                <p>The major part of stuff hats are <hi rend="italic">finished</hi> in London,
                    whilst body-making and ruffing is managed chiefly in Gloucester and Derbyshire.
                    Plated and short-nap hats are made principally in Lancashire, Cheshire, and
                    Staffordshire, owing to local advantages.</p>
                <p>150,000 dozens of silk and covered hats are annually made in London, and about
                    100,000 dozens in Manchester, Liverpool, Birmingham, and Glasgow. Throughout
                    Edinburgh and the other parts of Scotland there may be an additional 50.000
                    dozens made yearlv.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Value of plated hats manufactured
                            annually, L.1,080,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Stuff hats</p><p>Wool felt hats and
                            military caps..</p><p>Silk hats</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>.
                            640,000</p><p>160,000</p><p>570,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>L.2,450,000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Imported hats are each subject to ten shillings and sixpence of duty. In 1832
                    there were exported 62,854 dozens. In this branch of manufacture there are
                    employed annually nearly 25,000 men, besides about 10,000 females in the
                    trimming and picking departments.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hats, Straw.</hi> Any attempt to ascertain when straw was
                    first used in the manufacture of hats would be useless, because it would be
                    impossible to fix a date with any correctness. In Italy it had arrived at a
                    great degree of perfection two centuries ago; but it is not above sixty or
                    seventy years since it began to be followed as a trade in England. Wheat straw
                    is the material chiefly used by our <pb break="no" facs="nls:193641266"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-1266-0167"/>manufacturers; and the counties most favourable
                    for its production are Bedford, Hertford, and Buckingham, which have been called
                    the <hi rend="italic">straw-plait district.</hi> The making of straw hats is
                    carried on in other places, but not to the same extent as there. Leghorn bonnets
                    had long been a considerable article of import; but the late war having put a
                    stop to this, a new spirit was given to the home manufacture. It now became a
                    flourishing trade, which produced competition and a consequent improvement in
                    the article. At the close of the war, however, Leghorn hats again usurped the
                    market to a considerable extent, and the domestic manufacture proportionally
                    declined. Many of the straw plaiters having been reduced to great distress, the
                    Society of Arts turned its attention to the subject, and offered premiums for
                    improvements in plaiting, finishing, and bleaching. The straw of Tuscany having
                    been found very superior to British straw, the former became an article of
                    import; and the Italian method of plaiting the straw has also been introduced.
                    So completely successful has this scheme been, that, whilst the importation of
                    Leghorn hats has gradually decreased during the last few years, the introduction
                    of the raw material has gradually increased. Upon this straw there is a düty of
                    only one penny per hundredweight, and it is chiefly plaited in our own straw
                    districts. What is called the Tuscan plait, upon which a heavy duty is levied,
                    has likewise been largely imported, and made into bonnets of equal fineness and
                    beauty to the genuine Leghorn hat.</p>
                <p>There are seven descriptions of plait in general use, the difference in the kinds
                    arising from the number of straws used in the plait, and from their being either
                    whole or split. Other varieties are also manufactured, but chiefly for
                    exportation. In Scotland, rye straw, dwarfed by being grown on poor land, has
                    been employed in plaiting straw in imitation of Leghorn, and with such complete
                    success, that the hats manufactured in Orkney, where the rye is raised, are
                    considered by the best judges as quite equal, both in colour and quality, to
                    those of Leghorn. The following description of the preparation of the Italian
                    straw is extracted from M‘Culloch’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of
                    Commerce,</hi> “The description of straw used, which is cultivated solely for
                    the purposes of the manufacture, and not for the grain, is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >triticum turgidum,</hi> a variety of bearded wheat, which seems to differ in no
                    respect from the spring wheat grown in the vale of Evesham and other parts of
                    England. <hi rend="italic">(Trans, of Soc. Arts.)</hi> After undergoing a
                    certain preparatory process, the upper parts of the stems (being first sorted as
                    to colour and thickness) are formed into a plait of generally thirteen straws,
                    which is afterwards knitted together at the edges into a circular shape called a
                    ‘ flat,’ or hat. The fineness of the flats is determined by the number of rows
                    of plait which compose them, counting from the bottom of the crown to the edge
                    of the brim, and their relative fineness ranges from about No. 20 to 60, being
                    the rows contained in the breadth of the brim, which is generally eight inches.
                    They are afterwards assorted into first, second, and third qualities, which are
                    determined by the <hi rend="italic">colour</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >texture</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the most faultless being denominated the
                    first, whilst the most defective is described as the third quality. These
                    qualities are much influenced by the season of the year in which the straw is
                    plaited. Spring is the most favourable, not only for plaiting, but for bleaching
                    and finishing. The dust and perspiration in summer, and the benumbed fingers of
                    the workwomen in winter, when they are compelled to keep within their smoky
                    huts, plaiting the cold and wet straw, are equally injurious to the colour of
                    the hats, which no bleaching can improve. The flats are afterwards made up in
                    cases of .ten or twenty dozen, assorted in progressive numbers or qualities, and
                    the price of the middle or average number governs the whole. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Brozzi</hi> make bears the highest repute, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Signa</hi> is considered secondary; which names are given to the
                    flats, from the districts where they are plaited. Florence is the principal
                    market, and the demand is chiefly from England, France, Germany, and America;
                    but the kinds mostly required are the lower numbers; the very finest hats, and
                    particularly of late, being considered as too expensive by the buyers. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">The following Statement shows the
                    Imports into England of Italian Straw Hats, Straw Plait, and Unmanufactured
                    Straw, from</hi> 1828 <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 1832.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Years.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Hats or Bonnets of Straw.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Plaiting of Straw.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Unmanufactured Straw.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Imported.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Exported.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Consumption.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nett Revenue.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Imported.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Exported.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Consumption.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nett Revenue.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Imported.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nett Revenue.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">No.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">No.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">No.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">L.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >Lbs.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >Lbs.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >Lbs.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">L.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >Lbs.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">L.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1828</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>384,072</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >8,3T7</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>274,906</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>77,784</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5,502</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>283</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5,100</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4,335</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4,199</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>420</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1829</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>160,195</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27,030</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>234,254</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>66,393</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6,282</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>487</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,340</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,834</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6,050</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>605</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1830</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>162,660</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>34,132</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>168,525</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>47,760</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6,183</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>756</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7,884</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6,669</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18,586</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,859</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>84,066</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24,980</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>93,947</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26,644</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>23,354</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,102</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16,450</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13,287</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22,344</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2,232</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1832</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>169,433</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>35,271</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60,830</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17,280</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19,109</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,605</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17,911</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15,174</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48,054</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>811</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>For further particulars relative to straw hats, see M‘Culloch’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dictionary,</hi> from which our information has been derived.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
