<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-6076-0537-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOME, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 537</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="32" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="28" ref="fasttopic:959074">Home</term>
                    <term n="28" ref="fasttopic:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193646076" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOME, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, a Scottish
                    dramatic writer of great celebrity, was born at Leith, on the 13th of September
                    1722. His father, Mr Alexander Home, was town-clerk of that place, and his
                    mother was a daughter of Mr John Hay, a writer, or solicitor, in Edinburgh. He
                    acquired the elementary branches of his classical education under Mr Hugh
                    Millar, master of the grammar-school of Leith, and entered the University of
                    Edinburgh in 1735, where he soon contracted an intimacy with William Robertson,
                    William Wilkie, Alexander Carlyle, Hugh Blair, John Blair, Sir Gilbert Elliot,
                    Sir John Dalrymple, and several others, afterwards well known in the literary
                    world. After having attended the humanity class taught by Mr Kerr, one of the
                    best Latin scholars of the age; mathematics, taught by the celebrated Maclaurin;
                    logic, taught by Dr Stevenson, who contributed more than any other man in
                    Scotland to inspire the young men of that period with a taste for good writing
                    and rational investigation; he proceeded to the study of moral and natural
                    philosophy, under Sir John Pringle and Sir Robert Stewart, and then passed
                    through the usual routine of theological instruction. He was licensed by the
                    presbytery of Edinburgh as a preacher of the gospel, on the 4th of April
                    1745.</p>
                <p>Before he had enjoyed many opportunities of exercising this peaceful function,
                    Scotland became the scene of a civil war; and the ardour of his mind, imbued as
                    it was with a love of enterprise, and a boundless admiration of military glory,
                    prompted him, on the first news of the approach of the rebel army, to join an
                    armed association, formed by the inhabitants of Edinburgh, for the defence of
                    the city. Ou the 9th of September 1745, he was enrolled in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >College Company of Volunteers, a</hi> corps which was dissolved within a week,
                    when the city was taken possession of by the Pretender’s troops. But Mr Home and
                    a few other spirited young men again formed themselves into a more select and
                    efficient company, in the month of November, and subsequently obtained
                    permission from General Hawley to serve in the field. Of this company Dr William
                    M‘Ghie was chosen captain, and Mr Home lieutenant. He had the command of the
                    company on the 17th of January 1746, at the battle of Falkirk, where, having
                    received no orders to act, he was an indignant witness of the disgraceful rout
                    of the royal forces, which had fought so well at Dettingen and Fontenoy; and
                    having been one of the last to retreat, he was taken prisoner, with five of his
                    company. They were sent to the Castle of Doun, in Perthshire, on the 25th of
                    January; but Mr Home, with some of his fellow prisoners, escaped on the 31st, by
                    twisting their blankets into ropes, and dropping from the battlements, a height
                    of seventy feet. At this time Mr Home was not less remarkable for the elegance
                    and symmetry of his person, than for his engaging and prepossessing address. His
                    appearance bespoke great vivacity, activity, and energy; his conversation was
                    not merely cheerful, but uncommonly sprightly and animated; and the unceasing
                    kindness which beamed from his countenance, and marked every action of his life,
                    was such as to render him an universal favourite.</p>
                <p>In the course of the year 1746, after the death of Mr Robert Blair, minister of
                    Athelstaneford, and author of the well-known poem entitled <hi rend="italic">The
                    Grave,</hi> Mr Home obtained the presentation to the living, by the interest of
                    Alexander Home of Eccles, afterwards solicitor-general. He was ordained to the
                    charge of the parish in February 1747, and proved very acceptable to the
                    parishioners. During a considerable part of his incumbency, he gave the use of
                    his manse to Mr Hepburn of Keith, a gentleman who had been engaged in both the
                    rebellions in 1715 and 1745, and whose insinuating manners and enticing
                    conversation in some measure reconciled Mr Home to the character of the
                    Jacobites. He boarded himself in the house of a grazier or butcher in the
                    village, at the moderate rate of L.12 a year; but as he passed a great part of
                    his time amongst his numerous friends in the neighbourhood, it is believed that
                    his host was not inadequately remunerated. Mr Home was frequently<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193646089" xml:id="kp-eb0711-6089-0538"/> absent from his lodgings
                    from Monday morning till Saturday night, and though he wrote a considerable
                    number of discourses for the pulpit, he seldom left himself time to finish any
                    one of them. After writing about two thirds of a sermon and committing it to
                    memory, he generally trusted for the remainder to the moment of delivery. These
                    unpremeditated perorations, occasionally eloquent, were delivered with more than
                    his usual vehemence of action, and are said to have been not a little admired by
                    his rustic audience.</p>
                <p>Amongst the most intimate friends of Mr Home at this time were Lord Elibank, then
                    residing at Ballancrieff, Dr Robertson, then minister of Gladsmuir, Dr Carlyle
                    of Inveresk, and Mr George Logan of Ormiston, a young clergyman of great
                    promise, who died soon after having been induced, by the solicitation of his
                    ablest contemporaries,, to undertake the refutation of David Hume’s sceptical
                    writings.</p>
                <p>From his earliest years Mr Home had been a passionate admirer of the tragic muse,
                    and about the time of his establishment in the church it was known to his
                    familiar friends that he was engaged in the composition of a tragedy founded on
                    the account of the death of Agis, as given in Plutarch’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lives.</hi> The play, when completed, was highly approved by his friends Blair,
                    Carlyle, and George Logan.</p>
                <p>In 1749, he went with this play to London, having obtained strong recommendations
                    to the attention of several leaders of the republic of letters; but his
                    reception was very discouraging, except amongst his own countrymen. Some
                    objected to the bloodiness of the catastrophe, and to the irregular sequence of
                    the scenes; others to the Scoti-cisms or vulgarisms of the style. Lord Lyttleton
                    was then reputed the chief arbiter of taste; but no importunity could prevail
                    upon him to read the play, because he did not like to express disapprobation,
                    and if he happened to be pleased, he did not wish to have the trouble of
                    supporting it, as he had lately found almost insuperable difficulty in carrying
                    through one of Thomson’s tragedies which he had warmly patronised. One
                    Englishman of some note remarked, that the author had formed himself too much on
                    Thomson’s <hi rend="italic">Seasons</hi> and Lee’s <hi rend="italic">Plays,</hi>
                    “I could not have been more surprised,” said Mr Home to a correspondent, “if he
                    had told me that 1 had formed myself upon Euclid’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elements</hi> and Maclaurin’s <hi rend="italic">Fluxions.”</hi> He had not a
                    very exalted opinion of the English intellect. “I sometimes hearken to the
                    coffee-house conversations upon poetry and politics, where there are such
                    fellows authors, whose wigs are worth L.3 sterling, that it is ready to make a
                    man of moderate patience <hi rend="italic">curse his better angel from his side,
                    and fall to reprobation?</hi> When Garrick refused to bring the play upon the
                    stage, the author, after giving vent to his mortified feelings in an address to
                    the shade of Shakspeare, composed in Westminster Abbey, returned to Scotland,
                    and resumed the labours of his pastoral office, not without devoting a large
                    share of his time to the society of his literary acquaintance, and to the
                    pursuit of his favourite study.</p>
                <p>He continued assiduously to cultivate the friendship of Mr Hepburn, from whose
                    sister-in-law, Mrs Janet Denoon, he first heard the old song of <hi
                    rend="italic">Gil Morrice.</hi> This ballad furnished the hint on which he
                    constructed the tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Douglas,</hi> in the composition of
                    which he amused himself occasionally the next five years, submitting the
                    successive scenes to the revision of a few friends. His own handwriting was
                    scarcely legible, and the play was repeatedly transcribed by Dr Carlyle. From
                    this circumstance, and from the warm interest which that gentleman took in the
                    success of the piece, he was commonly supposed to have had a principal share in
                    the composition. Sir Gilbert Elliot’s criticisms were acknowledged to be
                    particularly valuable, and he also was not unfrequently reputed the author. In
                    February 1755, Mr Home set out for London on horseback, with his tragedy in one
                    pocket, and some clean linen in the other; and was accompanied into
                    Northumberland by a cavalcade of clerical friends, two of whom, Carlyle and
                    Cupples, proceeded with him a stage or two beyond Durham. This play, as well as
                    <hi rend="italic">Agis,</hi> was rejected by Garrick, not so much, perhaps,
                    owing to any defect in his own taste, as because it did not contain much of that
                    pomp and circumstance which seemed to be the chief attractions of the tragedies
                    which were at this time favourites with the public.</p>
                <p>Whilst Mr Home was engaged in the composition of this play, he had not been
                    inattentive to other affairs more nearly connected with the clerical profession.
                    In 1752 he took an active part in the deliberations of the General Assembly,
                    when Mr Gillespie was deposed. The year before, he had made the motion to
                    suspend Mr Adams of Falkirk, for disobeying an order of the General Assembly,
                    and was seconded by Dr Robertson, the first time either had spoken in that
                    house. They were not members next year, but both spoke at the bar with great
                    effect. About this time Mr Home’s support was strongly solicited by Dr Cuming,
                    the leader of what was then called the moderate party; but he resolved to act an
                    independent part. He had become a great favourite of Lord Milton, nephew of the
                    famous Andrew Fletcher of Salton; and, as ĥis lordship managed the political
                    affairs of Scotland, under the direction of Archibald duke of Argyll, he took an
                    opportunity of introducing Mr Home to his grace, who was much delighted with his
                    cheerful and fascinating manners, and continued to befriend him ever afterwards.
                    Mr Home paid a visit to the duke at Inverary, in October 1756, and was most
                    kindly received. At this time he was closely connected in friendship with the
                    members of the <hi rend="italic">Select Society,</hi> established at Edinburgh
                    in 1754.</p>
                <p>It was resolved at last, by the friends of the author, in December 1756, to have
                    <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi> represented on the Edinburgh stage; and the
                    result far exceeded their most sanguine expectations. Digges performed <hi
                    rend="italic">Young</hi><hi rend="italic">Narval,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lady Randolph</hi> was personated by Mrs Ward, The theatre was crowded night
                    after night, and the applause of the audience was tumultuous. Not only all the
                    literati attended, but most of the judges and other grave characters, whose
                    presence in the theatre excited great surprise and not a little scandal. Before
                    this time the inhabitants of Edinburgh had not been much accustomed to dramatic
                    entertainments, as the leaders of the church had generally had sufficient
                    influence to induce the civil power to suppress them. In the year 1727, the
                    Presbytery of Edinburgh issued an <hi rend="italic">Admonition against the
                    Stqge</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and, in 1733, in consequence of a sermon on
                    the <hi rend="italic">Use and Abuse of</hi><hi rend="italic">Diversions,</hi> by
                    Mr George Anderson, a minister of Edinburgh, various pamphlets were published,
                    particularly one by Mr Anderson himself, in which he denounced the stage as an
                    unchristian diversion, and repeated all the arguments against it produced by
                    Prynne, Filmer, Baxter, and Collier. Following the example of their
                    predecessors, this body issued a similar admonition and exhortation to all
                    within their bounds, on the 5th of January 1757, and not only suspended Mr
                    White, minister of Libberton, for having been present at the performance of <hi
                    rend="italic">Douglas,</hi> but wrote letters to the presbyteries of Haddington,
                    Dalkeith, Ayr, Chirnside, and Dunse, informing against those of their members
                    who had been guilty of the same indecorum. Some of the clergymen accused were
                    allowed to escape with a gentle rebuke; but Dr Carlyle was libelled, as it is
                    called, by his presbytery, at the instigation, as he believed, of an eminent
                    lawyer, then lord advocate, whose conduct on that occasion was afterwards
                    sufficiently avenged by the ridicule heaped upon him in an humorous political
                    satire, by Dr Adam Ferguson, entitled <hi rend="italic">The History of
                    Sister</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193646102" xml:id="kp-eb0711-6102-0539"/><hi
                    rend="italic">Peg.</hi> Several abusive pamphlets against the play and its
                    supporters were known to proceed from the minions of this gentleman, who was
                    then rising to a degree of consequence which soon supplanted the declining
                    influence of Lord Milton.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The following are some of the most remarkable pamphlets published on this
                    occasion :—1. Admonition and Exhortation of the Presbytery of Edinburgh. 2∙
                    Witherspoon’s Serious Enquiry into the Nature and Effects of the Stage. 3. The
                    Immorality of Stage Plays in general, and ôf the Tragedy called Douglas in
                    particular, briefly illustrated. 4. The Usefulness of the Edinburgh Stage
                    seriously considered. 5. The Tragedy of Douglas analysed. G. A Letter to Mr
                    David Hume on the Tragedy of Douglas. 7∙ An Apology for the Writers against the
                    Tragedy of Douglas, with Remarks on that play. 8. The Deposition, or Fatal
                    Miscarriage, a tragedy. 9∙ Douglas, a Tragedy, weighed in the balances and found
                    wanting. 10. The First Night’s Audience, an excellent new ballad. 11. The Stage
                    or the Pulpit, two parts. 12. The Apostle to the Theatre his Garland. 13. The
                    Finishing Stroke, or Nothing, a ballad. 14. The Infernal Council, an excellent
                    new ballad. 15. A Song or a Sermon, a new ballad, Saturday, 29th January i757.
                    16. The Admonition, an execrable new ballad. 17∙ Advice to the Writers in
                    Defence of Douglas. 18. An Epilogue to the Tragedy of Douglas, spoke by the
                    Author. 19. An Argument to prove that the Tragedy of Douglas ought to be Burnt
                    by the Hands of the Hangman [ironical, by Dr Carlyle! 20. The Moderator, Nos. 1
                    and 2. 21. Votes of the Presbytery of Edinburgh, 29th December 1756. 22. A
                    Letter to the Reverend the Moderator, &amp;c. of the Presbytery of Haddington.
                    23. A Letter to the Author of the Ecclesiastical Characteristics. 24. The
                    Morality of Stage Plays seriously considered [by Dr Ferguson]. 25. Some serious
                    Remarks on a Pamphlet, entitled the Morality of Stage Plays seriously Considered
                    [by the Reverend Mr Harper,, an Episcopalian clergyman]. 26. The Players’
                    Scourge. 27∙ A Letter to the Author of the Ecclesiastical Characteristics. 28. A
                    Second Letter to the same. 29. Unto the Right Ethereal the Siplers, the Petition
                    of Poor Alexander Bonum Magnum. Most of these are unfavourable to the play (some
                    of them written by Mr Maclaurin, afterwards Lord Dreghorn); others contain very
                    indecorous strictures on the conduct of Drs Cuming, Walker, and Webster, who
                    were active in discouraging the attendance on the theatre, and in prosecuting
                    offending brethren.</p></note></p>
                <p>After the play had been so amazingly successful in Edinburgh, it was eagerly
                    admitted on the stage of Covent-Garden early in 1757; but Garrick still excluded
                    it from Drury-Lane. The triumph of the author was, however, in no small degree
                    abated by the prosecution of his friends in the church courts, and by his own
                    threatened deposition. The subject was brought before the General Assembly by Dr
                    Carlyle in the form of an appeal from a sentence of the Synod of Lothian and
                    Tweeddale; and a decision favourable to the appellant was carried by a great
                    majority of 117 to 37. The result of this vote checked the introduction of a
                    very severe <hi rend="italic">Overture,</hi> which was intended to have been
                    enacted into a law; and next day another motion was substituted, so lenient as
                    to be seconded by Mr Dempster of Dunnichen, the friend of Home and Carlyle, in
                    consequence of which the assembly passed a declaratory law, prohibiting the
                    clergy from attending the theatre, but not discharging them from writing plays.
                    Immediately afterwards, Mr Home thought it expedient to resign his charge; and
                    having preached a most pathetic sermon, which deeply affected his congregation,
                    he took leave of them in the beginning of June 1757, without having incurred any
                    ecclesiastical censure. He then retired for three months to private lodgings at
                    Braid, near Edinburgh, where he gave the finishing hand to the play of <hi
                    rend="italic">Agis.</hi></p>
                <p>From the moment when Mr Home resigned his living, the prospects of his worldly
                    prosperity began to brighten. The people of England, ever alive to sentiments of
                    compassion, regarded him as a victim to the rigour of Presbyterian bigotry; and
                    though their critics decried the merits of <hi rend="italic">Douglas,</hi> as
                    being a faulty and languid composition, not sufficiently relieved by either
                    pathos or elegance of expression, they admitted that it exhibited unquestionable
                    indications of true poetical genius, and a power of awakening the most elevated
                    as well as the most tender emotions. Men of the highest rank and influence
                    expected to gain popularity by patronising the author, who, after being known to
                    possess the good graces of the Dukes of Cumberland and Argyll, was warmly
                    recommended by his friend, Sir Gilbert Elliot, to the Earl of Bute, who then
                    superintended the education of the Prince of Wales, afterwards George III. The
                    Princess Dowager of Wales granted him a pension of L.100 a year, an allowance
                    equal to the value of the living which he had resigned; and assurances were
                    given him of a more ample provision at no distant period.</p>
                <p>In one respect, the partiality of his literary friends, and the favour of the
                    great, had an injurious effect on his future fame, not only by producing an
                    impression that he had gained by flattering assiduities what merit alone was
                    seldom known to procure, but by exciting expectations in the minds of numbers
                    that his more mature exertions would far surpass the earliest specimen of his
                    powers as a dramatic writer. The warm encomiums of David Hume were naturally
                    ascribed to the partiality of friendship; but the opinion expressed by Gray the
                    poet, that the tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi> had “retrieved the true
                    language of the stage, lost for three hundred years,” seemed to imply a
                    preference of the muse of Home even to that of Shakspeare himself. The
                    objections of Garrick to the tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Agis</hi> were no
                    longer urged; and though this was in fact the earliest effort of an unpractised
                    writer, it appeared under the disadvantage of being considered as a work of
                    higher pretensions than that which had already been so well received by the
                    public. It is also to be presumed, that though in its finished state it retained
                    many lofty sentiments of freedom and patriotism, yet, as the author began to
                    breathe the atmosphere of a court, he was tempted to soften some of his boldest
                    images, so that the piece may have lost in spirit more than it gained in polish.
                    It was brought out at Drury-Lane in 1758, and, partly owing to the admirable
                    acting of Garrick in the character of Lysander, had a successful run of nine
                    nights. The author cleared several hundred pounds, but the anticipations of the
                    public were not fulfilled. “I cry,” said Gray, “to think it should have been by
                    the author of <hi rend="italic">Douglas.</hi> Why, it is all modern Greek. The
                    story is an antique statue, painted white and red, frizzed and dressed in a
                    negligee made by a Yorkshire mantua-maker.”</p>
                <p>In 1759, the <hi rend="italic">Siege of Aquileia</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">
                    \nũs&gt;</hi> first performed at Drury-Lane, but was by no means so successful
                    as Garrick had expected. Garrick and Home were now on the most intimate footing;
                    and as Home listened with much deference to the criticisms of this great actor,
                    and generally followed his advice, the latter, on the other hand, courted the
                    good graces of Home, by consulting him in his difficulties, and soliciting him
                    to act as his friend, or second, in certain quarrels, which threatened to
                    terminate in duels. Early in 1760, Mr Home’s first three plays were published in
                    one volume, which was dedicated to the Prince of Wales.</p>
                <p>After the accession of the prince to the throne, the Earl of Bute became prime
                    minister; and from this period Mr Home for many years lived constantly with his
                    lordship, at least from October to May, and was well known to possess the first
                    place in his confidence and favour. Mr Home was always most active in promoting
                    the interest of those who called themselves his friends, and conferred the most
                    valuable obligations upon many individuals, who <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193646115" xml:id="kp-eb0711-6115-0540"/>were more forward to solicit
                    his services than to testify their gratitude. But it is well known that he never
                    teased his patron with applications in his own behalf; and it is believed that
                    he might have been overlooked altogether, if Lord Bute had not been prompted by
                    another friend to bestow upon him some honourable and lucrative appointment. A
                    pension of L.300 a year was granted to him in July 1762, and another of equal
                    amount was at the same time conferred on Dr Johnson. In the course of the
                    following year, the place of <hi rend="italic">Conservator of Scots Privileges
                    at Campvere was</hi> bestowed upon him, the value of which appointment was also
                    L.300 a year; and from this period his name appears annually in the list of
                    members of the General Assembly, as elder for the church of Campvere, under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Lord Conservator.</hi> He regularly attended the
                    meetings of the assembly, and took a lively interest in the proceedings. He had
                    little turn for business, but he occasionally spoke with much energy and effect.
                    He was ambitious to have a seat in the House of Commons, and repeatedly
                    signified his wishes, which at one period might have been easily fulfilled, if
                    he had not been dissuaded by Sir Gilbert Elliot and Sir William Pulteney, not
                    only because they knew that he would be considered as disqualified, by having
                    been in orders, but because they were convinced that, even if that objection
                    were not started, he would make no great figure as a debater. When in London he
                    lived on terms of great cordiality with Armstrong, Smollett, Dr Pitcairn, Dr
                    William Hunter, Mr Wedderburn, afterwards chancellor, and the Honourable Charles
                    Townshend. He had a particular pleasure in fostering rising merit. In the year
                    1759, he stimulated James Macpherson to collect what were called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Poems of Ossian;</hi> and he afterwards accompanied him on one of
                    his tours, partly with the hope of sharing in the pleasure of discovering the
                    poetical remains of distant ages, but chiefly with the view of searching for
                    materials which might throw light on the history of the rebellion in 1745.</p>
                <p>In 1769, his tragedy of the <hi rend="italic">Fatal Discovery,</hi> the fable of
                    which is borrowed from one of the fragments ascribed to Ossian, was performed at
                    Drury-Lane, with indifferent success. At this time the prejudice against
                    Scotchmen was so strong in London that Garrick apprehended a total failure of
                    the play if the author were known. At his suggestion, therefore, the title was
                    altered from <hi rend="italic">Rivine</hi> to the <hi rend="italic">Fatal
                    Discovery</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and for some nights the representation
                    was greeted with loud applause, the play being ascribed either to Gray or to
                    Smith. Mr Home’s love of praise, however, betrayed the secret, and from that
                    moment the audience sensibly diminished every night. In February 1773, <hi
                    rend="italic">Alonzo</hi> was brought out, and was well received. This play is
                    recommended by the simplicity of the plot, the harmony of the versification, and
                    the dignity of the sentiments; but some of the incidents are improbable, the
                    language occasionally too mean, the apostrophes too frequent, and it has more
                    eloquent declamation than natural feeling, more graceful description than
                    pathetic effect. The acting of Mrs Barry affected the feelings of the audience
                    so powerfully as to disarm the severity of criticism. To this tragedy, as well
                    as the <hi rend="italic">Fatal Discovery,</hi> Garrick furnished an epilogue.
                    The theatrical career of Mr Home was closed with the play of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Alfred,</hi> which was represented at Drury-Lane in January 1778. It was
                    listened to the first evening; but a less crowded house was never known than on
                    the second, and after the third performance the author withdrew it.</p>
                <p>For many years Mr Home lived chiefly in London. In 1767 he obtained from Sir
                    David Kinloch a long lease of Kilduff, a farm in East Lothian, on which he built
                    a house. In 1770 he married Miss Home (daughter of Mr Home, minister of Fogo,
                    formerly of Polwarth), a lady of very delicate constitution, who, however,
                    survived him several years.</p>
                <p>In 1778, when the Duke of Buccleuch raised the regiment of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Smith Fencibles</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> Mr Home’s military
                    ardour induced him to accept a commission as lieutenant, the same rank which he
                    had held more than thirty years before ∙ and he gave occasion to some sneers
                    from his graver brethren, by sitting in the General Assembly in his scarlet
                    regimentals. After being nearly two years an officer he was disabled for
                    military service by a fall from his horse, which, though it did not permanently
                    affect his health, continued through life to impair the vigour of his faculties,
                    and to diminish tfie flow of his spirits. About this time he left Kilduff, and
                    took up his residence in Edinburgh for the remainder of his life. Till within
                    five years of his death, he was accustomed to pay an annual visit to London; and
                    such was the force of habit, that his friends experienced great difficulty in
                    prevailing with him to desist from these expensive and unnecessary journeys.</p>
                <p>In 1798 an edition of his plays was published, in two volumes, now rarely to be
                    procured.</p>
                <p>His last work, the <hi rend="italic">History of the Rebellion in</hi> 1745, was
                    published at London in 1802, in a quarto volume. It had long been understood to
                    be in a state of perfect preparation, but it was not expected to appear in the
                    author’s lifetime, as there was reason to apprehend that much of the matter
                    which it contained would prove offensive to some distinguished individuals,
                    whose hostility it was not desirable to encounter. In the first sketches of it,
                    the author is said to have ardently applauded the disinterested motives and
                    gallant conduct of the adherents of the house of Stuart, to whom he had been
                    opposed in the field; and whilst he did ample justice to their devoted
                    attachment and heroic efforts, he was not sparing of the indignation due to the
                    barbarities perpetrated by the pervailing party after the victory of Culloden.
                    Some influence, however, was exerted to hasten the publication, and the author
                    had not the courage to resist the temptation to suppress and qualify many of his
                    first statements. As a composition, it was certainly not improved by what were
                    intended as the finishing emendations; but, if its interest has been weakened,
                    its impartiality has probably been more effectually secured than if it had
                    retained its original form; and, though the book gave much less satisfaction
                    than if it had not been so anxiously expected, its merit has certainly been
                    unduly depreciated. The style, indeed, is negligent, and the reflections not
                    profound; but if the comments of the author are few and obvious, the detail is
                    generally so full as to enable the reader to draw just conclusions; the battles
                    are graphically described, and, as far as the narrative extends, it is entitled
                    to unreserved credit. Perhaps the chief cause why the work was never highly
                    applauded has been, that it is not written so as to gratify the prejudices
                    either of one party or another.</p>
                <p>Mr Home died at Merchiston, in the neighbourhood of Edinburgh, on the 5th of
                    September 1808, when he had nearly completed his eighty-sixth year. In private
                    life no man was ever more entirely beloved. His affections were equally warm and
                    stedfast; and much as he had moved in the highest circles, not without pluming
                    himself sufficiently on his intimacy with the great, he never forsook the
                    interest of his friends in humbler stations, or betrayed any expectation of
                    deference from those who were dependent on his good offices. His temper was
                    placid, and though there were occasions on which he manifested some warmth of
                    feeling, he was neither apt to resent injuries nor to inflict pain. He was never
                    known to grudge any exertion which tended to benefit or gratify his friends; and
                    long after the activity of his mind had begun to languish, he continued as eager
                    as ever to confer unsolicited favours, and to use all the influence which he
                    possessed to reward <pb break="no" facs="nls:193646128"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-6128-0541"/>neglected merit. He was alleged to be rather apt
                    to flatter; but the fact was, that he appeared never to discover any defects in
                    the character of those whom he esteemed; and, with all the blindness of a lover
                    to the objects of a first attachment, the overflowing benevolence of his heart
                    disposed him to invest his early friends with every perfection of which human
                    nature is susceptible, and to spread the veil of charity over blemishes and
                    offences. If he had not been early enticed into the vortex of fashion and
                    politics, he might have attained higher eminence as an author; but, in spite of
                    all the temptations of vanity, and the petulant and persevering attacks of envy,
                    he could scarcely, under any circumstances, have proved more amiable as a man.
                    (p. <hi rend="smallcaps">,p.</hi> p.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Home,</hi><hi rend="italic">Sir Everard,</hi> an eminent
                    surgeon, was born about the year 1755. He was of Scottish extraction, and his
                    connection with the Hunters brought him into notice at an early period of life.
                    At one time he was held in high estimation as a surgical practitioner, and
                    obtained the more substantial advantage of an extensive practice. He had the
                    good fortune to be appointed one of the surgeons to St George’s Hospital; and
                    this circumstance, added to the publication of various works which attained a
                    considerable share of celebrity, contributed to extend his reputation, the
                    advantages of which he lived nearly half a century to enjoy. In 1813 he was
                    created a baronet, and was also appointed serjeant-surgeon to the king. For
                    several years before his death, which took place on the 31st of August 1832, in
                    the seventy-seventh year of his age, Sir Everard Home had retired from practice,
                    and sought in private life the repose which his increasing age and infirmities
                    required. Sir Evcrard was the author of Practical Observations on Stricture, of
                    Lectures on Comparative Anatomy, and of various papers in the Philosophical
                    Transactions; but none of his productions discovers much depth of research, or
                    any great originality of speculation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
