<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0941-0142-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HAPPINESS, or Felicity</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 142</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1050382">Pain</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640941" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HAPPINESS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Felicity</hi></label>,
                    absolutely considered, denotes the durable possession of perfect good without
                    any admixture of evil; or the enjoyment of pure pleasure unalloyed with pain; or
                    a state in which all the wishes are satisfied. In these senses happiness is
                    known only by name upon the earth. The epithet <hi rend="italic">happy·,</hi>
                    when applied to any state or condition of human life, admits of no positive
                    definition, but is merely a relative term; in other words, when we call a man
                    happy, we mean that he is happier than some others with whom we compare him,
                    than the generality of others, or than he himself was in some other
                    situation.</p>
                <p>This subject has been treated by many eminent writers, and in a great variety of
                    ways; but by none does it appear to have been set in a clearer and more definite
                    point of view than by Archdeacon Paley in the sixth chapter of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Principles of Moral and Political Philosophy.</hi> In strictness,
                    says he, any condition may be denominated happy in which the amount or aggregate
                    of pleasure exceeds that of pain; and the degree of happiness depends upon the
                    quantity of this excess. And the greatest quantity of it, ordinarily attainable
                    in human life, is what we mean by happiness, when we inquire or pronounce what
                    human happiness consists in.</p>
                <p>If any <hi rend="italic">positive</hi> signification, distinct from what we mean
                    by pleasure, can be affixed to the term <hi rend="italic">happiness,</hi> it may
                    be taken to denote a certain state of the nervous system in that part of the
                    human frame in which we feel joy and grief, passions and affections. λVhether
                    this part be the heart, which the turn of most languages would lead us to
                    believe; or the diaphragm, as Buffon imagined; or die upper orifice of the
                    stomach, as Van Helmont thought; or rather a kind of fine net-work, lining the
                    whole region of die praecordia, as others have imagined; it is possible not only
                    that every painful sensation may violently shake and disturb the fibres at the
                    time, but that a series of such may at length so derange the very texture of the
                    system, as to produce a perpetual irritation, which will show itself by
                    fretfulness, restlessness, and impatience. It is possible also, on the other
                    hand, that a succession of pleasurable sensations may have such an effect upon
                    this subtle organisation, as to cause the fibres to relax, and return into their
                    place and order; and thereby to recover, or, if not lost, to preserve, that
                    harmonious conformation which gives to the mind its sense of complacency and
                    satisfaction. This state may be denominated <hi rend="italic">happiness</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> and is so far distinguishable from pleasure, that it does
                    not refer to any particular object of enjoyment, or consist, like pleasure, in
                    the gratification of one or more of the senses; but is rather the secondary
                    effect which such objects and gratifications produce -upon the nervous system,
                    or the state in which they leave it. The comparative sense, however, in which we
                    have explained the term <hi rend="italic">happiness,</hi> is more popular; and
                    in prosecuting the subject, we may consider, first, what human happiness does
                    not consist in; and, secondly, what it does consist in.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="italic">First,</hi> then, happiness does not consist in the
                    pleasures of sense, in whatever profusion or variety they may be enjoyed. By the
                    p!easures of sense are meant the animal gratifications of eating, drinking, and
                    that by which the species is continued, as well as the more refined pleasures of
                    music, painting, architecture, gardening, splendid shows, theatrical
                    exhibitions, and, lastly, the pleasures of active sports, as of hunting,
                    shooting, fishing, &amp;c. For, 1. These pleasures continue but for a little
                    while at a time. This is true of them all, especially of the grosser sort.
                    Laying aside the preparation and the expectation, and computing strictly the
                    actual sensation, we shall be surprised to find how inconsiderable a portion of
                    our time they occupy, how few hours in the four and twenty they are able to fill
                    up. 2. By repetition they lose their relish. It is a property of the machine,
                    for which we know no remedy, that the organs by which we perceive pleasure are
                    blunted and benumbed by being frequently exercised in the same way. There is
                    hardly any one who has not found the difference between a gratification when new
                    and when familiar, or any pleasure which does not become indifferent as it grows
                    habitual. 3. The eagerness for high and intense delights takes away the relish
                    from all others; and as such delights fall rarely in our way, the greater part
                    of our time becomes from this cause empty and uneasy. There is hardly any
                    delusion by which men are greater sufferers in their happiness, than by their
                    expecting too much from what is called <hi rend="italic">pleasure</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> that is, from those intense delights which vulgarly engross
                    the name of pleasure. The very expectation spoils them. When they do come, we
                    are often engaged in taking pains to persuade ourse!ves how much we are pleased,
                    rather than in enjoying any pleasure which springs naturally out of the object;
                    and whenever we depend upon being vastly delighted, we always go home secretly
                    grieved at missing our aim. Likewise, as has been just now observed, when this
                    humour of being prodigiously delighted has once taken hold of the imagination,
                    it hinders us from providing for or acquiescing in those gently soothing
                    engagements, the due variety and succession of which are the only things that
                    supply a continued stream of happiness.</p>
                <p>The truth seems to be, that there is a limit at which these pleasures soon
                    arrive, and from which they ever afterwards dec!ine. They are by necessity of
                    short duration, as the prgans cannot hold on their emotions beyond a certain
                    length of time; and if you endeavour to compensate for this imperfection in
                    their nature by the frequency with which you repeat them, you lose more than you
                    gain by the fatigue of the faculties and the diminution of sensibility. We have
                    in this account said nothing of the loss of opportunities or the decay of
                    faculties, which, whenever they happen, leave the voluptuary destitute and
                    desperate; teased by desires that can never be gratified, and the memory of
                    pleasures which must return no more. It will also be allowed by those who have
                    experienced it, and perhaps by those alone, that pleasure which is purchased by
                    the encumbrance of our fortune is purchased too dear; the pleasure never
                    compensating for the perpetual irritation of embarrassed circumstances.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193640954" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0954-0143"/>
                <p>These pleasures, after all, have their value; and as the young are always too
                    eager in the pursuit of them, the old are sometimes too remiss; that is, too
                    studious of their ease to be at the pains which they really deserve.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Secondly,</hi> Neither does happiness consist in an exemption
                    from pain, labour, care, business, suspense, molestation, and “those evils which
                    are without ;” such a state being usually attended, not with ease, but with
                    depression of spirits, a tastelessness in all our ideas, imaginary anxieties,
                    and the whole train of hypochondriacal affections. For this reason it seldom
                    answers the expectations of those who retire from their shops and
                    counting-houses to enjoy the remainder of their days in leisure and
                    tranquillity; much less of such as in a fit of chagrin shut themselves up in
                    cloisters and hermitages, or quit the world and their stations in it, for
                    solitude and repose.</p>
                <p>Where there exists a known external cause of uneasiness, the cause may be
                    removed, and the uneasiness will then cease. But those imaginary distresses
                    which men feel for want of real ones (and which are equally tormenting, and so
                    far equally reaD, as they depend upon no single or assignable subject of
                    uneasiness, so they admit oftentimes of no application or relief. Hence a
                    moderate pain, upon which the attention may fasten and spend itself, is to many
                    a refreshment; as a fit of the gout will sometimes cure the spleen. And the same
                    may be said of any moderate agitation of the mind, as a literary controversy, a
                    law-suit, a contested election, and, above all, gaming, the passion for which,
                    in men of fortune and liberal minds, is only to be accounted for on this
                    principle.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> Neither does happiness consist in greatness,
                    rank, or in elevated station.</p>
                <p>Were it true that all superiority afforded pleasure, it would follow, that by how
                    much we are the greater, that is, the more persons we are superior to, in the
                    same proportion, as far as depends upon this cause, we should be the happier;
                    but so it is, that no superiority yields any satisfaction, save that which we
                    possess or obtain over those with whom we immediately compare ourselves. The
                    shepherd perceives no pleasure in his superiority over his.dog; the farmer in
                    his superiority over the shepherd; the lord in his superiority over the farmer;
                    nor, lastly, the king in his superiority over the lord. Superiority, where there
                    is no competition, is seldom contemplated, and is a thing of which most men are
                    quite unconscious. But if the same shepherd can run, fight, or wrestle, better
                    than the peasants of his village; if the farmer can show better cattle, if he
                    keeps a better horse, or be supposed to have a longer purse, than any farmer in
                    the hundred; if the lord have more interest in an election, greater favour at
                    court, a better house, or larger estate, than any nobleman in the county; if the
                    king possess a more extensive territory, a more powerful fleet or army, a more
                    splendid establishment, more loyal subjects, or more weight and authority in
                    adjusting the affairs of nations, than any prince in Europe; in all these cases
                    the parties feel an actual satisfaction in their superiority. No superiority
                    appears to be of any account but a superiority over a rival. This, it is
                    manifest, may exist wherever rivalships do; and rivalships fall out amongst men
                    of all ranks and degrees. The object of emulation, the dignity or magnitude of
                    this object, makes no difference; as it is not what either possesses that
                    constitutes die pleasure, but what one possesses more than the other. Philosophy
                    smiles at the contempt with which the rich and great speak of the petty strifes
                    and competitions of die poor; not reflecting that these strifes and competitions
                    are just as reasonable as their own, and the pleasure which success affords the
                    same.</p>
                <p>It appears evident, then, that happiness does not consist in greatness, since
                    what are supposed to be the peculiar advantages of greatness, die pleasures of
                    ambition and superiority, are in reality common to all conditions. But whether
                    the pursuits of ambition be ever wise, whether they contribute more to the
                    happiness or misery of the pursuers, is a different question, and a question
                    concerning which we may be allowed to entertain great doubt. The pleasure of
                    success is exquisite; so also is the anxiety of the pursuit, and the pain of
                    disappointment; but, what is the worst part of the account, the pleasure is
                    short-lived. We soon cease to look back upon those whom we have left behind; new
                    contests are engaged in, new prospects unfold themselves; a succession of
                    struggles is kept up, whilst there is a rival left within the compass of our
                    views and profession; and when there is none, the pleasure terminates with the
                    pursuit.</p>
                <p>II. We have seen what happiness does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> consist in. We
                    are next to consider in what it <hi rend="italic">does</hi> consist. In the
                    conduct of life, the great matter is to know beforehand what will please us, and
                    what pleasures will hold out. So far as we know this, our choice will be
                    justified by the event. And this knowledge is more rare and difficult than at
                    first sight it may seem to be; for sometimes pleasures, which are wonderfully
                    alluring and flattering in the prospect, are found in the possession to be
                    extremely insipid, or do not hold out as we expected. At other times pleasures
                    start up which never entered into our calculation, and which we might have
                    missed by not foreseeing; and hence we have reason to believe that we actually
                    do miss many pleasures from the same cause.</p>
                <p>The original diversity of taste, capacity, and constitution, observable in the
                    human species, and the still greater variety which habit and fashion have
                    introduced, render it altogether impossible to propose any plan of happiness
                    which will succeed to all, or any method of life which is universally eligible
                    or practicable. All that can be said is, that there remains a presumption in
                    favour of those conditions of life in which men generally appear most cheerful
                    and contented; for though the apparent happiness of mankind be not always a true
                    measure of their real happiness, it is the best measure we have.</p>
                <p>Upon this principle, then, happiness appears to consist in the exercise of the
                    social affections. Those persons commonly possess good spirits who have about
                    them many objects of affection and endearment, as wife, children, kindred,
                    friends; and to the want of these may be imputed the peevishness of monks and of
                    such as lead a monastic life. Of the same nature with the indulgence of our
                    domestic affections, and equally refreshing to the spirits, is the pleasure
                    which results from acts of bounty and beneficence, exercised either in giving
                    money, or in imparting to those who want it the assistance of our skill and
                    profession.</p>
                <p>Another main article of human happiness is, the exercise of our faculties, either
                    of body or mind, in the pursuit of some engaging end. It seems to be true that
                    no plenitude of present gratification can make the possessor happy for a
                    continuance, unless he have something in reserve, something to hope for and look
                    forward to. This may be inferred from comparing the alacrity and spirits of men
                    who are engaged in any pursuit which interests them, with the dejection and <hi
                    rend="italic">ennui</hi> of almost all who are either born to so much that they
                    want nothing more, or who have <hi rend="italic">used up</hi> their
                    satisfactions too soon, and drained the sources of enjoyment. It is this
                    intolerable vacuity of mind which carries the rich and great to the race-course
                    and the gaming table, and often engages them in contests and pursuits, of which
                    the success bears no proportion to the solicitude and expense with which it is
                    sought.</p>
                <p>The question now occurs, how we are to provide ourselves with a succession of
                    pleasurable engagements. This requires two things; judgment in the choice of
                    ends adapted to our opportunities; and a command of imagination, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193640967" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0967-0144"/>so as to be able, when the
                    judgment has made choice of an end, to transfer a pleasure to the <hi
                    rend="italic">means</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> after which the end may be
                    forgotten as soon as we will. Hence those pleasures are most valuable, not which
                    are most exquisite in the fruition, but most productive of engagement and
                    activity in the pursuit.</p>
                <p>A man who is in earnest in his endeavours after the happiness of a future state,
                    has in this respect an advantage over all the world; for he has constantly
                    before his eyes an object of supreme importance, productive of perpetual
                    engagement and activity, and of which the pursuit (and this can be said of no
                    pursuit besides) lasts him to the end of his life. Yet even he must have many
                    ends beside the far end; but then they will conduct to that, be subordinate, and
                    in some way or other capable of being referred to that, and derive their
                    satisfaction, or an addition of satisfaction, from that.</p>
                <p>Engagement is every thing. The more significant, however, our engagements are,
                    the better; such as the planning of laws, institutions, manufactures, charities,
                    improvements, public works, and the endeavouring by our interest, address,
                    solicitations, and activity, to carry them into effect; or, upon a smaller
                    scale, the procuring of a maintenance and fortune for our families, by a course
                    of industry and application to our callings, which forms and gives motion to the
                    common occupations of life; training up a child; prosecuting a scheme for his
                    future establishment; making ourselves masters of a language or a science;
                    improving or managing an estate; labouring after a piece of preferment; and,
                    lastly, any engagement which is innocent is better than none, as writing a book,
                    building a house, laying out a garden, digging a fish-pond, even raising a
                    cucumber or a tulip. Whilst the mind is occupied with the objects or business
                    before it, we are commonly happy, whatever the objects or business be; when the
                    mind is absent, and the thoughts are wandering to something else besides what is
                    passing in the place in which we are, we are often miserable.</p>
                <p>The art in which the secret of human happiness in a great measure consists, is to
                    set the habits in such a manner that every change may be a change for the
                    better. The habits themselves are much the same; for whatever is made habitual
                    becomes smooth, and easy, and indifferent. The return to an old habit is
                    likewise easy, whatever the habit be. Therefore the advantage is with those
                    habits which allow of indulgence in the deviation from them. The luxurious
                    receive no greater pleasure from their dainties than the peasant does from his
                    bread and cheese; but the peasant whenever he goes abroad finds a feast, whereas
                    the epicure must be well entertained to escape disgust. Those who spend every
                    day at cards, and those who go every day to plough, pass their time much alike;
                    intent upon what they are about, wanting nothing, regretting nothing, they are
                    both in a state of ease. But then, whatever suspends the occupation of the
                    card-player distresses him, whereas to the labourer every interruption is a
                    refreshment; and this appears in the different effect which the Sabbath produces
                    upon the two, proving a day of recreation to the one, but a lamentable burden to
                    the other. The man who has learned to live alone, feels his spirits enlivened
                    whenever he enters into company, yet takes his leave of it without regret.
                    Another, who has long been accustomed to a crowd or continual succession of
                    company, experiences in company no elevation of spirits, nor any greater
                    satisfaction than what the man of a retired life finds in his chimney-corner. So
                    far their conditions are equal; but let a change of place, fortune, or
                    situation, separate the companion from his circle, his visitors, his club,
                    common-room, or coffee-house, and the difference of advantage in the choice and
                    constitution of the two habits will show itself. Solitude comes to the one
                    clothed with melancholy; to the other it brings liberty and repose. You will see
                    the one fretful and restless, ata loss how to dispose of his time, till the hour
                    comes round that he can forget himself in bed; the other easy and satisfied,
                    taking up his book or his pipe as soon as he finds , himself alone; ready to
                    admit any little amusement which casts up, or to turn his hands and attention to
                    the first business which presents itself; or content without either to sit
                    still, and let his trains of thought glide indolently through his brain, without
                    much use perhaps or pleasure, but without hankering after any thing better, and
                    without irritation. A reader who has inured himself to books of science and
                    argumentation, if a novel, a well-written pamphlet, an article of news, a
                    narrative of a curious .voyage, or the journal of a traveller, fall in his way,
                    sits down to the repast with relish, enjoys his entertainment while it lasts,
                    and can return, when it is over, to his graver reading without distaste.
                    Another, with whom nothing will go down but works of humour and pleasantry, or
                    whose curiosity must be interested by perpetual novelty, will consume a
                    bookseller’s window in half a forenoon, during which time he is rather in search
                    of diversion than diverted; and as books to his taste are few and short, and
                    rapidly read over, the stock is soon exhausted, when he is left without resource
                    from this principal supply of innocent amusement.</p>
                <p>As far as circumstances of fortune conduce to happiness, it is not the income
                    which any man possesses, but the increase of income, that affords the pleasure.
                    Two persons, of whom one begins with L.100, and advances his income to L.1000 a
                    year, and the other sets off with L.1000 and dwindles down to L.100, may, in the
                    course of their time, have the receipt and spending of the same sum of money;
                    yet their satisfaction, as far as fortune is concerned, will be very different;
                    the series and sum total of their incomes being the same, it makes a wide
                    difference which end they begin at.</p>
                <p>Happiness consists in health, understanding by health, not only freedom from
                    bodily distempers, but also that tranquillity, firmness, and alacrity of mind,
                    which we call <hi rend="italic">good spirits.</hi> For the sake of health,
                    according to this notion of it, no sacrifices can be too great. Whether it
                    requires us to relinquish lucrative situations, to abstain from favourite
                    indulgences, to control intemperate passion⅛ or to undergo tedious regimens;
                    whatever difficulties it lays us under, a man who pursues his happiness
                    rationally and resolutely will be content to submit to. When we are in perfect
                    health and spirits, we feel in ourselves a happiness independent of any
                    particular outward gratification whatever, and of which we can give no account.
                    This is an enjoyment which the Deity has annexed to life, and probably
                    constitutes in a great measure the happiness of infants and brutes, especially
                    of the lower and sedentary orders of animals, as of oysters, periwinkles, and
                    the like.</p>
                <p>The above account of human happiness will justify two conclusions, which,
                    although found in most books of morality, have seldom been supported by any
                    sufficient reasons, viz. first, that happiness is pretty equally distributed
                    amongst the different orders of civil society; and, secondly, that vice has no
                    advantage over virtue, even with respect to this world’s happiness.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
