<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-6037-0534-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOLT, Sir John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 534</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:830288">Benches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:984609">Judgments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:984572">Judgment</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:946934">Gray</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193646037" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOLT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label>, Lord
                    Chief-Justice of the Court of King’s Bench in the reign of King William, eldest
                    son of Sir Thomas Holt, serjeant-at-law, was born at Thame, Oxfordshire, in
                    1642. He entered himself at Gray’s Inn in 1658, and applied to the common law
                    with so much industry that he soon became an eminent barrister. In the reign of
                    James II. he was made recorder of London, an office which he discharged with
                    much approbation for about a year and a half; but he lost his place by refusing
                    to expound the law suitably to the king’s designs. On the arrival of the Prince
                    of Orange he was chosen a member of the Convention Parliament, which afforded an
                    opportunity of displaying his abilities; and as soon as the government was
                    settled, he was made Lord Chief Justice of the Court of King’s Bench and a privy
                    counsellor. In 1700, when Lord Somers resigned the great seal, King William
                    pressed Chief-Justice Holt to accept of it; but he replied that he never had in
                    his life but one chancery cause, which he lost, and that consequently he could
                    not think himself qualified for so great a trust. He continued as chief justice
                    for twenty-two years, during which time he obtained great reputation for
                    steadiness, integrity, and thorough knowledge in his profession. Upon great
                    occasions he asserted the law with intrepidity, though he thereby ventured to
                    incur by turns the indignation of both houses of parliament. Holt was a perfect
                    master of the common law, and as his judgment was sound, his capacity great, and
                    his understanding clear, so he possessed a firmness of mind, and a vigour of
                    resolution, which nothing could overcome when he found himself called upon to
                    assert the authority of the law, and to vindicate the purity of justice. Several
                    causes of the utmost importance, as affecting the lives, rights, liberties, and
                    property of the people, came in judgment before him, and his decisions were all
                    marked by the same high qualities. His definitions<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193646050" xml:id="kp-eb0711-6050-0535"/> were remarkable for
                    clearness and perspicuity; his arguments displayed equal powers of analysis and
                    arrangement; and he possessed the invaluable faculty of rendering perceptible
                    and obvious the natural differences of things, at the same time that he
                    discriminated, with the nicest tact, between real and fanciful resemblances. His
                    great secret consisted in the rigid and scrupulous adjustment of his premises;
                    and hence he seldom erred in his conclusions. His arguments were instructive and
                    convincing, whilst his integrity shrunk from any accommodation of judicial
                    opinion to existing interests or prejudices. His decisions are, most of them,
                    faithfully and judiciously reported by Chief-Justice Raymond, himself an eminent
                    lawyer; and his integrity and uprightness as a judge are celebrated by the
                    author of the <hi rend="italic">Tatter</hi> (No. 14), under the character of
                    Verus the magistrate. The following reports were published by him, in 1708,
                    folio, with notes: “A Report of divers Cases in Pleas of the Crown, adjudged and
                    determined in the reign of King Charles II. with directions for justices of the
                    peace and others, collected by Sir John Keyling, knight, Lord Chief Justice of
                    the Court of King’s Bench, from the original manuscript under his hand; to which
                    is added, the Report of three modern cases, viz. Armstrong and Lisle, the King
                    and Plumer, the Queen and Mawgridge.” A pretended second edition appeared in
                    1739, but the title only was new.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Holt</hi> (Saxon), a wood, by which the names of towns
                    beginning or ending with <hi rend="italic">holt,</hi> as Buck-∕zoZ∕, denote that
                    formerly there was plenty of wood in those places.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Holt,</hi> lately a village, now a town, in Wiltshire, in
                    the hundred of Bradford. It has grown up rapidly from opening a mineral spring
                    of slightly sulphureous water, which, with the establishment of suitable
                    accommodations, has attracted many scrofulous patients. It is a chapelry within
                    the parish of Bradford. The inhabitants amounted in 1811 to 1812, in 1821 to
                    2415, and in 1831 to 2519.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Holt,</hi> a pleasant market-town in the county of Norfolk,
                    giving its name to the hundred in which it is situated. It is 121 miles from
                    London, has a good market on Saturday, and an endowed grammar-school for thirty
                    boys under the patronage of the fishmongers’ company of London, who present from
                    it to a fellowship and scholarship at Sydney College, Cambridge. The inhabitants
                    amounted in 1801 to 1004, in 1811 to 1037, in 1821 to 1348, and in 1831 to
                    1622.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
