<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-5582-0499-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOADLY, Benjamin</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 499</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46688k0g">Sacraments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr70">Sin</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198506">Mark</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1103083">Sacraments</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1103074">Sacramentals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1119194">Sin</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1119629">Sins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193645582" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOADLY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Benjamin</hi></label>,
                    successively bishop of Bangor, Hereford, Salisbury, and Winchester, was born in
                    the year 1676. His first preferment in the church was to the rectory of St
                    Peter-le-Poor, and the lectureship of St Mildred’s in the Poultry. In the year
                    1706 he published some remarks on Bishop Atterbury’s sermon at the funeral of Mr
                    Bennet, in which Dr Atterbury had, in the opinion of Mr Hoadly, laid down some
                    dangerous propositions. Two years afterwards Mr Hoadly again entered the lists
                    against this formidable antagonist; and in his exceptions against a sermon
                    published by Dr Atterbury, entitled The Power of Charity to cover Sin, he
                    attacked the doctor with his usual strength of reasoning and dispassionate
                    inquiry. In 1709 another dispute arose between these two learned combatants
                    concerning the doctrine of non-resistance, occasioned by a performance of Mr
                    Hoadly’s, entitled the Measures of Obedience; some positions in which Dr
                    Atterbury endeavoured to confute in an elegant Latin sermon which he preached
                    that year before the London clergy. In this debate Mr Hoadly signalised himself
                    in so eminent a degree, that the House of Commons conferred on him a particular
                    mark of respect, by representing, in an address to the queen, the signal
                    services he had done to the cause of civil and religious liberty. The principles
                    which he espoused, however, being repugnant to the general temper <hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi> those times, drew on him the virulence of a party; yet it
                    was at this period, 1710, when, as he himself expressed it, fury seemed to be
                    let loose upon him, that Mrs Howland presented him to the rectory of Streatham
                    in Surrey, unasked, unapplied to, and without his ever having seen his
                    benefactress. Soon after the accession of King George I. Mr Hoadly was
                    consecrated to the see of Bangor; and, in 1717, having broached some opinions
                    concerning the nature of Christ’s kingdom, he again became the object of popular
                    clamour. At this juncture he was distinguished by a particular mark of the royal
                    regard, inasmuch as the convocation was successively prorogued, nor was it
                    permitted to sit, or to do any business, until that resentment had entirely
                    subsided. In 1721 he was translated to Hereford; and from thence, in 1723, to
                    Salisbury. In 1734 he was, on the demise of Dr Willis, translated to Winchester,
                    and published his Plain Account of the Sacrament; a performance which served as
                    a butt for his adversaries to shoot their arrows at, yet impartiality must own
                    it to be clear, rational, and manly, written with candour and judgment, and
                    suited to the capacity of every serious and considerate inquirer after truth.
                    His latter days were embittered by an instance of fraud and ingratitude. The
                    bishop took under his protection a French priest, who pretended to abjure his
                    religion, and who had no other recommendation than that of his necessities. In
                    return for this act of humanity, the priest found an opportunity of getting the
                    bishop’s name written by his own hand, and, causing a note of some thousand
                    pounds to be placed before it, offered it in payment. But the bishop denying it
                    to be his, it was brought before a court of justice, and was there found to be a
                    gross imposition. The ungrateful villain had now recourse to a pamphlet, in
                    which he charged the bishop with being a drunkard; and alleged that he had
                    received the note from him when he was in liquor. To this calumny the bishop
                    made a full and nervous answer, in which he exposed the man’s falsehood, and
                    solemnly averred that he was never drunk in his whole life. The world with
                    becoming ardour embraced his defence, and he had the happiness to find himself
                    perfectly acquitted even of any suspicion of such a charge. As a writer, he
                    possessed uncommon abilities. But his style was defective and cumbrous, owing to
                    the extreme length of his periods. His sermons, published in 1754 and 1755, are
                    esteemed inferior to few writings in the English language, for plainness and
                    perspicuity, energy and strength of reasoning, and a free and masterly manner.
                    In private life he was naturally facetious, easy, and complying; and, though
                    fond of company, accustomed frequently to retire for the purposes of study or
                    devotion. He was everywhere happy, <pb break="no" facs="nls:193645595"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-5595-0500"/>and particularly in his own family, where he took
                    all opportunities of instructing by his influence and example. Bishop Hoadly
                    died in 1761, aged eighty-three. Besides the works already mentioned, he wrote,
                    1. Terms of Acceptance, 8vo; 2. Reasonableness of Conformity; and 3. On the
                    Sacrament. His tracts and pamphlets are extremely numerous. A complete edition
                    of his works, in three volumes folio, was published by his son Dr John Hoadly,
                    in 1773, with a short life of the author prefixed. The appendix to this edition
                    contains some portion of his correspondence with Lady Sundon, formerly Mrs
                    Clayton, bed-chamber woman to Queen Anne, and a person to whom he appears to
                    have been chiefly indebted for his influence at court.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hoadly,</hi><hi rend="italic">Senjamin,</hi> son of the
                    former, was born in 1706, and studied at Bennet College, Cambridge, under the
                    tuition of Dr Herring, afterwards archbishop of Canterbury. He took his degree
                    in physic; and having, when young, applied himself to mathematical and
                    philosophical studies, he was admitted a member of the Royal Society. He was
                    made registrar of Hereford whilst his father filled that see, appointed
                    physician to his majesty’s household, and died at his house in Chelsea in 1757.
                    He wrote, 1. Three letters on the Organs of Respiration, 4to; 2. The Suspicious
                    Husband, a comedy; 3. Observations on a series of Electrical Experiments; 4.
                    Oratio Anniversaria, in Theatro Col. Med. Londin. ex Harvei instituto habita
                    1742.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
