<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-1682-0199-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HEBREW</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 199</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:819237">Assyrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sf6k">Talmud</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193641682" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HEBREW</label>, something relating to the Hebrew.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Hebrew</hi><hi rend="italic">Character.</hi> There
                    are two kinds of Hebrew characters; the ancient, called also the <hi
                    rend="italic">square</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and the modern, or rabbinical
                    character.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Square Hebrew</hi> takes its denomination from the figure
                    of its characters, which stand more square, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193641695" xml:id="kp-eb0711-1695-0200"/>have their angles more exact
                    and precise, than the other. This character is used in the text of Scripture,
                    and in other principal and important writings. When both this and the rabbinical
                    character are employed in the same work, the former is used for the text, and
                    the latter for the accessory part, as the gloss, notes, commentaries, and so
                    forth.</p>
                <p>The best and most beautiful characters of this kind are those copied from the
                    characters used in the Spanish manuscripts; next, those from the Italian
                    manuscripts; then those from the French; and, lastly, those of the Germans,
                    whose characters are much the same, with respect to the other genuine square
                    Hebrew characters, as the Gothic or Dutch characters are with respect to the
                    Roman.</p>
                <p>Several authors contend, that the square character is not the real ancient Hebrew
                    character, written from the beginning of the language till the time of the
                    Babylonish captivity; but that it is the Assyrian or Chaldaic character, which
                    the Jews having become accustomed to during the captivity, afterwards retained.
                    They allege, that the Jews, during their captivity, had quite disused their
                    ancient character; so that Ezra found it necessary to have the sacred books
                    transcribed into the Chaldaic square character. These authors also contend, that
                    what we call the Samaritan character is in reality the genuine ancient Hebrew.
                    Of this opinion are Scaliger, Bochart, Casaubon, Vossius, Grotius, Walton,
                    Capellus, and, amongst the ancients, Jerome and Eusebius. It is urged, that the
                    present characters are called Assyrian by the ancient Jewish writers of the
                    Talmud, and therefore must have been brought from Assyria. But to this argument
                    it is replied, that there were two sorts <hi rend="italic">of</hi> characters
                    anciently in use, viz. the sacred or present square character, and the profane
                    or civil, which we call Samaritan; and that the sacred is called Assyrian,
                    because it first began in Assyria to come into common use. It is further
                    alleged, that the Chaldaic letters, which the Jews now use, were unknown to the
                    ancient Jews before the captivity (Dan. i. 4). Moreover, it is inferred from a
                    passage in Second Kings (xvii. 28), where we learn that a Jewish priest was sent
                    to teach the Samaritans the worship of Jehovah, that on this occasion he must
                    have taught them the law; and yet no mention occurs of his teaching them the
                    language or character in which the law was then written, namely, the character
                    which the Samaritans used. But the chief argument is derived from some ancient
                    Jewish shekels, having a legend on one side, “The shekel of Israel,” and on the
                    other, “Jerusalem the holy,” both in Samaritan characters. These shekels, it is
                    said, must have been coined before the division of the two kingdoms of Judah and
                    Israel, or at least before the Assyrian captivity, because the Samaritans never
                    afterwards reckoned Jerusalem holy. On the other side, namely, in favour of the
                    primitive antiquity of the square character, are the two Buxtorfs, Leusden,
                    Calovius, Hottinger, Spanheim, Lightfoot, and others, who urge (from Matthew, V.
                    18) that ,∕o&lt;Z is really the least of the consonants in the present Hebrew,
                    whereas it is one of the largest characters in the Samaritan alphabet; but
                    Walton replies, that if our Saviour here speaks of the least letter of the
                    alphabet, we can only infer that the Chaldaic character was used, in our
                    Saviour’s time, which is not denied by those who maintain the Samaritan to be
                    the original. They also allege that the Jews were too obstinate and
                    superstitious to allow their sacred character to be altered; but if this was
                    effected under the direction and authority of Ezra, the argument will be much
                    invalidated. Further, they maintain that Ezra could not alter the ancient
                    character, because it was impossible to make the alterations in all their
                    copies. This argument, however, is contradicted by fact, since the old English
                    black letter is actually changed for the Roman. They likewise allege that Ezra
                    was not disposed to profane the sacred writings with a heathen character; but
                    this supposes that Ezra was so superstitious as to imagine that there was some
                    peculiar sanctity in the shape of the letters. Moreover, the advocates of this
                    opinion appeal to ancient coins found in Judaea, with a legend in the Chaldaic
                    orAs-syrian character. But the genuineness of these coins is much disputed. The
                    learned Souciet maintains that the ancient Hebrew character is that found on the
                    medals of Simon, and others, commonly called Samaritan medals, but which, he
                    affirms, were really Hebrew medals, struck by the Jews, and not by the
                    Samaritans.</p>
                <p>Buxtorf endeavours to reconcile these two opinions by producing a variety of
                    passages from the Rabbin to prove that both these characters were anciently
                    used; the present square character being that in which the tables of the law,
                    and the copy deposited in the ark, were written, and the other character being
                    used in the copies of the law which were written for private and common use, and
                    in civil affairs in general; and that after the captivity, Ezra ordered the
                    former to be used by the Jews on all occasions, leaving the latter to the
                    Samaritans and apostates. But it can scarcely be allowed by any who consider the
                    difference between the Chaldaic and Samaritan characters, with respect to
                    convenience and beauty, that they were ever used at the same time. After all, it
                    is of no great moment which of these, or whether either of them, formed the
                    original characters; since it appears that no change of the words has arisen
                    from the manner of writing them, because the Samaritan and Jewish Pentateuch
                    almost invariably agree. It is most probable that the form of these characters
                    has varied at different periods. This appears from the testimony of Montfaucon
                    <hi rend="italic">{Hexapla Origenis,</hi> vol. i. p. 22), and is implied in Dr
                    Kennicot’s making the characters in which manuscripts are written one test of
                    their age.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Modern,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Rabbinical,</hi> is a
                    good, neat character, formed of the square Hebrew, by rounding it, and
                    retrenching most of the angles or corners of the letters, to render it more easy
                    and flowing. The letters used by the Germans are very different from the
                    rabbinical character employed everywhere else, though all formed alike from the
                    square character, but in a more slovenly manner than the rest. The Rabbin
                    frequently make use either of their own, or the square Hebrew character, to
                    write the modern languages in. There are even books in the vulgar tongues
                    printed in Hebrew characters, instances of which are seen in the king’s library
                    at Paris.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Hebrew</hi><hi rend="italic">Language,</hi> that
                    spoken by the Hebrews, and in which the books of the Old Testament are
                    written.</p>
                <p>The books of the Old Testament are the only compositions to be found, in all
                    antiquity, written in pure Hebrew; and the language of many of them is extremely
                    sublime. It appears; perfectly regular, particularly in its conjugations;
                    indeed, properly speaking, it has but one conjugation, but this is varied in
                    each seven or eight different ways, which has the effect of so many different
                    conjugations, and affords a great variety of expressions to represent by a
                    single word the different modifications of a verb, and many ideas which in the
                    modern and in many of the ancient and learned languages cannot be expressed
                    without a periphrasis.</p>
                <p>The primitive words, which are called <hi rend="italic">roots,</hi> have seldom
                    more than three letters or two syllables.</p>
                <p>In this language there are twenty-two letters, only five of which are usually
                    reckoned vowels; but then each vowel is divided into two, a long and a short;
                    the sound of the former being somewhat grave and long, and that of the latter
                    short and acute. It must however be remarked, that the two last vowels have
                    sounds which differ in other respects besides quantity and a greater or less
                    elevation. To these ten or twelve vowels may be added others, called <hi
                    rend="italic">semi-vowels,</hi> which serve to connect the consonants, and to
                    render easier the transitions from one to another. The <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193641708" xml:id="kp-eb0711-1708-0201"/>number of accents in this
                    language is prodigious. Of these ' there are nearly forty, the use of some of
                    which, notwithstanding all the inquiries of the learned, is not yet perfectly
                    known. We know, in general, that they serve to distinguish the sentences, like
                    the points called commas, semicoons, and colons in our language; to determine
                    the quantity of the syllables; and to mark the tone with which they are to be
                    spoken or sung. It is no wonder, then, that there are more accents in the Hebrew
                    than in other languages, since they perform three offices, which in other
                    languages are called by different names.</p>
                <p>As we have no Hebrew but that which is contained in the Scripture, the language
                    wants a great many words; not only because in those primitive times languages
                    were not so copious as at present, but also on this account, that the inspired
                    writers had no occasion to mention many of the terms which might be in use in
                    the language.</p>
                <p>The Chaldaic, Syriac, and Ethiopic languages, are by some held to be dialects of
                    the Hebrew; as the French, Italian, and Spanish, are dialects of the Latin. It
                    has been supposed by many learned men, that the Hebrew characters or letters
                    were often used hieroglyphically, and that each had its several distinct sense
                    understood as a hieroglyphic. Neumann, who seems to have taken infinite pains to
                    find out the secret meaning of these letters, gives the following explication;
                    x, <hi rend="italic">aleph,</hi> he says, is a character denoting motion,
                    readiness, and activity; ă, <hi rend="italic">beth,</hi> signifies matter, body,
                    substance, thing, also place, space, or capacity, and lastly, in, within, or
                    contained; 2, <hi rend="italic">ghimel,</hi> stands for flexion, bending, or
                    obliquity of any kind; 1, <hi rend="italic">dhaleth,</hi> signifies any
                    protrusion made from without, or any promotion of any kind; rτ, <hi
                    rend="italic">he,</hi> stands for the presence or demonstrative essence of
                    anything; ι, <hi rend="italic">vau,</hi> stands for copulation, or the growing
                    together of things; τ, <hi rend="italic">tsain,</hi> expresses vehement
                    protrusion and violent compression, such as is occasioned by at once violently
                    discharging and constringing a thing, and sometimes the straitening of any
                    figure into a narrow point at the end; π, <hi rend="italic">cheth,</hi>
                    expresses association, society, or any kind of composition or combination of
                    things; ta, <hi rend="italic">teth,</hi> stands for the withdrawing, drawing
                    back, or recession of any thing; <hi rend="italic">',jod,</hi> signifies
                    extension and length, whether in matter or in time; 2, <hi rend="italic"
                    >caph,</hi> expresses a turning, incurvation, or concavity , ⅛, <hi
                    rend="italic">lamech,</hi> stands for an addition, accession, impulse, or
                    adversation, and sometimes for pressure; a, <hi rend="italic">mem,</hi>
                    expresses amplitude, or the amplifying any thing in whatever sense, and in
                    regard to contiguous qualities it also signifies the adding length, breadth, and
                    circumference, lastly, multitude; 3, <hi rend="italic">nun,</hi> signifies the
                    propagation of one thing from another, or of the same thing from one person to
                    another; 0, <hi rend="italic">samech,</hi> expresses cincture and coarctation;
                    V, <hi rend="italic">ain,</hi> stands for observation, objection, or obviation;
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">ð,</hi><hi rend="italic">pe</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >phe,</hi> stands for a crookedness or an angle of any figure; -, <hi
                    rend="italic">tsadde,</hi> expresses contiguity and close succession; ρ, <hi
                    rend="italic">hoph,</hi> expresses a circuit or ambit; ι, <hi rend="italic"
                    >resh,</hi> expresses the egress of any thing, as also the exterior part of a
                    thing, and the extremity or end of any thing; <hi rend="italic">υ, schin</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">sin,</hi> signifies the number three, or the third degree, or
                    the utmost perfection of any thing; and n, <hi rend="italic">tau,</hi> expresses
                    a sequel, continuation, or succession of any thing.</p>
                <p>As, according to this explication, the several letters of the Hebrew alphabet
                    separately convey ideas of motion, matter, space, and several modifications of
                    matter, space, and motion; it follows that a language, the words of which are
                    composed of such expressive characters, must necessarily be of all languages the
                    most perfect and expressive; as the words formed of such letters, according to
                    their determinate separate significations, must convey the idea of all the
                    matters contained in the sense of the several characters, and be at once a name
                    and a definition, or succinct description, of the subject; and all things
                    material as well as spiritual, all objects in the natural and moral world, must
                    be known as soon as their names are known, and their separate letters
                    considered.</p>
                <p>The words <hi rend="italic">urirn</hi> and <hi rend="italic">thummim</hi> are
                    thus easily explained, and found to be perhaps the most apposite and expressive
                    words that ever were formed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rabbinical</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Modern</hi><hi
                    rend="italic smallcaps"> Hebrew,</hi> is the language used by the Rabbin in the
                    writings they have composed. Its basis or body is the Hebrew and Chaldaic, with
                    various alterations in the words of these two languages, the meanings of which
                    they have considerably enlarged and extended. They have borrowed freely from the
                    Arabic; and the rest is composed of words and expressions, chiefly from the
                    Greek, some from the Latin, and others from the modern tongues, particularly
                    that spoken in the place where each Rabbi lived or wrote.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
