<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-8091-0692-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HOSPITAL, or Hôpital, Michel de l’</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 692</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rj8h">Berries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830788">Berries</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:843075">Butlers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193648091" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HOSPITAL, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Hôpital</hi>, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Michel de l’</hi></label>, chancellor of France, and one of the
                    most illustrious magistrates of modern times, was born at Aigueperse, in
                    Auvergne, in the year 1505. His father, John de ľHôpital, who was at once
                    physician and counsellor to the Constable of Bourbon, sent him to study law,
                    first at Toulouse, and afterwards at Padua, the legal school of which then
                    enjoyed great celebrity. In that age jurisprudence was the principal science
                    cultivated, and no one could aspire to any employment without having studied it
                    profoundly. L’Hôpital, although he had already acquired the elements of this
                    science in France, spent six years at Padua in improving himself therein; he
                    also applied himself to the study of the belles-lettres, in which he made rapid
                    advances, and at the same time cultivated the Greek and the Latin languages,
                    with which he rendered himself perfectly familiar. Having completed his studies,
                    and finding his prospects clouded by the death of the Cardinal de Grammont, who
                    had induced him to return to France, and upon whose credit and influence he had
                    founded his hopes of preferment, he entered himself of the bar at Paris. In this
                    profession, his merit and virtue were soon appreciated. At the end of three
                    years, John Morin, criminal lieutenant, a person famous in the martyrology of
                    the Protestants, on account of the severity with which he enforced the laws
                    enacted against them, gave L’Hôpital his daughter in marriage, and at the same
                    time conferred upon him the office of counsellor to the parliament of Paris as
                    her dowry.</p>
                <p>In this situation, which he held during twelve years, the toleration he displayed
                    formed a remarkable contrast to the unrelenting severity by which his
                    father-in-law had rendered himself but too celebrated. When L’Hôpital entered
                    the parliament, that once illustrious body had much degenerated, owing to the
                    venality which the misfortunes of the time had forced Francis I. to introduce,
                    or at least to overlook. A witness of this corruption, L’Hôpital deplored its
                    consequences, and, in concert with some old magistrates who still remained,
                    endeavoured to set an example of assiduity and application, to a crowd of
                    inexperienced young men, who, by venality, had obtained admission into the
                    parliament, and who had no other title to that honour but the money they had
                    paid for it. L’Hôpital was long <pb break="no" facs="nls:193648104"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-8104-0693"/>cited as a model in the magistracy. He made it a
                    rule to listen with patience, to interrupt no one, to express himself as
                    concisely as possible, and to oppose all unnecessary delays; he was also
                    punctual in his attendance in court, where he generally remained until the
                    business of the day had been regularly gone through, and always rose with
                    reluctance, however late, if any portion of it remained unattended to. In short,
                    he was a laborious and conscientious judge, who to great talents united the most
                    steady and persevering industry. The vacations made no material change in his
                    way of life; his pursuits were indeed different, but his application was the
                    same; the perusal of the great writers of antiquity, the study of French
                    history, and the reading of the Holy Scriptures, each in its turn formed the
                    occupation of his leisure time. “There is nothing frivolous in my amusements,”
                    says he, in one of his letters; “sometimes Xenophon is the companion of my
                    walks; sometimes the divine Plato regales me with the discourses of Socrates.
                    History and poetry have their turns; but my chief delight is in the sacred
                    writings.”</p>
                <p>The next appointment which L’Hôpital received was that conferred upon him by
                    Henri II. of envoy or ambassador to the council of Trent, which was then sitting
                    at Bologna. But having soon grown tired of the inactivity to which he found
                    himself reduced, he was, at his own desire, recalled, and, upon his return,
                    experienced some coldness on the part of the court, which did not altogether
                    relish his evident disinclination to assist in the proceedings of that famous
                    council. This obscuration, however, proved only temporary, for ere long he was
                    restored to the royal favour, and appointed master of the requests. Nor did his
                    promotion stop here. In the beginning of 1554, he was constituted director and
                    superintendent of the royal finances in the chamber of accounts. At this time
                    the finances required a guardian at once vigilant and faithful. Enormous abuses
                    prevailed in the whole fiscal administration. On the one hand there existed
                    profusion without limits, and on the other malversation without shame. Scarcely
                    a third, or even a fourth part of the sums collected, ever reached the royal
                    treasury; the people were exposed to the most grinding exactions, yet the
                    revenue was in a state of gradual decline. To put an end to these disorders,
                    L’Hôpital revived the ancient laws which had fallen into desuetude; he struck
                    terror into defaulters by some examples of wholesome severity; he refused to
                    sanction any expenditure except for the immediate purposes of the state; he
                    defied the enmity of that numerous and vindictive class whose dishonest gains he
                    had destroyed; and he acted with so much personal disinterestedness, that, after
                    having been five years in office, he was unable to give a portion to his
                    daughter, and the deficiency was supplied by the liberality of the
                    sovereign.</p>
                <p>After the fatal accident which, in 1559, put an end to the life of the king, the
                    Cardinal de Lorraine, then at the head of affairs, introduced L’Hôpital into the
                    council of state; butas one of the articles of the treaty of Chateau-Cambré-sis
                    had provided that the Duchess of Berri, his benefactress, should espouse
                    Emanuel-Philibert, Duke of Savoy, he was appointed to conduct that princess into
                    Piedmont, whither he attended her in the capacity of chancellor. The distracted
                    situation of France, however, soon made it necessary to recall a man of such
                    undaunted firmness and nflexible integrity. In the midst of faction, turbulence,
                    and confusion, when the passions of men appeared, like the evil spirits, to have
                    been for a season unchained, he was advanced to the office of chancellor of
                    France, and in this elevated station conducted himself like a philosopher and a
                    hero, superior alike to weakness and to fear. At this period the destruction of
                    the Protestants had been determined on; it was resolved to leave them no
                    alternative but abjuration or death; and it was even in contemplation to
                    establish in France the redoubtable tribunal of the inquisition. The new
                    chancellor durst not attack this project in front, without compromising himself
                    with the governing party; but he sought indirectly to defeat the odious design,
                    and by the edict of Romorantin, which declared the crime of heresy to be
                    cognisable only by the ecclesiastical judge, he ultimately accomplished his
                    beneficent design, and thus decided the clergy to abandon all idea of
                    establishing the inquisition, which, they knew, would be powerless when deprived
                    of the aid of the secular arm. Upon all occasions, indeed, he was the advocate
                    of mercy and reconciliation, and a declared enemy to persecution on account of
                    religion; and hence the more bigoted Romanists, offended at his wisdom and
                    moderation, accused him of being a concealed Protestant, forgetting that by such
                    suspicions and accusations they paid the highest compliments to the spirit of
                    that faith which they were so desirous to eradicate. With a man of such
                    character, ability, and firmness at the head of affairs, it was hopeless to
                    attempt to carry through the violent measures which were already contemplated;
                    yet when the question of giving him a successor came to be seriously agitated,
                    Catherine of Medicis found herself involved in very great perplexity. The
                    ancient relations of L’Hôpital with the House of Lorraine; the estimation in
                    which he was universally held, his known love of his country, which, in his
                    mind, absorbed all other affections; and the difficulty of finding any one to
                    fill his place, who would not sink into insignificance or contempt in comparison
                    with this truly great man—were serious obstacles to his removal: but as nothing
                    could induce him to abandon or change the pacific character of his measures, all
                    other considerations were at length disregarded, and the queen excluded him from
                    the council of war, upon which he immediately withdrew to his country-house at
                    Vignay, near Estampes.</p>
                <p>His exclusion from the council was accompanied with insult. The Constable of
                    Montmorency told him that a man of his profession, a civilian, ought not to
                    intermeddle in what related to war. “That is a subject,” said the constable, “on
                    which you are not qualified to give advice.” “True,” replied the chancellor, “I
                    do not know how to make war, but <hi rend="italic">I know when it is
                    necessary”</hi> Several days after his retirement from office, when the seals
                    were demanded of him, he resigned them without regret, observing that the
                    affairs of the world were too corrupt for him to meddle with them. He spent his
                    time in lettered ease, amusing himself with writing Latin poetry, and enjoying
                    the society of some select friends, until his peace was broken by the bloody
                    tragedy of St Bartholomew, which, with his usual sagacity, he had foreseen. Of
                    this barbarous and inexpiable massacre the judgment he pronounced has been
                    ratified by posterity. He was himself near becoming one of its victims. The
                    inhabitants of the country had risen, and were devastating the fields, and
                    dragging the farmers in chains towards the city. But the queen, anxious about
                    his fate, sent a detachment of cavalry for his protection. The sudden apparition
                    of this troop, whose destination was unknown, produced great consternation in
                    his house, which was open on all sides. He was asked by the inmates if they
                    would close the gates. “No, no,” said he; “if the small gate will not admit
                    them, throw open the large one.” When informed that the persons who prepared the
                    lists of proscription had pardoned him the opposition which he had always given
                    to their projects; “I did not know,” replied he coldly, “that I had done any
                    thing to deserve either pardon or death.” But what most deeply affected
                    L’Hôpital on this mournful occasion, was the danger to which his daughter, who
                    happened to be in Paris, was in consequence exposed. She was saved by the
                    interference of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193648117" xml:id="kp-eb0711-8117-0694"
                    />Anne d’Este, duchess of Guise, whom L’Hôpital thanked for this signal service,
                    in an epistle overflowing with the warmest feelings of paternal gratitude. These
                    cruel events, however, deeply affected his health and spirits, and he died at
                    Vignay, on the 13th of March 1573, at the age of sixty-eight, and less than one
                    year after the massacre.</p>
                <p>“L’Hôpital,” says Brantôme, “was the greatest, worthiest, and most learned
                    chancellor that was ever known in France. His large white beard, pale
                    countenance, and austere manner, made all who saw him think they beheld a true
                    portrait of St Jerome, and, in fact, he was called St Jerome by the courtiers.
                    All orders of men feared him, particularly the members of the courts of justice;
                    and when he examined them on their lives, their discharge of their duties, their
                    capacities or their knowledge, and particularly when he examined candidates for
                    offices, and found them deficient, he made them feel it. He was profoundly
                    versed in polite learning, very eloquent, and an excellent poet. His severity
                    was never ill natured; he made due allowance for the imperfections of human
                    nature; he was always equal and firm. After his death, his very enemies
                    acknowledged that he was the greatest magistrate whom France had known, and that
                    they did not expect to see such another.” The productions of L’Hôpital are, 1.
                    Latin Poems; 2. Speeches delivered at the Meeting of the States at Orleans; 3.
                    <hi rend="italic">Mémoires, contenant plusieurs Traités de Paix,</hi> &amp;c.,
                    from 1551 to 1560, Cologne, 1672, in 12mo. A work which he had undertaken on law
                    is lost; and it is said that he had also projected a history of his own time, on
                    the model of the ancient historians; but of this no part appears to have been
                    executed. In 1807, Μ. Bernardi published his <hi rend="italic">Essai sur
                    la</hi><hi rend="italic">Vie,</hi><hi rend="italic">les Ecrits, et les Loix de
                    Michel de</hi><hi rend="italic">Ĩ</hi><hi rend="italic">Hôpital,</hi> in one
                    volume 8vo, from which and other documents Mr Charles Butler published his Essay
                    on the Life of L’Hôpital, principally with the view of exhibiting him as a
                    friend of toleration. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Hospital,</hi><hi rend="italic">William-Hr</hi><hi rend="italic">ancis-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Antony, Marquis of,</hi> an eminent French mathematician, was born
                    of an ancient family in 1661. He was a geometrician almost from his infancy; for
                    one day being at the Duke of Rohan’s, where some able mathematicians were
                    speaking of a problem of Pascal’s which appeared to them extremely difficult, he
                    ventured to say that he believed he could solve it. They were amazed at such
                    presumption in a boy of fifteen, for he was then no more; nevertheless, in a few
                    days he sent them the solution. He entered early into the army, and rose to be a
                    captain of horse; but being extremely shortsighted, and exposed on that account
                    to perpetual inconveniences and errors, he at length quitted the army, and
                    applied himself entirely to his favourite pursuit. He contracted a friendship
                    for Malebranche, whose opinion he followed upon all occasions. In 1693 he was
                    received as an honorary member of the Academy of Sciences at Paris; and he
                    published a work upon Sir Isaac Newton’s calculations, entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">L’Analyse des Infinimens Petits.</hi> He was the first in France
                    who wrote upon this subject, and on this account was regarded almost as a
                    prodigy. He engaged afterwards in another work of the mathematical kind, in
                    which he included <hi rend="italic">Les Sections</hi><hi rend="italic">Coniques,
                    les Lieux Géométriques,</hi><hi rend="italic">la Construction des
                    Equations,</hi><hi rend="italic">et Une Théorie des Courbes Mécaniques;</hi> but
                    a little before he had finished it, he was seized with a fever, of which he died
                    on the 2d of February 1704, at the age of forty-three. It was published after
                    his death.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
