<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-8949-0758-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HURD, Richard</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 758</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193648949" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HURD, <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard</hi></label>, an eminent
                    and learned English prelate, was born at Congreve, in the parish of Penkrich,
                    Staffordshire, on the 13th of January 1720. He was the second son of John and
                    Hannah Hurd, whom he describes as “plain, honest, and good people, farmers, but
                    of a turn of mind that might have honoured any rank and any condition and they
                    appear to have been solicitous to give their son the best and most liberal
                    education. Young Hurd received his elementary education at the grammarschool of
                    Brerewood, and, in 1733, was admitted of Emmanuel College, Cambridge, though he
                    did not go to reside there until a year or two afterwards. He took the degree of
                    bachelor of arts in 1739, and that of master in 1742; the same year he was
                    elected a fellow, and ordained deacon in St Paul s Cathedral, London; and in
                    1744 he was admitted into priest’s orders at Cambridge. Dr Hurd’s first literary
                    production was Remarks on Weston’s <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Rejection
                    of the Christian Miracles by the Heathens,</hi> published in 1746; and, in 1748,
                    upon the conclusion of the peace of Aix-la-Chapelle, he contributed some verses
                    to the university collection for 1749. In the same year he took the degree of
                    bachelor of divinity, and published his Commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Ars
                    Poetica</hi> of Horace, in which he laboured to prove that the Roman poet has
                    treated his subject with systematic order and the strictest method; an idea
                    which has been strenuously combated by several eminent critics. In the preface
                    to this Commentary he took occasion to compliment Warburton in a manner which
                    won him the favour of that learned dogmatist, and procured for him a return in
                    kind in the bishop’s edition of Pope’s works, where Hurd’s Commentary is spoken
                    of in terms of the highest approbation. This commerce of flattery gave rise to
                    an intimacy between these persons, which continued unbroken during their lives,
                    and is supposed to have exercised considerable influence on the opinions of
                    Hurd, who was long considered as the first scholar in what has been termed the
                    Warburtonian school. This Commentary was reprinted in 1757, with the addition of
                    two Dissertations, one on the drama, the other on poetical imitation, and a
                    letter to Mr Mason on the Marks of Imitation; in 1765, a fourth edition,
                    corrected and enlarged, was published in three vols. 8vo, with a third
                    Dissertation on the idea of universal poetry; and the whole was again reprinted
                    in 1776. This work fully established the reputation of Hurd as an elegant and
                    acute, if not always a sound and judicious critic. In May 1750, he was appointed
                    by Sherlock, bishop of London, one of the Whitehall preachers. About this period
                    the university of Cambridge was disturbed by internal divisions, occasioned by
                    an exercise of discipline against some of its members who had been wanting in
                    respect towards those invested with authority. The delinquents having refused to
                    submit to the punishment awarded, and appealed from the vice-chancellor’s
                    jurisdiction to that of the senate, the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193648962"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-8962-0759"/>right of the university, and those to whom its
                    power was delegated, became thus a subject of discussion, and several pamphlets
                    appeared on both sides of the question. Amongst those who signalized themselves
                    on this occasion may be mentioned Hurd, who wrote The Opinion of an eminent
                    Lawyer (the Earl of Hardwicke) concerning the Right of Appeal from the
                    Vice-Chancellor of Cambridge to the Senate, supported by a short historical
                    account of the Jurisdiction of the University; in answer to a pamphlet, entitled
                    <hi rend="italic">An Inquiry into the Right of Appeal from the Vice
                    Chancellor,</hi> 1751, in 8vo; a production which passed through three editions,
                    and was defended in a Letter to the Author of a Further Inquiry, 1752, in 8vo,
                    by whom it had been attacked. In 1751, he published a Commentary on the Epistle
                    to Augustus; in 1753, a new edition of both commentaries, with a dedication to
                    Warburton; and the same year two occasional sermons, one preached at the Norwich
                    assizes, and the other in behalf of the charity schools at Cambridge, but
                    neither of which has been retained in his works. The friendship he had formed
                    with Warburton continued to increase by mutual good offices; and, in 1755, Hurd
                    eagerly embraced an opportunity which offered of evincing the warmth of his
                    attachment. Dr Jortin having, in his Dissertations, spoken of Warburton with
                    less deference and submission than the exactions of an overbearing and insolent
                    superiority could easily tolerate, Hurd wrote a bitter satire, entitled the
                    Delicacy of Friendship, a seventh Dissertation, addressed to the author of the
                    sixth, 1755, in 8vo; a production in which he was betrayed into too close an
                    imitation of Warburton’s manner, and displayed a degree of warmth far beyond any
                    thing that the supposed offence could either call for or justify. Hurd
                    accordingly took pains to suppress the pamphlet; but, in 1788, it was
                    republished in a volume entitled Tracts by Warburton and a Warburtonian. Hurd
                    continued to reside at Cambridge, in learned retirement, if not learned ease,
                    until 1756, when, on the death of Dr Arnold, he succeeded, as senior fellow of
                    Emmanuel College, to the rectory of Thurcaston, to which he was instituted in
                    1757, and where, having entered into residence, he continued to prosecute his
                    studies, which were principally confined to subjects of elegant literature. The
                    Remarks on Hume’s Essay on the Natural History <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> of
                    Religion appeared soon afterwards. But Warburton appears to have had the chief
                    hand in the composition of that tract, which, accordingly, we find republished
                    by Hurd in the quarto edition of that prelate’s works, and enumerated in the
                    list of them. It appears to have occasioned some uneasiness to Hume, who, in the
                    account of his own life, notices it with a degree of acrimony quite unusual in
                    his compositions. In 1759, Hurd published a volume of Dialogues on Sincerity,
                    Retirement, the Golden Age of Elizabeth, and the Constitution of the English
                    Government; and this was followed by his Letters on Chivalry and Romance, which,
                    with his Dialogues on Foreign Travel, were republished in the year 1765, with
                    the author’s name, and a preface on dialogue writing. In the preceding year, he
                    published another of those zealous tracts in vindication of Warburton, which
                    have added little to his fame as a writer, and procured him the reputation of an
                    illiberal and discourteous polemic. It was entitled a “Letter to the Reverend Dr
                    Thomas Leland, in which his late <hi rend="italic">Dissertation on the
                    Principles of Human doquence</hi> is criticised, and the Bishop of Gloucester’s
                    idea of the nature and character of an inspired language, as delivered in his
                    Lordship’s <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of Grace,</hi> is vindicated from all the
                    objections of the learned author of the Dissertation.” This, with Hurd’s other
                    controversial tracts, has been republished in the eighth volume of the
                    authorized edition of his works, where we find prefixed to it, by way of
                    advertisement, the following lines, written by the author not long before his
                    death: “The controversial tracts which make up this volume were written and
                    published by the author at different times, as opportunity imited, or occasion
                    required. Some sharpness of style may be objected to them, in regard to which he
                    apologises for himself in the words of the poet:</p>
                <p>Me quoque pectoris Tentavit in dulci juventa Fervor nunc ego mitibus Mutare
                    quaero tristia.”</p>
                <p>In 1762, the sinecure rectory of Folkton was conferred on him by Lord Chancellor
                    Northmgton; in 1765, he was chosen preacher of Lincoln’s Inn; and in August
                    1767, he was collated to the archdeaconry of Gloucester by Bishop Warburton. In
                    July 1768, he was admitted doctor of divinity at Cambridge; the same day he was
                    appointed to open the lecture founded by Warburton for the illustration of the
                    prophecies; and the Twelve Discourses which he preached there were published in
                    1772, under the title of an Introduction to the Study of the Prophecies
                    concerning the Christian church, and in particular concerning the church of
                    Papal Rome. This volume drew from Gibbon, under a fictitious name, a private
                    letter to the author respecting the book of Daniel, which Dr Hurd answered; but
                    it was not until the appearance of the historian’s Miscellaneous Works, in which
                    Dr Hurd’s answer was printed, that the latter knew the name of his
                    correspondent. In 1769, he published the Select Works of Abraham Cowley, with a
                    preface and notes, in two vols. 8vo; an edition which has been condemned as
                    interfering with the totality of Cowley’s works, and which certainly is not the
                    most judicious of Dr Hurd’s undertakings. In 1775, he was, by the recommendation
                    of Lord Mansfield, promoted to the bishopric of Lichfield and Coventry,
                    consecrated early in that year, and, soon after entering on the episcopal
                    office, he delivered a charge to the clergy of the diocese, as well as a Fast
                    Sermon for “the American rebellion,” which was preached before the House of
                    Lords. In May 1781, Bishop Hurd received a gracious message from his majesty,
                    conveying to him an offer of the see of Worcester, with the clerkship of the
                    closet, both of which he accepted. Nor did his majesty’s kindness stop here.
                    For, on the death of Dr Cornwallis, in the year 1783, he was offered the
                    archiepiscopal see of Canterbury, with many gracious expressions, and even
                    pressed to accept it; but he humbly begged leave to decline it, “as a charge not
                    suited to his temper and talents, and much too heavy for him to sustain in these
                    times,” alluding, we presume, to the distractions arising from the conflict of
                    political parties. In 1788, Hurd published a complete edition of the works of
                    Warburton, in seven vols. 4to; but the Life did not appear until 1795, when it
                    came forth under the title of a Discourse by way of General Preface to the
                    quarto edition of Bishop Warburton’s works, containing some account of the Life,
                    Writings, and Character of the Author. This work excited considerable attention,
                    and the style is equally remarkable for its purity and elegance; but the stream
                    of panegyric is too uniform not to subject the author to the suspicion of
                    long-confirmed prejudices. Even the admirers of Warburton would have been
                    content with less laborious efforts to magnify him at the expense of all his
                    contemporaries; and, conscious that imperfection is the common lot of all men,
                    they conceived that age and reflection should have abated, if not wholly
                    extinguished, the unworthy animosities of times gone by. But in all this they
                    were disappointed. Hurd was a true di aeiple of the great dogmatist; and hence
                    it was with regret they observed the worst characteristics of Warburton, his
                    inveterate dislikes, his fierce contempt, and his sneering rancour, still
                    employed to perpetuate his personal antipathies, and employed too against such
                    men as Secker and Loŵth. If these were the feelings <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193648975" xml:id="kp-eb0711-8975-0760"/>of the friends who venerated
                    Warburton and esteemed Hurd, others, who never had much attachment to the Bishop
                    of Gloucester or his school, found little difficulty in accumulating against his
                    biographer charges of gross partiality and illiberal abuse. The remainder of
                    Hurd’s life appears to have been spent in the discharge of his episcopal duties,
                    and in studious retirement. He died on the 28th of May 1808, being then in his
                    eighty-ninth year. As a writer, his taste, learning, and talents have been
                    universally acknowledged; and though, like his master, contemptuous and
                    intolerant, he was nevertheless shrewd, ingenious, and original. In his private
                    character he is said to have been in all respects amiable; nor were the
                    relations of life in any degree embittered by the gall and wormwood which so
                    frequently flowed from his pen. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
