<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0711-6063-0536-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">HOME, Henry</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 536</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:959074">Home</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1353235">Homes</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193646063" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">HOME, <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi></label>, Lord Kames, an
                    eminent Scottish lawyer, and author of many celebrated works on various
                    subjects, was descended of an ancient family, and born in Berwickshire in the
                    year 1696. In his early youth he was lively, and eager in the acquisition of
                    knowledge. He never attended a public school, but was instructed in the ancient
                    and modern languages, as well as in several branches or mathematics, and the
                    arts necessarily connected with that science, by Mr Wingate, a man of
                    considerable parts and learning, who spent many years as preceptor or private
                    tutor to young Home.</p><p>After studying at the university of Edinburgh, the civil law, and the municipal
                    jurisprudence of his own country, Mr Home early perceived that a knowledge of
                    these alone was not sufficient to form an accomplished lawyer. An acquaintance
                    with the forms and practical business of courts, and especially of the supreme
                    court, as a member of which he was to seek for fame and emolument, he considered
                    as essentially necessary to qualify him to become a finished bar- 1 ister. He
                    accordingly attended for some time the chamber of a writer to the signet, where
                    he had an opportunity of learning the styles of legal deeds, and the modes of
                    conducting different species of business. This wise step, independently of his
                    great genius and unwearied application, procured him, after his admission to the
                    bar, peculiar respect from the court, and proportional employment in his
                    profession of advocate. These qualifications, together with the strength and
                    vivacity of his natural abilities, soon rendered him an ornament of the Scottish
                    bar; and, on the 2d day of February 1752, he was advanced to the bench as one of
                    the judges of the Court of Session, under the assumed title of Lord Kames.</p><p>Before this period, however, notwithstanding the unavoidable labours of his
                    profession, Mr Home had favoured the world with several useful and ingenious
                    works. In the year 1728 he published Remarkable Decisions of the Court of
                    Session from 1716 to 1728, in one volume folio. In 1732 appeared Essays upon
                    several subjects in law, viz. <hi rend="italic">Jus</hi><hi rend="italic">tertii, Beneficium cedendarum Actionum, Vinco Vincentem,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Prescription,</hi> in one volume 8vo. The first produce of his
                    genius excited not only the attention, but the admiration of the judges, and of
                    all the other members of the College of Justice. This work was succeeded, in the
                    year 1741, by Decisions of the Court of Session from its first institution to
                    the year 1740, abridged and digested under proper heads, in the form of a
                    Dictionary, in two volumes folio; a very laborious work, and of the greatest
                    utility to every practical lawyer. In 1747 appeared Essays upon several subjects
                    concerning British antiquities, viz. 1. Introduction of the Feudal Law into
                    Scotland; 2. Constitution of Parliament; 3. Honour, Dignity; and, 4. Succession
                    or Descent, with an appendix upon hereditary and indefeasible right, composed in
                    1745, and published 1747, one vol. 8vo. Though not in the order of time, we
                    shall continue the list of all our author’s writings on law, before we proceed
                    to his productions on other subjects. In 1757, he published the Statute Law of
                    Scotland Abridged, with historical notes, in one volume 8vo; a most useful and
                    laborious work. In the year 1759, he presented to the public a new and very
                    interesting work under the title of Historical Law Tracts, in two volumes 8vo.
                    In 1760, he published, in one volume folio, the Principles of Equity; a work
                    which shows both the fertility of the author’s genius and his indefatigable
                    application. In 1766, he gave to the public another volume in folio of
                    Remarkable Decisions of the Court of Session from 1730 to 1752. In 1777,
                    appeared his Elucidations respecting the Common and Statute Law of Scotland, in
                    one volume 8vo. This book contains many curious and interesting remarks upon
                    some intricate and dubious points which occur in the law of Scotland. In 1780,
                    he published a volume in folio of Select Decisions of the Court of Session from
                    1752 to 1768.</p><p>But Lord Kames’s mind was much inclined to metaphysical disquisitions. When a
                    young man, he had corresponded with Berkeley bishop of Cloyne, Dr Butler bishop
                    of Durham, Dr Samuel Clarke, and many other ingenious and learned men both in
                    Britain and Ireland. The year 1751 gave birth to the first fruits of his
                    lordship’s metaphysical studies, in an octavo volume, published under the title
                    of Essays on the Principles of Morality and Natural Religion. It contained, in
                    more explicit terms than perhaps any other work of a religious theist then known
                    in Scotland, a statement of the doctrine of philosophical necessity, than which
                    it is scarcely possible to conceive any more irrational and un philosophi cal,
                    or more essentially adverse to the best interests of morality and religion. Lord
                    Kames continued an advocate of this doctrine until the day of his death; but in
                    a subsequent edition of the Essays, he exhibited a remarkable proof of his
                    candour and liberality of sentiment, by altering some expressions, which,
                    contrary to his intention, had given offence. In 1761, he published an
                    Introduction to the Art of Thinking, in one volume 12mo. This small book was
                    originally intended for the instruction of his <pb break="no" facs="nls:193646076" xml:id="kp-eb0711-6076-0537"/>own family. His
                    Elements of Criticism appeared in 1762, in three volumes 8vo. This valuable work
                    was intended to show that the art of criticism is founded on the principles of
                    human nature. Before it was published, Rollin’s book on the belles-lettres, a
                    dull performance, from which a student could derive little advantage, was
                    generally recommended; but after the Elements of Criticism appeared, the work of
                    Rollin lost its hold of the public.</p><p>A further proof of the various pursuits of this active mind was given in the year
                    1772, when his lordship published a work in one volume 8vo, under the title of
                    The Gentleman Farmer, being an attempt to improve Agriculture by subjecting it
                    to the Test of Rational Principles. In the year 1773, he favoured the world with
                    Sketches of the History of Man, in two vols. 4to. These sketches contain much
                    useful information, and, like all his lordship’s performances, are lively and
                    entertaining. They were republished in four vols. 8vo.</p><p>We now come to Lord Kames’s last work, to which he modestly gives the title of
                    Loose Hints upon Education, chiefly concerning the cultivation of the heart. It
                    was published in the year 1781, in one volume 8vo, when the venerable author was
                    in the eighty-fifth year of his age. Though his lordship chose to call it Loose
                    Flints, the intelligent reader will perceive in this composition an uncommon
                    activity of mind, at an age so far advanced beyond the usual period of human
                    life, and an earnest desire to form the minds of youth to honour, virtue,
                    industry, and a veneration of the Deity.</p><p>Besides the books which we have enumerated, Lord Kames published many temporary
                    and fugitive pieces in different periodical works. In the Essays Physical and
                    Literary, published by a society of gentlemen in Edinburgh, we find compositions
                    of his lordship on the Laws of Motion, on the Advantages of Shallow Ploughing,
                    and on Evaporation, all exhibiting evident marks of original thinking.</p><p>Lord Kames was as remarkable for public spirit as for mental activity and great
                    exertion. For a long tract of time he had the principal management of all the
                    societies and boards for promoting the trade, fisheries, and manufactures in
                    Scotland; and, as conducive to those ends, he was a strenuous advocate for
                    making and repairing turnpike roads throughout every part of the country. He was
                    in some measure the parent of what was called the Physical and Literary Society,
                    which was afterwards incorporated into the Royal Society of Edinburgh. From what
                    has been said concerning the various productions of his genius, it is obvious
                    that there could be few idle moments in his protracted life. His mind, either
                    teeming with new ideas, or pursuing active and laborious occupations, found
                    incessant employment. In his temper he was naturally warm, though kind and
                    affectionate. In the friendships he formed he was ardent, zealous, and sincere.
                    So far from being inclined to irréligion, as some ignorant bigots insinuated,
                    few men possessed a more devout habit of thought. A constant sense of the
                    presence of the Deity, and a veneration for Providence, dwelt upon his mind.
                    From this source arose that propensity which appears in all his writings, of
                    investigating final causes, and tracing the wisdom of the Supreme Author of
                    nature. Lord Kames died on the 27 th of December 1782. As he had no marked
                    disease, but the debility necessarily resulting from extreme old age, a few days
                    before his death he went to the Court of Session, addressed all the judges
                    separately, told them he was speedily to depart, and took 3 solemn and an
                    affectionate farewell. A full account of his Life and Writings, including much
                    of the Literary History of Scotland, was published by the late Lord
                    Woodhouselee, in two vols. 4to, 1807.</p></div></body></text></TEI>