<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-2120-0055-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LANDEN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 55</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67b9q">Mathematicians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1004133">Luxembourgers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1012154">Mathematicians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1243607">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193202120" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LANDEN</label>, a town of the Netherlands, in the province
                    <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Liège and arrondissement of Huy, on the river Beake.
                    It is remarkable for the battle fought near it, usually called the battle of
                    Neerwinden, in 1693, in which the allies were defeated by Marshal Luxembourg.
                    Long. 4. 55. Ľ. Lat. 50. 45. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Landen,</hi><hi rend="italic">John,</hi> an eminent
                    mathematician, was born at Peakirk, near Peterborough, in Northamptonshire, in
                    January 1719. He early became a proficient in the mathematics, for we find him a
                    respectable contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Ladies Dairy</hi> in 1744; and
                    he was soon amongst the foremost of those who then contributed to the support of
                    that small but valuable publication, in which a number of English mathematicians
                    at one period or other contended for fame. Mr Landen continued his contributions
                    to it under various signatures till within a few years of his death.</p>
                <p>In the forty-eighth volume of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Transactions</hi> for the year 1754, Mr Landen published an Investigation of
                    some theorems which suggest several very remarkable properties of the circle,
                    and are at the same time of considerable use in resolving fractions, the
                    denominators <hi rend="italic">of</hi> which are certain multinomials, into more
                    simple ones, and by that means facilitate the computation of fluents. This paper
                    was handed to the Society by Mr Thomas Simpson of Woolwich; a circumstance which
                    will convey to those who are not themselves judges some idea of its merits. In
                    the year 1755 he published a volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Mathematical
                    Lucubrations.</hi> It contains a variety of tracts relative to the rectification
                    of curve lines, the summation of series, the finding of fluents, and many other
                    points in the higher parts of the mathematics.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193202133" xml:id="kp-eb0713-2133-0056"/>
                <p>About the latter end of 1757, or the beginning of 1758, he published proposals
                    for printing by subscription <hi rend="italic">The Residual Analysis,</hi> a new
                    branch of the algebraic art; and in 1758 he published a small tract in quarto,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">A Discourse on the Residual Analysis,</hi> in which
                    he resolved a variety of problems, to which the method of fluxions had been
                    usually applied, by a mode of reasoning entirely new; compared these solutions
                    with solutions of the same problems investigated by the fluxionary method; and
                    showed that the solutions by his new method were, in general, more natural and
                    elegant than the fluxionary ones. In the fifty-first volume of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for the year 1760, he published a
                    New Method of computing the sums of a great number of Infinite Series. This
                    paper was also presented to the society by his ingenious friend Mr Thomas
                    Simpson. In 1774&lt; he published the first book of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Residual Analysis,</hi> in 4to, with several copperplates. In this treatise,
                    besides explaining the principles on which his new analysis was founded, he
                    applied it to drawing tangents and finding the properties of curve lines; to
                    describing their involutes and evolutes, finding the radius of curvature, their
                    greatest and least ordinates, and points of contrary fluxure; to the
                    determination of their cusps, and the drawing of asymptotes ;—and he proposed in
                    a second book to extend the application of this new analysis to a great variety
                    of mechanical and physical subjects. The papers which were to have formed this
                    book lay long by him; but he never found leisure to put them in order for the
                    press. In January 1766 Mr Landen was elected a fellow of the Royal Society, and
                    admitted in the April following. In the fifty-eighth volume of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for the year 1768, he published a
                    specimen of a new method of comparing curvilineal areas, by means of which many
                    areas are compared, that did not appear to be comparable by any other method; a
                    circumstance of no small importance in that part of natural philosophy which
                    relates to the doctrine of motion. In the sixtieth volume of the same work, for
                    the year 1770, he gave some new theorems for computing the whole areas of curve
                    lines, where the ordinates are expressed by fractions of a certain form, in a
                    more concise and elegant manner than had been done by Cotes, Demoivre, and
                    others, who had considered the subject before him. In the sixty-first volume,
                    for 1771, he investigated several new and useful theorems for computing certain
                    fluents, which are assignable by arcs of the conic sections. This subject had
                    been considered before, both by Mr Maclaurin and Μ. d’Alembert; but some of the
                    theorms which were given by these celebrated mathematicians, being in part
                    expressed by the difference between an arc of a hyperbola and its tangent, and
                    that difference being not directly attainable when the arc and its tangent both
                    become infinite, as they will do when the whole fluent is wanted, although such
                    fluent be finite; the theorems therefore fail in those cases, and the
                    computation becomes impracticable without further help. This defect Mr Landen
                    has removed by assigning the <hi rend="italic">limit</hi> of the difference
                    between the hyperbolic arc and its tangent, whilst the point of contact is
                    supposed to be removed to an infinite distance from the vertex of the curve. And
                    he concludes the paper with a curious and remarkable property relating to
                    pendulous bodies, which is deducible from these theorems. In the same year he
                    published an animadversion on Dr Stewart’s computation of the Sun"s distance
                    from the Earth. In the sixty-fifth volume of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Transactions</hi> for 1775, appeared the investigation of a general theorem,
                    which he had promised in 1771, for finding the length of any arc of a conic
                    hyperbola by means of two elliptic arcs; and by the theorems there investigated,
                    both the elastic curve and the curve of equable recession from a given point may
                    be constructed in those cases where Mr Maclaurin’s elegant method fails. In the
                    sixty-seventh volume, for 1777, he gave a new theory of the motion of bodies
                    revolving about an axis in free space, when that motion is disturbed by some
                    extraneous force, either percussive or accelerative. At this time he did not
                    know that the subject had been handled by any other person; and he considered
                    only the motion of a sphere’s spheroid and cylinder. The publication of this
                    paper, however, was the cause of his being told that the doctrine of rotatory
                    motion had been considered by Μ. d’Alembert; and having purchased that author’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Opuscules</hi><hi rend="italic">Mathématiques,</hi> he there
                    learned that Μ. d’Alembert was not the only one who had considered the matter
                    before him; for Μ. d’Alembert speaks of some mathematician, though he does not
                    mention his name, who, after reading what had been written on the subject,
                    doubted whether there existed any solid whatever, besides the sphere, in which a
                    line, passing through its centre of gravity, would be a permanent axis of
                    rotation. In consequence of this, Mr Landen took up the subject again; and
                    though he did not then give a solution of the general problem, namely, to
                    determine the motions of a body of any form whatever revolving without restraint
                    about any axis passing through its centre of gravity, he fully removed every
                    doubt of the kind which had been started by the person alluded to by Μ.
                    d’Alembert, and pointed out several bodies, which, under certain dimensions,
                    possess that remarkable property. This paper is published, amongst many others
                    equally curious, in a volume of <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> which he gave to
                    the world in 1780. But what renders that volume yet more valuable, is a very
                    extensive Appendix, containing theorems for the calculation of fluents. The
                    tables which contain these theorems arc more complete and extensive than any
                    which are to be found in other authors, and are chiefly of his own
                    investigating; being such as had occurred to him in the course of a long and
                    curious application to almost every branch of the mathematical sciences. In the
                    years 1781, 1782, and 1783, he published three little tracts on the summation of
                    converging series, in which he explained the extent of some theorems which had
                    been given for that purpose by Demoivre, Mr Sterling, and Thomas Simpson, in
                    answer to some things which he thought had been written to the disparagement of
                    these mathematicians.</p>
                <p>About the beginning of the year 1782 Mr Landen had made such improvements in his
                    theory of rotatory motion, as he thought would enable him to give a solution of
                    the general problem specified above; but finding the result to differ very
                    materially from that of the solution which had been given by Μ. d’Alembert, and
                    not being able to see clearly where that gentleman had erred, he did not venture
                    to make his own public. In the course of that year having procured the Memoirs
                    of the Berlin Academy for 1757, containing Μ. Euler’s solution of the problem,
                    he found that it gave the same result as had been deduced by Μ. d’Alembert; but
                    the perspicuity of Μ. Euler’s manner of writing enabled him to discover where he
                    had erred, which the obscurity of the other did not do. The agreement, however,
                    of two writers of such established reputation as Μ. Euler and Μ. d’Alembert made
                    him long dubious of the truth of his own solution, and induced him to revise the
                    process again and again with the utmost circumspection; but being every time
                    more convinced that his own solution was right and theirs wrong, he at length
                    gave it to the public in the seventy-fifth volume of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophical</hi><hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> for 1785.</p>
                <p>The extreme difficulty of the subject, joined to the concise manner in which Mr
                    Landen had been obliged to give his solution in order to confine it within
                    proper limits for the Transactions, rendered it too difficult, or at least too
                    laborious a piece of business, for most mathematicians<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193202146" xml:id="kp-eb0713-2146-0057"/>to read it; and this
                    circumstance, joined to the established reputation of Euler, induced many to
                    think that his solution was right and Mr Landen’s wrong, an opinion which
                    attempts were made to establish by proof. But although these attempts were
                    manifestly abortive, as every one who perused them saw, yet they convinced Mr
                    Landen that there was a necessity for giving his solution at greater length, in
                    order to render it more generally understood. About this time also he met by
                    chance with Frisi’s work on cosmography, physics, and mathematics, in the second
                    part of which there is a solution of this problem, agreeing in the result with
                    those of Euler and D’Alembert; which is not surprising, as Frisi employed the
                    same principle that they did. Here Mr Landen learned that Euler had revised the
                    solution which he had formerly inserted in the Berlin Memoirs, and given it in
                    another form and at greater length in a volume published at Gryphiswald in 1765,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Theoria Motus Corporum solidorum seu rigidorum.</hi>
                    Having procured this book, Mr Landen found the same principles employed in it,
                    and of course the same conclusion resulting from them, which he had observed in
                    Euler’s former solution of the problems; but as the reasoning was given at
                    greater length, he was enabled to see more distinctly how Euler had been led
                    into the mistake, and to set that mistake in a stronger point of view. As he had
                    been convinced of the necessity of explaining his idea on the subject more
                    fully, he found it necessary to lose no time in setting about it. He had for
                    several years been severely afflicted with calculus in the bladder, and towards
                    the latter part of his life to such a degree as to be confined to his bed for
                    more than a month at a time, yet even this dreadful disorder did not abate his
                    ardour for mathematical studies, the second volume of his Memoirs having been
                    written and revised during the intervals of his disorder. This volume, besides a
                    solution of the general problem concerning rotatory motion, contains the
                    resolution of the problem concerning the motion of a top; an investigation of
                    the motion of the equinoxes, in which Mr Landen first pointed out the cause of
                    Sir Isaac Newton’s mistake in his solution of this celebrated problem; and some
                    other papers of considerable importance. He lived to see this work finished, and
                    received a copy of it the day before his death, which happened on the 15th of
                    January 1790, at Milton, near Peterborough, in the seventy-first year of his
                    age.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
