<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-9002-0583-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LUC, John Andrew de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 583</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1026687">Mosaics</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1026685">Mosaicism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155558">Travel</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355164">Travels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698c21">Mosaics</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193209002" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LUC, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Andrew de</hi></label>, a
                    natural philosopher of great merit and celebrity, born at Geneva on the 8th of
                    February 1727, was the son of James Francis de Luc, descended From a family
                    which had emigrated from Lucca and settled it Geneva in the fifteenth
                    century.</p>
                <p>His father was the author of some very respectable pub-ications in refutation of
                    Mandeville and other sceptical writers; and he had the means of giving his son
                    an excellent education, although he found it convenient to establish him in a
                    commercial engagement, which principally occupied the first forty-six years of
                    his life, without any other interruption than that which was occasioned by some
                    journeys of business into the neighbouring countries, and a few scientific
                    excursions among the Alps. During these, however, he collected by degrees, in
                    conjunction with his brother William Antony, a splendid museum of mineralogy,
                    and of natural history in general, which is still preserved at Geneva by the
                    younger Deluc, his nephew. He at the same time took his share of the public
                    business of the state, as one of the council of Two Hundred; and he is still
                    remembered with respect by his fellow citizens, though he revisited them but
                    once, and hat for a few days only after his emigration, which was the
                    consequence of some unexpected misfortunes in commerce. He bore them with
                    fortitude, and he rather rejoiced than lamented at the change of his pursuits,
                    when ιe removed to England in 1773. He was made a fellow of the Royal Society in
                    the same year, and was appointed leader to the queen; a situation which he
                    continued to told for forty-four years, and which afforded him both leisure and
                    a competent income. In the latter part of his life he obtained leave to perform
                    several tours in Swit-erland, France, Holland, and Germany. In this last country
                    he passed six years, from 1798 to 1804; and after his return he undertook a
                    geological tour through England. When he was at Göttingen, in the beginning of
                    his Ger man tour, he received the compliment of being appointed honorary
                    professor of geology in that university; but he never entered upon the active
                    duties of a professorship. He was also a correspondent of the Academy of
                    Sciences at Paris, and a member of several other scientific associations.</p>
                <p>His favourite studies were geology and meteorology. The situation of his native
                    country had naturally led him to contemplate the peculiarities of the earth’s
                    structure, and the properties of the atmosphere, as particularly displayed in
                    mountainous countries, and as subservient to the measurement of heights. He
                    inherited from his father a sincere veneration for the doctrines of
                    Christianity, and a disposition to defend the Mosaic account of the creation,
                    against the prevailing incredulity of the age. His royal patroness was most
                    anxious to encourage and promote his labours in this field; and he is
                    universally allowed to have had great success in removing the specious
                    objections which had been advanced by his antagonists, against the comparatively
                    recent formation of the present continents. The testimony of Cuvier is
                    sufficient to establish his character in this capacity, and to place him, at the
                    same time, in the first rank of modern geologists. His original experiments
                    relating to meteorology are, however, not less valuable to the natural
                    philosopher; and he discovered many facts of considerable importance relating to
                    heat and moisture. He noticed the disappearance of heat in the thawing of ice,
                    about the same time that Black founded on it his ingenious hypothesis of latent
                    heat. He ascertained that water was more dense about forty degrees of Fahrenheit
                    than at the temperature of freezing, expanding equally on each side of the
                    maximum; and he was the original author of the opinion since re-advanced by Mr
                    Dalton, that the quantity of aqueous vapour contained in any space is
                    independent of the presence or density of the air, or of any other elastic
                    fluid; though it appears difficult to reconcile this opinion with some of the
                    experiments of our author’s great rival, Saussure, a philosopher who, as he very
                    candidly allows, made, in many respects, more rapid progress in hygrometry than
                    himself. Deluc’s comparative experiments on his own hygrometer, and on
                    Saussure’s, show only that both are imperfect; but it may be inferred from them,
                    that a mean between both would in general approach much nearer to the natural
                    scale than either taken separately. It appears also probable that Saussure’s is
                    rather less injured by time than Deluc’s, which has been found to indicate a
                    greater degree of mean moisture every year than the last.</p>
                <p>Deluc was a man of warm feelings, and of gentle and obliging manners, fulfilling
                    on all occasions the various duties of a husband, a father, a master, and a
                    friend; at the same time that his literary and scientific merits, and his
                    unremitting attention to the service of the queen, insured her respect and her
                    kindness. He saw her daily for many years, and in his last illness, which was
                    long and painful, she showed him repeated marks of benevolent regard. He died at
                    Windsor on the 7th of November 1817, leaving a variety of works, which will long
                    be remembered in the scientific world.</p>
                <p>1. Recherches sur les modifications de l’Atmosphère, 2 vols. 4to, Geneva, 1772; 4
                    vols. 8vo, Par. 1784. This contains many accurate and ingenious experiments upon
                    moisture, evaporation, and the indications of hygrometers and thermometers,
                    applied to the barometer employed in the measurement of the height of
                    mountains.</p>
                <p>2. Relation de différens Voyages dans les Alpes de Fau-cigny, 12mo, Maestricht,
                    1771. This relation was written principally by Dentand, who accompanied the two
                    Delues in these expeditions.</p>
                <p>3. Account of a new Hygrometer, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1773, p. 404.
                    Like a mercurial thermometer, with an ivory bulb, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193209015" xml:id="kp-eb0713-9015-0584"/>which expanded by moisture,
                    and caused the mercury to descend.</p>
                <p>4. Rules for measuring Heights by the Barometer, <hi rend="italic">Phil.
                    Trans.</hi> 1771, p. 158. The first correct rules that had been made public.</p>
                <p>5. Barometrical observations on the depth of the mines in the Harz, <hi
                    rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1777, p. 401. Examples of the application of the
                    rules.</p>
                <p>6. An Essay on Pyrometry and Areometry, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1778,
                    p. 419. A paper containing many valuable remarks on physical measures in
                    general.</p>
                <p>7. Lettres physiques et morales sur l’Histoire de la Terre, 6 vols. 8vo, Hague,
                    1778. Dedicated to the queen; relating particularly <hi rend="subscript"> ι</hi>
                    to the appearances of mountains, and to the antiquity of the human race;
                    explaining the six days of the Mosaic creation as so many periods preceding the
                    epoch of the actual state of the globe; and attributing the Deluge to the
                    filling up of cavities supposed to have been left void in the interior of the
                    earth. The whole work is intermixed with interesting observations on men and
                    manners.</p>
                <p>8. A second paper concerning some Barometrical Measurements in the Mines of the
                    Harz, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1779, p. 485.</p>
                <p>9. Lettres sur quelques parties de la Suisse, 8vo, 1781. Also addressed to the
                    queen.</p>
                <p>10. Nouvelles idées sur la Météorologie, 2 vols. in 3, 8vo, Lond. 1787. A very
                    valuable collection of observations and experiments, including some original
                    remarks on electricity.</p>
                <p>11. Several papers on Hygrometry, on Vapour, and Rain, on Meteorology in general,
                    on Expansion, and on Refraction, in Rosier’s <hi rend="italic">Journal de
                    Physique,</hi> xxx. xxxii. xxxvi. xxxvii. xliii.</p>
                <p>12. Some letters on the physical History of the Earth, in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Monthly Review,</hi> enlarged, especially June 1790, and vol. ii. appendix.</p>
                <p>13. On Hygrometry, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1791, p. 1, 389. In one of
                    these very important papers the whalebone hygrometer is described.</p>
                <p>14. On Evaporation, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.</hi> 1792, p. 400. Amongst the
                    fundamental principles laid down in this paper, the independence of vapour and
                    air is asserted.</p>
                <p>15. Lettres sur l’Histoire physique de la Terre, 8vo, Par. 1798. Addressed to
                    Professor Blumenbach, and published by Mr Emery, a clergyman, at Paris. The
                    substance had already appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Journal de Physique,
                    for</hi> 1790, 1791, and 1798. We find in this volume an essay written for a
                    prize at Haarlem in 1791, but without success, on the existence of a General
                    Principle of Morality. It contains an interesting account of some conversations
                    of the author with Voltaire and Rousseau.</p>
                <p>16. Lettres sur l’Education religieuse de l’Enfance, 8vo, Berlin, 1799.</p>
                <p>17. Bacon tel qu’il est, 8vo, Berlin, 1800. Showing the bad faith of the French
                    translator, who had omitted many passages favourable to revealed religion.</p>
                <p>18. Précis de la Philosophie de Bacon, 2 vols. 8vo, Paris, 1802. Giving an
                    interesting view of the progress of natural science.</p>
                <p>19. Lettres sur le Christianisme, Berlin and Hanover, 1801, 1803. A
                    correspondence with Mr Teller.</p>
                <p>20. Introduction à la Physique terrêstre par les Fluides expansibles, 8vo, Par.
                    1803.</p>
                <p>21. Traité élémentaire sur le Fluide Galvanique, 8vo, Paris, 1804.</p>
                <p>22. A paper on Lavas, <hi rend="italic">Journal des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Mines,</hi> cxv. Nicholson, XX.</p>
                <p>23, 24. Several articles in the <hi rend="italic">British Critic</hi> and in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Monthly Magazine.</hi></p>
                <p>25. Traité élémentaire de Géologie, 8vo, Paris, 1809; also in English, by
                    Delafite, the same year. This volume is less strictly introductory to geology
                    than the <hi rend="italic">Lettres sur</hi><hi rend="italic">lα Terre.</hi> It
                    is principally intended as a refutation of the Vulcanian system of Hutton and
                    Playfair, who deduced the changes of the earth’s structure from the operation of
                    fire, and attributed a higher antiquity to the present state of the continents
                    than is required in the Neptunian system adopted by Deluc after Dolomieu.</p>
                <p>26. He sent to the Royal Society, in 1809, a long paper on separating the
                    chemical from the electrical effects of the pile, with a description of the
                    electric column and aërial electroscope, in which he advanced opinions so little
                    in unison with the latest discoveries of the day, especially with those of the
                    president of the society, that the council probably thought it would be either
                    encouraging error or leading to controversy to admit them into the <hi
                    rend="italic">Transactions.</hi> He had, indeed, on other occasions shown
                    somewhat too much scepticism in the rejection of new facts; and he had never
                    been convinced even of Mr Cavendish’s all-important discovery of the composition
                    of water. The paper was afterwards published in Nicholson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Journal</hi> (xxvi.), and the dry column described in it was constructed by
                    various experimental philosophers. It exhibited a continual vibrating motion,
                    which was made more sensible by the sound of a little bell, struck by the
                    pendulum at each alternation; and the vibration was more or less rapid,
                    according to the state of the atmospherical electricity, and according to other
                    circumstances affecting the column; but the motion ceased at last, after a
                    continuance of several months, or perhaps years. There are also papers in
                    volumes xxi. xxii. xxvii. xxviii. xxxii. xxxiii. and xxxv. mostly on electricity
                    and galvanism, together with one on hygrology, a letter to Bode on comets, and a
                    fanciful theory of the origin of the heat derived from compression. Some of them
                    are dated from Ashfield, near Honiton, in Devonshire.</p>
                <p>27. In the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Magazine,</hi> volumes xxxv xlii.
                    xliii. and xlv. there are also some papers, on electricity and geology,
                    especially on that of St Michael’s Mount, of Vesuvius, and of Northumberland;
                    and a note on the sympathetic vibrations of the pendulums of two clocks placed
                    near each other.</p>
                <p>28. Geological Travels in the north of Europe, 8vo, Lond. 1810.</p>
                <p>29. Geological Travels in England, 2 vols. 8vo, Lond. 1811.</p>
                <p>30. Geological Travels in Switzerland and Germany, 2 vols. 8vo, Lond. 1813.</p>
                <p>31. An Abridgment of Geology, published in 1817, when he was in his ninetieth
                    year, is mentioned as one of his best works; but it seems to have been only a
                    republication or a translation of some former treatise, perhaps the <hi
                    rend="italic">Traite Elémentaire.</hi><hi rend="italic">{Philosophical
                    Magazine,</hi> November 1817; Monod and Weiss, in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Biographie Universelle,</hi> tome xxv. 8vo, Paris, 1820.) (<hi rend="subscript"
                    > l</hi>, <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi>,)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
