<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-8820-0569-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LOTTERY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 569</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45717p75">Prizes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058861">Persons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193208820" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LOTTERY</label>, a kind of public game at hazard, in’order to
                    raise money for the service of the state, being with us appointed by the
                    authority of parliament, and managed by commissioners appointed by the Lords of
                    the Treasury for that purpose. It consists of several numbers of blanks and
                    prizes, which are drawn out of wheels, one of which contains the numbers, and
                    the other the corresponding blanks or prizes.</p>
                <p>The Romans invented lotteries in order to enliven their Saturnalia. This festival
                    began by the distribution of tickets which gained some prize. Augustus made
                    lotteries which consisted of things of little value; but Nero established some
                    for the people, in which a thousand tickets were distributed daily, and several
                    of those who were favoured by fortune got rich by means of them. Heliogabalus
                    invented some very singular ones, in which the prizes were either of great value
                    or of none at all; one gained a prize of six slaves, and another of six flies;
                    some got <hi rend="subscript"> -</hi> valuable vases, and others vessels of
                    common earth.</p>
                <p>The first English lottery which we find mentioned in history was drawn in the
                    year 1569. It consisted of 40,000 lots, at 10s. each lot. The prizes were plate;
                    and the profits were to go towards repairing the havens of the kingdom. It was
                    drawn at the west door of St Paul’s cathedral. The drawing began on the 11th of
                    January 1569, and continued incessantly, day and night, until the 6th day of May
                    following. (Maitland, vol. i. p. 257.) There were then only three
                    lottery-offices in London. The proposals for this lottery were published in the
                    years 1567 and 1568. It was at first intended to have been drawn at the house of
                    Mr Dericke, her majesty’s jeweller; but it was afterwards drawn as above
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>In 1748, Dr Rawlinson showed the Antiquarian Society “A proposal for a very rich
                    lottery-general without any blankes, contayning a great number of good prizes,
                    as well of redy money as of plate and certain sorts of merchandizes, having been
                    valued and prised by the com- ∣mandment of the queene’s most excellent
                    majestie’s order, to the intent that such commodities as may chance to arise
                    thereof, after the charges borne, may be converted towards the reparations of
                    the havens and strength of the realme, and towards such other public good
                    workes.” He then goes on to say, “The number of lotts shall be foure hundred
                    thousand, and no more; and every lott shall be the summe of tenne shillings
                    sterling, and no more. To be filled by the feast of St Bartholomew. The shew of
                    prizes are to be seen in Cheapside, at the sign of the Queene’s Armes, the house
                    of Mr Dericke, goldsmith, servant to the queene.”</p>
                <p>In the reign of Queen Anne, it was thought necessary to suppress lotteries as
                    public nuisances. Since that time, however, they have been licensed by act of
                    parliament, under a variety of regulations. The act passed in 1778 restrains any
                    person from keeping an office for the sale of tickets, shares, or chances, or
                    for buying, selling, insuring, or registering, without a license; for which
                    license each office-keeper must pay L.50, to continue in force for one year, and
                    the produce to be applied towards defraying the expense of the lottery. And no
                    person is allowed to sell my share or chance less than a sixteenth, on the
                    penalty of L.50. All tickets divided into shares or chances are to be deposited
                    in an office, to be established in London by the commissioners of the Treasury,
                    who are to appoint a person to conduct the business thereof; and all shares are
                    to be stamped by the said officer, who is to give a receipt for every ticket
                    deposited with him. The numbers of all tickets so deposited are to be entered in
                    a book, with the names of the owners, and the number of shares into which they
                    are divided. All tickets deposited in the office are to remain there three days
                    after the drawing. Any person keeping an office, or selling shares, or who shall
                    publish any scheme for receiving moneys in consideration of any interest to be
                    granted in any ticket in the said lottery, without being in possession of such
                    ticket, shall forfeit L.500, and suffer three months imprisonment. No business
                    is to be transacted at any of the offices after eight in the evening, except on
                    the evening of the Saturday preceding the drawing; and no person is to keep any'
                    office for the sale of tickets in Oxford or Cambridge, on penalty of L.20.
                    Before this regulating statute was passed, there were upwards of four hundred
                    lottery - offices in and about London only; but the number for all Britain, as
                    appears by the list published by authority, afterwards amounted to’not more than
                    fifty-one. Subsequently, however, they increased greatly in number.</p>
                <p>Some further regulations to prevent the frauds committed by insurances were made
                    in 1793. In 1808 the reports of a committee of the House of Commons disclosed a
                    dreadful scene of vice and misery brought on by lotteries, and recommended their
                    abolition, or at least that they should be put under other regulations. The
                    gross sum received by government from the lottery was estimated at L.750,000 per
                    annum, of which L.500,000 was for tickets, and the remainder for postages,
                    stamps, &amp;c. At length, lotteries, which had proved eminently prejudicial to
                    public morals, by fostering among the people a propensity to gambling, and
                    which, in a fiscal point of view, had yielded but a trifling amount of revenue
                    to the state, were put an end to by a Treasury minute, which provided, that,
                    from and after the 18th of October 1826, they should cease and determine; and
                    this abolition was accompanied with a prohibitory declaration against all
                    attempts on the part of individuals to revive or continue them in any mode or
                    form whatsoever. Some years ago, however, a bill was brought into parliament for
                    disposing, in this sort of way, of some property in Glasgow; and, as the
                    obnoxious denomination of lottery was carefully excluded, general terms alone
                    being employed in the bill, it accidentally escaped notice, and thus passed into
                    a law. But it is well understood that this took place <hi rend="italic"
                    >per</hi><hi rend="italic">incuriam,</hi> and that any' future attempt of a
                    similar description will certainly prove unsuccessful.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
