<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-4426-0231-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LEON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 13, page 231</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w237">Running</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dj11">Cow</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1101348">Running</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193204426" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LEON</label>, a province, or, as it is more commonly called
                    by the natives, a kingdom, of Spain. Asturias bounds it on the north side,
                    Galicia on the west, Estremadura and Old Castile on the south, and New Castile
                    on the east. Its extent is 1207 square leagues, and the number of its
                    inhabitants is 714,037. It is frequently divided into six departments, those of
                    Leon, Palencia, Valladolid, Tora, and Zamora; but the more recent division into
                    two departments, each clearly defined by the course of the river Duero, is more
                    natural, and less likely to perplex. The two divisions are denominated that of
                    Leon to the north, and that of Salamanca to the south, of the Duero. Of the
                    various rivers that cross Leon, the most considerable is the Pisuerga, in the
                    northern limits, to the eastward of the fountains of the Ebro and Reynosa. This
                    is one of the points of separation which divide those streams that run to the
                    Atlantic, from those which run to the Mediterranean, and is consequently one of
                    the most elevated districts in Spain. From its great elevation, it is
                    necessarily cold; and some of its summits reach the line of perpetual snow.
                    These hills produce the loftiest and best oaks in the peninsula, and are highly
                    useful in the construction of ships. Many bears and some wolves are found in
                    this range of mountains. The principal part of the labour of the mountaineers is
                    directed to the iron mines, and to the manufactory of hardware. In the intervals
                    between the highest hills they have good pastures, and feed many cows, from
                    whose milk butter is made, which, if the natives understood, or rather
                    practised, the simple art of salting, and packing in casks, might become a
                    valuable branch of commerce with the other parts of Spain, which draw their
                    supplies of that commodity from Holland or from Ireland. The mountains which
                    diverge from these towards the west are very steep, and gradually increase in
                    height till they Teach the border of Asturias, with which the communication is
                    held by fissures in the mountains called the Puertos de Piedrafita, de Pajares,
                    de Someeda, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The height of these mountains has never been accurately ascertained; but if the
                    various plants that grow on their tops is a certain criterion of their
                    elevation, they are equal to the Pyrenees, and to most of the points of the
                    Alps. The inhabitants of these mountains are a detached race, and are thus
                    described by Don Mariano Lagasea, a recent and very intelligent traveller. “The
                    villages have few inhabitants, and are mostly in the valleys. The inhabitants
                    are robust and simple in their manners; they are equally ignorant of luxury and
                    drunkenness; all are clothed very coarsely, but warmly, from the looms of their
                    own females, and have their garments made in, the simplest fashion. Without
                    physician, surgeon, or apothecary; without irregular pleasures, they live
                    happily, drinking the milk of their cows, and eating their barley-bread and
                    salted meat. They have no other bed than a table fixed to the wall at one end of
                    their dwellings, which in shape resembles a coffin. They cultivate a few
                    vegetables, and grow barley in some of the least cold parts of the district, but
                    not sufficient for even their scanty consumption. From June to September they
                    have abundant pasture for their own cattle, as well as for the migratory flocks
                    of merino sheep that pass through their confines. In the valleys they have
                    meadows, on which they make hay for winter food for their cattle. The only
                    industry that is exercised is in making wooden shoes, and bowls and platters of
                    the same substance, which they sell in the neighbouring lower districts. Some
                    are also employed in collecting medicinal plants, which are sold to the city of
                    Leon. Before the year 1803, it was not known that the district abounded in the
                    Iceland moss. Since that period considerable quantities of that substance have
                    been collected, and it is now sold in Madrid at twenty reals the pound, whereas
                    before it was sold at 160. It has beļŗun to form a branch of commerce with the
                    mountaineers, and in time it may become an important article of subsistence for
                    them, as it is for the natives of Iceland.”</p>
                <p>The river Pisuerga, descending to the plains, receives on the right the river
                    Carrion, and on the left the Arlanza, and passes by Palencia, and through the
                    fertile valley of Tierra de Campos, abounding in wine and oil, till it is joined
                    by the Esgueva near the city of Valladolid, whence it has a short course to the
                    Duero. The other rivers of Leon are the Esla, the Torio, the Bernesga, the Sil,
                    and the Boeza, all of which unite ultimately with the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193204439" xml:id="kp-eb0713-4439-0232"/>Duero. On the southern part
                    of Leon, the department of Salamanca, the population is thicker, and the country
                    more fertile. There are some mines of copper, and quarries of marble. Many cows,
                    sheep, horses, and mules, are bred; and, though not a rich, yet, when compared
                    with the mountain districts, it is a fertile tract of land. The principal rivers
                    that water it are the Daraton, the Eresma, the Adaja, the Tormes, and the
                    Agueda, which run to the Duero, and the Alogon, which runs south, and, after
                    crossing part of Estremadura, loses its name in the Tagus.</p>
                <p>The different agricultural and commercial productions of the kingdom of Leon will
                    be found under the places in which they are created; and the history of Leon,
                    long a separate kingdom, is included in the general history of Spain. The
                    province of Leon, one of the five in the kingdom, according to the ancient mode
                    of dividing it, is 493 square leagues in extent, and is inhabited by 239,810
                    people. It contains two cities, 197 towns, and 1284 villages, in 1373 parishes;
                    and has fifty monasteries, and sixteen charitable institutions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Leon,</hi> a city of Spain, in the province of the same
                    name, and capital of it, as it was of the ancient kingdom of Leon before its
                    union with Castile. It is situated on a kind of peninsula, formed by two rivers,
                    the Torio and the Bernesga. It contains a population of about 7000 souls, who
                    are employed principally in spinning thread, and making it into coarse linen.
                    The country around it yields wheat, barley, and particularly flax; and they have
                    meadows where the cattle are pastured, and, what is not usual in Spain, where
                    they make hay. It is the see of a bishop, and, among various public buildings
                    that attract attention, the most remarkable is his cathedral, a most beautiful
                    specimen of the Gothic style of architecture. It contains thirteen parish
                    churches, nine monasteries, four hospitals, 1500 houses, and 6170 inhabitants.
                    Lat. 42. 45. N. The inhabitants make worsted stockings and caps, in forty looms;
                    leather and leathern gloves; and have some tanneries.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Leon,</hi><hi rend="italic">Peter</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Cicca</hi><hi rend="italic">de,</hi> author of the history of Peru. He left
                    Spain, his native country, at thirteen years of age, in order to go into
                    America, where he resided seventeen years, and observed so many remarkable
                    things, that he resolved to commit them to writing. The first part of his
                    history was printed at Seville in 1553. He began it 1541, and ended it in 1550.
                    He was at Lima, the capital of the kingdom of Peru, when he .gave the finishing
                    stroke to it, and was then thirty-two years of age.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
