<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-9637-0755-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MEURSIUS, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 755</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z139">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b09t">Tactics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vf0v">Jaws</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:851811">Chairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1736460">Soras</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1141865">Tactics</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844591">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:982138">Jaws</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830121">Belgica</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194209637" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MEURSIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>, one of the
                    most laborious of antiquaries, was born in the year 1579, at Losdun, a town near
                    the Hague. It appears that the name of his family was <hi rend="italic">De
                    Meurs,</hi> which he latinized, according to the usage of the learned of his
                    time. His father, a regular canon of the house of the Twelve Apostles at
                    Utrecht, having embraced the reform of Calvin, took refuge in 1569 at the Hague,
                    and some time afterwards obtained the pastoral charge of Losdun. He taught his
                    son the principles of the Latin language, and then sent him to study at Leyden,
                    where he made so rapid progress, that, at the age of twelve, he composed
                    harangues in Latin, and, at thirteen, verses in Greek. His taste led him to
                    cultivate philology; he particularly directed his attention to Lycophron, the
                    most obscure of all the Greek authors, whom he undertook to illustrate; and, at
                    the age of sixteen, he completed bis commentary on that difficult writer, a work
                    which astonished the greatest scholars and critics of the time. When he had
                    finished his course of study, the grand pensionary Barneveld confided to him the
                    education of his sons; and he was also appointed to accompany them to the
                    different courts of Europe. He turned his travels to account, by availing
                    himself of the opportunities which they afforded for extending his knowledge;
                    and, in passing through Orleans in 1608, he was admitted doctor of Jaws. On his
                    return to Holland, he was, in 1610, appointed professor of history in the
                    academy of Leyden; and the following year he was promoted to the chair of Greek,
                    which he filled with great distinction. The states of Holland conferred on him
                    the title of historiographer to their high mightinesses, and honoured him with
                    other marks of their esteem; but after the execution of the unfortunate
                    Barneveld in 1619, the persecution soon extended itself to all who had been in
                    any degree connected with him; and Meursius, the most gentle of human beings,
                    who, from his habits, was an entire stranger to the disputes which then agitated
                    his unfortunate country, did not escape molestation. As his simple and retired
                    life did not afford his enemies any pretext for accusing him, they attempted to
                    drive him from his professorship by insults, which were daily repeated, even in
                    the apartment where he delivered his prelections; they reproached him with
                    writing too many books, and alleged that, in consequence, the university did not
                    reap any benefit from his studies. The interests of his family, which depended
                    entirely on the emoluments of his office, forced him to submit in silence to
                    these affronts; but the king <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Denmark having, in 1625,
                    offered him the chair of history in the university of Sora, together with the
                    place of historiographer, he at once accepted the situation, and fully justified
                    the high opinion which foreigners had conceived of his talents. The remainder of
                    his life was divided between his official duties and literary pursuits; and he
                    died of the stone, on the 20th of September 1639, at the age of sixty. He was
                    buried in the principal church of Sora, in a tomb adorned with an epitaph, which
                    may be found in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Belgica</hi> of Foppens, and also in the work of Niceron.</p>
                <p>Meursius rendered an unappreciable service to letters by the numerous editions
                    which he published of the Greek authors, with corrections, critical remarks, and
                    Latin versions. The principal works which he edited are, the Poems of Lycophron;
                    the Tactics of the Emperor Leo; the <hi rend="italic">Opuscula</hi> of
                    Hesychius; the Elements of Music by Aristoxenes; the Letters of Philostratus;
                    the <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Lausiacaoi</hi> Pal-lades;
                    the Annals of Manasses; the History of Theodosius Metochites; the Tactics of
                    Constantine Porphyrogennetes; the Marvellous Histories of Phlegon Trallianus,
                    Antigonus Carystius, and Apollonius Dyscoles; and the works of Porphyry,
                    Procopius, Gaza, and others. The works of Meursius were collected by Lami,
                    Florence, 1741-1763, in twelve volumes folio. This collection is rare and much
                    prized. In the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of Niceron (tom. xii. and xx.)
                    will be found a list of all the productions of this indefati <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194209650" xml:id="kp-eb0714-9650-0756"/>gable writer, in number
                    sixty-seven; but we shall here only indicate those which are most deserving of
                    the attention of the curious. I. <hi rend="italic">Glossarium</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Graeco-Barbarum,</hi> Leyden, 1614, in 4to; a work which, in
                    regard to the Greek writers of the Lower Empire, holds the same place as the
                    Glossary of Du Cange does for the writers of the corresponding age of Latinity.
                    II. De Funare liber singularis, in quo Graeci et Romani ritus explicantur; De
                    Puerperio Syntagma, Hague, 1604, in 8vo; Roma Luxurians, sive de Luxu Romanorum,
                    Leyden, 1631, in 4to; De Populis Atticae liber, 1616, in 4to; Atticarum
                    Lectionum libri vi. 1617, in 4to; Orchestra, sive de Saltationibus Veterum,
                    1618; Graecia Feriata, sive de Festis Graecorum, 1619; Panathenaea, sive de
                    Minervae Festo genuino, 1619; Eleusinia, sive de Cereris Eleusinae sacro et
                    festo, 1619; De Tragoediis Graecis, 1619, in 4to; Archontes Athenienses, 1622;
                    Fortuna Attica, seu de Athenarum origine, 1622; Cecropia, seu de Athenarum Arce,
                    1622; Graecia Ludibunda, sive de Ludis Graecorum, 1622, in 8vo; Pisistratus,
                    sive de ejus liberorumque Vita et Tyrannide, 1623; Areopagus, sive de Senatu
                    Areopagitico 1624; Athenae Atticae, sive de praecipuis Atheniensium
                    Antiquitatibus, 1624; Denarius Pythagoricus, 1631, in 4to; Solon, sive de ejus
                    Vita, Copenhagen, 1632, in 4to; Regnum Atticum, Amsterdam, 1633; Theophrastus,
                    sive de illius libris qui injuria temporis interciderunt, Leyden, 1640, in 12mo;
                    Miscellanea Laconica, Amsterdam, 1641, in 4to; Ceramicus Geminus, sive de
                    Ceramici Atheniensis utriusque antiquitatibus, Utrecht, 1662, in 4to; Creta,
                    Cyprus, Rhodus, sive de Insularum rebus et antiquitatibus, Amsterdam, 1675, in
                    4to; Theseus, sive de ejus Vita, Utrecht, 1684; Themis Attica, sive de Legibus
                    Atticis, 1685; De Regno Laconico 1687. III. Rerum Belgicarum liber primus, de
                    Induciis belli Belgici, 1612, in 4to, very rare. IV. Athenae Batavae, sive de
                    urbe Leydensi et academia, Leyden, 1625. V. Historia Danica, usque ad annum
                    1523, Copenhagen, 1630, in 4to. The historical works of Meursius were collected
                    and published at Amsterdam, 1638, in folio.</p>
                <p>The memory of Meursius has suffered by his being sometimes represented as the
                    author of the infamous dialogues <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Arcanis Amoris</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Veneris.</hi>
                    This licentious work, it is now well known, was the production of one Chorier,
                    an advocate of Grenoble, who probably prefixed to it the name of Meursius for
                    the purpose of throwing ridicule on the grave and learned professor. His son
                    John was a scholar of considerable eminence, and produced some works evincing
                    erudition and research. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
