<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-4047-0325-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ΜATTO-GROSSO, or Great Thicket</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 325</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1205550">Paraguay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194204047" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ΜATTO-GROSSO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Great
                    Thicket</hi></label>, is a province of Brazil. It is bounded on the north by
                    Para, and on the south by Paraguay, extending in this direction about nine
                    hundred miles. The rivers Araguaya and Parana separate it on the east from the
                    provinces of Goyaz and San Paulo; and on the west the rivers Madera, Guapore,
                    Jauru, and Paraguay, divide it from Peru and La Plata. Its greatest breadth,
                    which is in the upper part, where it borders on Para, is about 950 miles, and it
                    continues so for 240 miles, when it rapidly narrows till it joins Paraguay. This
                    is one of those Brazilian provinces the greater part of which still remains in
                    the hands of the unsubdued Indians, the Portuguese having only effected partial
                    settlements in the country. It comprises nearly four climates, and is naturally
                    partitioned into three grand districts, of which two are divided into six
                    smaller ones. These seven divisions are Camapuania on the south; Matto-Grosso
                    proper, Cuyaba, and Bororonia in the centre; and Juruenna, Arinos, and
                    Tippiraquia on the north. Tippiraquia, so called from the Tippiraquia Indians,
                    lying between the rivers Araguaya and Xingu, is altogether unknown, except along
                    its eastern boundary. Arinos and Juruenna, named from the rivers which intersect
                    them, must also still be considered as <hi rend="italic">terra incognita.</hi>
                    The rivers Arinos and Juruenna unite to form the great Tapajos. Bororonia, which
                    takes its name from the Bororo Indians, is situated between Goyaz and Cuyaba,
                    and is watered by the San Lourenço. It is destitute of any settlement, except an
                    arraial and register on the Cuyaba road.</p>
                <p>Camapuania, the southern division of the province, takes its name from the river
                    Camapuan. Except in its northern limits, it is nearly a uniform level; and a
                    great part of its western half is annually submerged by the inundations of the
                    Paraguay, which is said to cover in some parts more than seventy miles of plain.
                    In the north it is intersected by a chain of mountains stretching from east to
                    west, and here the Paraguay and its branches have their origin, flowing to the
                    southward, and the heads of the Tapajos and the Xingu, which take a northerly
                    course. This canton is divided into east and west by a cordillera of
                    inconsiderable elevation, called the Serra Amambahy. From this chain of hills
                    numerous other rivers have their origin, so that the whole is in every part well
                    watered, and might be rendered a valuable country in the hands of civilized men.
                    The only <hi rend="italic">povoaçoes</hi> in this district are the fazenda of
                    Camapuan, situated in latitude 19. 36. S.; and Miranda, a prezidio on the river
                    Aranhary or Mondego, founded in 1797. Attempts have been made by the Spaniards
                    to establish themselves at several points in this district, but without
                    success.</p>
                <p>Of the savage nations who retain undisputed possession of this country we can
                    afford but a brief account. The most formidable are the Guaycurues, who are
                    still a populous nation, divided into various hordes, and dwelling chiefly on
                    the eastern side of the Paraguay, from 19. 28. to 23. 36. south latitude. Those
                    who inhabit the western side of this river hold no alliance with other nations.
                    Indeed the various tribes are declared enemies to each other, although no
                    difference of origin, idiom, or usage has been observed amongst them. They
                    recognise three degrees of rank; the first, called captains, seems to be
                    equivalent to <hi rend="italic">noblesse</hi> or lords of the soil√the second,
                    denominated soldiers, are a species of hereditary vassals, whose military
                    servitude descends<pb break="no" facs="nls:194204060"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-4060-0326"/> from sire to son; and the third are captives or
                    slaves, being the prisoners of war and their descendants. The Guaycurues are of
                    medium stature, well made, healthy, robust, and capable of executing painful and
                    laborious undertakings. The men are diligent in hunting, fishing, gathering
                    honey, and wild fruits, and in the manufacture of arms and canoes. The women
                    spin, manufacture clothes and girdles of cotton, and make cords, mats, and other
                    articles. They rear all the species of domestic birds and quadrupeds introduced
                    into the country, but agriculture they hold in contempt. They are excellent
                    horsemen, being almost constantly on horseback, so that they constitute a very
                    formidable cavalry in their cruel wars, and are in consequence much dreaded by
                    the surrounding nations. Like the Arabs, they have no permanent dwelling-places,
                    shifting their residences according to circumstances, but always encamping near
                    some river or lake. The woods which border on the Igatimy, the Miamaya, and the
                    Esco-pil, streams flowing from the Serro Amambahy into the Parana, are inhabited
                    by the Cahans, or people of the wood, so called to distinguish them from their
                    enemies the Guaycurues, who keep the open country. From the accounts which we
                    have of this semi-civilized tribe, they appear to be descendants of some of the
                    Indians civilized by the Jesuits of Paraguay. They cultivate the cotton-tree,
                    the produce of which they spin and weave in a manner peculiar to themselves.
                    They live in villages, and have amongst them men who pretend to be at once
                    surgeons, doctors, divines, and priests. They carry in their hands a cross; and,
                    in their religious observances, solemnity is strongly blended with the wildest
                    extravagance.</p>
                <p>The cantons of Cuyaba and Matto-Grosso are, properly speaking, the only districts
                    of the province which have been colonized. The latter contains the official
                    capital, Villa Bella, which is situated in a champaign country, near the margin
                    of the Gnapore. It is a neat small city, and contains, besides the residence of
                    the governor and the ouvidor, a smelting-house, the parochial church, and two
                    hermitages. The Guapore, which the Spaniards call Itenez, whilst it sometimes
                    goes by the name of the Mamore, originates nearly one hundred miles north-east
                    of the capital. After flowing eighty miles in a southerly course, it runs nearly
                    the same distance in a westerly direction; it then curves towards the north-west
                    and westnorth-west, and ultimately joins the Mamore, forming the majestic
                    Madera. The banks of this stream are for the most part swampy and unhealthy.
                    From the western side of a continuation of the Serra Paricis, issue a number of
                    rivers, which join it by the right margin; but the largest does not exceed one
                    hundred miles in length. Thirty miles to the east of the Guapore, the Jauru
                    originates, in the campos of the Serra Paricis, and, after a lengthened
                    southerly course, bends to the east-south-east, and falls into the Paraguay in
                    lat. 16. 24. south. At this confluence, one hundred and seventy miles south-east
                    of Villa Bella, a stone with an inscription was erected in 1754, as a boundary
                    mark between the Spanish and Portuguese territories. The northern portion of the
                    canton is occupied by the Serra Paricis, an elevated range, with extensive sandy
                    campos on its summits, inhabited by various aboriginal tribes.</p>
                <p>To the cast of Matto-Grosso is the canton of Cuyaba, probably the most valuable,
                    as it is the most richly diversified part of the province. It is said to abound
                    with spacious plains, superb woods, and gently undulating elevations, which
                    occasionally assume the aspect of mountains, and the greater portion is
                    irrigated by numerous rivers. The Cuyaba, from which the district derives its
                    name, traverses it from north to south, and falls into the Lourenço in lat. 17.
                    20. The latter river separates it from Bororonia, on the east and south, whilst
                    the Paraguay bounds it on the west. Villa Real de Cuyaba, the capital, is a
                    larger and more flourishing place than Villa Bella. It is situated near a small
                    river, at one mile’s distance from the Cuyaba. The streets are mostly paved, and
                    the houses, as well as a church and three chapels which it contains, arc built
                    of <hi rend="italic">taipé.</hi> The population amounts to about 30,000. The
                    orange-tree grows here luxuriantly, and the melon, water-melon, and pine-apple
                    also flourish; as well as mandioc, maize, cotton, and sugar, which are
                    cultivated by the inhabitants. Villa Maria, which is situated on the eastern
                    bank of the Paraguay, twenty-five miles from the mouth of the Jauru, is the only
                    other place of any consideration in the canton. Its inhabitants are chiefly
                    Indian, but its position is excellent, and it may probably yet become an
                    important commercial town. The adventurous Paulistas, who first formed
                    settlements in this remote district, were attracted thither by the gold which
                    the country afforded. The early explorers found it in great quantities, and a
                    vast number of persons belonging to San Paulo were induced to undertake long and
                    laborious voyages in search of the precious metal. Several of these expeditions
                    proving fatal to those who embarked in them, it was deemed necessary to despatch
                    a strong armament to subdue the native Indians. A desperate conflict took place
                    in 1735, which at last terminated in favour of the Paulistas. A road having been
                    opened to Goyaz, and intelligence brought of new gold mines in Matto-Grosso,
                    almost the whole population of Cuyaba left that town for the west. There still
                    exist, however, as well in this canton as in that of Matto∙Grosso, various
                    hordes of Bororo Indians; but the greater part of the population is stated to
                    consist of Mamalucoes, descended from the alliance of the Paulistas with the
                    Paricis Indians. With regard to the gross number of inhabitants in the province
                    of Matto-Grosso, no idea can be formed. Dr Von Martius enumerates no less than
                    thirty-five native tribes as peopling this vast tract of country.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">{On the State of Civil and Natural Rights among the Aboriginal
                    Inhabitants of Brazil</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> an Essay, by Dr C. F. Ph. Von
                    Martius, Munich, 1832. See an abstract of the work in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Journal of the Royal Geographical</hi><hi rend="italic">Society</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of London,</hi> volume second.) (<hi rend="smallcaps">k. r.
                    n.</hi>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
