<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-0485-0051-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MALACCA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 51</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219926">Malaya</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205085">Romania</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1056939">Peninsulas</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1134302">Straits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194200485" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MALACCA</label>, an extensive region of India beyond the
                    Ganges, consisting of a large peninsula, connected, by the isthmus of Kraw,
                    about ninety-seven miles in breadth, with the province of Tenasscrim to the
                    north, whilst on all other sides it is bounded by the Eastern Ocean, having on
                    the west the Indian Ocean and the Straits of Malacca, which separate it from
                    Sumatra, and on the east the Gulf of Siam and the Sea of China. It extends from
                    the eleventh to the twelfth degrees of north latitude, and is 775 miles in
                    length, by 125 in average breadth. The country is a long, narrow strip of land,
                    traversed by a chain of lofty mountains, and covered with extensive forests and
                    marshes, so that it is very difficult to penetrate into the interior. A range of
                    extremely bleak mountains runs through it from one extremity to the other; and
                    they give rise to innumerable streams, the courses of which, from the proximity
                    of the mountains to the sea, are short, and they are obstructed at the mouths by
                    bars and sandbanks, so that they cannot be ascended by vessels of any size. At
                    the southern extremity of the continent are the islands of Bintang, Bataug, and
                    Sincapore, with many others, so thickly clustered together, that they are only
                    separated from the continent by narrow straits, and seem to be a prolongation of
                    the land. On the west coast also there are numerous islands, amongst which may
                    be mentioned Pulo Pinang, or Prince of Wales Island.</p>
                <p>The soil is not remarkable for its fertility, though, like other Malay countries,
                    the coast is well covered with wood, and exhibits a great extent of verdure; but
                    the teak tree has never yet been discovered in these forests. The fruits are
                    excellent and plentiful; but grain is not produced in sufficient quantity, and
                    is therefore imported from Bengal and Sumatra. The jungles, from their density
                    and great luxuriance, are impervious to animals, and game is in consequence
                    scarce. From the rivers, as well as the sea, the inhabitants derive a plentiful
                    supply offish.</p>
                <p>The political state of Malacca has been subject to many revolutions, having been
                    occasionally dependent on Siam, when that monarchy was in the height of its
                    power, and when its supremacy was owned by the whole peninsula. But since the
                    Siamese have yielded to the increasing power of the Burmans, all the southern
                    portion of the peninsula has shaken off the yoke; and the northern states pay
                    only a moderate tribute. The whole of the sea-coast, from that latitude to Point
                    Romania, is still possessed by the Malays, who are mixed in some places with the
                    Buggesses from Celebes, and who have still a small settlement at Salengore. The
                    northern and inland parts of the peninsula are inhabited by the Patany people,
                    who appear to be a mixture of Siamese and Malays, and who inhabit independent
                    villages. The negro race is found in the interior amongst the aboriginal
                    natives. The great majority of the inhabitants are, however, of the Malay race,
                    who are well known and widely diffused amongst all the eastern <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194200498" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0498-0052"/>islands. The origin of this
                    remarkable race is not very distinctly known. They are understood, however, not
                    to be natives of this country, but to have come originally from the district of
                    Palembang, in the interior of Sumatra, situated on the banks of the river
                    Malaya. Having crossed over about the end of the twelfth century to the opposite
                    continent, they, in 1252, founded the city of Malacca. They are of a daring,
                    restless, and intrepid disposition; their character forming in this respect a
                    striking contrast to that of the timid inhabitants of Hindustan. They are brave
                    in war, but ferocious and vindictive, merciless to enemies and strangers, and
                    capricious and passionate even to friends. They are proud and irascible,
                    carrying the point of honour to excess, with a quick sensibility to the
                    slightest insult, which drives them to a degree of fury bordering on
                    desperation; and it is by a series of what they, in their overwrought fancies,
                    consider to be insults, that they are excited to a state of frenzy which ends in
                    that act of wild atrocity known by the name of running amok, from the word <hi
                    rend="italic">amok,</hi> signifying kill, kill. The Malay,when he has resolved
                    on this desperate step, proceeds still farther to inflame his passions, by
                    taking a dose of opium, when he throws loose his black hair, and, drawing his
                    deadly crease, rushes into the streets, thirsting for vengeance, and, crying
                    “kill, kill,” slays every one whom he meets in this furious mood. But it has
                    been found that these unruly passions, which often broke out into violent
                    excesses under the tyrannies of their Dutch rulers, were greatly allayed by kind
                    treatment; and that the Malay, in these circumstances, was transformed into an
                    entirely different character, displaying gratitude, affection, fidelity, and
                    higher sentiments of honour than are found amongst any other class of natives in
                    India. Those Europeans who have engaged them as servants, and who have treated
                    them well, inform us that they found them faithful and attached domestics. The
                    free Malays are an intelligent, active, industrious body of men, engaged, like
                    the Chinese, in foreign trade. They have always addicted themselves to seafaring
                    pursuits, and to piracy, which they follow as if it were a lawful trade; and
                    hence they are the terror of the effeminate Asiatics. Their prows are many of
                    them fine vessels, and navigated with skill; but the Malay, though in general a
                    bold and hardy mariner, is apt to sink under a continuance of cold or bad
                    weather, even sooner than the feeble but more docile lascar of Bengal. Though
                    they have been much circumscribed in their piracies by the maritime superiority
                    of the Europeans in the Eastern Seas, and no longer retain those daring habits
                    which rendered them the scourge of the peaceful trader, they still carry on
                    petty depredations; and trading vessels are sometimes cut off, and their crews
                    murdered with every circumstance of atrocity.</p>
                <p>The government of the Malays is a rude description of monarchy, with a turbulent
                    aristocracy, or something like the principles of the feudal system. The head of
                    the government is a rajah or sultan, a name assumed from the Arabians; and under
                    him a certain number of nobles, with their train of vassals. But in practice
                    there is no regular system of subordination, the king trampling on the chiefs
                    and the people, and they again rebelling against his authority; so that there is
                    little else amongst them but violence and disorder, which contributes to nourish
                    their ferocious habits.</p>
                <p>The language of the Malays has obtained very general currency in several states
                    upon the continent, as well as amongst the eastern islands, though it has gained
                    no footing in the interior of Hindustan. On the sea-coast, and at the mouths and
                    on the banks of navigable rivers, it is the medium of commercial and foreign
                    intercourse; and the currency which it has acquired may be ascribed partly to
                    the commercial and enterprising character of the people, who, by their
                    mercantile habits, or the power of their arms, have established themselves in
                    every part of the archipelago, and also to its own valuable qualities of
                    simplicity in the structure, and even of pronunciation. In writing it, they use
                    the Arabic character, with the addition of six other letters. The Malays have
                    few books in their language, and these consist chiefly of transcripts and
                    versions of the Koran, commentaries on the Mahommedan law, and tales in prose
                    and verse, many of them translations of the popular tales current in Arabia,
                    Persia, India, and the neighbouring island of Java. They have also some
                    historical compositions.</p>
                <p>The Malayans profess the Mahommedan religion. Until the year 1276 they were
                    pagans, or followed some corrupted form of Hindu idolatry. Sultan Mahommed Shah,
                    who ascended the throne in the thirteenth century, was the first prince who, by
                    the propagation of this faith, acquired great celebrity during his long reign of
                    fifty-seven years. His dominion extended over the neighbouring islands of Lingen
                    and Bintang, together with Johore, Patany, Quedah, and Pera, on the coasts of
                    the peninsula, besides several districts in Sumatra, all of which acquired the
                    appellation of Malaya. During part of the fifteenth century, Malacca was under
                    the Siamese sovereigns. In 1509, Sultan Mahmood repelled the aggression of the
                    king of Siam; but in 1511 he was conquered by the Portuguese under
                    Albuquerque.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Malacca</hi> is the capital of the country of Malacca, and
                    is situated on the straits of the same name, near the southern extremity of the
                    Malay peninsula. The town is large; many of the houses are built of stone; and
                    there are several spacious and handsome streets. But that part of it inhabited
                    by the natives consists of bamboo and mat huts. Since the formation of the
                    British settlement at Pulo Pinang, or Prince of Wales Island, its commercial
                    importance has declined. The surrounding country is fertile and beautiful, being
                    finely diversified for eight miles round with hill and dale; and beyond that
                    distance it is rendered impracticable by woods and morasses. There is a good
                    roadstead for large ships, about a mile and a half from the place; but the
                    entrance to the river is rendered intricate by a bar, over which boats cannot
                    pass before quarter flood, nor after last quarter ebb, without much difficulty.
                    Under the lee of the island, near to the fort, there is a harbour, where, in the
                    south-west monsoon, vessels of light burden may be secured. On the southern side
                    of the river is a fort, the walls of which are in a ruinous condition. The chief
                    imports are grain, which is brought in considerable quantities from Bengal,
                    Java, and Sumatra, opium, piece-goods, silks, and dollars. The exports are
                    chiefly tin, pepper, sago, canes, elephants’ teeth, biche de mer, and some gold
                    dust. Fruits and vegetables are abundant; and there is also plenty of buffaloes,
                    hogs, poultry, and fish, at moderate prices, though sheep and bullocks are
                    scarce. Malacca was founded about the year 1252; and in 1508 it was first
                    visited by the Portuguese, who, on a quarrel which broke out, were arrested by
                    the king, and being thrown into prison, several of them were put to death.
                    Albuquerque, the renowned Portuguese commander, immediately declared war against
                    this eastern prince; and, after an obstinate contest, stormed the town of
                    Malacca, which became one of their principal settlements, and the key of their
                    trade with the seas beyond India. In 1605 it was attacked by the Dutch, who
                    destroyed a Portuguese fleet in the roads, but failed to take the place. In
                    1640, however, they reduced it, after an obstinate resistance, and retained it
                    till the year 1795, when it was subjected by a British force, but was restored
                    at the peace of Amiens. It was afterwards recaptured by the British, in whose
                    possession it still remains. Long. 102. 12. E. Lat. 2. 14. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
