<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-2890-0236-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANTUA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 236</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39453">Silk</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs7w">Leather</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1118724">Silk</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:995089">Leather</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:938081">Garrisons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194202890" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANTUA</label>, a delegation of the Austrian kingdom ol
                    Lombardy, within the government of Milan. It is bounded on the south side by the
                    duchies of Modena and Parma, and on all the others by the other provinces of
                    Austrian Italy. It is generally a level district, watered by the river Mincio,
                    which falls into the Po. It extends over 610 square miles, and comprehends one
                    city, fifteen market-towns, some of them very extensive, fifty-seven villages,
                    33,700 houses, and 239,436 inhabitants. Until the year 1705, it had its dukes of
                    the family of Gonzaga. The last of that title, Charles IV., having taken part
                    with the king of France in the war of the Spanish succession, was deposed by the
                    emperor; and as he died soon afterwards without issue, his dominions were
                    granted to the house of Austria. It was in 1797 constituted by Bonaparte a part
                    of the Cisalpine republic, and afterwards formed a division of the province of
                    the Mincio in the kingdom of Italy. The fall of his power in 1814 restored it to
                    the house of Austria. The soil is various, but upon the whole productive,
                    yielding abundance of wine, silk, rice, maize, and some wheat; and in some parts
                    it has abundant pastures, on which much cheese is made from large dairies. It
                    has some manufactures of stuffs, silk, cloth, and leather. The climate in
                    general is moist, and occasions fever, more especially near the junction of the
                    river Mincio with the Po; but in the northern part of the district, where it
                    comes in contact with the lake of Garda, the climate is purer, and fevers are as
                    little known as in any part of Italy.</p>
                <p>The capital of this district is the city of the same name, celebrated as the
                    birth-place of the poet Virgil, and in modern times as one of the strongest
                    fortresses of Europe. To those who approach it, it has much the appearance of
                    Venice, from its lofty towers and magnificent domes, rising, like that city, out
                    of the water by which it is surrounded on all sides. To this peculiarity of
                    position it is mainly indebted for its impregnable strength, since it can only
                    be assailed by gaining possession of the narrow causeways which lead through the
                    lake, and which are defended by powerful outworks, and long fortified bridges.
                    One of these bridges may be more properly considered as a covered way, because
                    it only admits one passage for the water. The bridge leading to St George’s Gate
                    is a masterpiece of workmanship, being 1500 feet in length, and commanding a
                    view over the whole of the city. It requires at least a garrison of 30,000 men
                    to man the several batteries, and has often contained many more than that
                    number. It can only be taken by a long blockade, attended with the consumption
                    of all the provisions and ammunition contained in it. It was taken by the French
                    in 1796, after a blockade of very long duration, in which General Wurmser, the
                    Austrian commander, and his troops, had become exhausted by the united effect of
                    fatigue and starvation. It was retaken by the Austrian general Kray in 1799,
                    after the French garrison and the inhabitants had been nearly starved. In 1801
                    it was given up to the French by the treaty of Campo Formio; but at the peace of
                    1814 it was surrendered to Austria, having then but few troops within it, and no
                    stock of provisions or stores. The interior of the city is large, with broad and
                    regular streets, recently well paved, and a great number of fine old buildings,
                    mostly erected when it was the seat of the ducal sovereign, and contained 50,000
                    inhabitants. The ancient palace, which Bonaparte fitted up and furnished for an
                    imperial residence, is of vast extent, but at present scarcely occupied. The
                    other most remarkable edifices are, the church and library formerly belonging to
                    the Franciscans; the church of the Jesuits, with its lofty astronomical
                    observatory; the Palazzo della Gi-ustizia; the palace called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Te,</hi> from its form like T, with the picture gallery, in which
                    are the best pictures of Julio Romano, and the artists of his school; the
                    university, founded in 1625; and the academy of sciences and arts.</p>
                <p>There are several fine piazzas, the most distinguished of which bears the name of
                    the great poet, Piazza Virgiliana. It was planned by the French; the centre is
                    laid out in gardens; and around them are new and elegant mansions, and at the
                    end is the street Foro Virgiliano, which is terminated by a magnificent
                    triumphal arch, to commemorate the visit of the Emperor Francis in 1825.</p>
                <p>Mantua now contains only 25,000 inhabitants, and one half of the older large
                    houses are unoccupied. The employment of greatest extent is that of making
                    leather, both tanned and curried; and, besides, there are small establishments
                    for making silk goods, twine and cordage, parchment, linens, paper, glass, soap,
                    and barges and boats, to be used on the lakes. Virgil’s birth-place is in the
                    neighbouring village, formerly called Andes, and now Pietola.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
