<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-0238-0032-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAHOMMEDANISM</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 32</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="27" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1213323">Aden</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:937845">Gardeners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194200238" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAHOMMEDANISM</label>, the system of religion established by
                    Mahommed, and still adhered to by his followers. (See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mahommed,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Koran.)</hi> Mahommedanism is professed
                    by the Turks, Persians, and several nations amongst the Africans, and by many
                    amongst the East Indians.</p>
                <p>The Mahommedans divide their religion into two general parts, faith and practice.
                    Of these, the first is divided into six distinct branches; belief in God, in his
                    angels, in his Scriptures, in his prophets, in the resurrection and final
                    judgment, and in God’s absolute decrees. The points relating to practice are,
                    prayer with ablutions, alms, fasting, the pilgrimage to Mekka, and
                    circumcision.</p>
                <p>I. Of the Mahommedan faith. That both Mahommed and those amongst his followers
                    who are reckoned orthodox, had and continue to have just and true notions of God
                    and his attributes, appears so plain from the Koran itself, and all the
                    Mahommedan divines, that it would be loss of time to refute those who suppose
                    the God of Mahommed<pb break="no" facs="nls:194200251"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-0251-0033"/> to be different from the true God, and only a
                    fictitious deity or idol of his own creation.</p>
                <p>The existence of angels, and their purity, are absolutely required to be believed
                    in the Koran; and he is reckoned an infidel who denies that there are such
                    beings, or hates any of them, or asserts any distinction of sexes amongst them.
                    They believe them to have pure and subtile bodies, created of fire; that they
                    neither eat nor drink, nor propagate their species; that they have various forms
                    and offices, some adoring'God in different postures, and others singing praises
                    to him, or interceding for mankind. They hold, that some of them are employed in
                    writing down the actions of men; others in carrying the throne of God, and
                    performing various services besides. The four angels whom they look on as more
                    eminently in God’s favour, and often mention on account of the offices assigned
                    them, arc, Gabriel, to whom they give several titles, particularly those of the
                    Holy Spirit, and the Angel of Revelations, supposing him to be honoured by God
                    with a greater confidence than any other, and to be employed in writing down the
                    divine decrees; Michael, the friend and protector of the Jews; Az-rael, the
                    angel of death, who separates men’s souls from their bodies; and Israsil, whose
                    office it will be to sound the trumpet at the resurrection. The Mahommedans also
                    believe that two guardian angels attend on every man, to observe and write down
                    his actions; that they are changed every day, and therefore belong to <hi
                    rend="italic">al Moakkibat,</hi> or the angels who continually succeed one
                    another. The devil, whom Mahommed names Eblis, from his despair, was once one of
                    those angels who were nearest to God’s presence, being called Azazil; and he
                    fell, according to the doctrine of the Koran, for refusing to pay homage to Adam
                    at the command of God. Besides angels and devils, the Mahommedans are taught by
                    the Koran to believe in an intermediate order of creatures, which they call <hi
                    rend="italic">jin</hi> or genii, created also of fire, but of a grosser fabric
                    than angels, since they eat and drink, and propagate their species, and are
                    subject to death. Some of these are supposed to be good’and others bad, and
                    capable of future salvation or damnation, as men are; and henceMahommed
                    pretended to be sent for the conversion of genii as well as for that of men.</p>
                <p>As to the Scriptures, the Mahommedans are taught by the Koran, that God, in
                    different ages of the world, gave revelations of his will in writing to several
                    prophets, the whole and every one of which it is absolutely necessary for a good
                    Moslem to believe. The number of these sacred books was, according to them, a
                    hundred and four. Of these, ten were given to Adam, fifty to Seth, thirty to
                    Edris or Enoch, ten to Abraham; and the other four, being the Pentateuch, the
                    Psalms, the Gospel, and the Koran, were successively delivered to Moses, David,
                    Jesus, and Mahommed; but the last being the seal of the prophets, those
                    revelations are now closed, and are no more to be expected. All these divine
                    books, except the four last, they admit to be now entirely lost, and their
                    contents unknown; though the Sabians have several books which they attribute to
                    some of the antediluvian prophets. And of these four, the Pentateuch, Psalms,
                    and Gospel have, according to them, undergone so many alterations and
                    corruptions, that, though there may possibly be found therein some part of the
                    true word of God, yet no credit is to be given to the present copies in the
                    hands of the Jews and Christians. The Mahommedans have also a gospel in Arabic,
                    attributed to St Barnabas, in which the history of Jesus Christ is related in a
                    manner very different from that in which we find it narrated in the true
                    gospels, and corresponding to those traditions which Mahommed has followed in
                    his Koran. Of this gospel the Moriscoes in Africa have a translation in Spanish;
                    and there was, in the library of Prince Eugene of Savoy, a manuscript of some
                    antiquity, containing an Italian translation of the same gospel, made, it is to
                    be supposed, for the use of renegades. This book appears to be no original
                    forgery of the Mahommedans; though they have, doubtless, interpolated and
                    altered it since, the better to serve their purpose; and in particular, instead
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Paraclete,</hi> or Comforter, they have in this
                    apocryphal gospel inserted the word <hi rend="italic">Periclyte,</hi> meaning
                    the “famous” or “illustrious,” by which they pretend their prophet was foretold
                    by name, that being the signification of “Mohammed” in Arabic; and this they say
                    to justify that passage of the Koran where Jesus Christ is formally asserted to
                    have foretold his coming, under his other name of <hi rend="italic">Ahmed,</hi>
                    which is derived from the same root as “Mohammed,” and of the same import. From
                    these, and some other forgeries of the same stamp, the Mahommedans quote several
                    passages, of which there are not the least traces to be found in the New
                    Testament.</p>
                <p>The number of the prophets which have from time to time been sent by God into the
                    world, amounts to no less than two hundred and twenty-four thousand according to
                    one Mahommedan tradition, or to a hundred and twenty-four thousand according to
                    another. Amongst these were three hundred and thirteen apostles, sent with
                    special commissions to reclaim mankind from infidelity and superstition; whilst
                    six, Adam, Noah, Abraham, Moses, Jesus, and Mahommed, introduced new laws or
                    dispensations, which successively abrogated those that preceded them. All the
                    prophets in general the Mahommedans believe to have been free from great sins
                    and errors of consequence, and professors of one and the same religion, that is,
                    Islamism, notwithstanding the different laws and institutions which they may
                    have observed. They allow of degrees amongst them, and hold some to be more
                    excellent and honourable than others. The first place they give to the authors
                    and founders of new dispensations, and the next to the apostles. In this great
                    number of prophets, they not only reckon various patriarchs and persons named in
                    Scripture, but not recorded to have been prophets, such as Adam, Seth, Lot,
                    Ishmael, Nun, Joshua, and others, and introduce some of them under different
                    names, as Enoch, Heber, and Jethro, who are called, in the Koran, Edris, Hud,
                    and Shoaib; but likewise several others whose very names do not appear in
                    Scripture, though they endeavour to find some persons there with whom to connect
                    them, as Saleh, Khedr, Dhu’lkefl, and others.</p>
                <p>The belief of a general resurrection and a future judgment forms part of the
                    creed of Islamism. <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> When a corpse is laid in the
                    grave, they say it is received by an angel, who gives notice of the coming of
                    the two examiners, two black and livid angels, of a terrible appearance, named
                    <hi rend="italic">Manlier</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nahir.</hi> These order the
                    dead person to sit upright, and then examine him concerning his faith as to the
                    unity of God, and the mission of Mahommed. If he answer rightly, they suffer the
                    body to rest in peace, and it is refreshed by the air of paradise; but if
                    otherwise, they beat him on the temples with iron maces, till from anguish he
                    roars out so loudly that he is heard by all from east to west, excepting men and
                    genii. They then press the earth on the corpse, which is gnawed and stung till
                    the resurrection, by ninety-nine dragons, with seven heads each; or,as others
                    say, their sins become venomous beasts, the more grievous ones stinging like
                    dragons, the smaller like scorpions, and the others like serpents; circumstances
                    which some understand in a figurative sense. As to the soul, they hold, that,
                    when it is separated from the body by the angel of death, who performs his
                    office with ease and gentleness towards the good, and with violence towards the
                    wicked, it enters into that which they call <hi rend="italic">al berzahlι,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">the interval</hi> between death and the resurrection. If
                    the departed person was a believer, they say two angels meet the soul, and
                    convey it to heaven, that its place there may be assigned, according to its
                    merit and degree. They distinguish the souls of the faithful into three classes;
                    the first, those of prophets, whose <pb break="no" facs="nls:194200264"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-0264-0034"/>spirits are admitted into paradise immediately;
                    the second, those of martyrs, whose spirits, according to a tradition of
                    Mahommed, rest in the crops of green birds, which eat of the fruits and drink of
                    the rivers of paradise; and the third, those of other believers, concerning the
                    state of whose souls before the resurrection there are various opinions.</p>
                <p>Though some amongst the Mahommedans have thought that the resurrection will be
                    merely spiritual, and no more than the returning of the soul to the place whence
                    it first came, an opinion defended by Ebn Sina, and called by some the “opinion
                    of the philosophers ;” and others, who allow man to consist of body only, allege
                    that it will be merely corporeal; the received opinion is, that both body and
                    soul will be raised, and their doctors argue strenuously for the possibility of
                    the resurrection of the body, and dispute with great subtilty concerning the
                    manner of it. But Mahommed.has taken care to preserve one part of the body,
                    whatever becomes of the rest, to serve as a basis for the future edifice, or
                    rather a leven for the mass which is to be joined to it. He taught that a man’s
                    body was entirely consumed by the earth, excepting only the bone called <hi
                    rend="italic">al ajb,</hi> which we name the <hi rend="italic">os
                    coccygis</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> or rump-bone; and that, as it
                    was the first formed in the human body, it will also remain uncorrupted till the
                    last day, as a seed whence the whole is to be renewed; and this, he said, would
                    be effected by a forty years’ rain, which God would send, and which would cover
                    the earth to the height of twelve cubits, and cause the bodies to sprout forth
                    like plants. In this also Mahommed is beholden to the Jews, who say the same
                    thing of the bone <hi rend="italic">luz,</hi> excepting that what he attributes
                    to a great rain will, according to them, be effected by a dew impregnating the
                    dust of the earth.</p>
                <p>The time of the resurrection the Mahommedans allow to be a perfect secret to all
                    but to God alone; the angel Gabriel himself having acknowledged his ignorance on
                    this point when Mahommed asked him about it. The approach of that day may,
                    however, be known from certain signs which are to precede it. These signs are
                    distinguished into two sorts, the lesser and the greater. The lesser signs are,
                    the decay of faith amongst men; the advancing of the meanest persons to eminent
                    dignity, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> maid-servant becoming the mother of her
                    mistress (or master), by which is meant, either that towards the end of the
                    world men shall be much given to sensuality, or that the Mahommedans shall then
                    take many captives; tumults and seditions; a war with the Turks; great distress
                    in the world, so that a man, when he passes by another’s grave, shall say, Would
                    to God that I were in his place; the provinces of Irak and Syria refusing to pay
                    their tribute; and the buildings of Medina reaching even unto Yahab. Amongst the
                    greater signs may be mentioned, the sun’s rising in the west, which some have
                    imagined it originally did; and the appearance of the beast, which shall rise
                    out of the earth, in the temple of Mekka, or on Mount Safa, or in the territory
                    of Tayer, or in some other place. This beast, they say, is to be sixty cubits in
                    height; though others, not satisfied with so small a size, will have her reach
                    to the clouds and to heaven, when her head only is out, and that she will appear
                    for three days, but show only a third part of her body. They describe this
                    monster as, in respect of form, a compound of various species, having the head
                    of a bull, the eyes of a hog, the ears of an elephant, the horns of a stag, the
                    neck of an ostrich, the breast of a lion, the colour of a tiger, the back of a
                    cat, the tail of a ram, the legs of a camel, and the voice of an ass. Some say
                    that this beast is to appear three times in several places, and that she will
                    bring with her the rod of Moses and the seal of Solomon, and, being so swift
                    that none can overtake or escape her, will with the first strike all the
                    believers on the face, and mark them with the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >mumen</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> y</hi> or believer; and with the latter
                    will likewise mark the unbelievers on the face with the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >kiafir</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> or infidel, that every person
                    may be known for what he really is. They add, that the same beast is to
                    demonstrate the vanity of all religions except Islamism, and to speak Arabic.
                    All this stuff seems to be the result of a confused idea of the beast in the
                    Revelation. The third sign is, war with the Greeks, and the taking of
                    Constantinople by seventy thousand of the posterity of Isaac, who shall not win
                    that city by force of arms, but the walls shall fall down whilst they cry out,
                    “There is no God but God; God is most great.” As they are dividing the spoil,
                    tidings will come to them of the appearance of Antichrist, upon which they shall
                    leave all, and return to the place whence they came. The fourth sign is the
                    coming of Antichrist, whom the Mahommedans call <hi rend="italic">Ma-sib al
                    Dajjal,</hi> that is, the false or lying Christ, and simply <hi rend="italic">Al
                    Dajjal.</hi> He is to be one-eyed, and marked on the forehead with the letters
                    signifying <hi rend="italic">kia</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">fir,</hi> or infidel. They say that the Jews give him the name of
                    Messiah Ben David; and pretend that he is to come in the last days, and to be
                    lord both of land and sea, and that he will restore to them the kingdom. The
                    fifth sign is the descent of Jesus upon earth. They pretend that he is to
                    descend near the white tower to the east of Damascus, when the people are
                    returned from the taking of Constantinople; that he is to embrace the Mahommedan
                    religion, marry a wife, beget children, kill Antichrist, and at length to die
                    after forty years’, or, according to others, twenty-four years’, continuance on
                    earth. Under him, they say, there will be great security and plenty in the
                    world; all hatred and malice will then be laid aside; lions and camels, bears
                    and sheep, shall live in peace, and a child shall play with serpents unhurt. The
                    sixth sign is, war with the Jews, of whom the Mahommedans are to make a
                    prodigious slaughter; the very trees and stones discovering such of them as hide
                    themselves, excepting only the tree called <hi rend="italic">gharkad,</hi> which
                    is the tree of the Jews. The seventh sign is the irruption of Gog and Magog, or,
                    as they are called in the east. <hi rend="italic">Yajuj</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Majuj</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi> whom many things are related in the Koran and in the traditions of
                    Mahommed. These barbarians, we are told, having passed the lake of Tiberias,
                    which the vanguard of their vast army are to drink dry, will come to Jerusalem,
                    and there greatly distress Jesus and his companions; until, at his request, God
                    shall destroy them, and fill the earth with their carcasses, which, after some
                    time, birds of prey will be sent to carry away at the prayers of Jesus and his
                    followers. Their bows, arrows, and quivers, the Moslemins will burn for seven
                    years together; and at last God will send a rain to cleanse the earth and to
                    make it fertile. The eighth sign is to be a smoke which shall fill the whole
                    earth. The ninth is an eclipse of the moon. Mahommed is reported to have said,
                    that there would be three eclipses before the last hour; one to be seen in the
                    east, another in the west, and a third in Arabia. The tenth sign is the
                    returning of the Arabs to the worship of Allât and Al Uzza, and the rest of
                    their ancient idols, after the decease of every one in whose heart there was
                    faith equal to a grain of mustard seed, none but the very worst of men being
                    left alive; for God, they say, will send a cold odoriferous wind, blowing from
                    Syria Damascena, which shall sweep away the souls of all the faithful, and the
                    Koran itself, so that men will remain in the grossest ignorance for a hundred
                    years. The eleventh sign is the discovery of a vast heap of gold and silver by
                    the retreating of the Euphrates, which will be the destruction of many; the
                    twelfth is the demolition of the Kaaba, or temple of Mekka, by the Ethiopians;
                    the thirteenth, the speaking of beasts and inanimate tilings; the fourteenth,
                    the breaking out or fire in the province of Hedjaz, or, according to others, in
                    Yemen; the fifteenth, the appearance of one of the descendants of Kahtan, who
                    shall drive men before him by <pb break="no" facs="nls:194200277"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-0277-0035"/>means of his staff; the sixteenth, the coming of
                    the Mohdi, or the Director, concerning whom Mahommed prophesied, that the world
                    should not have an end till one of his own family should govern the Arabians,
                    whose name should be the same with his own name, and whose father’s name should
                    also be the same with his father’s name, and who should fill the earth with
                    righteousness. This person the Shecites believe to be now alive, and concealed
                    in some secret place till the time of his manifestation arrive; for they suppose
                    him to be no other than the last of the twelve imams, named Mahommed Abu’lkasem,
                    as their prophet was, and the son of Hassan al Askeri, the eleventh of that
                    succession, having been born at Sermanrai, in the 255th year of the Hejira. From
                    this tradition it is to be presumed that an opinion pretty current amongst the
                    Christians took its rise, namely, that the Mahommedans are in expectation of
                    their prophet’s return. The seventeenth sign is to be a wind which shall sweep
                    away the souls of all who have but a grain of faith in their hearts, as has been
                    mentioned under the tenth sign.</p>
                <p>These are the greater signs, which, according to the doctrine of Islamism, are to
                    precede the resurrection, but still leave the hour of it uncertain, for the
                    immediate sign of its being come will be the first blast of the trumpet, which
                    they believe will be sounded three times. The first they call the <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t’!</hi> blast of consternation,” at the hearing of which
                    all creatures in heaven and earth shall be struck with terror, excepting those
                    whom God shall please to exempt from it. The effects attributed to this first
                    sound of the trumpet are very wonderful. It is believed that the earth will be
                    shaken, and not only all buildings, but the very mountains levelled; that the
                    heavens shall melt, the sun be darkened, the stars fall, upon the death of the
                    angels who, as some imagine, hold them suspended between heaven and earth; and
                    that the sea shall be troubled and dried up, or, according to others, turned
                    into flames, the sun, moon, and stars being thrown into it. The Koran, to
                    express the greatness of the terror of that day, adds, that women who give suck
                    shall abandon the care of their infants, and that even the she-camels which have
                    gone ten months with young (a most valuable part of the substance of that
                    nation) shall be utterly neglected. A further effect of this blast will be that
                    concourse of beasts mentioned in the Koran, although some doubt whether it is to
                    precede or to follow the resurrection. They who suppose it will precede, think
                    that all kinds of animals, forgetting their natural fierceness or timidity, will
                    run together into one place, being terrified by the sound of the trumpet and the
                    sudden shock of nature. The Mahommedans believe that this first blast will be
                    followed by a second one, which they call the “blast of exinanition,” by which
                    all creatures both in heaven and earth shall die or be annihilated, excepting
                    those which God shall please to exempt from the common fate; and this, they say,
                    shall happen in the twinkling of an eye, nay, in an instant, nothing surviving
                    except God alone, with paradise and hell, and the inhabitants of those tw’O
                    places, and the throne of glory. The last who shall die will be the angel of
                    death. Forty years after this will be heard the “blast of resurrection,” when
                    the trumpet shall be sounded for the third time by Israsil, who, together with
                    Gabriel and Michael, will be previously restored to life, and, standing upon the
                    rock of the temple of Jerusalem, shall, at God’s command, call together all the
                    dry and rotten bones, and other dispersed parts of the bodies, and the very
                    hairs, to judgment. This angel having, by the divine order, set the trumpet to
                    his mouth, and called together all the souls from every part, will throw them
                    into his trumpet, whence, on his giving the last sound, at the command of God,
                    they will fly forth like bees, and fill the whole space between heaven and
                    earth, and then repair to their respective bodies, which the opening earth will
                    suffer to arise; and the first who shall so arise, according to a tradition of
                    Mahommed, will be the prophet himself. For this birth the earth will be prepared
                    by the rain above mentioned, which is to fall continually for forty years, and
                    will resemble the seed of a man, and be supplied from the water under the throne
                    of God, which is called “living water,” by the efficacy and virtue of which the
                    dead bodies shall spring forth from their graves as they did in their mother’s
                    womb, or as corn sprouts forth by common rain, until they become perfect; after
                    which breath will be breathed into them, and they will sleep in their sepulchres
                    till they are raised to life by the last trumpet.</p>
                <p>When those who have risen shall have waited the limited time, the Mahommedans
                    believe that God will at length appear to judge them; Mahommed undertaking the
                    office of intercessor, after it shall have been declined by Adam, Noah, Abraham,
                    and Jesus, who shall beg deliverance only for their own souls. They say, that
                    upon this solemn occasion God will come in the clouds surrounded by angels, and
                    will produce the books in which the actions of every person are recorded by
                    their guardian angels, and will command the prophets to bear witness against
                    those to whom they have been respectively sent. Then every one will be examined
                    concerning all the words and actions uttered and done by him in this life; not
                    as if God needed any information in these respects, but to oblige the person to
                    make public confession and acknowledgment of God’s justice. The particulars of
                    which they are to give an account, as Mahommed himself enumerated them, are,
                    1st, of their time, how they spent it; 2d, of their wealth, by what means they
                    acquired it, and how they' employed it; 3d, of their bodies, in what they
                    exercised them; and, lastly, of their knowledge and learning, what use they made
                    of them. To the questions we have mentioned each person shall answer, and make
                    his defence in the best manner he can, endeavouring to excuse himself by-casting
                    the blame of his evil deeds upon others; so that a dispute shall arise even
                    between the soul and the body, to which of them their guilt ought to be imputed.
                    The soul will say, “O Lord, my body I received from thee; for thou createdst me
                    without a hand to lay hold with, a foot to walk with, an eye to see with, or an
                    understanding to apprehend with, till I came and entered into this body;
                    therefore punish it eternally, but deliver me.” The body', on the other side,
                    will make this apology; “0 Lord, thou createdst me like a stock of wood, having
                    neither hand that I could lay hold with, nor foot that I could walk with, till
                    this soul, like a ray of light, entered into me, and my tongue began to speak,
                    my eye to see, and my foot to walk; therefore punish it eternally, but deliver
                    me.” But God will propound to them the parable of the blind man and the lame
                    man. A certain king having a pleasant garden, in which were ripe fruits, set two
                    persons to keep it, one of whom was blind, and the other lame; the former not
                    being able to see the fruit, nor the latter to gather it. The lame man, however,
                    seeing the fruit, persuaded the blind man to take him upon his shoulders, and by
                    that means he easily gathered the fruit, which they divided between them. The
                    lord of the garden coming some time afterwards, and inquiring after his fruit,
                    each began to excuse himself. The blind man said he had no eyes to see with; and
                    the lame man, that he had no feet to approach the trees. But the king, ordering
                    the lame man to be set on the blind, passed sentence on and punished them both.
                    And in the same manner will God deal with the body and the soul. As these
                    apologies will not avail on that day, so it will be in vain for any one to deny
                    his evil actions, since men and angels, and his own members, nay, the very earth
                    itself, will be ready to bear witness against him.</p>
                <p>At this examination, the Mahommedans also believe that <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194200290" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0290-0036"/>each person will have the
                    book in which all the actions of his life are written delivered to him. These
                    the righteous will receive into the right hand, and read with great pleasure and
                    satisfaction; but the ungodly will be obliged to take them, against their will,
                    in their left, which will be bound at their back, their right hand being tied up
                    to their necks.</p>
                <p>To show the exact justice which will be observed on this great day of trial, the
                    next thing they describe is the balance, in which all things shall be weighed.
                    It will be held by Gabriel; and it is of so vast a size that its two scales, one
                    of which hangs over paradise, and the other over hell, are capacious enough to
                    contain both heaven and hell. Though some are willing to understand what is said
                    in the Koran concerning this balance allegorically, and only as a figurative
                    representation of God’s equity, yet the more ancient and orthodox opinion is,
                    that the words are to be taken literally; and since words and actions, being
                    mere accidents, are not capable of being themselves weighed, they say that the
                    books in which they are written will be thrown into the scales, and according as
                    those in which the good or evil actions are recorded shall preponderate,
                    sentence will be given. Those whose balances laden with good works shall prove
                    heavy, will be saved; but those whose balances are light, will be condemned. Nor
                    will any one have cause to complain that God suffers good actions to pass
                    unrewarded, because the wicked for the good they do have their reward in this
                    life, and therefore can expect no favour in the next.</p>
                <p>This examination being ended, and every one’s works weighed in a just balance,
                    that mutual retaliation will follow, according to which every creature will take
                    vengeance one upon another, or have satisfaction made them for the injuries
                    which they have suffered. And since there will then be no other way of returning
                    like for like, the manner of giving this satisfaction will be by taking away a
                    proportional part of the good works of him who offered the injury, and adding it
                    to those of him who suffered it. This being done, if the angels by whose
                    ministry it is to be performed say, “Lord, we have given to every one his due,
                    and there remaineth of this person’s good works so much as equalleth the weight
                    of an ant,” God will, of his mercy, cause it be doubled unto him, that he may be
                    admitted into paradise; but if, on the contrary, his good works be exhausted,
                    and there remain evil works only, and any who have not yet received satisfaction
                    from him, God will order that an equal weight of their sins be added unto his,
                    that he may be punished for them in their stead, and he will be sent to hell
                    laden with both. This will be the method of God’s dealing with mankind. As to
                    brutes, after they shall have likewise taken vengeance upon one another, he
                    shall command them to be changed into dust; wicked men being reserved to a more
                    grievous punishment, so that they shall cry out, on hearing this sentence passed
                    on the brutes, “Would to God that we were dust also.” As to the genii, many
                    Mahommedans are of opinion that such of them as are true believers will undergo
                    the same fate as the irrational animals, and have no other reward than the
                    favour of being converted into dust; and for this they quote the authority of
                    their prophet.</p>
                <p>These trials being over, and the assembly dissolved, the Mahommedans hold that
                    those who are to be admitted into paradise will take the right-hand way, and
                    those who are destined to hell-fire will take the left; but both of them must
                    first pass the bridge called in Arabic <hi rend="italic">Al Sirat,</hi> which
                    they say is laid over the midst of hell, and describe to be finer than a hair,
                    and sharper than the edge of a sword, so that it seems very difficult to
                    conceive how any one shall be able to stand upon it; and, for this reason, most
                    of the sect of the Motazalites reject it as a fable, though the orthodox think
                    it a sufficient proof of the truth of this article. that it was seriously
                    affirmed by him who never asserted a falsehood, meaning their prophet. To add to
                    the difficulty of the passage, he has likewise declared that this bridge is
                    beset on each side with briars and hooked thorns; which will, however, be no
                    impediment to the good, for they shall pass with wonderful ease and swiftness,
                    like lightning, or the wind, Mahommed and his Moslemins leading the way:
                    whereas, from the slipperiness and extreme narrowness of the path, the
                    entangling of the thorns, and the extinction of the light which directed the
                    good to paradise, the wicked will soon miss their footing, and fall down
                    headlong into hell, which is gaping beneath them.</p>
                <p>As to the punishment of the wicked, the Mahommedans are taught that hell is
                    divided into seven stories or apartments, one below another, designed for the
                    reception of as many distinct classes of the damned. The first, which they call
                    <hi rend="italic">Jehennam,</hi> will, according to them, be the receptacle of
                    those who acknowledge one God, that is, the wicked Mahommedans, who, after
                    having been there punished according to their demerits, will at length be
                    released. The second, named <hi rend="italic">Ladha,∙</hi> they assign to the
                    Jews; the third, named <hi rend="italic">Al Hotama,</hi> to the Christians; the
                    fourth, named <hi rend="italic">Al Sair,</hi> to the Sabians; the fifth, named
                    <hi rend="italic">Sakar,</hi> to the Magians; the sixth, named <hi rend="italic"
                    >Al Jaliim,</hi> to the idolaters; and the seventh, or lowest and worst of all,
                    which is called <hi rend="italic">Al īīawyat,</hi> to the hypocrites, or those
                    who outwardly professed some religion, but who in their hearts believed none.
                    Over each of these apartments they believe that there will be set a guard of
                    angels, nineteen in number, to whom the damned will confess the just judgment of
                    God, and beg them to intercede with him for some alleviation of their pain, or
                    that they may be delivered by being annihilated.</p>
                <p>Mahommed, in his Koran and traditions, has been very exact in describing the
                    various torments of hell, which, according to him, the wicked will suffer, both
                    from intense heat and from excessive cold. We shall, however, enter into no
                    detail respecting them here, but only observe, that the degrees of these pains
                    will also vary in proportion to the crimes of the sufferer, and the apartment he
                    is condemned to inhabit; and that he who is punished the most lightly of all
                    will be shod with shoes of fire, the heat of which will cause his skull to boil
                    like a cauldron. The condition of these unhappy wretches, as the same prophet
                    teaches, cannot be properly called either life or death; and their misery will
                    be greatly increased by their despair of being ever delivered from that place,
                    since, according to the frequent expression of the Koran, “they shall remain
                    therein for ever.” It must be remarked, however, that the infidels alone will be
                    liable to eternal damnation; for the Moslemins, or those who have embraced the
                    true religion, and have been guilty of heinous sins, will be delivered thence
                    after they shall have expiated their crimes by their sufferings. According to a
                    tradition handed down from their prophet, the time during which these believers
                    shall be detained there, will not be less than nine hundred years, nor more than
                    seven thousand. And as to the manner of their delivery, they shall be
                    distinguished by the marks of prostration on those parts of their bodies with
                    which they used to touch the ground in prayer, and over which the fire will
                    therefore have no power; and that, being known by this characteristic, they will
                    be released by the mercy of God, at the intercession of Mahommed and the
                    blessed; upon which those who shall have been dead will be restored to life, and
                    those whose bodies shall have contracted any filth from the flames and smoke of
                    hell will be immersed in one of the rivers of paradise, called “the river of
                    life,” the waters of which will wash them whiter than pearls.</p>
                <p>The righteous, as the Mahommedans are taught to believe, having surmounted the
                    difficulties, and passed the sharp bridge above mentioned, before they enter
                    paradise, <pb break="no" facs="nls:194200303" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0303-0037"/>will
                    be refreshed by drinking at the reservoir of the prophet, who describes it as an
                    exact square of a month’s journey in compass; its water, which is supplied by
                    two pipes from Al Cawthar, one of the rivers of paradise, being whiter than milk
                    or silver, and more odoriferous than musk, with as many cups set around it as
                    there are stars in the firmament, and of this water whoever drinks will thirst
                    no more for ever. This is the first taste which the blessed will have of their
                    future and now approaching felicity. ∙</p>
                <p>Though paradise be so frequently mentioned in the Koran, yet it is a dispute
                    amongst the Mahommedans whether it be already created, or only to be created
                    hereafter; the Motazalites and some other sectaries asserting that there is not
                    at present any such place in nature, and that the paradise which the righteous
                    will inhabit in the next life will be different from that which Adam was
                    expelled from. However, the orthodox profess the contrary; maintain that it was
                    created even before the world; and describe it from their prophet’s traditions.
                    They say that it is situated above the seven heavens, or in the seventh heaven,
                    and next under the throne of God; and to express the amenity of the place, they
                    allege that the earth of it is of the finest wheat flour, or of the purest musk,
                    or, as others will have it, of saffron; that its stones are pearls and jacinths,
                    the walls of its buildings enriched with gold and silver; and that the trunks of
                    all its trees are of gold, amongst which the most remarkable is the tree called
                    <hi rend="italic">Tuba,</hi> or the Tree of Happiness. Concerning this tree,
                    they pretend that it stands in the palace of Mahommed, though a branch of it
                    will reach to the house of every true believer; and that it will be laden with
                    pomegranates, grapes, dates, and other fruits, of surprising largeness, and of
                    tastes unknown to mortals; so that if a man desire to eat of any particular
                    kind, of fruit, it will be immediately presented to him; or, if he choose flesh,
                    birds ready dressed will be set before him, according to his wish. They add,
                    that the boughs of this tree will spontaneously bend down to the hand of the
                    person who would gather of its fruits, and that it will supply the blessed not
                    only with food, but also with silken garments, and beasts to ride on ready
                    saddled and bridled, and adorned with rich trappings, which will burst forth
                    from its fruits; and that this tree is so large, that a person, mounted on the
                    fleetest horse, would not be able to gallop from one end of its shade to the
                    other in a hundred years.</p>
                <p>As plenty of water is one of the greatest additions to the pleasantness of any
                    place, particularly in a burning climate, the Koran often speaks of the rivers
                    of paradise as a principal ornament of that blessed place. Some of these rivers,
                    they say, flow with water, some with milk, some with wine, and others with
                    honey, and all take their rise from the root of the tree Tuba. But all these
                    glories will be eclipsed by the resplendent and ravishing damsels of paradise,
                    called, from their large black eyes, <hi rend="italic">Huτ-al-oyun,</hi> the
                    enjoyment of whose society will be the principal felicity of the faithful.
                    These, they say, are created, not of clay, as mortal women are, but of pure
                    musk, being, as their prophet often affirms in his Koran, free from all natural
                    impurities, defects, and inconveniences incident to the sex, of the strictest
                    modesty, and secluded from public view in pavilions of hollow pearls, so large
                    that, as some traditions have it, one of them extends no less than four
                    parasangs in length, and as many in breadth.</p>
                <p>The name which the Mahommedans usually give to this happy mansion is <hi
                    rend="italic">Al Jannat,</hi> or the Garden; and sometimes they call it, with an
                    addition, <hi rend="italic">Jannat al Ferdaus,</hi> the Garden of Paradise; <hi
                    rend="italic">Jannat Aden,</hi> or the Garden of Eden (though they generally
                    interpret the word <hi rend="italic">Eden,</hi> not according to its acceptation
                    in Hebrew, but according to its meaning in their own tongue, in which it
                    signifies a settled or perpetual habitation); <hi rend="italic">Jannat al
                    Mawa,</hi> the Garden of Abode; <hi rend="italic">Jannat al Naim,</hi> the
                    Garden of Pleasure, and the like. By these several appellations some understand
                    so many different gardens, or at least places of different degrees of felicity
                    (for they reckon no less than a hundred of them in alD, the very meanest of
                    which will afford its inhabitants so many pleasures and delights that one would
                    conclude they must even sink under the enjoyment of them, had not Mahommed
                    declared, that, in order to qualify the blessed for their happy state, God will
                    give to every one the capabilities of enjoyment of a hundred men.</p>
                <p>With regard to God’s absolute decree and predestination both of good and evil,
                    the orthodox doctrine is, that whatever has or shall come to pass in this world,
                    whether it be good or whether it be evil, proceeds entirely from the divine
                    will, and is irrevocably fixed and recorded from all eternity in the preserved
                    table; God having secretly predetermined not only the adverse and prosperous
                    fortune of every person in this world, in the most minute particulars, but also
                    his faith or infidelity, his obedience or disobedience, and consequently his
                    everlasting happiness or misery after death; a fate or predestination which it
                    is not possible by any foresight or wisdom to avoid. Of this doctrine Mahommed
                    makes great use in the Koran for the advancement of his designs; encouraging his
                    followers to fight without fear, and even desperately, for the propagation of
                    their faith, by representing to them, that all their caution cannot avert their
                    inevitable destiny, or prolong their lives for a moment; and deterring them from
                    disobeying or rejecting him as an impostor, by setting before them the danger
                    they thereby incur of being, by the just judgment of God, abandoned to
                    seduction, hardness of heart, and a reprobate mind, as a punishment for their
                    obstinacy.</p>
                <p>II. Of Religious Practice. In this the first point is <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prayer,</hi> under which are also comprehended those legal washings or
                    purifications which are necessary preparations thereto.</p>
                <p>Of these purifications there are two degrees, one called <hi rend="italic"
                    >ghost,</hi> being a total immersion or bathing of the body in water; and the
                    other called <hi rend="italic">wodu</hi> (by the Persians <hi rend="italic"
                    >abdest’),</hi> which is the washing of the face, hands, and feet, after a
                    certain manner. The first is required in some extraordinary cases only, as after
                    having lain with a woman, or being polluted by emission of semen, or by
                    approaching a dead body; women are also obliged to perform it after menstruation
                    or childbirth. The latter is the ordinary ablution in common cases, and before
                    prayer, and must necessarily be employed by every person before he can enter
                    upon that duty. It is performed with certain formal ceremonies, which have been
                    described by some writers, but which are much more easily apprehended by ocular
                    observation, than by the best description.</p>
                <p>That his followers might be more punctual in this duty, Mahommed is said to have
                    declared, that “the practice of religion is founded on cleanliness,” which is
                    the “one half of the faith,” and the “key of prayer,” without which it will not
                    be heard by God. That these expressions may be the better understood, Al Ghazali
                    reckons four degrees of purification; the first of which is the cleansing of the
                    body from all pollution, filth, and excrements; the second, the cleansing of the
                    members of the body from all wickedness and unjust actions; the third, the
                    cleansing of the heart from all blameable inclinations and odious vices; and the
                    fourth, the purging a man’s secret thoughts from all affections which may divert
                    their attendance on God. The body, according to Him, is but as the outward
                    shell, in respect to the heart, which is as the kernel.</p>
                <p>Circumcision, though it be not once mentioned in the Koran, is yet held by the
                    Mahommedans to be an ancient and.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194200316" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0316-0038"/>
                <p>divine institution, confirmed by the religion of Islam, and, though not so
                    absolutely necessary that it may not be dispensed with in some cases, yet highly
                    proper and expedient. The Arabs used this rite for many ages before that of
                    Mahommed, having probably learned it from Ishmael, though not only his
                    descendants, but the Hamyarites and other tribes, practised the same rite. The
                    Ishmaelites, we are told, used to circumcise their children, not on the eighth
                    day, as is the custom of the Jews, but when about twelve or thirteen years old,
                    at which age their father underwent that operation; and the Mahommedans imitate
                    them so far as not to circumcise children before they are able distinctly to
                    pronounce that profession of their faith, “There is no God but God, and Mahommed
                    is the prophet of God but pitch on whatever age they please for the purpose,
                    between six and sixteen or thereabouts.</p>
                <p>Prayer was by Mahommed thought so necessary a duty, that he used to call it “the
                    pillar of religion” and “the key of paradise and when the Thakifites, who dwelt
                    at Tayer, sent, in the ninth year of the Hejira, to make their submission to the
                    prophet, after the keeping of their favourite idol had been denied them, they
                    begged at least that they might be allowed to dispense with saying the appointed
                    prayers; but the prophet answered, that “There could be no good in that religion
                    in which there was no prayer.”</p>
                <p>That so important a duty, therefore, might not be neglected, Mahommed obliged his
                    followers to pray five times every twenty-four hours, at certain stated times,
                    viz. in the morning before sunrise; when noon is past, and the sun begins to
                    decline from the meridian; in the afternoon before sunset; in the evening after
                    sunset, and before the day be shut in; and after the day is shut in, and before
                    the first watch of the night. For this institution he pretended to have received
                    a divine command from the throne of God himself, when he took his night journey
                    to heaven; and the observation of the stated times of prayer is frequently
                    insisted on in the Koran, though they be not particularly prescribed therein.
                    Accordingly, at the aforesaid times, of which public notice is given by the
                    Muezzins or Criers, from the steeples of the mosques, every conscientious
                    Moslemin prepares himself for prayer, which he performs either in the mosque, or
                    in any other place, provided it be clean, after a prescribed form, and with a
                    certain number of praises or ejaculations, which the more scrupulous count by a
                    string of beads, at the same time using certain postures of worship; all which
                    have been particularly set down and described, and ought not to be abridged,
                    unless in special circumstances, as on a journey, in preparing for battle, and
                    other cases of a similar kind.</p>
                <p>For the regular performance of the duty of prayer amongst the Mahommedans,
                    besides the particulars above mentioned, it is also requisite that they should
                    turn their faces, whilst they pray, towards the temple of Mekka, the quarter
                    where the same is situated being for that reason pointed out within their
                    mosques by a niche, which they call <hi rend="italic">Al Mehrab,</hi> and
                    without, by the situation of the doors opening into the galleries of the
                    steeples. There are also tables calculated for the ready finding of the Keblah,
                    or part towards which they ought to pray, in places where they have no visible
                    direction to guide them.</p>
                <p>Secondly, <hi rend="italic">Alms</hi> are of two sorts, legal and voluntary. The
                    legal alms are of indispensable obligation, being commanded by the law, which
                    directs and determines both the portion to be given, and of what things it ought
                    to be given; but the voluntary alms are left to every one’s choice, to give more
                    or less as he shall think proper. The former kind of alms, some think, are
                    properly called <hi rend="italic">zacat,</hi> and the latter <hi rend="italic"
                    >sadakat,</hi> though this last name be also frequently given to the legal alms.
                    They are called <hi rend="italic">zacat,</hi> either because they increase a
                    man’s store by drawing down a blessing thereon, and produce in his soul the
                    virtue of liberality, or because they purify the remaining part of one’s
                    substance from pollution, and the soul from the filth of avarice; and <hi
                    rend="italic">sadakat,</hi> because they are a proof of a man’s sincerity in the
                    worship of God. Some writers have called the legal alms <hi rend="italic"
                    >tithes,</hi> but improperly, since in some cases they fall short, and in others
                    exceed the proportion of a tenth part.</p>
                <p>Thirdly, <hi rend="italic">Fasting</hi> is a duty of so great moment, that
                    Mahommed used to say it was “the gate of religion,” and that the “odour of the
                    mouth of him who fasteth is more grateful to God than that of musk and Al
                    Ghazali reckons fasting “one fourth part of the faith.” According to the
                    Mahommedan divines, there are three degrees of fasting; 1<hi rend="italic"
                    >st,</hi> the restraining the belly and other parts of the body from satisfying
                    their lusts; <hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">2-dly,</hi>
                    the restraining the ears, eyes, tongue, hands, feet, and other members, from
                    sin; and, 3<hi rend="italic">dly,</hi> the fasting of the heart from worldly
                    cares, and restraining the thoughts from everything besides God.</p>
                <p>lhe Mahommedans are obliged, by the express command of the Koran, to fast during
                    the whole month of Ramadan, from the time that the new moon first appears till
                    the appearance of the next new moon; during which period they must abstain from
                    eating, drinking, and women, from daybreak till night or sunset. And this
                    injunction they observe so strictly, that, whilst they fast, they suffer nothing
                    to enter their mouths, or other parts of their body, esteeming the fast broken
                    and null if they smell perfumes, take a clyster or injection, bathe, or even
                    purposely swallow their spittle; some being so cautious that they will not open
                    their mouths to speak, lest they should breathe the air too freely. The fast is
                    also deemed void if a man kiss or touch a woman, or if he vomit designedly. But
                    after sunset they are allowed to refresh themselves, and to eat and drink, and
                    enjoy the company of their wives till daybreak; though the more rigid begin the
                    fast again at midnight. This fast is extremely rigorous and mortifying when the
                    month of Ramadan happens to fall in summer (for the Arabian year being lunar,
                    each month runs through all the different seasons in the course of thirty-three
                    years); the length and heat of the days making the observance of it then much
                    more difficult and uneasy than in winter. The reason given why the month of
                    Ramadan was pitched on for this purpose is, that on that month the Koran was
                    sent down from heaven. Some also pretend, that Abraham, Moses, and Jesus,
                    received their respective revelations in the same month.</p>
                <p>Fourthly, The pilgrimage to Mekka is so necessary a point of practice, that,
                    according to a tradition of Mahommed, he who dies without performing it may as
                    well die a Jew or a Christian; and the same is expressly commanded in the
                    Koran.</p>
                <p>The temple of Mekka stands in the midst of the city, and is honoured with the
                    title <hi rend="italic">Alasjad al Elharam,</hi> “the sacred or inviolable
                    Temple.” What is principally reverenced in this place, and gives sanctity to the
                    whole, is a square stone building, denominated the <hi rend="italic">Kaaba.</hi>
                    To this temple every Mahommedan who has health and means sufficient ought, once
                    in his life at least, to repair on a pilgrimage; nor are women excused from the
                    performance of this duty. The pilgrims meet at different places near Mekka,
                    according to the different parts whence they come, during the months of Shawal
                    and Dhu’lkaada, being obliged to be there by the beginning of Dhu’lhajja, which,
                    as its name imports, is peculiarly set apart for the celebration of this
                    solemnity.</p>
                <p>At the place above mentioned the pilgrims properly assume that character, when
                    the men put on the lbram or sacred habit, which consists only of two woollen
                    wrappers, one wrapped about the middle to cover their nakedness, and the other
                    thrown over their shoulders, having their heads bare, and a kind of slippers
                    which cover neither the heel nor the instep, and thus they enter the sacred
                    territory in their way to <pb break="no" facs="nls:194200329"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-0329-0039"/>Mekka. Whilst they wear this habit they must
                    neither hunt nor fowl, though they are allowed to fish; a precept which is so
                    punctually observed, that they will not kill even vermin if they should find
                    them on their bodies. There are some noxious animals, however, which they have
                    permission to kill during their pilgrimage, as kites, ravens, scorpions, mice,
                    and dogs given to bite. During the pilgrimage, it behoves a man to keep a
                    constant guard upon his words and actions; to avoid all quarrelling or bad
                    language, all converse with women, and all obscene discourse, and to apply his
                    whole attention to the good work in which he is engaged.</p>
                <p>The pilgrims, having arrived at Mekka, immediately visit the temple, and enter
                    upon the performance of the prescribed ceremonies, which consist chiefly in
                    going in procession round the Kaaba, in running between the Mounts Safa and
                    Merwa, in making the station upon Mount Arafat, and slaying the victims and
                    shaving their heads in the valley of Mina. In compassing the Kaaba, which they
                    do seven times, beginning at the corner where the black stone is fixed, they use
                    a short quick pace the first three times they go round it, and a grave ordinary
                    pace the last four; a practice which, it is said, was ordered by Mahommed, that
                    his followers might show themselves strong and active, to cut off the hopes of
                    the infidels, who gave out that the immoderate heats of Medina had rendered them
                    weak. The quick pace, however, they are not obliged to exert every time they
                    perform this piece of devotion, but only at some particular times. As often as
                    they pass by the black stone, they either kiss it, or touch it with their hand,
                    and then kiss that member. The running between Safa and Merwa is also performed
                    seven times, partly at a slow pace and partly with speed. They walk gravely till
                    they come to a place between two pillars, and there they run, and afterwards
                    walk again, sometimes looking back, and sometimes stooping, like one who had
                    lost something, to represent Hagar seeking water for her son, the ceremony being
                    said to be as ancient as her time.</p>
                <p>On the ninth of Dhu’lhajja, after morning prayer, the pilgrims leave the valley
                    of Mina, whither they had arrived the day before, and proceed in a tumultuous
                    and rushing manner to Mount Arafat, where they stay to perform their devotions
                    till sunset; then they <hi rend="italic">go</hi> to Mozdalifa, an oratory
                    between Arafat and Mina, and there spend the night in prayer and reading the
                    Koran. The next morning by daybreak they visit <hi rend="italic">Al Masher al
                    Karam, or</hi> the Sacred Monument; and, departing thence before sunrise, hasten
                    by Batn Mohasser to the valley of Mina, where they throw seven stones at three
                    marks or pillars, in imitation of Abraham, who, meeting the devil in that place,
                    and being by him disturbed in his devotions, or tempted to disobedience when he
                    was going to sacrifice his son, was commanded by God to drive him away by
                    throwing stones at him. But others pretend that this rite is as old as Adam, who
                    also put the devil to flight in the same place, and by the same means. This
                    ceremony being over, on the same day, the tenth of Dhu’lhajja, the pilgrims slay
                    their victims in the valley of Mina; and of these they and their friends eat
                    part, whilst the rest is given to the poor. The victims must be either sheep,
                    goats, kine, or camels; males if of either of the two former kinds, and females
                    if of either of the latter, and also of a proper age. When the sacrifices are
                    ended, they shave their heads and cut their nails, after which the pilgrimage is
                    looked upon as completed; though they again visit the Kaaba, in order to take
                    their leave of that sacred building.</p>
                <p>The rapid success which attended the propagation of this new religion was owing
                    to causes which are sufficiently obvious, and must remove, or rather prevent,
                    any surprise, when they are attentively considered. The terror of Mahommed’s
                    arms, and the repeated victories gained by him and his successors, were no doubt
                    the irresistible arguments which persuaded such multitudes to embrace his
                    religion and submit to his dominion. Besides, his law was artfully adapted to
                    the corrupt nature of man, more particularly to the manners and opinions of the
                    eastern nations, and the vices to which they were naturally addicted; for the
                    articles of faith which it proposed were few in number, and extremely simple,
                    and the duties which it required were neither many nor difficult, nor such as
                    were incompatible with the empire of appetites and passions. It may also be
                    observed, that the gross ignorance under which the Arabians, Syrians, Persians,
                    and the greater part of the eastern nations, laboured at this time, rendered
                    many an easy prey to the artifice and eloquence of this bold adventurer. To
                    these causes may be added the bitter dissensions and cruel animosities which
                    reigned amongst the Christian sects, particularly the Greeks, Nestorians,
                    Eutychians, and Monophysites; dissensions which filled a great part of the East
                    with carnage, assassinations, and other detestable enormities, which rendered
                    the very name of Christianity odious. We may further add, that the Monophysites
                    and Nestorians, full of resentment against the Greeks, from whom they had
                    suffered the bitterest and most injurious treatment, assisted the Arabians in
                    the conquest of several provinces, into which, of course, the religion of
                    Mahommed was afterwards introduced. The contrast between Chtisrianity and
                    Islamism is therefore abundantly striking.</p>
                <p>The Christian religion is the religion of a civilized people, and is entirely
                    spiritual; in it everything tends to mortify the senses, nothing to excite them.
                    Islamism is the religion of a people in the infancy of civilization, and it
                    appeals to the senses alone. Mahommed promised to his followers odoriferous
                    baths, rivers of milk, black eyed houris, and groves of perpetual shade; and the
                    Arab, thirsting for water, and parched by a burning sun, was ready to do any
                    thing for such a recompence. The reward which Christ promised to the elect was
                    that they should see God face to face. Hence it maybe justly said that the
                    religion of Christ is a menace, whilst that of Mahommed is, on the other hand, a
                    promise. The one seeks to mortify the senses and subdue the passions; the other
                    to excite and inflame them by the promise of unlimited enjoyment. The essential
                    difference of these religions is also strongly marked by the history of their
                    respective establishment. The progress of Christianity was slow, and three or
                    four centuries elapsed before it attained a firm footing in the world. It
                    requires much time to destroy, by the mere influence of persuasion, a religion
                    consecrated by time, and still more when the new faith neither appeals to any
                    prejudices, nor kindles any passion, nor admits any temporal auxiliaries. The
                    progress of Islamism was, on the other hand, rapid, and, even before the death
                    of the prophet, it had established itself in the countries where it was first
                    preached. Unlike Jesus Christ, who declared that his kingdom was not of this
                    world, Mahommed became a king; and, having declared that the whole universe
                    ought to be subjected to his sway, he ordered his followers to employ the sword
                    to destroy idolaters and infidels. Hence, as soon as Islamism had triumphed at
                    Mekka and Medina, it served as a rallying point to the different Arabic tribes;
                    the idolaters of Arabia were soon converted or destroyed; the infidels in Asia,
                    in Syria, and in Egypt, were attacked and conquered; and a whole nation, imbued
                    with a fanatical spirit, precipitated itself upon its neighbours. Christianity
                    proclaimed peace on earth, and good will to men. Islamism preached intolerance
                    and the destruction of infidels. Accordingly, the one advanced slowly and
                    imperceptibly; whilst the progress of the other was that of an overwhelming
                    torrent, and the Arabian armies, impelled by fanaticism, at once attacked the
                    Ilo- ,man empire and that of Persia. In the history of its diffusion,
                    Christianity presents the most striking evidence of <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194200342" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0342-0040"/>its divine origin and the
                    omnipotence of truth. But it is not so with Islamism, which, engendered in
                    fanaticism, was propagated by the sword, and established by terror, by conquest,
                    and by extermination.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
