<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2903-0237-07" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">MANUTIUS, Aldus</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 237</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1353199">Grammar</term><term n="11" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7751w">Press</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4125q963">Dominicans</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194202903" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">MANUTIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Aldus</hi></label> (in
                    Italian, <hi rend="italic">Aldo Pio Manuzio),</hi> the first of those justly
                    celebrated printers, illustrious for their learning as well as for uncommon
                    skill in their profession, who were in Italy what the Stephens afterwards became
                    in France. He was born in 1447, at Bassiano, a small town of the duchy of
                    Sermoneta, in the Roman state. He was educated at Rome, and, after completing
                    his course of study, repaired to Ferrara to study Greek under Guarini, a learned
                    professor of that language. In 1482, he quitted Ferrara, then threatened with a
                    siege by the Venetians, and retired to Mirandola, where he was received with
                    distinction by the all-accomplished Pico Yielding to the entreaties of Alberto
                    Pio, he then went to Carpi, where he was soon joined by Pico the uncle of the
                    prince. Μ. Renouard conjectures, with much apparent probability, that it was at
                    this time that Aldus conceived the design of forming a printing establishment,
                    with the view of multiplying the best works of the Greek and Latin authors, and
                    that the two princes (Alberto Pio and Picodi Mirandola) undertook to defray the
                    expense of setting up the establishment. In the course of the year 1488, he
                    repaired to Venice, a city which, from its position, its commerce, and the
                    literary taste of its inhabitants, appeared the best suited for his design. His
                    first object was to make himself advantageously known, and, with this view, he
                    commenced by giving public instructions in Greek and Latin; but in the mean time
                    he was very busily occupied in organizing his printinghouse; and at length, in
                    1494, he published the poem of Hero and Leander in Greek and Latin, which was
                    followed by the Grammar of Lascaris, that of Theodore Gaza, and die works of
                    Theocritus, Apollonius, and Herodian. But it was the publication of the works of
                    Aristotle which placed Manutius in the first rank of printers. It is impossible
                    to form a just conception of the patience and sagacity necessary to read and
                    decipher the manuscripts which served as the basis of this edition, to compare
                    and collate them with one another, to select the best readings when they
                    exhibited variations, and to supply the omissions of the copyists. This edition
                    alone, though less correct than the greater part of those which followed it,
                    would be sufficient to earn for Manιιtius the gratitude of posterity, and to
                    justify all the commendations which have been bestowed upon him. But if we
                    reflect that he published, with the same care, and almost always with the same
                    success, the greater part of the <hi rend="italic">chefs</hi><hi rend="italic">d’oeuvre</hi> of Greece; that, in multiplying good books, then so rare, he
                    changed the direction of study, hitherto limited to scholastic theology and a
                    barbarous jurisprudence; and that he thereby contributed in the most essential
                    manner to the progress of the human mind, and the advancement of civilization;
                    we cannot but entertain a sentiment of . profound veneration for the man whose
                    whole life was consumed in a series of labours which will extend their useful
                    influence even to the latest generations. Before this time the greater part of
                    books had been printed in the folio or largest size; Manutius, however,
                    conceived the happy idea of publishing a collection of the Latin classics in a
                    more convenient form, and with this view he had a character cast in imitation
                    (it is said) of the hand-writing of Petrarch, and employed it, for the first
                    time, in the impression of his Virgil which appeared in 1501. This character,
                    long afterwards known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Aldine,</hi> and now by
                    that of <hi rend="italic">Italic,</hi> was designed and cut by Francesco of
                    Bologna, an artist highly esteemed in his particular line. The multiplicity of
                    works which now issued from his presses having rendered it impossible for one
                    individual to superintend the impressions, he had recourse to the assistance of
                    some learned men, his personal friends; and out of this association of persons
                    united in one common object he formed the Aldine Academy, whose short duration
                    did not prevent it from attaining great celebrity. It reckoned amongst its
                    members, Bembo, Erasmus, Battista Egnazio, and Andrea Navagero, who every year
                    burned, in honour of Catullus, a copy of Martial; the monk Bolzani, the first
                    who wrote in Latin the principles of Greek grammar; Alcyonio, who is accused of
                    having destroyed the only manuscript of Cicero’s treatise <hi rend="italic">De
                    Gloria,</hi> after having transferred its finest passages to one of his own
                    works; the Greek Musurus Demetrius Chalcondylas, who published the first edition
                    of Homer; and Ale-andro, afterwards cardinal, who acted a prominent part in the
                    ecclesiastical affairs of the sixteenth century. In 1506, war obliged Aldus to
                    withdraw from Venice; and during his absence his goods were pillaged and his
                    domains seized. He made repeated efforts to recover possession of his property,
                    but, unfortunately, without success. On quitting Milan, where his friends had
                    sheltered him, he fell into the hands of a troop of soldiers, who, taking him
                    for a spy, conducted him to prison at Caneto. But he recovered his liberty,
                    through the good offices of Jaffredo Carolo, vice-chancellor of the senate of
                    Milan, and returned to Venice much poorer than when he left it. In 1507, he
                    resumed his typographical labours; but the want of funds rendered it impossible
                    for him to execute any great work. In these circumstances, Andrea Toresano
                    d’Asola, his father-in-law, came to his assistance; and, in 1512, they formed a
                    partnership, of which Aldus was constituted the head. He then re-opened his
                    printing-house, which for two years had been shut, and resumed his labours with
                    increased activity. But when he was on the point of publishing a Bible in three
                    languages, which would have secured to him the distinction of being the first
                    author of a polyglott, he was in 1515 removed from all his pursuits by death, at
                    the age of about seventy. By his marriage with the daughter of Andrea d’Asola he
                    had three sons and a daughter; but Paolo, his third son, was the only one who
                    followed in the footsteps of his father.</p><p>The Greek editions which issued from the presses of Aldus are less correct than
                    either the Latin or the Italian editions; but it should be remembered that he
                    had frequently only a single manuscript, incomplete or half effaced, from which
                    to reproduce a work, and that the conservation of many is entirely owing to his
                    laborious patience. The mark of his press, it is well known, is a dolphin coiled
                    round an anchor. Besides the prefaces, and the Greek or Latin dissertations with
                    which he enriched most of his editions, Manutius was <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202916" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2916-0238"/>the author of
                    several works, which would of themselves have been sufficient to insure to him a
                    distinguished place amongst the learned men of his age, if he had not been the
                    most celebrated printer it produced. Of these works the most important are, 1.
                    Rudimenta Grammatices Linguae Latinae, Venice, 1501, in 4to, very rare; 2.
                    Grammaticae Institutiones Graecae, 1515, in 4to; 3. Dictionarium Graeco-Latinum,
                    1497,1524, in folio; 4. De Metris Horatianis, a little work often reprinted
                    during the sixteenth century; 5. Scripta Tria longe rarissima denuo edita et
                    illustrata, Bassano, 1806, in 8vo. The Abbé Morelli is the editor of this
                    collection, which contains a poem of ^Aldus, entitled <hi rend="italic">Musarum</hi><hi rend="italic">Panegyris,</hi> in two little pieces addressed
                    to the Prince of Carpi. The original edition in 4to, without date, must have
                    appeared before 1489. Manutius translated from Greek to Latin the Grammar of
                    Lascaris, the Batrachomyomachia, the Sentences of Phocylides, the Golden Verses
                    of Pythagoras, and the Fables of Aesop and of Gabrias (Babrius). (See Life of
                    Aldus Manutius the Elder, by Unger, augmented by Geret, Wittenberg, 1753, in
                    4to; also his Life by Manni.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Manutius,</hi><hi rend="italic">Paulus,</hi> son of the
                    preceding, was born at Venice in 1512, and, after the death of his father,
                    remained under the care of his maternal uncle, Andrea Toresano. Part of his
                    early youth he passed at Asola, where his education was much neglected; but, on
                    his return to Venice, the old friends of his father furnished him the means of
                    gratifying his taste for learning. Under their direction he applied to his
                    studies with such zeal and assiduity, as even to injure his health, and induce
                    his physicians to enjoin a temporary abstinence from labour. But he suffered
                    more domestic disquiet than from the illness thus occasioned. Andrea Toresano
                    died in 1529; and∙the partition of his succession excited keen disputes between
                    his own sons and those of Aldus. Paul, however, entered into an agreement with
                    his uncles, whereby he remained at the head of the printing'establishment,
                    which, having been shut up in 1529, was re-opened in 1533, for the common
                    benefit of the heirs of Aldus and Andrea d’Asola. In imitation of his father, he
                    sought the assistance of learned men, of whose counsels he availed himself;
                    published new editions, particularly of the Latin classics, much more correct
                    than the preceding ones; and enriched them with prefaces, notes, and indexes,
                    the usefulness of which now began to be felt. Being passionately fond of the
                    works of Cicero, which he read and re-read incessantly, in order to form his own
                    style, he published a careful re-impression of the oratorical treatises and
                    familiar letters; and this was followed by a complete edition of the works of
                    the prince of Roman eloquence. But fresh annoyances which he experienced on the
                    part of his uncles forced him to suspend his labours in 1538; and he employed
                    part of that year in visiting the ancient libraries of Tuscany and the Milanese.
                    The partnership which he had formed with the Toresani was at length dissolved;
                    and the printing establishment having been re-opened in 1540, under the name of
                    the sons of Aldus, soon began to recover its ancient splendour. Manutius married
                    in 1546; but the attention which he owed to his wife and his young family did
                    not abate his ardour for study. Frequent illnesses, caused by excessive labour,
                    or the difficulties with which he had to contend, could alone withdraw him from
                    his habitual occupations. The little encouragement which he met with at Venice,
                    however, led him to think of removing his establishment to some other place; and
                    having been received with distinction in two journeys which he had made to Rome
                    in 1535 and 1543, he persuaded himself that he would there find more liberal
                    patronage and support. But every project of change was adjourned by the erection
                    of the Venetian Academy, which was founded by the senator Badoaro in 1558, upon
                    nearly the same plan as that afterwards adopt ed for the Institute of France.
                    Paulus Manutius was appointed professor of eloquence, and director of the press
                    of the academy. But this magnificent establishment, from which the most
                    advantageous results were expected, was dissolved in 1561; and almost at the
                    same time Manutius received a letter from Cardinal Scripandi, who, in the most
                    pressing manner, invited him to establish himself at Rome, in order to
                    superintend the impression of the works of the Fathers. After some hesitation,
                    he accepted the offers made to him, and repaired to Rome, where he was not long
                    after joined by his family. The new printing establishment was fixed in the
                    capitol (⅛ <hi rend="italic">aedibus</hi><hi rend="italic">populi</hi><hi rend="italic">Romani),</hi> and the first work which proceeded from it was a
                    small treatise of Cardinal Polo, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Concilio et Reformatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Angliae,</hi> dated 1562. But
                    after the death of Paul IV., the payment of the allowance granted to Manutius
                    was discontinued. The vexation he in consequence experienced affected his
                    health, which was already in a precarious state; and, about the end of 1570, he
                    returned to Venice in a much worse condition than when he had left it. He went
                    to the country in quest of that repose and diversion of which he had so much
                    need; and, in the autumn of the year 1571, he travelled to Genoa, Reggio, and
                    Milan, labouring at intervals on his Commentary on the Orations of Cicero. In
                    1572, he went to visit his daughter, whom he had left in a convent at Rome,
                    intending to remain there only for a few weeks; but the liberality of Pope
                    Gregory XIII. overcame all his scruples, and induced him to. remain in that
                    city. Being now easy as to the lot of his family; he was proceeding to complete
                    the works which he had so long meditated, when the infirmity of ĥis’health
                    forced him to abandon every kind of occupation; and, after languishing for
                    several months, he died on the 6th April 1574, and was interred in the church of
                    the Dominicans, but without an inscription. Although, during the last years of
                    his life, his presses had begun to decline, Paulus Manutius, as a printer and
                    editor, was equal to his illustrious father; and his works place him in the rank
                    of the best critics and most polished writers of his age. These were, 1.
                    Epistolarum libri xii. Praefationes &amp;c. Venice, 1580, in 8vo; 2. Lettere
                    Volgari divise in quattro libri, ibid. 1560, in 8vo; 3. Degli Elementi e di loro
                    notabili Effetti, ibid. 1557, in 4to; 4. Antiquitatum Romanarum liber de
                    Legibus, ibid. 1557, in folio, with an ample index; 5. Liber de Senatu Romano,
                    ibid. 1581, in 4to; 6. De Comitiis Romanorum, Bologna, 1585, in folio; 7. De
                    Civitate Romana, Rome, 1585, in 4to. These four last treatises have been
                    inserted in the <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquitatum
                    Romanarum,</hi> tom. i. and ii. Manutius translated into Latin the <hi rend="italic">Philippics</hi> of Demosthenes, Venice, 1549, 1552, in 4to; and he
                    published Commentaries on the Familiar Letters of Cicero, the Letters to
                    Atticus, Brutus, and Quintus, and the Orations; as well as Scholia, on the
                    oratorical and philosophical treatises of the same author. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Manutius,</hi><hi rend="italic">Aldus,</hi> the
                    younger,'eldest son of Paulus, was an extraordinary infant and a mediocre man.
                    Born at Venice on the 13th of February 1567, he exhibited precocious talents,
                    which his father cultivated with the greatest care. At the age of eleven, he
                    published a collection of Elegances in the Latin and Italian languages, which
                    had great success; but it is generally believed that in making this collection
                    he had been assisted by his father. Three years after, there appeared his <hi rend="italic">Orthographies Ratio,</hi> a work which presents a complete system
                    of Latin orthography, founded on the inscriptions, the medals, and the best
                    manuscripts. In 1562 he went to join his father at Rome, and profited by his
                    residence in that city to augment his collection of ancient inscriptions. He
                    returned to Venice at the latest in 1565, and assumed the direction of the
                    Aldine press, the useful labours of which were <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202929" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2929-0239"/>not interrupted
                    by the absence of his father. In 1576 he was named professor of belles-lettres
                    in the schools of the chancery; and to this employment he, in 1584, joined that
                    of secretary to the senate. He transferred his printing establishment, which he
                    had much neglected, to Nicoo Manassi, one of his workmen; and, notwithstanding
                    the proofs of esteem which he had received from his fellow-citizens, he quitted
                    Venice in 1585, in order to occupy, at Bologna, the chair of eloquence, vacant
                    by the death of Ligonio. The offer of a more advantageous appointment decided
                    him, in 1587, to settle at Pisa; and, two years after, yielding to the
                    solicitations of his friends, he accepted the chair which Muretus had occupied
                    with so much distinction at Rome, and which had been kept for him since the
                    death of that learned professor. The condition ofManntius was still further
                    ameliorated under the pontificate of Clement VIII., who, in 1590, confided to
                    him the direction of the Vatican press. But he had the fault of indulging to
                    excess in the pleasures of the table; and he died in consequence of a debauch,
                    on the 28th of October 1597, in the fifty-first year of his age. He had memory
                    and erudition, but much less taste and critical ability than his father; and he
                    was justly accused of plagiarism in publishing, under his own name, notes on
                    Paterculus, which had been communicated to him by the learned Dupuis. His
                    natural inconstancy prevented him from undertaking anything truly great; and he
                    owed his reputation less to his own merit than to the celebrity which his father
                    and grandfather had acquired. His works are, 1. Eleganze, insieme con la copia
                    della Lingua Toscana e Latina, Venice, 1558, in 8vo; 3. Orthographia? Ratio,
                    collecta ex libris antiquis grammaticis, &amp;c. ibid. 1561 and 1568, in 8vo; 3.
                    Discorso intorno all’ eccellenza delle Re-publiche, 1591, in 8vo; 4. Locuzioni
                    delľ Epistole di Cicerone, 1575, in 8vo,∙ 5. De Quaesitis per Epistolam libri
                    iii. 1576, in 8vo; 6. Oratio in funere B. Rottarii, ducis Sabaudiae apud Remp.
                    Venetam legati, 1578, in 4to; 7. Il perfetto Gentil’homo, 1584, in 4to; 8.
                    Locuzioni di Terentio, 1585, in 8vo; 9. La Vita di Cosimo I. de’ Medici gran
                    duca di Toscana, Bologna, 1586, in folio; 10. Le Azioni di Castruccio
                    Castracani, Rome, 1590, in 4to; 11. Lettere Volgari, ibid. 1592, in 4to; 12.
                    Viginti cinque Discorsi sopra Livio della seconda Guerra Cartaginese, ibid.
                    1601, in 8vo. Aldus the younger also wrote some Discourses; an Explication of
                    the ode of Horace, <hi rend="italic">De Lau∙ dibus Vitae rusticae</hi>;
                    Commentaries on the Art of Poetry by Horace, as well as on the Rhetoric and the
                    Philosophical Books of Cicero. After his death, the rich and extensive library
                    collected by his grandfather and his father was divided between his creditors
                    and his nephews. His intention, it is said, was to bequeath it to the city of
                    Venice. (See Renouard, <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    l’lmprimerie des Aldes</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> Paris,
                    1803-1812, in three vols. 8vo.) <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p><p>Μ AN WAS, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Gundwana, the capital of a
                    district of the same name, and situated ninety-five miles south-west by south
                    from Benares. Long. 82. 5. E. Lat. 24. 13. N. The district is situated about the
                    twenty-fourth degree of north latitude, and contains a thin population of wild
                    inhabitants, scattered over a great tract of country.</p></div></body></text></TEI>