<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-5789-0459-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MECHAIN, Peter Francis Andrew</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 459</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh9r">Comets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49w0975m">Terns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45717p75">Prizes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p65z">Architects</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47659q39">Surveyors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:869108">Comets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1077716">Prizes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1147958">Terns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194205789" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MECHAIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter Francis
                    Andrew</hi></label>, a well-known practical astronomer and geographer, was born
                    at Laon, on the 16th April 1744. His father was an architect, and educated him
                    with the intention of making him his successor in his business. He afterwards
                    took charge of two young men at Sens, as their private tutor, and accidentally
                    became acquainted with Lalande, under whose patronage he was subsequently
                    brought forward as an observer, surveyor, and computer. He made two voyages with
                    Μ. de la Bretonniére, and assisted him in surveying some parts of the coast of
                    France. He was afterwards employed in various computations by the Marquis de
                    Chabert, and the Duc D’Ayen. Having obtained a prize from the Academy of
                    Sciences in 1782, for a <hi rend="italic">Memoir on Comets,</hi> he became a
                    member of the Academy the same year. About the year 1785, he undertook the
                    publication of the <hi rend="italic">Connaissance</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Terns,</hi> and continued it till he was employed in geodetical operations at a
                    distance from Paris. He was appointed member of a committee, along with Cassini,
                    de Thury, and Legendre, to meet the English astronomers for the determination of
                    the relative situation of the observatories, which had been proposed by Cassini.
                    It was in these operations that he first brought Borda’s circle into general
                    use. In 1791 he was appointed, in conjunction with Delambre, to execute the
                    intentions of the Constituent Assembly, with regard to the determination of a
                    basis of linear measures. A variety of delays and difficulties occurred in these
                    operations. In Spain he was wounded in the head and side, by an accident which
                    occurred whilst he was inspecting a water-wheel; and the political circumstances
                    of the times produced many embarrassments, which caused him to linger in Italy
                    perhaps a little longer than was actually necessary; but the establishment of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Bureau des Longitudes,</hi> and his nomination as a member
                    of it, determined his immediate return to Paris. He was now director of the
                    Observatory, and he entered with great zeal on a series of observations, which
                    were to rival those of Flamsteed, of Bradley, and of Maskelyne; but he seems to
                    have been a little tired of the confinement, and he readily accepted, or rather
                    solicited, the appointment to assist in the measurements required for the still
                    farther extension of the arc of the meridian to the south of Barcelona. But the
                    secret motive for his seeking this humbler employment appears to have been a
                    desire to remove some doubts which he entertained respecting the latitude of
                    Barcelona, as it appeared after his death from his papers, that there had been a
                    discordance of 3' ’ in some observations which he had not made public. In this
                    unfortunate undertaking, he paid a heavy penalty for any want of candour which
                    may have been attributed to the concealment. Shipwreck and disease awaited him;
                    and he died at last, on the 20th of September 1805, of a fever, which fatigue
                    and a bad climate had brought on. From the time of his accident in Spain he had
                    become habitually melancholy and timid, though regardless of personal danger in
                    the pursuit of his professional objects. His whole time was occupied in
                    observing and calculating; he published little; and never ventured to advance
                    any reflections on the subjects which employed him, being probably more in the
                    habit of acting than of speculating. He married, in 1777, Mademoiselle Thérèse
                    Maijon, with whom he had become acquainted at Versailles. This connexion was in
                    every respect happy; he was indebted to it for a competent fortune, and he left
                    a daughter and two sons.</p>
                <p>1. Of his publications the most important are to be found in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires des</hi><hi rend="italic">Savans</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >étrangers;</hi> that is, besides some <hi rend="italic">Observations of
                    eclipses and occulaticyns,</hi> a <hi rend="italic">Memoir on the comets</hi>
                    q/T532«wíZ1661, showing that theyare not the same; and their non-appearance
                    seven or eight years afterwards fully; ustified his conclusions, and the
                    adjudication of the prize. 2. In the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the
                    Academy,</hi> from 1782 to 1784, there are several of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Observations of transits, eclipses, occulations, and comets.</hi> 3. There are
                    also some letters of Méchain in Zach’s <hi rend="italic">Geographical
                    Ephemerides</hi> about 1800, on the instruments of <hi rend="italic">∖hoParisian
                    Observatory,</hi> and on other subjects. 4. He edited the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Connaissance</hi><hi rend="italic">des Τems,</hi> from 1786 <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194205802" xml:id="kp-eb0714-5802-0460"/>to 1794. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Lalande.)</hi><hi rend="italic">5. Base</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >du système métrique,</hi> décimal. 3 v. 4. Paris, 1806, 1807, 1810. This last
                    is the joint work of Méchainand his friend and colleague Delambre.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
