<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-2539-0209-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAN, Isle of</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 209</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="30" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="31" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="30" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194202539" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Isle of</hi></label>, lies between
                    54° and 55° N. lat., and 4° and 5° W. long., in the middle of the Irish Sea, and
                    nearly equidistant from the shores of England, Scotland, and Ireland. It is
                    about thirty miles in extreme length, and eleven miles at its greatest breadth;
                    but the latter varies considerably, as its coasts are in many places deeply
                    indented by the sea, and converge at their northern and southern extremities
                    into narrow points. Whilst some, therefore, estimate its superficial contents at
                    only 220 square miles, others make it a little less, or 130,000 acres.</p>
                <p>At its southern extremity, and separated from it'by a narrow channel of only a
                    few hundred yards across, is a little island called the Calf. It is about three
                    miles in circumference; its precipitous coasts rise high above the level of the
                    sea, and its scanty vegetation does little more than afford food for a few sheep
                    and rabbits; and a shepherd’s family, and the keepers of the two light-houses,
                    are its only human inhabitants. These light-houses were erected by the
                    Commissioners of Northern Lights, from the same humane concern for the safety of
                    the storm-tossed mariner which induced them to raise a similar structure, equal
                    in elegance and utility, on the most northerly point of the main island. Like
                    the Calf, the greater part of Man presents to the sea a bold and rocky coast.
                    Its bays, however, are both numerous and spacious, and the anchorage in many of
                    them is extremely good; but as none of them is land-locked, or even completely
                    protected by elevated headlands, vessels ride there in safety only in offshore
                    gales; and the sailor must too frequently shun them when the winter’s tempests
                    sweep that dangerous sea.</p>
                <p>For certain civil and ecclesiastical purposes, it is divided into a northern and
                    a southern district: each of these contains three sheadings, and the whole
                    island is again thrown into seventeen parishes. Its towns are Castletown,
                    Douglas, Peel, and Ramsay. The first of these is a clean and neat town, being
                    the capital of the island, the residence of the lieutenant-governor, the seat of
                    the legislature and courts of law, and adorned in its centre by a fine old
                    Gothic fortress, round which are entwined many heart-stirring associations.
                    Douglas is the chief seat of commerce; it is larger than Castletown, and the
                    stile of its buildings is finer; where they have risen within the last two
                    years. Close to it is Castle Mona, once the princely residence of the Duke of
                    Atholl, but now a very spacious and elegant hotel. In feudal times Peel was a
                    place of considerable note; and, till very lately, the herring fishery was
                    briskly carried on there; but it is now remarkable only for its ancient castle,
                    which it too much resembles in its own ruinous condition. Ramsay is also much
                    less than Douglas; but it is a thriving and spirited little town, and would be
                    no despicable rival to the other, were it less restricted in its trade. All the
                    towns are built on the alluvial deposit at the mouths of the principal rivers,
                    where they flow into the sea at very nearly opposite parts of the island. They
                    have all tide-harbours, piers, and harbourlights; and they are connected by
                    excellent roads with each other, and with the villas, villages, and little
                    hamlets which thickly enliven and adorn the scenery of the adjacent country.</p>
                <p>The climate of the Isle of Man is rather variable, moist, and windy. Compared
                    with the countries around it, its winters are mild and open, and its summers
                    cool. Snow seldom lies many hours. Its fields during the whole of winter
                    generally wear a spring-like appearance; and the extreme cold of an English
                    winter is never felt. A meteorological journal was long kept by the late
                    Receiver-General Stuart, at his residence, Villa Marina, situated on the shore
                    of the Bay of Douglas; and the annexed tables were prepared and circulated
                    amongst his private friends, by that truly upright officer and accomplished
                    gentleman.</p>
                <p>General State of the Weather for 1831.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Months.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Medium of Thermometer.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Wind, Number of Days.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weather, Number of Days.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Rain Fallen.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A. Μ.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>P. Μ.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>N.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>s.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>E.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>w.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Rain.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Snow.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fair.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>100 Parts.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Januarv</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>55</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>February</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>39</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>42</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>March</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>April</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>72</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>May</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>54</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>36</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>June</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>July</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>60</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>31</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>August</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>58</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>81</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>September</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>October</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>55</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>56</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>- 4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>November</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>78</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>December</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>45</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>80</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>General medium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>93</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>118</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>99</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>75 1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>114</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>237</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Highest state of thermometer 77
                            Lowest 26</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>REMARKS, 1831.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>March 11. Strong aurora
                            borealis.</p><p>13. Violent lightning, 8 p. <hi rend="smallcaps">μ.</hi>
                            Sept. 29; Thunder and lightning.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nov. 15 and 16. Extraordinary thunder
                            and lightning. Several sheep destroyed in the island.</p><p>Dec. 9.
                            Lightning,—no thunder.</p><p>10. Ditto, with thunder.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202552" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2552-0210"/>
                <p>General Average for Eight Years, from 1824 to 1831 inclusive, the fractional
                    parts being omitted.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Years.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Medium of Thermometer.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Wind, Number of Days.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>Weather, Number of Days.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Rain Fallen.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A. Μ.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>P. Μ.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ν’.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>s.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>E.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>w.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Rain.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Snow.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fair.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>100 Parts.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1824</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>93</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>61</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>92</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>120</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>150</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>201</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>75</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1825</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>51∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48∙6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>80</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>97</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>126</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>145</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>213</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>38</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>68</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1826</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>82</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>86</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>87</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>110</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>126</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>227</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>29</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>52</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1827</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>105</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>93</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>102</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>65</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>152</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>198</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>43</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>41</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1828</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>51</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>64</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>113</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>107</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>82</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>147</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>210</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>35</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>"90</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1829</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>46</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>102</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>91</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>no</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>135</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>217</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>33</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>89</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1830</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48∙8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>46∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>83</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>104</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>84</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>94</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>167</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>183</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>38</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>55</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>93</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>118</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>99</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>75</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>114</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>237</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Medium for 8 years....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>50</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>87</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>82</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>97</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>92</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>142</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>210</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>37</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>General Remarks.—Fahrenheit’s thermometer was situated on a northern exposure,
                    and always out. The observations were taken at nine o’clock <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a. μ.,</hi> and at eleven o’clock p. <hi rend="smallcaps">μ.</hi> With
                    reference to the wind, “the prevailing point of the day is taken.” If any rain,
                    snow, or sleet fell during the day, it was not considered fair.</p>
                <p>The Manx mountains have rather an imposing appearance, whether as seen from the
                    sea, or as viewed from the highest summits. They almost bisect the island
                    diagonally in a line running from its north-east to its southwest shore. One of
                    them rises to upwards of 20,001 feet above the level of the sea. They are green
                    to their tops; for the most part gently rounded towards the south, but sinking
                    abruptly on the alluvial plains of the northern district. To the south and north
                    of this mountain range the country has a very different appearance. Hills
                    prevail in the former part, and the land is generally better adapted for feeding
                    than for cropping. The surface of the latter is nearly level, or gently
                    undulating; and the sand, marl, and morass of which it is composed, resting on a
                    substratum of gravel and diluvial boulders, is, to a very great extent, covered
                    with crops that do equal honour to the soil and to the farmer.</p>
                <p>In the stratification of its rocks there is nothing uncommon, and the variety of
                    its minerals is far from being considerable. Of the primary rocks, granite in
                    some places may be seen rising to the surface, whilst masses of quartz and
                    hornblende are to be met with frequently both above and below it. Slate,
                    graywacke, and graywacke slate, passing into old red sandstone; black and gray
                    limestone, greenstone, and clinkstone, passing into basalt, comprehend its
                    transitionary formations. The slate is often found of a quality that fits it for
                    the covering of houses; and is met with, too, of such a fibrous structure, as to
                    make, in lengths of six and eight feet, excellent piles, posts, and lintels. The
                    steps at the great entrance to St Paul’s are of the black limestone of Man. It
                    admits of a fine polish, and is much used for tomb-stones and chimney-pieces.
                    Its gray limestone is also good; it abounds in organic remains; and, happily for
                    the interests ofManx agriculture, its beds occupy as much of the southern
                    extremity of the island as the strata of its marl do of the opposite one. Copper
                    and lead are the only metals which have yet been discovered in its mines. Three
                    of these are in full operation. One is conducted at the risk of several
                    public-spirited individuals belonging to the island; the others by an English
                    company; and all of them are carried on with much enterprise and success.</p>
                <p>There are no lakes in Man. Its larger morasses, too, have been all reclaimed.
                    Springs and rivulets of the purest water everywhere abound. The largest of its
                    rivers, however, like the island itself, is only a small one, short in its
                    course, and very variable in size, as drought or rain happens to prevail. Plenty
                    of trout are still to be found in its streams; but the salmon and salmon-trout
                    have almost ceased to frequent them.</p>
                <p>Only one little <hi rend="italic">brassica,</hi> called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >simbrium Monensis,</hi> distinguishes the Manx from the British Flora. Owing to
                    the extreme mildness of the climate, many plants thrive exposed all the year in
                    the open shrubberies, that can be preserved only in the greenhouses of countries
                    in a much lower latitude. Trees are scarce in Man, and the deficiency forcibly
                    attracts the notice of every stranger. Thriving plantations, however, are rising
                    fast round every villa; horticulture is much attended to; and the fruits of its
                    graperies and pineries are both excellent and abundant.</p>
                <p>The animal kingdom has nothing in it peculiar to the island. Horses of an active
                    and hardy breed; sheep, small, coarse woolled, and well flavoured; pigs and
                    black cattle; are there, as in England, the common stock of every farmer. Hares
                    are rather scarce. The Calf and many parts of the island abound in rabbits.
                    Beasts of prey, and venomous reptiles, if ever indigenous, are now never
                    seen.</p>
                <p>Manxmen are tinctured a little with the pride of ancestry. They do not, indeed,
                    lay claim to that extreme antiquity for their race which is demanded by some
                    nations; nor are their traditions interwoven with any of those beautiful
                    mythologies by which the absence of truth is almost atoned for in the histories
                    of others. There are of their writers, however, who have amply availed
                    themselves of the legendary tale; and, if credit is to be given to their
                    recitals, a long succession of magicians, druids, saints, and seakings, ruled in
                    Man many ages before the time at which this brief sketch of its history
                    begins.</p>
                <p>Caesar speaks of Mona, Pliny of Monobia, Ptolemy of Monaoeda or Monoida, Orosius
                    and Beda of Menavia, and Nennius of Eubonia, in a manner distinctly indicating
                    that the island was known in their days by each and all of these different
                    names. Whether Man, its present appellation, be a contraction or a corruption of
                    any of these, or more immediately derived from the ancient British words <hi
                    rend="italic">Mòn,</hi> isolated, or <hi rend="italic">Manaw,</hi> a little
                    island; from the Saxon <hi rend="italic">many,</hi> among; from <hi
                    rend="italic">Alaune,</hi> the surname of St Patrick; from the Manx <hi
                    rend="italic">moany,</hi> solitary, rough, uncultivated; or from Mannin Macler,
                    the name of the greatest of its traditionary kings; is still one of those
                    questions which remain for its antiquaries to investigate and decide.</p>
                <p>It is likely that long before the tenth century Man participated largely in all
                    the chances and changes of the barbarous septs around it; that its people were
                    alternately the friends, the foes, and the subjects of the Scottish and Irish
                    chiefs, and the petty princes of the heptarchy; but it is then only that a gleam
                    of its true and continued history first breaks upon us, as the conquest and the
                    residence of some of the Scandinavian seakings. A series of" these, to the
                    number of twenty-four, were undoubtedly its sovereigns until beyond the middle
                    of the thirteenth centurv. About <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202565"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-2565-0211"/>that time Alexander of Scotland obtained
                    possession of it by force of arms; and after his death, and during the reigns of
                    the Edwards and the first Bruce, it was alternately possessed by the English and
                    Scottish monarchs. From an early part of the fourteenth until the beginning of
                    the fifteenth century, the sovereignty of Man passed through the hands of
                    various English and Scottish nobles, who held it as the vassals of their
                    respective kings; and it was at last bestowed by Henry IV. under the same
                    conditions, on Sir John Stanley. It remained with his descendants until towards
                    the middle of the eighteenth century, when it passed by the female line from the
                    Derby into the Atholl family. Between that period and 1829 it was gradually
                    shorn of many of its feudal honours; but it was then that government purchased
                    from the late Duke of Atholl the whole of his remaining rights, titles, revenue,
                    and patronage, in his lordship of Man, for L.430,000.</p>
                <p>It was in 1726 that the first act of parliament was passed to purchase the island
                    from the Earl of Derby. Powerful influence, however, put off the sale until
                    1764, when a Duke of Atholl disposed of his sovereign rights in the island, all
                    his civil patronage, and the two castles of Peel and Rushin, for L.70,000, to
                    which sum was afterwards added an annuity of L.2000 to his duchess. His title of
                    Lord of Man, his manorial rights, his patronage of the bishopric and parish
                    livings, mines and minerals, treasure-trove, and other privileges, were all
                    reserved. From a conviction, also, on the part of government, that a hard
                    bargain had been driven with his predecessor, the late duke obtained a perpetual
                    grant of the fourth of the nett customs revenue of the island, and was also
                    appointed its governor-general. Little more than another score of years had
                    passed when further changes took place. The large sum already mentioned was paid
                    down; every vestige of its lord’s rights were bought up; and the Isle of Man was
                    elevated from the state of a feudal appanage, to the prouder, and, we hope,
                    happier condition of a British colony.</p>
                <p>The executive department of the government of the Isle of Man is carried on by a
                    lieutenant-governor, who is the captain-general of the island, and also presides
                    in the upper chamber of its legislature, and in most of its judicial assemblies.
                    He acts on all important occasions by advice of the council, which consists of
                    the bishop, attorney-general, the two deemsters, receiver-general,
                    water-bailiff, clerk of the rolls, archdeacon, the two vicars-general, and its
                    clerk. Deemsters are of great antiquity and high authority in Man. Formerly
                    depositaries of the <hi rend="italic">lex non</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >scripta,</hi> they are still the interpreters of the law of the land, in
                    doubtful cases, to all the other authorities. The receiver-general is also an
                    ancient and important officer. He was the lord’s treasurer, the chief receiver
                    of rentsand revenues, and paid all the salaries and wages of the lord’s
                    retainers. Water-bailiff is an officer synonymous with judge of admiralty; he
                    was at one time also collector of the customs under the receiver-general. By the
                    clerk of the rolls were entered all pleas and proceedings before the lord; and
                    he is the keeper of the most important records of the courts and the government.
                    Besides the officers now enumerated, there is a high bailiff in each of the four
                    towns; a seneschal, who looks after the enrolments of all the lord’s tenants; a
                    coroner in each of its sheadings, who performs many of the duties of a she-rifl;
                    a moar, who is a kind of parish officer; and from a dozen to twenty constables.
                    All these appointments emanate directly or indirectly from the Home Office.</p>
                <p>No act of the imperial parliament, however applicable it may be to every part of
                    the united kingdom, extends to the Isle of Man, except that island be expressly
                    mentioned in it. Its own legislature consists of two chambers; the council, and
                    the house of keys. The latter is a self-elected assembly, consisting of
                    twenty-four members, who hold their seats for life. They are in no way
                    responsible to the people. The presence of thirteen is required to give validity
                    to their acts. It discharges both legislative and judicial functions; and,
                    whilst sitting in the latter capacity, its members often decide, as judges, in
                    appeal cases of their own, brought up to it from the lower courts. Luckily for
                    the unfortunate litigant who has not a seat or friends in the house of keys, a
                    further hearing, and a reversal of their judgment, may be obtained from the king
                    in council. As a legislative assembly, it originates laws; and, if thirteen or
                    upwards of its number approve, the bill is transmitted to the council. There it
                    may be thrown out; but if favourably received, it is laid before the king, whose
                    assent is seldom refused. Last of all, it must be promulgated by the
                    lieutenant-governor, who does so, seated in great state, on the top of an
                    ancient tumulus called the Tynwald Mount, round which are collected, at the same
                    time, the council, the keys, the officers of government, and, generally, a
                    numerous concourse of the people. Hence its laws are commonly called Acts of
                    Tynwald.</p>
                <p>One small volume contains the whole of these laws; and the lawyers of the island
                    practise in the double capacity of attorneys and barristers. Where their own
                    laws are silent, the judges are much influenced by the decisions of the English
                    courts. Lord Coke says, that “its laws are such as scarce to be found anywhere
                    else.” The drift of the remark is not very obvious. It is true that there are
                    Manx enactments still in force which prevent a tailor from leaving the island
                    without permission of his lord, and which threaten banishment, as vagrants, to
                    all Scotch <hi rend="italic">men</hi> and Irish <hi rend="italic">women</hi>
                    found in it; but it is equally certain that these, and many such like elements
                    of folly and injustice, which its code undoubtedly contains, had then too many
                    and too faithful counterparts in a statute-book with which the learned lord was
                    still better acquainted. It is also gratifying to think that most of the absurd
                    laws have fallen into desuetude in Man, and are to be regarded as proofs of a
                    state of manners no longer existing in that island.</p>
                <p>The proper revenue of the island consists of three branches; of customs,
                    harbour-dues, and insular taxes. Duties levied on certain goods imported are the
                    sources of the first; charges on vessels and boats that have enjoyed the benefit
                    of its harbours, form the second; and the last consists of small taxes levied on
                    dogs, carriages, and public houses. The customs average from L.20,000 to
                    L.25,000 per annum: out of them all the government officers’ salaries are paid;
                    and a yearly surplus of from L.12,000 to L.15,000 is remitted to England. It is
                    in the repairs of harbours, roads, and bridges, that the money collected under
                    the other two heads is expended; and the outlay is regulated by commissioners
                    and committee-men appointed for the purpose. In each of the four towns there is
                    a customhouse; but they are all subordinate to the one in Douglas. The treasury
                    nominates the officers of customs; the collectors of the local taxes are
                    appointed by insular influence. Since the Duke of Atholl’s remaining rights in
                    the island were entirely bought up by government, there are also certain lord’s
                    land and mine rents, tithes, and fines and forfeitures, which are collected and
                    managed by the crown agent, a gentleman who represents there the commissioners
                    of woods and forests.</p>
                <p>All religious sects are tolerated in Man; but its establishment is connected with
                    the Church of England. It is a diocese in the province of York; but its bishop
                    has not a seat in the house of peers. His double title of Sodor and Man has its
                    origin in one of those ages so fertile in materials for antiquarian guess-work.
                    Some will have it that Sodor is derived from Sotor, the ancient name of a
                    village in Iona; others allege that it is a contraction of the Danish word
                    Sodoroe, significant of the Hebrides, which the Scandinavian rovers approached
                    generally from the north.*</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202578" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2578-0212"/>
                <p>and said to have been at one time under the spiritual jurisdiction of the Manx
                    bishops; whilst more than one, with equal propriety, maintain that it was
                    applicable only to a little island off Peel, and formerly called Sodor, on which
                    a lordly castle once stood, containing the cathedral in which many of its
                    bishops were consecrated, and the cemetery where the dust of most of the wise,
                    and the brave, and the noble of the land was deposited.</p>
                <p>The bishop is assisted in ecclesiastical matters by an archdeacon, two
                    vicars-general, a registrar, and a sumner-general. Therwingsof the clergy arise
                    chiefly from tithes; the patronage, from the bishopric downwards, with the
                    exception of three in the gift of the diocesan, is vested in the crown. The
                    revenue of the church of Man is a good one, and amply sufficient to maintain all
                    its clergy comfortably, were it only a little more equitably divided. At
                    present, some of its parish ministers, in humility, simplicity, zeal, piety, and
                    <hi rend="italic">poverty^</hi> are not a little like the fishermen of Galilee.
                    A respectable and numerous body of the islanders are Wesleyan Methodists.
                    Whitefield has also a few followers. The Church of Scotland has a chapel in
                    Douglas; the English Independents or Congregationalists have also one; and the
                    Roman Catholics have one there, and another in Castletown. Before the present
                    bishop was consecrated to the see of the Isle of Man, not a few of its churches
                    were miserably dark, and damp, and ruinous. Under his auspices several churches
                    have been rebuilt, and all of them greatly improved. Dr Ward has been the chief
                    mover, too, in the erection of a college in the neighbourhood of Castletown,
                    which is now attracting pupils from all parts of the empire.</p>
                <p>Its parish schools are likewise improving. Too many of them, like its churches,
                    have long been wretched hovels, unskilfully taught, ill attended, and the
                    teachers badly paid.</p>
                <p>Such a state of things is to be ascribed chiefly to the bulk of the peasantry of
                    Man not yet feeling sufficiently the importance of education. In the towns,
                    however, and in their neighbourhood, there are many excellent seminaries.
                    Classical and commercial education, drawing, dancing, and singing, are there
                    taught to the children of the wealthy by well-qualified masters; and the
                    children of the poorer classes are not less ably and amply provided for by day
                    schools, Sunday schools, charity schools, and schools of industry.
                    Reading-rooms, circulating and public libraries; book, music, and missionary
                    associations; temperance societies; and not less than four spiritedly conducted
                    newspapers; testify that religion, literature, and politics, are not left
                    amongst the Manx mountains without their organs.</p>
                <p>The population of the island has no doubt varied greatly at different periods of
                    itsjliistory; but whilst some writers, even in sober prose, tell us of halcyon
                    days, “when every rood of ground maintained its man,” and when its fleets and
                    armies were the terror of all the surrounding nations, others allege that its
                    families, so lately as the sixteenth century, amounted to only six or seven
                    hundred; and that, in the following one, the sum total of its inhabitants was
                    considerably below three thousand. Perhaps equal disregard should be paid to all
                    these statements. Subsequent returns, on much better authority, assign for 1726,
                    14,027; 1757, 19,144; 1784, 24,924; 1791, 27,913; and the census of 1831, on
                    which alone any dependence can be placed, rates it at 40,958. That census was
                    obtained, at the expense of government, by persons disposed and qualified to
                    make a correct one; and it is probable that the only alteration it admits of, in
                    1836, is a considerable increase in the population, and in the number, size, and
                    elegance of their dwellings.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Towns and Parishes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inhabited Houses.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Houses Building.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Houses not inhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families in</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Trade, &amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All</p><p>Others.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Douglas</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>794</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1458</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>455</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>963</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2985</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3801</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0780</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Castletown</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>318</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>469</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>209</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>241</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>961</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1101</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>O ∕ OU</p><p>9009</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ramsay</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>303</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>419</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>172</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>246</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>765</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>J. J vl</p><p>989</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1754</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Peel</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>288</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>412</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>o</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>146</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>259</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>' 787</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9Λ9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1799</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>German</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>295</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>314</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>216</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>41</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>907</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 f ŴĨ7</p><p>1791</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Patrick</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>390</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>412</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>42</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>238</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>‘ ß3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>111</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1096</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 OQQ</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>91Q5</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Marown</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>242</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>258</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>153</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 IMO</p><p>581</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11FU&lt;√</p><p>035</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1910</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Conchan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>251</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>276</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>135</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>97</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>705</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ouu</p><p>777</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 ŵiu</p><p>14ft9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Braddan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>318</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>340</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>255</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>58</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>995</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >III</hi></p><p>1009</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 Q97</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Santon</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>138</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>145</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>107</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ĩ7 ŵU <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >qωq</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 VUŵ</p><p>4ß0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7Qft</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Malew</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>482</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>519</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>238</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>93</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>J. V</p><p>188</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>j√o</p><p>∣Q19</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1430</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                            ĲO</p><p>9778</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Arbory</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>261</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>271</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>136</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>73</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>750</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>701</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4 « ∕ o</p><p>1 511</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Rushen</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>520</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>560</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>182</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>111</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>267</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>f uv</p><p>1303</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">I</hi> U 1</p><p>1
                            300</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>lull</p><p>9739</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Michael</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>246</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>260</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>113</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>139</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1OU□</p><p>019</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>lûQJ</p><p>705</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ŵ &lt; Uŵ</p><p>1317</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Jurby</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>198</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>199</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>177</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">∖; ±</hi><hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ŵ</hi></p><p>526</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p> UU</p><p>571</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1□1 »</p><p>1097</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ballaugh</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>279</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>279</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>o</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>89</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>100</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>90</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>685</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>796</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1411</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bride</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>183</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>190</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>β</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>102</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>34</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>t∕ V t/í</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>530</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >caq</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>l <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> r
                            11</p><p>1 ∏QQ</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ayre</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>386</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>412</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>182</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>136</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>94</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>UDO</p><p>928</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>uUu</p><p>1051</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >.LUdU</hi></p><p>1979</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Maughold</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>259</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>313</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>104</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>54</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>155</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>657</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>684</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1341</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lonan</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>318</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>350</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>180</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>66</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∩A</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>917</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>QΛO</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 Q93</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Andreas</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>395</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>403</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>379</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 wt <hi rend="superscript">
                            l</hi></p><p>9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >ULI</hi></p><p>1122</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>JUD</p><p>1095</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>lθ&lt;4u</p><p>2217</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In a land so situated, so frequently conquered, devastated, and ruled, by the
                    marauding bands of other countries, it is vain to seek for traces of its
                    earliest inhabitants. There cannot be a doubt, however, that those who have at
                    present the best claims to be considered as the aborigines of its soil are a
                    small branch of that great Celtic family, the scattered remains of which are now
                    to be found only in the remote islands and the mountain fastnesses of kingdoms
                    perhaps once their own. For a dialect of the Gaelic is still the ordinary
                    language of the peasantry of Man; and there are many amongst them who are
                    strangers to every other tongue. In their persons the men are generally stout
                    and well made. During the late war, it was observed that, whilst the Manx
                    soldier was surpassed in height by the British and Irish troops, any company of
                    its fencibles covered a greater space of ground than the same number of men
                    belonging to the other regiments. The ancient attire of blue cloaks and felt
                    hats has given place <pb break="no" facs="nls:194202591"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0714-2591-0213"/>amongst the Manx females to a more becoming dress;
                    and, whether at home or abroad, they need feel no apprehension from a comparison
                    with the same ranks in the neighbouring countries. The Manx peasant is lively,
                    honest, frugal, obliging; he is well lodged, clothed, and fed; and he might be
                    much happier were he less addicted to strong liquors and litigation. His
                    fondness for the latter, however, arises far more from a prodigious anxiety to
                    be thought always in the right, than from a disposition to overreach his
                    neighbour. The small farmers, who are also, in most instances, the proprietors
                    of the fields they cultivate, greatly impair their means of comfort by too early
                    marriages: it is not uncommon for three or four generations of a family to be
                    located and supported upon the same little property. Amongst the gentry, the
                    manners, the hospitality, and the elegancies of English life prevail to an
                    extent which a stranger to them and their country could not easily imagine. The
                    gas-light, steam-boat, and water companies, and the joint-stock and savings
                    banks of the capital, have all their humble representatives in the towns of Man.
                    Nor are even the medical and soup dispensaries of England without their
                    well-supported counterparts in her little imitator.</p>
                <p>It is only in recent times that the Manxman’s attention has been turned to
                    agriculture. The distracted state of his country under its own kings and feudal
                    superiors; the small and uncertain holdings into which it was divided; his
                    predilections for other and apparently more lucrative pursuits; his entire
                    ignorance of all the new and more approved modes of management; and perhaps,
                    too, that sloth which appears to be the common inheritance, in all countries and
                    ages, of uncivilized man; prevented him from reaping those advantages from it
                    which nature, or rather the God of nature, had placed within his reach. An
                    alteration wonderfully for the better has since taken place in his views and his
                    condition. For many years past a spirit of improvement has been rapidly
                    diffusing itself amongst the Manx farmers. By the daily intercourse they enjoy
                    with England, they now see and become impressed with the importance of better
                    breeds of cattle, and more approved systems of cropping, than were known to
                    their fathers; and many respectable farmers from England and Scotland are now
                    settled in Man, who, along with their capitals, have imported into it an amount
                    of agricultural experience and information still more valuable to their adopted
                    country. It has thus happened, that although the soil of the island is generally
                    very far from being rich, and its farms much smaller than is compatible with the
                    fullest development of the agricultural capabilities of a country, still it is
                    in a very thriving state; more than two-thirds of its surface are under
                    cultivation; every year the corn-fields are making encroachments on the waste
                    land, and the plantations creeping farther up the mountain side; and the cattle
                    and corn it exports in considerable number and quantity are considered as second
                    only to the best in the Liverpool market.</p>
                <p>The salmon-fishings in the rivers of Man were at one time so productive as to
                    form a considerable article of direct trade to the Mediterranean. It is long
                    since they ceased to be of any importance, and the supplies for the inhabitants
                    come from Scotland and Ireland. Nor is the herring-fishery so productive as it
                    was even at the beginning of the present century. It employs about two hundred
                    and fifty boats of from fifteen to thirty tons burden, and from 2000 to 3000
                    men. In some years, however, their failure is complete, and the loss to their
                    families is a great and severe one. More successful years yield from 40,000 to
                    50,000 barrels. From a third to a half of these is consumed upon the island, and
                    the remainder, in salted and smoked states, is exported. Owing to the falling
                    off in the produce of the fishery, its uncertainty, its calling away the farmers
                    from their rural occupations, when their presence is most needed in their
                    fields, to the dissolute lives they too frequently lead whilst they are engaged
                    as fishermen, many of the most intelligent and best friends of Man wish that the
                    herrings would for ever take leave of its coasts. The same truly patriotic
                    persons are equally urgent for the advancement of its deep-sea fishing, which
                    has long been mismanaged and neglected.</p>
                <p>For their manufactured goods, the inhabitants of the Isle of Man look principally
                    to the workshops of England. The Manx linen has long borne a high character, and
                    there is one establishment in the vicinity of Douglas where it is manufactured
                    in considerable quantities. There are also a paper and a woollen-cloth
                    manufactory, and several breweries. Many obstacles, however, prevent the rise of
                    manufactures in Man; and it is still to be seen whether they are to be
                    surmounted by those vigorous and laudable efforts which its people are now
                    making to better both their moral and physical condition. The most obvious of
                    these impediments are its fiscal regulations, and the probability that coal does
                    not exist amongst its minerals. By an apparent excess of legislative
                    interference in the former, the erection of distilleries in the island is
                    strictly forbidden; and whilst the Manx manufacturer must pay, on the greater
                    number of the articles he imports from England for the purposes of his business,
                    a two and a half per cent, <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> duty, over and
                    above all that is paid by the English merchant, he is annoyed with prohibitions,
                    restrictions, and countervailing duties, when he attempts to carry the produce
                    of his own industry into the British markets; and, owing to the entire absence
                    of native coal-fields, the lead and copper of its mines must all be sent in the
                    state of ores to the Welsh smelting furnaces.</p>
                <p>The trade of the Isle of Man is regulated chiefly by the act 3 and 4 Guliel. IV.
                    cap. 60. Its exports are corn, cattle, and other farm produce, lead and copper
                    ores, herrings, and linen, to the English markets, where they are admitted free
                    of duty, as if from any part of the united kingdom. .The imports are coalsand
                    flax, cotton and woollen stuffs, hardware, wearing apparel, and household
                    furniture; hemp, iron, and timber; spirits, coffee, tea, sugar, tobacco, and
                    wines. The articles composing the first of these classes are duty-free on
                    importation; those of the second, even when brought from England, pay a two and
                    a half per cent. <hi rend="italic">ad valorem</hi> duty; and the greater number
                    of the third and fourth are liable to only about a fifth of the English duties,
                    but they are much restricted in respect of quantity, time, and place of
                    importation. It is thus that its import trade admits of no great augmentation;
                    the foreign articles are intended to be confined entirely to the use of the
                    island; they cannot be legally exported to the united kingdom; and the spirits,
                    coffee, tea, sugars, tobacco, and wines, can be imported for the use of its
                    families only under a license granted by the board of customs. These licenses
                    are distributed annually by the lieutenant-governor; and although little errors
                    may occasionally find their way into the apportionments, and the object of the
                    law is occasionally defeated by those into whose possession they have fallen,
                    still the system works well, and, with a few slight amendments that could easily
                    be made, it is perhaps infinitely better both for the revenue and the island,
                    than any other of the many that are every day suggested. All the trade of the
                    island is carried on by a paper issue from three respectable banks; by a
                    circulating medium of English gold, silver, and copper coinage; and by a copper
                    currency peculiar to itself, amongst which are frequently to be seen the pence
                    and halfpence of the once regal houses of Derby and Atholl. In the present year,
                    1836, one of these banking establishments has merged into an extensive
                    joint-stock company bank, from which the most beneficial results are anticipated
                    to both the commercial and agricultural interests of the island.</p>
                <p>To him who delights in speculations on the early his <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194202604" xml:id="kp-eb0714-2604-0214"/>ţory of the earth and its
                    inhabitants, there are many objects of the deepest interest in the Isle of Man.
                    In its peat-bogs and marl-pits there are frequently discovered, under a few feet
                    of alluvial deposit, the trunks of sturdy oaks and fir trees, of a size no
                    longer to be found growing on its surface; and entombed beside these vigorous
                    memorials of other days, are the bones of those gigantic elks which had formerly
                    browsed below their branches. These venerable groves have indeed ceased to
                    exist; but the circle and the temple still remain, where the druids performed
                    their sylvan rites; and the humble graves of the misletoe worshippers can still
                    be easily traced. Tumuli, barrows, cairns, mounts, mounds, and Runic monuments,
                    are to be seen in all directions, either pointing out the spot where the warrior
                    fought, or where the affections of roving Norsemen marked the last resting-place
                    of their gallant chieftain. Monasteries and nunneries, too, have left vestiges
                    of their existence and their grandeur; whilst the ruins of one noble baronial
                    castle, and the massive battlements of another frowning unscathed by the storms
                    of nearly a dozen centuries, still more strikingly attest, that amongst the
                    former families of this little island the best and worst feelings of our
                    naturehadall theirusual manifestations. In sucha land, and amongst the
                    descendants of such a people, it might -fairly be expected that imagination
                    would be found taking some of her loftiest flights, and that songs and poems
                    would abound, in which the chivalrous deeds of its heroes were perpetuated and
                    embalmed. But if any such productions of Manx bards ever existed, they have long
                    since perished.</p>
                <p>This little island is surrounded by a dangerous sea, which is hourly traversed by
                    a very valuable portion of our mercantile marine; and not a winter passes that
                    its shores are not strewed with the wrecks of many noble vessels, and its waters
                    do not become the untimely graves of many gallant men, whose lives might have
                    been preserved to their country, had there been constructed there a great
                    central harbour accessible in the worst weather and at the lowest tides. That
                    central harbour the genius and benevolence of Sir William Hillary has devised;
                    and the conception has obtained the sanction of the highest practical science in
                    the warm approval of Sir John Rennie. For such a project the sum required is
                    indeed a very large one; but a small tonnage duty, restricted to the passing
                    vessel, would be fully commensurate for its completion; and the property saved
                    by it in half a century would abundantly repay the outlay, and vindicate the
                    wisdom of the measure. To England the Isle of Man would then become a cheap
                    purchase and a truly valuable territorial acquisition, not more in the
                    protection afforded to her commerce, than by rising, under her benign influence,
                    from a once comparatively desert waste, the abode of the serf, the smuggler, and
                    the profligate refugee, to be the rival of the average of her own counties in
                    wealth, beauty, and intelligence.</p>
                <p>Descriptions of the island have been published by Waldron, Feltham, Townley,
                    Wood, and Bullock. The most recent and the best, however, are those by Dr Oswald
                    and the Rev. Samuel Haining of Douglas.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
