<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0714-4242-0340-07" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">MAZARIN, Julius</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 14, page 340</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="11" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1921429">Sicilians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194204242" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">MAZARIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Julius</hi></label>, son of
                    Pietro Mazarini, a noble Sicilian, was born at Piscina in the Abbruzzi on the
                    14th of July 1602. Having received the elementary part of his education at Rome,
                    he passed into Spain with the abbé, afterwards cardinal, Jerome Colonna, at the
                    age of seventeen, and, during three years, he attended courses of law in the
                    universities of Alcala and Salamanca. But he soon abandoned jurisprudence in
                    order to embrace the military profession, and in 1625 was sent, with the rank of
                    captain, into the Valteline, where the pontiff then had an army. From this time
                    he began to display his talents for diplomacy. The generals of his Holiness,
                    Conti and de Bagni, sent him successively to the Duke de Feria, general of the
                    Spaniards, and to the Marquis de Coeuvres, afterwards Marshal d’Estrées, who
                    commanded the French troops; and in both missions he acquitted himself in such a
                    manner as to merit the commendations of these chiefs. He then returned to Rome,
                    where he resumed the study of jurisprudence, and took his doctor’s degree. But
                    the disputed succession to the duchies of Mantua and Montferrat having kindled
                    up a new war, he quitted law for diplomacy, in which line nature had peculiarly
                    qualified him to excel. The competitors were the Duke d’c Nevers, whose cause
                    was espoused by the court of France, at which he resided, and the Duke de
                    Guastalla, who was supported by the emperor, the king'o. Spain and the Duke of
                    Savoy. The pope, desirous to prevent<pb break="no" facs="nls:194204255" xml:id="kp-eb0714-4255-0341"/> a war, of
                    which Italy was about to become the theatre, sent cardinal Sacchetti to Turin to
                    act in favour of the Duke de Nevers, and Mazarin accompanied him in this
                    mission. The talentsofthe latter were very soon appreciated by the cardinal, who
                    confided to him the care of the negotiation. The mediation of the pope was
                    disregarded, the war commenced, and Louis XIII., in person, forced the pass of
                    Susa, which constrained the Duke of Savoy to treat with him and to separate
                    himself from the Spaniards. Sacchetti returned to Rome, leaving to Mazarin the
                    title of in ternuncio, with power to continue the negotiations, and to effect a
                    peace. Cardinal Barbarini, nephew of the pope, having been sent by his uncle in
                    quality of legate to Piedmont, honoured Mazarin with the same confidence which
                    had been reposed in him by Sacchetti; and thus a young man, less than thirty
                    years of age, with a title of little or no importance, was seen interposing with
                    different powers, and treating with all, in order to effect a pacification. With
                    this view he made several journeys, one of which laid the foundation of his
                    fortune. It was at Lyons in 1630 that he first saw Louis XIII., and had a long
                    conference with cardinal Richelieu. The cardinal conceived the highest opinion
                    of him, and feeling that France wanted an able and devoted man in Italy, he
                    succeeded in gaining the young diplomatist, who from this time openly shewed
                    himself favourable to the interests of France. He returned to Italy without
                    having obtained any success in his mission, and the war continued; but the Duke
                    of Savoy having died his son gave his entire confidence to Mazarin, who
                    immediately resumed the work of peace with fresh ardour. The Spaniards were
                    besieging Casal, and the French wished to relieve the place; but by negotiating
                    with the chiefs of both armies he induced them to consent to an armistice for
                    six weeks. When this truce had expired he demanded a prolongation, which the
                    French refused, and at the same time prepared to attack the lines. Mazarin then
                    proposed a treaty, in which they stipulated the hardest conditions. To engage
                    them to relax in their demands, he represented the formidable state of the
                    Spanish army, and the hazard of an attempt to force their entrenchments; but
                    failing to persuade them, he passed over to the Spaniards, reported to them the
                    conditions required by the French, and, still employing the same logic, urged
                    the superiority of the French, and their ardent desire for the combat. This time
                    he succeeded. The Spanish general assented to every thing. Mazarin immediately
                    quitted the Spanish trenches, and riding at full gallop towards the French,
                    regardless of the balls which whistled around him, waved his hat, exclaiming
                    “Peace, peace.” The soldiers repulsed him, crying ont “No peace ;” but he,
                    nevertheless, addressed himself to the marshal de Schomberg, who accepted the
                    treaty, and caused his troops to lay down their arms. This peace was confirmed
                    the following year by the treaty of Cherasco, which was negotiated by Mazarin.
                    About the same time he secured to France the town of Pignerol, having persuaded
                    the Duke of Savoy that he would be indemnified for the sacrifice, and deceived
                    both the Spaniards and imperialists who had only evacuated Casal and Mantua on
                    condition that the French garrison should quit Pignerol. Such conduct excited
                    against him all the hatred of the Spaniards; but it earned for him the
                    acknow-ledgmeqts of Louis XIII. and of Richelieu. This minister wrote to the
                    pope, on the part of his master, to congratulate liis Holiness on the ability
                    displayed by his negotiator. But in a court altogether ecclesiastical, the
                    military habit was no recommendation. In 1632, Mazarin quitted it, and
                    immediately received a benefice, with the office of referendary of the two
                    signatures in the chancery. Richelieu gave instructions to the French ambassador
                    at Rome to obtain for Mazarin an employment which should bring the latter into
                    contact with himself. In 1634 he was appointed vicelegate of Avignon, and before
                    he had quitted Rome to repair to his post, his wishes were fulfilled by an order
                    which he received to proceed to the court of France in the capacity of nuncio
                    extraordinary. The object of this mission was to intercede in favour of the Duke
                    of Lorraine, who had been deprived of his estates by Louis XIII.</p><p>Received with the greatest distinction by Richelieu, who even wished to provide
                    him with lodgings in his own palace, Mazarin neglected no means of preserving
                    the good graces of the king and his minister; and in this he was so successful
                    that Louis XIII. promised to name him for the cardinalate, if he was not
                    anticipated therein by the pope. In 1635, the Spaniards had carried off the
                    elector of Treves, who was under the protection of France. This was the pretext
                    for a war which lasted five and twenty years. Mazarin, as minister of the court
                    of Rome, wished to interpose in an affair which regarded a prelate; but the
                    Spaniards remembered his conduct at Pignerol, and their intrigues with the
                    sovereign pontiff procured his recall to Avignon. They even attempted to get his
                    vice-legation revoked; but he anticipated them, and fearing that he would not be
                    left in oblivion at Avignon, he demanded his recall, and in 1636 returned to
                    Rome, where he openly supported the interests of France. It was he whom
                    Richelieu charged to demand a cardinal’s hat for the famous Père Joseph; but the
                    death of this capuchin put an end to the negociation. Richelieu, who lost a
                    faithful friend and useful confidant, now resolved to replace him by attaching
                    to himself Mazarin, who had already given him so many proofs of devotion; and he
                    engaged Louis XIII. to place on his head the cardinal’s hat which had been given
                    to Père Joseph. This demand hurt Urban VIII., who, though at first favourable to
                    Mazarin, had since allowed himself to be influenced against him by his numerous
                    enemies. But Richelieu had himself made the demand, and he knew not what it was
                    to recede. Mazarin nowattach-ed himself irrevocably to France. Being called by
                    Richelieu, he quitted Italy in the beginning of 1639, and proceeded to join the
                    cardinal. The war, which for so many years desolated Europe, had exhausted the
                    different powers, and all were now desirous of peace. The king of Denmark,
                    Christian IV., offered himself as mediator; and Hamburg was fixed upon as the
                    place for the assembling of their ambassadors. Louis XIII. had cast his eyes
                    upon Mazarin, whom he wished to send to this congress; but the troubles which
                    broke out in Savoy led the king to think that he would be more useful in a
                    country with which he was acquainted; and, accordingly, in the beginning of
                    1640, he was sent thither with the title of ambassador extraordinary. The
                    successes of the Count d’Harcourt in Piedmont enabled him, in December 1641, to
                    conclude a treaty between the Duchess of Savoy and <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi>
                    her brothers-in-law, who, supported by Spain, had disputed with her the
                    guardianship of her son. It was then that Mazarin obtained the hat long since
                    demanded for him; he was included in the nomination of the 16th December 1641,
                    and on the 25 th of February 1642 he received the cap from the hands of Louis
                    XIII. The intrigues which had pursued Richelieu during his whole life assumed
                    fresh force towards its close; but these did not prevent Mazarin from remaining
                    faithful towards his protector, to whom he rendered especial service, when the
                    discovery of the conspiracy of the fifth of March re-established his credit and
                    authority. This minister on his death-bed recommended him warmly to the king;
                    and if Mazarin did not succeed him in his title he was really first minister of
                    Louis XIII., since he had the direction of all affairs of state. Richelieu had
                    governed by terror; but Mazarin was not of a character to employ similar means,
                    and preferred to make himself friends. It was at his request that Marshal de
                    Bassompierre, Marshal de Vitry, andmany other victims of thelastministerwere
                    released from the Bastille. He also recalled several exiled members of
                    parliament, and contributed to the reconciliation of the Duke d’Orleans with the
                    king.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:194204268" xml:id="kp-eb0714-4268-0342"/><p>On the 14th of May 1643 Louis XIII., whose health had for some time been
                    declining, terminated his melancholy existence. We cannot enter into any details
                    of the events that followed, and for an account of which we must refer the
                    reader to the memoirs and histories of the period. It is sufficient to state
                    that, during the minority of Louis XIV. and the regency of Anne of Austria, the
                    administration of affairs was entirely in the hands of Mazarin. The commencement
                    of his sway was attended with the happiest success; and the advantages gained by
                    the king’s armies secured to the cardinal the applause of the nation. But these
                    favourable dispositions were soon succeeded by the murmurs, not loud but deep,
                    of an oppressed people, and also by a combination of the high nobility who were
                    jealous of his advancement and power. The civil wars of 1649, 1650, 1651, and
                    1652, followed; and as the dissatisfaction daily became more general, it was at
                    length insisted on that he should be dismissed from the royal presence. Mazarin,
                    who knew when to yield as well as how to resist, demanded permission to retire,
                    and immediately withdrew from the kingdom. But such was the singular fortune of
                    the man, that this event may be considered as one of the incidents which mainly
                    contributed to his greatness. Decree upon decree was fulminated against him; his
                    fine library was sold; and a price was even put upon his head; yet, in spite of
                    all the rage of his enemies, he was enabled to return to court with greater
                    power than ever; and so mutable is popular opinion that many who had formerly
                    been his bitterest enemies now became his warmest friends. After this he was
                    instrumental in rendering the state some important services. He put an end to
                    the war between France and Spain, and, in order to consolidate the peace he had
                    re-established, negotiated a marriage between the king and the infanta, which
                    was celebrated at Sant-Jean-de-Luz on the 9th of June 1660. But the cardinal’s
                    glass was now nearly run. His continual application to business brought on a
                    dangerous illness, which terminated his existence at Vincennes on the 9th of
                    March 1661, in the fifty-ninth year of his age. Mazarin, like most ministers,
                    was but little regretted. A courtier writing at the time, says, “Le roi est, ou
                    parait, le seul touche de la mort du cardinal.” He had accumulated immense
                    wealth by very doubtful or equivocal means. His fortune is said to have amounted
                    to near eight millions sterling, all acquired in a period of external war or of
                    internal commotion. On the approach of death he began to feel some scruples of
                    conscience on the subject, but observed that he had nothing except what the
                    bounty of the king had conferred on him. His confessor, however, plainly told
                    him that he must distinguish between what he had actually received from the king
                    and what he had taken at his own hand; and that, in regard to the latter,
                    restitution was indispensable to salvation. In this dilemma Colbert counselled
                    him to give up all his property to the king, which he did by an act dated a few
                    days before his death; but the king, as had no doubt been foreseen, declined the
                    proposed donation, and the cardinal’s conscience was, we presume, satisfied.</p><p>The only productions of Mazarin which have been published are his letters. Of
                    these, thirty-six, written by him whilst negotiating of the peace of the
                    Pyrenees, made their appearance in the year 1690; and seventy-seven more on the
                    same subject were published in 1693. The whole were collected and re-printed at
                    Amsterdam, in two volumes, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Négociations</hi><hi rend="italic">Secretes des Pyrenees·</hi> These letters
                    are not arranged in the order of their dates; but this error was corrected in a
                    later edition, for which we are indebted to the care of the Abbé Allainval, and
                    the value of which is still further enhanced from its being augmented by fifty
                    letters never before published. This work is entitled, <hi rend="italic">Lettres</hi><hi rend="italic">du Cardinal Mazarin,</hi><hi rend="italic">où</hi><hi rend="italic">l’on</hi><hi rend="italic">voit le</hi><hi rend="italic">Secret</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Négociation de la Paix</hi><hi rend="italic">des Pyrenees,</hi> Paris, 1745, in two vols. 12mo. All these
                    letters have been found in an original collection which is preserved in the
                    royal library at Paris. Mazarin wrote a relation of the conferences for the
                    instruction of the king, and with the intention of accustoming him to affairs,
                    and there exist no better diplomatic lessons; for what passed in the conferences
                    is there unfolded with a clearness and precision which in some sort place the
                    reader <hi rend="italic">en</hi><hi rend="italic">tiers</hi> with the two
                    plenipotentiaries. In 1663, there was published at Cologne a <hi rend="italic">Testament Politique du Cardinal Mazarin</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but this
                    work, like so many other romances of the same kind, is undeserving of attention.
                    Another political testament of Mazarin appeared under the title of <hi rend="italic">Breviarium Politicoum</hi><hi rend="italic">secundum</hi><hi rend="italic">Rubricas</hi><hi rend="italic">Mazarinicas.</hi> It is a bitter
                    satire on his government, and represents him as recommending to Louis XIV. such
                    Machiavellian maxims as these: <hi rend="italic">Simula,</hi><hi rend="italic">dissimula</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">nulli crede,</hi><hi rend="italic">omnia</hi><hi rend="italic">lauda,</hi> &amp;c. “Ce livre,” says
                    a French writer, “est assez bon dans son espece diabolique.” Much more besides
                    hasbeen written concerning Mazarin, and in regard to his ministry, which
                    embraces nearly twenty years of the history of France. Count Galeazzo Gualdo
                    Priorato is authorof aliis-tory of Cardinal Mazarin, translated into French,
                    Paris, 1688, in two vols. 12mo, but which is not always exact. Another work of
                    the same kind by one Aubery, author of a great number of mediocre productions,
                    professed to give an account of Mazarin from his birth till his death; it was
                    originally printed at Paris in 1688 and 1695, in two vols. 12mo. The history of
                    the ministry of Cardinal Mazarin from 1643 to 1652, by a clergyman, is an able
                    work, but has more reference to the history of France during the period in
                    question, than to that of Mazarin in particular. One of the best apologies which
                    has yet appeared for the conduct of this minister is contained in the work of
                    Jean de Silhou, councillor of state, which was published in 1650, under the tide
                    of <hi rend="italic">Eclaircissements sur quelques difficultés touchant</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi rend="italic">Administration du Cardinal
                    Richelieu,</hi> and deserves to be consulted by every student of French history.
                    The Cardinal was the object of innumerable satires directed against him by the
                    Fronde, particularly during the year 1669; but, on the other hand, amongst his
                    most servile flatterers we find the great Corneille, who, in his <hi rend="italic">Mort de Pompée,</hi> calls him “homme au-dessus de ľhomme.”</p><p>The character of Mazarin has been compared, or rather contrasted with that of
                    Richelieu, and variously shaded according to the opinions and predilections of
                    those by whom it is delineated. “Cardinal Mazarin,” says President Hénault, “was
                    as gentle as Cardinal Richelieu was violent; one of his greatest talents
                    consisted in knowing men thoroughly. The character of his policy was rather
                    finesse and prudence than force....This minister thought that force should never
                    be employed but in default of other means; and his mind supplied the courage
                    required by circumstances; bold at Cassai, tranquil and active in his retreat at
                    Cologne; enterprising when it was necessary to cause the princes to be arrested,
                    but insensible to the pleasantries of the Fronde; despising the bravadoes of the
                    coadjutor, De Retz,and listening to the murmurs of the people as one listens on
                    the shore to the noise of the waves of the sea. There was in Cardinal Richelieu
                    something greater, vaster, and less composed; in Cardinal Mazarin, more address,
                    more management, and fewer extravagances. People hated the one and derided the
                    other; but both were masters of the state.” The parallel between these two great
                    men has been attempted by several writers, and some have placed Mazarin above
                    the minister who had the merit of distinguishing him amongst the crowd. That
                    which Voltaire has traced in the seventh canto of his <hi rend="italic">Henriade</hi> is more just, but incomplete. Gaillard gives the preference to
                    Mazarin. “If we inquire,” says he, “of what use they have been to the world, we
                    shall find that it is unquestionably better to have allayed disorders than to
                    have occasioned them; that it is better to have terminated a war <pb break="no" facs="nls:194204281" xml:id="kp-eb0714-4281-0343"/>of thirty
                    years, than to have maintained and kept it alive. The peace of Westphalia and
                    that of the Pyrenees are two epochs which place Mazarin above Richelieu and the
                    greatest ministers. These monuments of peace far outweigh the honour of having
                    invented means that were new, or revived means that were old, for disturbing
                    Europe.” Bussy, in his <hi rend="italic">Mémoires,</hi> has preserved a portrait
                    of Mazarin: “Never man,” says he, “had so fortunate a birth as his. He was born
                    a Roman gentleman; and he had studied in the university of Salamanca, where,
                    having one day had his horoscope cast, he had been assured that he would be
                    pope. He had the finest physiognomy in the world; the eyes and the mouth
                    beautiful, the forehead large, the nose well proportioned, and the visage open.
                    He had much wit; no one related a story or anecdote more agreeably. He was
                    insinuating, and was sure to be loved by those whom he took the trouble to
                    please. He excelled in all games of skill and address.” Insensible to the
                    pamphlets which were daily discharged against him, he usually observed when any
                    one of them was mentioned, <hi rend="italic">Laissons parler et faisons.</hi>
                    Indifferent about an opposition, which exhaled in satirical couplets, <hi rend="italic">“Qu’ils</hi><hi rend="italic">cantent,</hi><hi rend="italic">ces
                    Français,”</hi> said he, “<hi rend="italic">pourvu</hi><hi rend="italic">qu</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">ils</hi><hi rend="italic">payent”</hi> Of all the
                    pieces directed against him, the only one which appears to have given any
                    annoyance was the <hi rend="italic">Mazarinadeoĩ</hi> Scarron,who in consequence
                    lost his pension of 1500 livres, which had been bestowed upon him by the
                    minister whom he sought to render ridiculous. But he did not neglect men of
                    letters, and charged Menage to furnish him with a list of those who deserved
                    rewards or encouragement. The arts were also the object of his protection; and
                    it is well known that he introduced the opera into France. As a statesman, he
                    belonged almost entirely to the Italian school, themaxims of which he had early
                    imbibed; he trusted chiefly to his knowledge of men, and the dexterous
                    employment of those arts by which that knowledge may be made effectual; his
                    policy was too subtle and refined to impress a common observer with a just
                    conception of its real quality; and as to his ambition, it had nothing of that
                    high-reaching and aspiring character, which dignified even the aberrations of
                    Richelieu, and was too nearly allied to avarice to command general respect. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>